<exhibit id="fakeblakesshort" title="Fake Blakes Short" article="fakeblakesshort.exhibit.html"
    composition_date_string="September 2021">

    <image dbi="1.fb.exh" id="1">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 1: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption>1. This impression of "Spring" is from <i>Songs of <i>Innocence</i></i> copy T, which has
            no known provenance before it was sold anonymously at Hodgson amp Company’s book
            auction, 21 April 1910, lot 246. It was described as "title page plus 26 plates,
            coloured, printed on one side only; bound in old russia, blind tooled sides, gilt inner
            border, early copy before the numbering of the plates, 7 1/8 x 6 1/8." Where does
                <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy T belong in the history of <i><i>Innocence</i></i> or <i>Songs of
                <i>Innocence</i> and of <i>Experience</i></i>?</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="2.fb.exh" id="2">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>2. The catalogue description of <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy T raises a few red flags. The
            absence of numbers in the top right corner of the designs suggests an “early copy,” such
            as <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy B, printed and colored in 1789, but the washes behind the text
            and the sheep drawn in at the right margin are features of late copies of illuminated
            books, those printed and colored in the last decade of Blake’s life, such as
                <i><i>Songs</i></i> copy U, printed and colored in 1818. <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy T has 29
            plates, not 27 as recorded in the catalogue, but all other copies of <i><i>Innocence</i></i>
            printed on one side of the leaves have 28 plates. More troubling, it has plates 34, 35,
            and 36 (“Little Girl Lost” and “Little Girl Found”), the three plates that Blake moved
            to <i><i>Experience</i></i> in 1794 and are only in copies of <i><i>Innocence</i></i> with 31 plates,
            i. e., copies printed in 1789. <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy T is slightly larger than early
            copies, but more troubling is that it follows the palette and placement of colors of
                <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy B as well as copy B’s plate order. Both features are
            suspicious because Blake did not copy himself in these ways and all early copies of
                <i><i>Innocence</i></i> have unique plate orders. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="3.fb.exh" id="3">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>3. The anomalies of <i><i>Innocence</i></i> copy T force a closer look at its impressions
            to see if they were printed by Blake. They were unquestionably printed from Blake’s
            relief-etched plates, but the designs are slightly larger than in life time impressions,
            which is a sign they were printed posthumously on dry paper rather than damp and thus
            did not shrink like Blake’s impressions. Printing on dry paper was characteristic of
            Frederick Tatham’s practice, but not Blake’s or Catherine Blake’s (see Galleries 5 and
            6) A sure sign that copy T was posthumously printed is its impression of “The Little
            Black Boy.” The first of its two plates is in a second state. The mother’s hair and back
            were trimmed with a burin or scraper, as in <i>Songs</i> copy h, a posthumous copy printed by
            Tatham on paper watermarked 1831 and 1832 (lower case letters designate posthumous
            copies, but not all posthumous copies are so designated). In all life time impressions,
            such as <i>Songs</i> copies O and U, printed 1795 and 1818 respectively, the plate is in its
            first state, with back and hair untouched. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="4.fb.exh" id="4">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>4. <i>Songs</i> of <i>Innocence</i> copy T is a forgery. It began as a copy of <i>Songs</i> posthumously
            printed by Tatham on Whatman paper in black ink, c. 1831-32. The copy initially had 53
            plates, missing plates 15 and 53, but probably including “A Divine Image.” It was one of
            six complete copies of <i>Songs</i> that Tatham had abridged to 40-42 plates, c. 1832-40, by
            extracting a cluster of 12 to 14 <i>Experience</i> plates (see Viscomi, “Posthumous Blake”).
            Someone, probably a dealer, acquired the abridged copy and extracted the remaining
            <i>Experience</i> plates to transform it into a near complete copy of <i>Innocence</i> and had the
            impressions colored and ordered in imitation of <i>Innocence</i> copy B. Subtracting
            impressions to make a complete looking copy of <i>Innocence</i> was easier than finding and
            adding the missing <i>Experience</i> impressions to build a complete copy of <i>Songs</i>, and, in
            turn, a complete colored copy of <i>Innocence</i> was more lucrative financially than an
            incomplete monochrome copy of <i>Songs</i>, let alone one recognizably posthumous. The dealer
            may have assumed that the impressions were life-time; nevertheless, the actions
            performed on <i>Innocence</i> copy T were done with the intent to deceive, which makes the copy
            a forgery. The provenance of the forgery’s model, <i>Innocence</i> copy B, is unknown between
            1834, at the death of R. H. Clarke, its first known owner, and 1906, when it was sold
            anonymously at Sotheby’s to the book dealer Robson. <i>Innocence</i> copy T was unknown until
            1910, when it sold anonymously at Hodgson’s as “coloured by Blake.” The creation of copy
            T appears to have occurred between 1906 and 1910. Copy T was given to Princeton
            University Library in 1984 as a life time copy and unmasked in 1993 (see Viscomi, Blake
            and the Idea of the Book, 244-9). </caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="5.fb.exh" id="5">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 2: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> copy <span style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption>5. Pierpont Morgan bought a complete 54 plate copy of <i>Songs</i> in 1901 from James
            Toovey, a well-known and respected book dealer. It comprised 40 impressions printed in
            sepia, now designated as <i>Songs</i> copy e, and 14 impressions printed in brown ink extracted
            from a set of uncolored <i>Experience</i> impressions, now designated as <i>Songs</i> copy K. The
            sepia and brown impressions were printed by different printers and colored long after
            they were printed, possibly by different colorists. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="6.fb.exh" id="6">
        <title>
        </title>
        <caption>6. The sepia ink of <i>Songs</i> copy e, as demonstrated by “The Little Black Boy,” is
            smooth and flat, noticeably different than the brown ink of <i>Songs</i> copy K, as
            demonstrated by “To Tirzah.” The sepia is a relief ink, which is made with a boiled
            linseed oil that enables the ink to transfer with light pressure. The brown is an
            intaglio ink, which is made with a viscous burnt linseed oil that enables the ink to
            stay in intagliate lines when the plate’s surface is wiped clean; consequently, when
            printed with light pressure, the ink reticulates. The different kinds of ink represent
            different materials, practices, and printers. Blake, a trained engraver, printed on damp
            paper with intaglio ink, as did Catherine; Tatham, a sculptor and portraitist by
            training, printed on dry paper with relief inks.</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="7.fb.exh" id="7">
        <title>
        </title>
        <caption>7. Blake and Catherine did not print in sepia colored inks. Tatham, however,
            printed copies of <i>Songs</i>, <i>America</i>, <i>Europe</i>, and <i>Jerusalem</i> in a sepia relief ink on Whatman
            papers dated 1831 and 1832. The examples from <i>America</i> copy P, <i>Europe</i> copy M, and
            <i>Jerusalem</i> copy I demonstrate the quality of Tatham’s printing and the ink’s range of
            hue, from a reddish brown to a brownish red. These impressions, printed on dry paper,
            are a few mm. larger than life-time impressions and have flat, smoother ink surfaces.
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="8.fb.exh" id="8">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>8. The sepia impressions of copy e were printed by Tatham around 1831 or 1832 but
            were colored by an unknown artist toward the end of the 19th century. The colorist used
            <i>Songs</i> copy Y as the model, imitating the palette and style closely. Blake printed and
            colored <i>Songs</i> copy Y around 1826 for Edward Calvert, one of the young artists who
            surrounded Blake in his last years and in whose family it remained till 1893.</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="9.fb.exh" id="9">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>9. The 14 brown <i>Experience</i> impressions were printed by Blake around 1795 with a set
            of <i>Innocence</i> impressions that is now part of <i>Songs</i> copy O. The leaves of the two parts
            were uncolored and numbered sequentially in the top right corner of the designs. This
            copy of <i>Songs</i> was separated sometime in the early 19th century and its 28 <i>Experience</i>
            impressions, now designated as copy K, were acquired by Toovy in the 1890s. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="10.fb.exh" id="10">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>10. The colorist of the brown impressions did not use <i>Songs</i> copy Y as a model,
            which suggests that copy Y was not available, which in turn suggests that the brown
            impressions were colored after 1893, when copy Y was acquired by the book dealers Ellis
            and Elvey and where it appears to have remained till 1901.</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="11.fb.exh" id="11">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>11. The colorist of the brown impressions did not imitate <i>Songs</i> copy Y or any life
            time copy and may not have been the colorist of the sepia impressions, as the more
            opaque colors and style of laying in colors suggest. The second colorist, however,
            attempted to match the sepia impressions by repeating some of their features, such as
            outlining designs in black ink and painting letters and decorative fills in gold paint,
            which the first colorist used to imitate Blake’s gold leaf in many of the titles in
            <i>Songs</i> copy Y. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="12.fb.exh" id="12">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>12. Pierpont Morgan bought a composite copy of <i>Songs</i> that was a forgery. <i>Songs</i> copy
            e was posthumously printed by Tatham on Whatman paper in sepia, c. 1831 and originally
            had 54 plates. As he had with 5 other complete copies of <i>Songs</i>—including the one that
            was used to form <i>Innocence</i> copy T— Tatham extracted a cluster of <i>Experience</i> plates
            between 1832 and 1840, reducing this sepia copy to 40 uncolored impressions, the
            condition in which it sold at Sotheby’s in 1862, when it was acquired by Toovey,
            presumably believing it was an incomplete but original copy. Toovey may or may not have
            been responsible for having <i>Songs</i> copy e colored; he may have sold the copy uncolored
            decades earlier only to reacquire it in the 1890s in its transformed condition. If so,
            he would have assumed the copy was original and not have recognized it as the uncolored
            copy he acquired in 1862. He was responsible, though, for completing the copy with 14
            life time impressions extracted from <i>Songs</i> copy K and having them colored to cohere with
            the sepia impressions. The idea that anyone would color what they believed to be
            uncolored impressions printed by Blake strikes us as audacious, if not an outright act
            of vandalism (for that, see <i>Songs</i> copy M). Admittedly, Victorian standards for editing
            texts and images—for respecting the integrity of original art objects—were lower than
            today’s. Nevertheless, the person responsible for transforming <i>Songs</i> copy e in imitation
            of copy Y committed fraud. So did Toovey by completing <i>Songs</i> copy e with life time
            impressions and posthumous coloring. Unravelling the posthumous printing and coloring of
            the once combined copy e/K was first demonstrated 1993 in Viscomi’s Blake and the Idea
            of the Book, 299-302. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="13.fb.exh" id="13">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 3: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> copy <span style="text-transform:none">f</span>/<span style="text-transform:none">j</span></p>
        </title>
        <caption>13. The impressions making up <i>Songs</i> of <i>Innocence</i> and of <i>Experience</i> copy j are well
            printed and professionally colored, but neither printing nor coloring was by Blake.
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="14.fb.exh" id="14">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>14. The coloring is in Blake’s late style, with light washes behind texts and frame
            lines around the design, but the colors in the vignette are thicker and laid in more
            heavily than was characteristic of Blake’s late style of finishing, as is demonstrated
            by <i>Songs</i> copy U, printed and colored by Blake in 1818. The sepia printing ink and style
            of finishing in copy j raise suspicions. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="15.fb.exh" id="15">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>15. Comparing “The Little Black Boy” from <i>Songs</i> copy j to the <i>Songs</i> copy U
            impression reveals that the copy j impression is posthumous. The mother’s hair bun was
            trimmed, the ink lays unreticulated and flat, and the design is slightly larger than the
            copy U impression, all characteristic of posthumous pulls.</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="16.fb.exh" id="16">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>16. The colorist of <i>Songs</i> copy j did not imitate any late copy exactly, but did
            copy very closely an ornamental flourish around the words “Of <i>Innocence</i> and Of” that
            appears only in the title plate of <i>Songs</i> copy X, the last copy of <i>Songs</i> printed and
            colored by Blake. Copy X was acquired in 1921 by the book dealer Joseph F. Sabin for
            £510. </caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="17.fb.exh" id="17">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>17. In 1919, Sabin had acquired a 54-plate uncolored copy of <i>Songs</i> printed by
            Tatham in sepia c. 1831-32. This copy, designated copy f, was first acquired by an
            unknown collector in 1836 (according to a note on a flyleaf), bound by 1869 by Leighton,
            and subsequently disappeared. It reappeared in 1919 at auction, where Sabin acquired it
            for £39. Sabin had it colored in Blake’s late style and sold it in 1925 to A. E. Newton
            as a life time copy for £550. He transformed copy f into copy j, as it is now known.
            Copy j’s connection to Sabin’s <i>Songs</i> copy X—discovered in preparing this
            exhibition—reveals that Sabin was responsible for the forgery. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="18.fb.exh" id="18">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 4: <i>For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</i> copy F</p>
        </title>
        <caption>18. Catherine was a fine printer in her own right. She knew how to ink and print
            intaglio plates, skills that enabled her, in 1805, to print Blake’s two engravings for
            William Hayley’s biography of Cowper in an edition of 500 copies, which amounted to 1000
            impressions (E 726). She and Tatham were the only people with access to Blake’s press
            and plates after the artist died, 27 August 1827. By mid-September 1827, Catherine had
            moved herself and Blake’s plates, press, art works, and all of their belongings to the
            Fitzroy Square studio of John Linnell. She stayed till early Spring, 1828, by which time
            she appears to have printed a few copies of Blake’s Canterbury Pilgrims engraving and
            copies F, G, H, and I of <i><i>For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</i></i>(Viscomi, “Posthumous
            Blake”). These were the first of Blake’s works posthumously produced and demonstrate her
            ability to print Blake’s plates on her own.</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="19.fb.exh" id="19">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 5: <i>America a Prophecy</i> copy Q</p>
        </title>
        <caption>19. Catherine also knew how Blake printed relief etchings, presumably from handling
            the press and paper while Blake inked the plates and brought them to the press bed. In
            c. 1829, she printed <i>America</i> a Prophecy copies N and Q and <i>Europe</i> a Prophecy copies I
            and L. <i>America</i> a Prophecy, dated 1793, was the first of Blake's "Continental
            Prophecies," followed by <i>Europe</i> a Prophecy in 1794, executed in the same style and size
            but usually colored, and, in 1795, "Africa" and "Asia," two sections making up The Song
            of Los. All lifetime copies were folio in size—approximately 37 x 27 cm.—except <i>America</i>
            copy O and <i>Europe</i> copy K, the last copies that Blake printed, in 1821 for John Linnell,
            which are quarto in size, at 30 x 24 cm. Catherine Blake appears to have used these late
            copies as her model, printing <i>America</i> copy Q and <i>Europe</i> copy L as matching quartos, at
            32.6 x 23.6 cm., on paper dated 1813, and <i>America</i> copy N and <i>Europe</i> copy I as matching
            quartos, at 29.5 x 22.1 cm., c. 1829 on paper dated 1812. <i>America</i> copy Q and <i>Europe</i> copy
            L follow the pattern of <i>Innocence</i> copy T, <i>Songs</i> copy e, and <i>Songs</i> f/j, in that they were
            printed soon after Blake died and colored much later by a third party who sold them as
            life time copies. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="20.fb.exh" id="20">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>20. <i>America</i> comprises 18 major text and design plates and a small plate (e) bearing
            the word "Preludium" and printed above the design on plate 3. Ten of the 14 life time
            extant copies of <i>America</i> were printed in 1793 on both sides of leaves in bluish and
            greenish black inks and left uncolored. The last five lines of plate 4 were masked and
            did not print, and plate 13 was printed in its first of two states. Catherine Blake
            printed plate 4 unmasked, plate 13 in its final state, and did not print plate e. She
            printed on one side of the leaf and left the impressions uncolored. Her impressions are
            closer in appearance and feel to Blake’s monochrome impressions than Tatham’s. She
            printed in black intaglio ink on dampened paper, resulting in reticulated surfaces; she
            touched up impressions in light washes and numbered them in the top right corner. These
            features are characteristic of Blake’s practice and differentiate her books from all the
            posthumous illuminated books printed by Tatham. The impressions of plate 4 from <i>America</i>
            copies Q and N share accidentals and traces of ink printed from the shallows (which grey
            washes cover up in copy Q), evidence that Catherine printed <i>America</i> copy N and copy Q
            back to back in the same session. With Tatham acting as intermediary, Catherine sold
            <i>America</i> copy N to James Ferguson, who also bought <i>Europe</i> copy I, which she printed, and
            <i>Visions of the Daughters of Albion</i>copy N, which Blake had printed in 1818. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="21.fb.exh" id="21">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>21. <i>America</i> copy Q was acquired between 1913 and 1918 by Walter T. Spencer, who had
            it colored in imitation of copy A, which Blake printed and colored in 1795. Spencer’s
            colorist, however, did not use Blake’s original; he used William Muir’s 1887
            lithographic facsimile of <i>America</i> copy A, which was based on tracings. Using a facsimile
            as the model allowed the colorist to work undetected. Copy Q was first recognized as
            posthumously colored in 1939, when exhibited in Philadelphia. The status of the coloring
            was confirmed by Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf in their 1953 Census. The possibility
            that copy Q was also posthumously printed was first suggested by G. E. Bentley Jr., in
            his 1977 <i>Blake Books</i>. The original owner of <i>America</i> copy N and early curators at the
            Auckland Library where the book now resides assumed that this copy was printed by Blake.
            The paper is dated 1812. The first owners of copy Q, which is on paper dated 1813, may
            have thought the same, and that includes Spencer. Nevertheless, coloring copy Q in
            imitation of a life time copy was fraud. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="22.fb.exh" id="22">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 6: <i>Europe a Prophecy</i> copy L</p>
        </title>
        <caption>22. <i>Europe a Prophecy</i> presents in mythopoeic form the conflict between liberty and
            tyranny, the fundamental philosophical issues of Blake's revolutionary era. Blake etched
            <i>Europe</i>’s 18 plates in relief, with considerable white-line work in some designs, on the
            versos of <i>America</i>’s 18 plates. The posthumous copies are missing plate 3, a whimsical
            prefatory statement—present only in copies H and K—about a “Fairy [who] sat upon the
            table, and dictated <i>Europe</i>.” </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="23.fb.exh" id="23">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>23. <i>Europe</i> copies I and L were printed by Catherine Blake in the same printing
            session. The traces of ink printed from the shallows are covered in copy L by washes
            that were laid in by the same colorist who finished <i>America</i> copy Q, between 1913 and
            1918, and with the same intent to deceive. Coloring the book to pass as life time copy
            greatly increased its value.</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="24.fb.exh" id="24">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>24. <i>Europe</i> copy L follows the same pattern as <i>America</i> copy Q. It was acquired
            between 1913 and 1918 by Walter T. Spencer, who had it colored in imitation of <i>Europe</i>
            copy A, which Blake printed and colored in 1795. Spencer’s colorist, however, did not
            use Blake’s original; he used William Muir’s 1887 lithographic facsimile of <i>Europe</i>,
            which was made from tracings of a copy of <i>Europe</i> with most impressions hand colored in
            imitation of copy A. Working from facsimiles rather than originals allowed the colorist
            to work undetected. <i>Europe</i> copy A’s coloring was first recognized as posthumous by
            Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf in their 1953 Census. However, they did not report
            posthumous printing for <i>Europe</i> copy L, a possibility first suggested by G. E. Bentley,
            Jr., in his 1977 <i>Blake Books</i> and confirmed by Robert N. Essick in his 1985 catalogue of
            the Huntington collection. The identity of Catherine Blake as printer of <i>Europe</i> copy L
            (as well as <i>America</i> copy Q) is demonstrated in Joseph Viscomi’s “Posthumous Blake.” The
            original owner of <i>Europe</i> copy I and early curators at the Auckland Library where the
            book now resides assumed that this copy was printed by Blake. The paper is dated 1813.
            The first owners of copy L may have thought the same, and that includes Spencer.
            Nevertheless, coloring copy L in imitation of a life time copy and selling it as Blake’s
            work was fraud. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="25.fb.exh" id="25">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 7: Photolithographs and Keriographs</p>
        </title>
        <caption>25. <i>America</i> copy B was printed by Blake in 1795, along with copy A, as part of a
            deluxe set of illuminated books apparently commissioned by George Romney. By 1868, when
            copy B entered the collection of A.G. Dew-Smith, it was missing plates 4 and 9. To
            complete the copy, Dew-Smith replaced these missing plates with photolithographic
            facsimiles, which he appears to have executed himself. An independently wealthy
            collector of romantic literature who had trained at Cambridge in physiology, Dew-Smith
            owned a company that provided photolithographic facsimiles to publishers of maps and old
            texts. Though apparently executed as facsimiles to complete his copy of <i>America</i>, not as
            forgeries to deceive, the facsimiles were taken as originals after copy B was sold in
            1870 and were not discovered as copies until 1978 (see Viscomi, “Two Fake Blakes
            Revisited”). </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="26.fb.exh" id="26">
        <title>
           
        </title>
        <caption>26. Dew-Smith used <i>America</i> copy F, in the British Museum, as his model for plates 4
            and 9. Blake’s intaglio ink printed lighter than the lithographic ink, which was mixed
            with a magnesium powder to increase its opacity (see Viscomi, “Forgery or Facsimile”).
            Nothing in the images gives them away. Comparing plates 4 and 9 in copy B to life-time
            impressions would not reveal that they were fakes. Making that determination required
            examining the physical objects, which revealed that these plates were printed on thicker
            paper than the other plates. Height and width are the same as life-time impressions, but
            diagonally the designs was elongated, the result of a convex lens projecting the image
            onto a photosensitized zinc plate. The faint embossments of genuine relief etchings were
            created by slightly scoring the paper along the design’s edge with a beveled ruler to
            create the illusion of a plate printed into paper as opposed to being printed
            planographically on paper. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="27.fb.exh" id="27">
        <title>
           
        </title>
        <caption>27. The Book of Job reproductions in Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 1863, were the
            first photolithographic reproductions of works by Blake. They were produced at the
            urging of Dante Rossetti, who, with his brother William Michael, assisted Anne Gilchrist
            in completing the biography. William Linton, who designed and provided over 100
            illustrations for the Life, thought they were too dark and wanted to reproduce them as
            wood engravings, the medium of which he was a master. Linton, a very Blakean figure in
            his own right, was an illustrator, printmaker, poet, and inventor. For the Life, he had
            invented “keriography,” a process by which he could make type-high line blocks from
            tracings that could be printed with letterpress. He used this method to produce a
            facsimile of the <i>Experience</i> title plate, which was missing from the set of plates that
            Tatham had lent Gilchrist for the purpose of making electrotypes and printing them as
            facsimiles in the <i>Life</i> (see Viscomi, “Blake after Blake”). </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="28.fb.exh" id="28">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>28. <i>There is No Natural Religion</i>, c. 1788, appears originally to have had
            twenty plates. No impressions, however, exist from its initial printings. The twelve
            extant copies comprised different plates and different number of plates, all apparently
            from 1794, 1795, and c. 1811, which made editing this tiny series of emblems and
            precepts impossible. In 1989, six of the twelve copies were revealed to be forgeries,
            each comprised of eight impressions that were assumed to be genuine when discovered in
            the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The designs were clearly printed from relief
            plates and on wove paper watermarked 1811. They were not, however, printed from Blake’s
            relief plates. They appear to have been part of an aborted facsimile project modeled
            after Blake’s copy C and possibly produced by keriography, c. 1870 (see Viscomi,
                <i>Blake and the Idea of the Book</i> 198-216). </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="29.fb.exh" id="29">
        <title>

        </title>
        <caption>29. Once the bogus copies were removed from the canon, the remaining genuine
            impressions revealed that Blake had abridged the twenty plate <i>No Natural Religion</i> to
            twelve plates from the book’s a and b series. Around 1794, he color printed enough
            impressions to form six copies (A, B, C, D, G, and M); the following year, he printed
            copy L, which comprised only the b series of plates and was part of his deluxe set of
            illuminated books. </caption>
    </image>
</exhibit>
