<exh.pngibit id="fakeblakesshort" title="Fake Blakes Short" article="fakeblakesshort.exh.pngibit.html"
    composition_date_string="September 2021">

    <image dbi="1.fb.exh.png" id="1">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Innocence
                copy T, Spring</p>
        </title>
        <caption>1. This impression of "Spring" is from *Songs of Innocence* copy T,
            which has no known provenance before it was sold anonymously at Hodgson amp Company’s
            book auction, 21 April 1910, lot 246. It was described as "title page plus 26 plates,
            coloured, printed on one side only; bound in old russia, blind tooled sides, gilt inner
            border, early copy before the numbering of the plates, 7 1/8 x 6 1/8." Where does <hi
                rend="i">Innocence</hi> copy T belong in the history of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>
            or <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>? .</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="2.fb.exh.png" id="2">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">three
                impressions of Spring</p>
        </title>
        <caption>2. The catalogue description of Innocence copy T raises a few red flags. The
            absence of numbers in the top right corner of the designs suggests an “early copy,” such
            as Innocence copy B, printed and colored in 1789, but the washes behind the text and the
            sheep drawn in at the right margin are features of late copies of illuminated books,
            those printed and colored in the last decade of Blake’s life, such as Songs copy U,
            printed and colored in 1818. Innocence copy T has 29 plates, not 27 as recorded in the
            catalogue, but all other copies of Innocence printed on one side of the leaves have 28
            plates. More troubling, it has plates 34, 35, and 36 (“Little Girl Lost” and “Little
            Girl Found”), the three plates that Blake moved to Experience in 1794 and are only in
            copies of Innocence with 31 plates, i. e., copies printed in 1789. Innocence copy T is
            slightly larger than early copies, but more troubling is that it follows the palette and
            placement of colors of Innocence copy B as well as copy B’s plate order. Both features
            are suspicious because Blake did not copy himself in these ways and all early copies of
            Innocence have unique plate orders. </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="3.fb.exh.png" id="3">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Four copies of l. black boy, details</p>
        </title>
        <caption>3. The anomalies of Innocence copy T force a closer look at its impressions to see if they were printed by Blake. They were unquestionably printed from Blake’s relief-etched plates, but the designs are slightly larger than in life time impressions, which is a sign they were printed posthumously on dry paper rather than damp and thus did not shrink like Blake’s impressions. Printing on dry paper was characteristic of Frederick Tatham’s practice, but not Blake’s or Catherine Blake’s (see Galleries 5 and 6)  
            
            A sure sign that copy T was posthumously printed is its impression of “The Little Black Boy.” The first of its two plates is in a second state. The mother’s hair and back were trimmed with a burin or scraper, as in Songs copy h, a posthumous copy printed by Tatham on paper watermarked 1831 and 1832 (lower case letters designate posthumous copies, but not all posthumous copies are so designated). In all life time impressions, such as Songs copies O and U, printed 1795 and 1818 respectively, the plate is in its first state, with back and hair untouched. 
            </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="4.fb.exh.png" id="4">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Innocence copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption>4. Songs of Innocence copy T is a forgery. It began as a copy of Songs posthumously printed by Tatham on Whatman paper in black ink, c. 1831-32. The copy initially had 53 plates, missing plates 15 and 53, but probably including “A Divine Image.” It was one of six complete copies of Songs that Tatham had abridged to 40-42 plates, c. 1832-40, by extracting a cluster of 12 to 14 Experience plates (see Viscomi, “Posthumous Blake”). 
            
            Someone, probably a dealer, acquired the abridged copy and extracted the remaining Experience plates to transform it into a near complete copy of Innocence and had the impressions colored and ordered in imitation of Innocence copy B. Subtracting impressions to make a complete looking copy of Innocence was easier than finding and adding the missing Experience impressions to build a complete copy of Songs, and, in turn, a complete colored copy of Innocence was more lucrative financially than an incomplete monochrome copy of Songs, let alone one recognizably posthumous. 
            
            The dealer may have assumed that the impressions were life-time; nevertheless, the actions performed on Innocence copy T were done with the intent to deceive, which makes the copy a forgery. 
            
            The provenance of the forgery’s model, Innocence copy B, is unknown between 1834, at the death of R. H. Clarke, its first known owner, and 1906, when it was sold anonymously at Sotheby’s to the book dealer Robson. Innocence copy T was unknown until 1910, when it sold anonymously at Hodgson’s as “coloured by Blake.” The creation of copy T appears to have occurred between 1906 and 1910. Copy T was given to Princeton University Library in 1984 as a life time copy and unmasked in 1993 (see Viscomi, Blake and the Idea of the Book, 244-9). 
        </caption>
      
    </image>
    <image dbi="5.fb.exh.png" id="5">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Songs copy e/K, Black Boy pl. 2 and To Tirzah</p>
        </title>
        <caption>5. Pierpont Morgan bought a complete 54 plate copy of Songs in 1901 from James Toovey, a well-known and respected book dealer. It comprised 40 impressions printed in sepia, now designated as Songs copy e, and 14 impressions printed in brown ink extracted from a set of uncolored Experience impressions, now designated as Songs copy K. The sepia and brown impressions were printed by different printers and colored long after they were printed, possibly by different colorists. 
            
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="6.fb.exh.png" id="6">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I:
                Introduction</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="7.fb.exh.png" id="7">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I:
                Introduction</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="8.fb.exh.png" id="8">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I:
                Introduction</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>

    <image dbi="9.fb.exh.png" id="9">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="10.fb.exh.png" id="10">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="11.fb.exh.png" id="11">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="12.fb.exh.png" id="12">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="13.fb.exh.png" id="13">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="14.fb.exh.png" id="14">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="15.fb.exh.png" id="15">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="16.fb.exh.png" id="16">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery
                II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>

    <image dbi="17.fb.exh.png" id="17">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="18.fb.exh.png" id="18">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="19.fb.exh.png" id="19">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="20.fb.exh.png" id="20">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="21.fb.exh.png" id="21">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="22.fb.exh.png" id="22">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="23.fb.exh.png" id="23">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p>
        </title>
        <caption>"posthumously colored in imitation of *Innocence* copy B in the late 19th century
            or early 20th century"</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="24.fb.exh.png" id="24">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy <span
                    style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="25.fb.exh.png" id="25">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy <span
                    style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="26.fb.exh.png" id="26">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy <span
                    style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="27.fb.exh.png" id="27">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy <span
                    style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="28.fb.exh.png" id="28">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy <span
                    style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
    <image dbi="29.fb.exh.png" id="29">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV:
                    <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy <span
                    style="text-transform:none">e</span>/K</p>
        </title>
        <caption/>
    </image>
</exh.pngibit>
