<bad id="but442.1" type="wc" work="Pestilence: Death of the First-Born" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="boston" catalog="butlin" catid="442" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born"><main>Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 89KB to 1600KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages illustrated.  They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings.  The present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and 1805.  These designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine.  In works such as <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive.  In other designs, including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction.
            <lb/><lb/>
            This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible.  In coming months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series executed for Butts.  Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> of c. 1824.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2010 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>September 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>April 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>30.4 x 34.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>30.4 x 34.2 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color over pencil</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name><date>1890</date><dealer>Bernard Quaritch</dealer><price>$5,000 for the group of 32 works by Blake (see the note  
               on provenance below)</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1805; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 119 (£1.1s. to John Clark Strange); the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, in item 13,842 with 31 other works by Blake in three volumes (£1,200), in the same group at the same price in Quaritch's advertising flyer of <hi rend="i">William Blake's Original Drawings</hi> of May 1885 and Nov. 1886, and in Quaritch's <hi rend="i">General Catalogue of Books</hi> of 1887, item 13,842, in the same group (£1,200); one of the "Nine large Drawings to illustrate the Bible" offered with the same group of three volumes of works by Blake in Quaritch's 1890 <hi rend="i">Hand-List of a Peerless Collection of Books and Manuscripts Exhibited to the Bibliophiles of America</hi>, item 156 ($5,000); the entire group in three volumes sold by Quaritch in 1890 to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution><addressline>Avenue of the Arts</addressline><addressline>465 Huntington Avenue</addressline><addressline>Boston, Massachusetts 02115-5597</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-617-267-9300</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.mfa.org/</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Digital Image Resources: 1-617-369-4339</addressline><addressline>Fax, Digital Image Resources: 1-617-437-7471</addressline><addressline>Email, Digital Image Resources: mfaimages@mfa.org</addressline><department>Prints, Drawings, and Photographs</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">90.106</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but442.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT442.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 442)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>30.4 x 34.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="700" height="670"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This water color illustrates Exodus 12:21-3, the tenth plague of Egypt and the deaths of the first-born children. Dominating the design is a large figure, a personification of Pestilence. This figure is male and nude, and covered with scales. There are wispy wing-like protrusions along his torso, upper legs, feet, and right arm. The lower half of his body faces left, while the upper half is twisted to face forward, and he turns his head to look slightly to the right. His right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe to indicate that he is mid-stride. His arms are raised horizontally, palms down. There appears to be liquid flowing from the palms of both hands, probably representing the disease he is spreading. He also has short, flame-like hair and may be smiling or speaking. Between the giant figure's legs is an angel, standing in the background. The angel stands in a doorway, is possibly female, has wings and wears a gown. She also has short, curly hair. She faces forward and slightly right and holds her arms at her sides. She stands, perhaps looking at the giant, and her mouth may be slightly open in surprise or shock, or she may be speaking.
  In the foreground on the left of the design is a group of three figures. The leftmost figures in the left foreground are emerging from a doorway. The figure in the doorway is female. She has long hair and stands facing right and slightly forward. She wears a gown and has her arms raised at 135 degrees, with the fingers of her left hand spread. Her mouth is open, suggesting she is speaking or, more probably, shouting or screaming. She bends forward slightly as she looks at the figure to the right. The middle figure of this group is an old man, facing right. He has a beard and wears a gown. In his right arm, which is bent, he carries a lit torch. His knees are bent and his right leg extended backward to indicate forward movement. He bends forward slightly and may be looking at the group of figures to his right. The rightmost figure of this group is that of a young man, gowned from the waist down, who kneels, facing right and with his head thrown back and face looking upward. His right arm is bent but dangling at his side and his mouth is open, suggesting he may be speaking or crying out in pain. He has short, curly hair. He may be dying. 
  In the center of the foreground is a group of two figures. The figure to the left is a male youth who lies, supine, with his legs together and his arm at his side. He may wear a gown and has short, curly hair. His eyes are closed. He may be dead. The figure to the right is a woman who kneels and bends forward to face left and slightly forward. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her left arm is bent upward so that her hand rests, palm up, on the ground next to the dead man's head. She rests her head on his chest and has her mouth open. She may be speaking, praying or crying. In the right foreground of the design is a group of five figures. The leftmost figure of this group may be a young man, partly clothed with a cloth secured around his waist. He kneels and leans backward with his face upward. His arm is bent, with his hand on the ground, palm down. He has short, curly hair. The second-to-left figure is that of a woman with long, curly hair pulled up into a bun. She faces left and slightly forward, and looks down at the kneeling figure to the left, with her mouth open. She may be surprised, speaking or screaming. Her left leg is bent and she bends slightly forward. She wears a gown and has her arms crossed. In her arms, she holds an infant. It faces left and forward and wears a gown. Its arms are at its sides and it may have short, curly hair. Its eyes are open and it may be smiling. The second-to-right figure in this group is that of an infant, probably dead, of indeterminable gender. The infant lies in what may be its mother's arms and faces left and up. Its head is back, drooping over the mother's left arm, and its eyes are closed. Its arm hangs limply. The rightmost figure is that of a female, wearing a gown and with long hair or a veil over her hair. She faces left and turns her head to face forward. Her left arm is bent to hold a dead infant. Her mouth is open as she looks at the infant. On the left and right sides of the design, and in the center background, are three buildings, each with open doorways and squared pillars or pilasters. Four square windows may also be visible. In the background, to either side of the giant, are large pyramids. The scene takes place at night and thus is dark. The night sky is cloudy.    
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disease</characteristic><characteristic>Pestilence</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><characteristic>poison</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dominating the design is a large figure, a personification of Pestilence. This figure is male and nude, covered in scales and has wispy wing-like protrusions along his torso, upper legs, feet, and right arm.  These wispy forms may represent diseases. The lower half of his body faces left, while the upper half is twisted to face forward, and he turns his head to look slightly to the right. His right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe to indicate that he is mid-stride. His arms are raised horizontally, palms down. Liquid appears to flow from both palms. He also has short, flame-like hair and may be smiling or speaking.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between Pestilence's legs is an angel, standing in the background. The angel stands in a doorway, is perhaps female, has wings and wears a gown. She also has short, curly hair. She faces forward and slightly right and holds her arms at her sides. She may be looking at the giant, and her mouth may be slightly open suggesting surprise, shock or that she is speaking.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>screaming</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground on the left side of the design is a group of three figures. The leftmost figures are emerging from a doorway. The figure in the doorway is female. She has long hair and stands facing right and slightly forward. She wears a gown and has her arms raised at 135 degrees, with the fingers of her left hand spread. Her mouth is open, suggesting that she is surprised, or speaking or, more probably, shouting or screaming. She bends forward slightly as she looks at the figures to the right.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>torch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground on the left side of the design is a group of three figures. The middle figure of this group is an old man, facing right. He has a beard and wears a gown. In his right arm, which is bent, he carries a lit torch. His knees are bent and his right leg extended backward to indicate his forward movement. He bends forward slightly and may be looking at the group of figures to the right.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>dying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>pain</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground on the left side of the design is a group of three figures. The rightmost figure of this group is a young man, gowned from the waist down, who kneels, facing right and with his head thrown back to face up. His right arm is bent but dangling at his side and his mouth is open; he may be speaking or crying out in pain. He has short, curly hair. He may be dying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the foreground is a group of two figures. The figure to the left is a male who lies, supine, with his legs together and his arm at his side. He may wear a gown and has short, curly hair. His eyes are closed. He may be dead. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the foreground is a group of two figures. The figure to the right is a woman who kneels and bends forward to face left and slightly forward. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her left arm is bent upward so that her hand rests on the ground, palm up, next to (and perhaps holding) the dead man's head. She rests her head on his chest and has her mouth open. She may be speaking, praying or crying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>dying</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right foreground of the design is a group of five figures. The leftmost figure of this group may be that of a young man, partly clothed with a cloth secured around his waist. He kneels and leans backward, his face turned upward. His arm is bent, with his hand on the ground, palm down. He has short, curly hair. He may be dying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>screaming</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right foreground of the design is a group of five figures. The second-to-left figure is that of a woman with long, curly hair pulled up into a bun. She faces left and slightly forward, and looks down at the kneeling figure to the left, with her mouth open. She may be surprised, speaking or screaming. Her left leg is bent and she bends slightly forward. She wears a gown and has her arms crossed. She may be the mother of the infant she holds. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right foreground of the design is a group of five figures. The third figure from the left in this group is an infant of indeterminable gender, sitting in what may be its mother's arms. It faces left and forward and wears a gown. Its arms are at its sides and it may have short, curly hair. Its eyes are open and it may be smiling.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right foreground of the design is a group of five figures. The second-to-right figure in this group is that of a dead infant of indeterminable gender. The infant lies in its mother's arms and faces left and up. Its head is back, drooping over the mother's arm and its eyes are closed. Its arm hangs limply. It may wear a gown.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right foreground of the design is a group of five figures. The rightmost figure is that of a female, wearing a gown and with long hair or a veil over her hair. She faces left and turns her head to face forward. She may be the mother of the infant she holds. Her mouth is open as she looks at the infant. She may be surprised, speaking or crying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>temple</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left and right sides of the design, and in the center background are three buildings, each with open doorways and squared pillars or pilasters. The buildings left and right may be houses; the building in the background may be a temple. The base of the temple may be a step or plinth. Four square windows may also be visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>pyramid</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the background, to either side of the giant, are large pyramids.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place at night and thus is dark.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The night sky is cloudy.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but442.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">inv</l><l n="but442.1.wc.01.02" justify="left">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>