<bad id="but497.1" type="wc" work="The Crucifixion: 'Behold Thy Mother'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="497" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Crucifixion: 'Behold Thy Mother'"><main>The Crucifixion: "Behold Thy Mother"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 9KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 72KB to 834KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2011 Tate Collection</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>May 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>July 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition and metadata collection</change><date>March 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">The Crucifixion: "Behold Thy Mother"</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>41.3 x 30.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>41.3 x 30.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Tate Collection</name><date>1949</date><dealer>none recorded</dealer><price>£1,155</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1805; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; offered from the Butts collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 124, with Blake's water color, <hi rend="i">The Entombment</hi>" (not sold; bought-in at £1.10s.), and at Foster and Son, 8 March 1854, lot 14, with two other works by Blake (not sold; bought-in at 10s.); by inheritance in 1862 to Captain Frederick J. Butts; his widow; sold April 1906 through Carfax &amp; Co. to W. Graham Robertson; sold from his collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 34 (£1,155 to the executors of Robertson's estate for presentation through the National Art Collections Fund to the Tate Gallery, now Tate Collection).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Tate Collection</institution><addressline>Millbank</addressline><addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7887 8888</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Images: +44 (0)20 7887 8871</addressline><addressline>Fax, Images: +44 (0)20 7887 8805</addressline><addressline>Email, Images: picture.library@tate.org.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">N 05895 / B 497</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but497.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT497.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Crucifixion: "Behold Thy Mother"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 497)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower left with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>41.3 x 30.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="700" height="800"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is based on John 19:25-27. In the center hangs Jesus on a cross, with nails through each hand and his feet and hints of blood around those nails. He faces forward and looks down, wearing only a loincloth and a crown of thorns. His arms are raised horizontally and his feet are touching. He has long, slightly curly hair and a beard. Jesus also emanates a halo-like aura around his head. Jesus hangs on a wooden cross with the letters "INRI" on the top. To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. Only the top of the head, facing right, is visible of the leftmost figure. Only the head, facing right and slightly down, is visible of the second-to-left figure, which is probably female, given the veil covering her hair. The third-to-left figure is that of a female with long, curly hair. She faces right and has her head down. Her right leg is bent slightly and her arms are bent upward, with her hands on her face. She leans on the shoulder of the figure to the right and may be crying. The fourth-to-left figure is that of a female with long, curly hair, facing away and to the left. Her head is slightly down and her left arm is bent. Her left leg is bent slightly and extended backward slightly. The fourth-to-right figure is visible only has a head, perhaps with long hair and a head veil, looking right. The third-to-right figure is a female facing right and looking up to Christ. Her right leg is bent and extended backward slightly. She wears a veil over her long hair, which is slightly curly. Her arms are bent upward, palms together as though in prayer or supplication. She is probably the Virgin Mary, given the slight aura that emanates from her. The second-to-right figure is that of a female with long, perhaps curly, hair and a head veil, facing right and down. The rightmost figure is that of a female with long, curly hair, facing right and down. Her arms are bent upward and her hands are on her face. She may be crying. This may be either Mary, the wife of Cleophas, or Mary Magdalene (see John 19:25). To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The leftmost figure is that of a female with long hair, facing left, down, and slightly away. Her right arm is at her side, but may be bent. She may be crying as she leans against the cross. This is may be either Mary, the wife of Cleophas, or Mary Magdalene. Only the top of the head of the second-to-left figure is visible, facing left. The third-to-left figure faces forward and slightly left, looking up at Jesus. He has short, curly hair and crosses his arms. He appears to be crying. This is the "disciple" addressed by Christ (John 19:27) and is probably represented here as John the apostle. The fourth-to-left figure is only visible as the top of a head, facing left and down. The third-to-right figure may be a male with short, curly hair, facing left and down. His face is covered, and he may be crying. The second-to-right figure faces right and down slightly. Its gender is indeterminable, but it has curly hair, and holds its arms bent upward with its hands on its face. The figure may be crying. The rightmost figure is a male, partly bald, who faces right and down. The sky is dark and cloudy, indicating that day has turned to night at the Crucifixion on the mount of Calvary. Streaks of light in the sky suggest lightning. A slight pink wash in the sky near the cross may indicate sunrise or sunset. The figures stand on a patch of bare earth.  
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>thorn</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><characteristic>dying</characteristic><characteristic>crucified</characteristic><characteristic>nail</characteristic><characteristic>blood</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>feet touching</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design hangs Jesus on a cross, with nails through each hand and his feet and hints of blood around those nails. He faces forward and looks down, wearing only a loincloth and a crown of thorns. His arms are raised horizontally and his feet are touching. He has long, slightly curly hair and a beard. Jesus also emanates a halo-like aura around his head. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cross</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus hangs on a wooden cross with the letters "INRI" on the top. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. Only the top of the head, facing right, is visible of the leftmost figure. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. Only the head, facing right and slightly downturned is visible of the second-to-left figure, which is probably female, given the veil covering her hair. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The third-to-left figure is that of a female with long, curly hair. She faces right and has her head down. Her right leg is bent slightly and her arms are bent upward, with her hands on her face. She leans on the shoulder of the figure to the right and may be crying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The fourth-to-left figure is that of a female with long, curly hair, facing awsay and to the left. Her head is slightly down and her left arm is bent. Her left leg is bent slightly and extended backward slightly. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The fourth-to-right figure is visible only has a head, perhaps with long hair and a head veil, looking right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The third-to-right figure is a female facing right and looking up to Christ. Her right leg is bent and extended backward slightly. She wears a veil over her long hair, which is slightly curly. Her arms are bent upward, palms together as though in prayer or supplication. She is probably the Virgin Mary, given the aura that emanates from her. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The second-to-right figure is that of a female with long, perhaps curly, hair and a head veil, facing right and down. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>Mary, wife of Cleophas</characteristic><characteristic>Mary Magdalene</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The rightmost figure is that of a female with long, curly hair, facing right and down. Her arms are bent upward and her hands are on her face. She may be crying. This is may be either Mary, the wife of Cleophas, or Mary Magdalene.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>Mary, wife of Cleophas</characteristic><characteristic>Mary Magdalene</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The leftmost figure is that of a female with long hair, facing left, down, and slightly away. Her right arm is at her side, but may be bent. She may be crying as she leans against the cross. This is may be either Mary, the wife of Cleophas, or Mary Magdalene.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. Only the top of the head of the second-to-left figure is visible, facing left. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The fourth-to-left figure is only visible as the top of a head, facing left and down. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>John</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The third-to-left figure faces forward and slightly left, looking up at Jesus. He has short, curly hair and crosses his arms. He appears to be crying. This is the "disciple" addressed by Christ (John 19:27) and is probably represented here as John the apostle.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The fourth-to-left figure is sketchy and may face left. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The third-to-right figure may be a male with short, curly hair, facing left and down. His face is covered, perhaps with his gown-covered hands to his face, and he may be crying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The second-to-right figure faces right and down slightly. Its gender is indeterminable, but it has curly hair, and holds its arms bent upward with its hands on its face. This figure may be crying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the cross stand at least eight gowned figures. The rightmost figure is a male, partly bald, who faces right and down. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>lightning</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>Calvary</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky is dark and cloudy, indicating that day has turned to night at the Crucifixion on the mount of Calvary. Streaks of light in the sky suggest lightning. A slight pink wash in the sky near the cross may indicate sunrise or sunset. The figures stand on a patch of bare earth.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but497.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="18">INRI</l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but497.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="11">inv</l><l n="but497.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="10">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>