<bad id="lt23oct1804.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="wilson" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-23oct1804"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804"><main>Letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 25.2KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 276KB
                to 1200KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to his trial for sedition.
                <lb/>
                The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the next stage of Blake’s life.  <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;    <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.   <lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.   <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.  
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2014 Wilson Library, University of North Carolina. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>December 2013-January 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1804.N">1804</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.<note>Dimensions unknown from original manuscript; given
                        dimensions refer to the photographed page of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
                            of William Blake</hi> volume 1; see note on Provenance in the Work
                        Information.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1<note>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript
                        letter by Blake, now lost. The letter begins near the top third of page 215
                        (object 1) and ends near the bottom of page 216 (object 2) of the revised
                        1880 edition of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William
                            Blake</hi> volume 1, described in the note on Provenance in the Work
                        Information. The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to
                        Blake in his letter to Hayley of 23 October 1804, which is surrounded by
                        biographical text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly
                        including the hands of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others
                        (see also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages 24-27). The text not
                        attributed to Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page. Page 215
                        (object 1) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to Hayley,
                        28 September 1804, which is now in the Library of Congress and can be
                        accessed through the Index of Letters.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink manuscript lost; <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> volume
                    1 is a letterpress book</medium><inkcolor>unknown from original manuscript; <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>
                    volume 1 is printed in black ink</inkcolor><support>unknown from original manuscript; <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>
                    volume 1 is printed on laid paper</support><watermark>unknown from original manuscript; leaf containing pages 215 and 216
                    (objects 1 and 2) includes the countermark "TDEB" in a top corner of the page;
                        <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> volume 1 printed on paper with a
                    large central watermark depicting a crown on top of a fleur-de-lis with
                    illegible cursive script at the bottom of the fleur-de-lis; countermarks
                    appearing in the volume include “TDEB”, “LDER”, and “VanG” </watermark><binding>bound in publisher's dark blue-green cloth, elaborately gilt stamped; a
                    small sticker on the recto of the last endpaper states "Bound by Burn &amp;
                    Co.”; the front cover design is based on a drawing in Blake's <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> that is now attributed to Blake's brother Robert (Bentley,
                        <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 1, page 13); the design on the spine is a
                    modified version of one of the angels in Blake's engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, object 16 </binding><postmark>unknown</postmark><sealDesc>unknown</sealDesc><addressee>William Hayley</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Rare Book Collection, Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</name><note>William Hayley; sold from the Hayley Correspondence, Sotheby's, 20 May 1878,
                    lot 23 (£6.14s to Quaritch); offered in Quaritch's 1880 General Catalogue
                    as part of Lot 12,803, which included Blake's letters to Hayley of 26 November
                    1800, 26 October 1803, 4 May 1804, 28 May 1804, 9 August 1804, 23 October 1804,
                    18 December 1804, 22 January 1805, 17 May 1805, 4 June 1805 (priced
                    £52.10s.); probably bought by Alexander MacMillan as part of group
                    advertised by Quaritch in 1880 (see Bentley, "A Checklist of Publications and
                    Discoveries in 1995," <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (Summer
                    2010), page 137n32); original manuscript untraced; letter only known from
                    printed transcription appearing in <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>
                    volume 1 (London: Macmillan, 1880).<lb/><lb/>The transcription of Blake’s letter
                    to William Hayley, 23 October 1804, was among the materials added in the revised
                    and expanded second edition (1880) of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of
                        William Blake, "Pictor Ignotus"</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863). Blake's
                    posthumous biographer Alexander Gilchrist died in 1861 before completing his
                    biography of Blake, which was finished by his wife, Anne Gilchrist, with
                    assistance from Dante Gabriel Rossetti and others (see also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages 24-27).<lb/><lb/> The title page of the
                    1880 volume containing the letter reads: "LIFE / OF / WILLIAM BLAKE / WITH
                    SELECTIONS FROM HIS POEMS AND OTHER WRITINGS / BY / ALEXANDER GILCHRIST / OF THE
                    MIDDLE TEMPLE, BARRISTER-AT-LAW / AUTHOR OF "THE LIFE OF WILLIAM ETTY, R.A." //
                    A NEW AND ENLARGED EDITION / ILLUSTRATED FROM BLAKE'S OWN WORKS / WITH
                    ADDITIONAL LETTERS AND A MEMOIR OF THE AUTHOR // IN TWO VOLUMES / VOL. 1 //
                    LONDON / MACMILLAN AND CO. / 1880 // The Right of Translation is Reserved". The
                    book was printed by R. Clay, Sons, and Taylor, Bread Street Hill,
                    London.<lb/><lb/>Images, object notes, and transcriptions are from a copy in the
                    Rare Book Collection of the Wilson Library at the University of North Carolina
                    at Chapel Hill. The copy photographed was owned by Annie G. Holden, and is
                    inscribed "Annie G. Holden / Xmas 1880" in brown ink on the recto of the first
                    flyleaf; later in the library of Tatton Henry Bower of Yorkshire (1867-1931),
                    whose armorial bookplate is also attached; the Wilson Library purchased this
                    copy from the dealer Claude Cox in 1978.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Wilson Library</institution><addressline>CB#3936 Wilson Library</addressline><addressline>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</addressline><addressline>Chapel Hill, NC 27514-8890</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 919-962-1143</addressline><addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: rbcref@email.unc.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.lib.unc.edu/rbc/</addressline><department>Rare Books, Special Collections</department><repositoryid label="Call number">PR4146 .G5 1880 C.1 V.1</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt23oct1804.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I received your kind letter with the note to Mr.
                    Payne</title> , <objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript letter by Blake,
                        now lost. The letter begins near the top third of page 215 (object 1) and
                        ends near the bottom of page 216 (object 2) of the revised 1880 edition of
                        Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> volume 1,
                        described in the note on Provenance in the Work Information.</p><p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to Blake in his
                        letter to Hayley of 23 October 1804, which is surrounded by biographical
                        text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly including the hands
                        of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to
                        Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page.</p><p>Page 215 (object 1) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to
                        Hayley, 28 September 1804, which is now in the Library of Congress and can
                        be accessed through the Index of Letters.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="13"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="42">23<hi rend="i">rd
                            Oct</hi>. 1804.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="2">DEAR SIR,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="7">I received your kind
                        letter with the note to Mr. Payne, and</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left">have had the cash from him. I
                        should have returned my thanks</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left">immediately on receipt of it, but
                        hoped to be able to send, before</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.06" justify="left">now, proofs of the two plates, the
                            <hi rend="i">Head</hi> of R. and the <hi rend="i">Shipwreck</hi>,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.07" justify="left">which you shall soon see in a much
                        more perfect state. I write</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.08" justify="left">immediately because you wish I
                        should do so, to satisfy you that</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.09" justify="left">I have received your kind
                        favour.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.10" justify="left" indent="2">I take the extreme
                        pleasure of expressing my joy at our good</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.11" justify="left">Lady of Lavant's continued
                        recovery, but with a mixture of sincere</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.12" justify="left">sorrow on account of the beloved
                        Councillor. My wife returns her</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.13" justify="left">heartfelt thanks for your kind
                        inquiry concerning her health. She is</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.14" justify="left">surprisingly recovered.
                        Electricity is the wonderful cause; the swell-</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.15" justify="left">ing of her legs and knees is
                        entirely reduced. She is very near as</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.16" justify="left">free from rheumatism as she was
                        five years ago, and we have the</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.17" justify="left">greatest confidence in her perfect
                        recovery.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.18" justify="left" indent="2">The pleasure of seeing
                        another poem from your hands has</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.19" justify="left">truly set me longing (my wife says
                        I ought to have said us) with</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.20" justify="left">desire and curiosity; but,
                        however, "Christmas is a coming."</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.21" justify="left" indent="2">Our good and kind
                        friend Hawkins is not yet in town—hope</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.22" justify="left">soon to have the pleasure of
                        seeing him—with the courage of con-</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.23" justify="left">scious industry, worthy of his
                        former kindness to me. For now!</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.24" justify="left">O Glory! and O Delight! I have
                        entirely reduced that spectrous</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.25" justify="left">Fiend to his station, whose
                        annoyance has been the ruin of my</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.26" justify="left">labours for the last passed twenty
                        years of my life. He is the</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.27" justify="left">enemy of conjugal love, and is the
                        Jupiter of the Greeks, an iron-</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.28" justify="left">hearted tyrant, the ruiner of
                        ancient Greece. I speak with perfect</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.29" justify="left">confidence and certainty of the
                        fact which has passed upon me.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.01.30" justify="left">Nebuchadnezzar had seven times
                        passed over him, I have had</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt23oct1804.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">cont.</title> , <objid><objnumber code="A1">object 2</objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript letter by Blake,
                        now lost. The letter begins near the top third of page 215 (object 1) and
                        ends near the bottom of page 216 (object 2) of the revised 1880 edition of
                        Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> volume 1,
                        described in the note on Provenance in the Work Information.</p><p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to Blake in his
                        letter to Hayley of 23 October 1804, which is surrounded by biographical
                        text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly including the hands
                        of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to
                        Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">twenty; thank God I was not
                        altogether a beast as he was; but I</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left">was a slave bound in a mill among
                        beasts and devils; these beasts</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">and these devils are now, together
                        with myself, become children of</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">light and liberty, and my feet and
                        my wife's feet are free from fetters.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">O lovely Felpham, parent of
                        Immortal Friendship, to thee I am</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">eternally indebted for my three
                        years' rest from perturbation and</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">the strength I now enjoy.
                        Suddenly, on the day after visiting the</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">Truchsessian Gallery of Pictures,
                        I was again enlightened with the</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">light I enjoyed in my youth, and
                        which has for exactly twenty years</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">been closed from me as by a door
                        and by window-shutters. Conse-</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">quently I can, with confidence,
                        promise you ocular demonstration</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">of my altered state on the plates
                        I am now engraving after Romney,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">whose spiritual aid has not a
                        little conduced to my restoration to the</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left">light of Art. O the distress I
                        have undergone, and my poor wife</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left">with me. Incessantly labouring and
                        incessantly spoiling what I had</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left">done well. Every one of my friends
                        was astonished at my faults,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left">and could not assign a reason;
                        they knew my industry and ab-</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left">stinence from every pleasure for
                        the sake of study, and yet—and yet</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.19" justify="left">—and yet there wanted the
                        proofs of industry in my works. I</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.20" justify="left">thank God with entire confidence
                        that it shall be so no longer:</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.21" justify="left">—he is become my servant who
                        domineered over me, he is even as</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.22" justify="left">a brother who was my enemy. Dear
                        Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.23" justify="left">rather madness, for I am really
                        drunk with intellectual vision when-</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.24" justify="left">ever I take a pencil or graver
                        into my hand, even as I used to be</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.25" justify="left">in my youth, and as I have not
                        been for twenty dark, but very profitable,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.26" justify="left">years. I thank God that I
                        courageously pursued my course through</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.27" justify="left">darkness. In a short time I shall
                        make my assertion good that I</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.28" justify="left">am become suddenly as I was at
                        first, by producing the <hi rend="i">Head of</hi></l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.29" justify="left"><hi rend="i">Romney</hi> and the
                            <hi rend="i">Shipwreck</hi> quite another thing from what you or</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.30" justify="left">I ever expected them to be. In
                        short, I am now satisfied and proud</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.31" justify="left">of my work, which I have not been
                        for the above long period.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.32" justify="left" indent="2">If our excellent and
                        manly friend Meyer is yet with you, please</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.33" justify="left">to make my wife's and my own most
                        respectful and affectionate</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.34" justify="left">compliments to him, also to our
                        kind friend at Lavant.</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.35" justify="left" indent="3">I remain, with my
                        wife's joint affection,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.36" justify="left" indent="24">Your sincere and
                        obliged servant,</l><l n="lt23oct1804.1.ltr.02.37" justify="left" indent="45">WILL. BLAKE.</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>