<exhibit id="absorbedbythepoets" title="&quot;Absorbed by the Poets&quot;"
    article="absorbedbythepoets.exhibit.html" composition_date_string="April 2024">
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.1" id="1">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 1: Reconstructing Hayley’s Turret House</p>
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">1. George Romney, <i>Flaxman Modeling the Bust of William
                    Hayley</i></p> c. 1795-6. Oil on canvas. Yale Center for British Art, New Haven.
                <p><br/>Hayley was an amateur physician, dispensing quack remedies to his friends
                and neighbours, and enthusiastically practicing and advocating sea-bathing as a
                cure-all treatment. Prompted by the frequent bouts of ill health suffered by his son
                in 1796, Hayley conceived of a dual-purpose residence near the coast:</p>
            <blockquote>I am finishing my little marine villa, in a comfortable hope that it will be
                singularly beneficial to the recovery of my dear artist, and we shall render it, I
                believe, so commodious, that it may even serve me for a winter residence.<sup><a
                        class="footnote">5<span>See Elizabeth Johnston, <i>For Friendship’s Sake,
                                William Blake and William Hayley</i>, (Manchester
                    1969).</span></a></sup></blockquote>
            <p>Thomas Alphonso was Hayley’s only child, born out of wedlock to the daughter of
                Hayley’s nursemaid, Sarah Betts. From a young age, Thomas Alphonso demonstrated an
                interest in art and became a pupil of both George Romney and John Flaxman. In this
                painting, Thomas Alphonso stands with his back to the viewer, assisting Flaxman in
                sculpting a gigantic bust of his father, who faces the viewer. Behind Hayley, Romney
                peers smirking above his easel. Thomas Alphonso’s contrapposto pose hints at the
                curvature of spine that contributed to his early death in May 1800.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.2" id="2">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">2. William Blake, <i>Thomas Alphonso Hayley</i></p> ca. 1800.
            Graphite on paper. Yale Center for British Art, New Haven. <p>
                <br/>This may have been a preparatory drawing for a more finished study or for an
                engraving. The drawing depicts Thomas Alphonso standing behind a table with a finger
                resting on his chin and holding a classical statue to signify the subject’s status
                as a sculptor. On the table is a scroll bearing “EPISTLES to John Flaxman Sculptor”.
                It is possible that Hayley wanted this image engraved for his poem, An <i>Essay on
                    Sculpture</i> (1800), which was dedicated to Flaxman and contains three
                engravings by Blake,<a
                    href="https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/bb467.1?descId=bb467.1.comeng.03"
                    target="blank"> including a portrait of Thomas Alphonso in profile after
                    Flaxman’s medallion of his pupil.</a> It is also conceivable that Blake made
                this drawing after the death of Thomas Alphonso to illustrate a biography that
                Hayley was writing during the first few years of the nineteenth
                    century.<sup><a class="footnote">6<span>Hayley’s biography of Thomas Alphonso appeared in the second volume
                    of Hayley’s own <i>Memoirs</i>, posthumously published in 1823. </span></a></sup>
            </p>
            <p> Hayley selected Felpham for the location of Thomas Alphonso’s 'Marine villa' as it
                was close to his own home at Eartham and a short walk from the English Channel,
                allowing him to be both close to his son and for Thomas Alphonso to enjoy daily
                sea-bathing sessions. Hayley contacted Flaxman and the architect responsible for
                George Romney’s studio, Samuel Bunce, about the project, proposing a circular
                    structure.<sup><a class="footnote">7<span>Bunce was also architect to the admiralty during this period. See
                    H. Colvin, <i>Biographical Dictionary of Architects, 1600-1840,</i> 2nd Edn.
                    (London, 1978) 15.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.3" id="3">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">3. John Flaxman, <i>Marine villa</i></p> Pen on paper. Flaxman
            to Hayley, 11 September 1796. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. <p>
                <br/>In a letter to Hayley of 11 September 1796, Flaxman reports that he and Bunce,
                whom he refers to as “the man of Capitals &#38; Cornices”, had recently “held a
                council concerning your intended building”.<sup><a class="footnote">8<span>Flaxman to Hayley of 11 Sept 1796 f.
                    3.</span></a></sup> Following Hayley’s suggestion, their initial proposal was a circular
                tower comprising three floors, a wraparound balcony on the first floor, and a
                vestibule leading to an internal staircase. In his letter, Flaxman includes three
                sketches depicting the front, oblique, and plan perspectives of the tower and notes
                that “the circle ‘tho a beautiful figure is much better suited to many other
                Architectural purposes than the conveniences of a dwelling, yet according to your
                idea I think it may be well employed”. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.4" id="4">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">4. Samuel Bunce, <i>First Design</i></p> Bunce to Hayley, 31
            March 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. <p>
                <br/>Writing to Hayley on 31 March 1797, Bunce optimistically states, “your building
                will not take more than between two &#38; three months.”<sup><a class="footnote">9<span>Fitzwilliam Museum
                    Hayley Letters, XXXII, fol. 2.</span></a></sup> The following month, Bunce sent Hayley a
                modified plan of the ‘Marine villa’ that incorporates Flaxman’s circular tower and
                internal staircase. This plan indicates that the new house was designed around the
                library, a circular room that was perhaps modelled after Horace Walpole’s at
                Strawberry Hill.<sup><a class="footnote">10<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley Letters, XXXII, fol. 5.</span></a></sup> The
                proposed library is located on the upper floor and was to be subdivided into two
                floors. A side elevation shows that there would be six windows on each floor, with a
                fireplace on the northern aspect of the room and chimney breasts on both floors.
                This early plan also indicates that the remainder of the house would comprise three
                ground-floor rooms, a kitchen and parlour, with the third room under the library
                left for Hayley to decide upon. Whether it was due to expense or taste, this plan
                was rejected.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.5" id="5">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">5. Samuel Bunce, <i>Second Design</i></p> Bunce to Hayley, 29
            April 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. <p>
                <br/>Bunce sent a series of revised plans to Hayley a month later. These plans are
                drawn on the verso of a sheet of paper included with Bunce’s letter to Hayley of 29
                April 1797 and demonstrate the importance of the library in the overall design of
                the dwelling.<sup><a class="footnote">11<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley Letters, XXXII, fol. 3.</span></a></sup> The
                redesigned "Marine villa" was a rectangular structure with a rectangular library
                again located on the second floor. The first sketched plan situates the library
                running the entire length of the northern aspect of the house. It is the largest
                room in the house and contains a fireplace opposite the only door. There is a window
                in each aspect.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.6" id="6">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">6. Samuel Bunce, <i>Third Design</i></p> Bunce to Hayley, 29
            April 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. <p><br/>In the same packet, Bunce sent a
                second set of plans labeled ground floor and upper floor. These plans include
                measurements and room designations.<sup><a class="footnote">12<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley Letters XXXII fol.
                    3.</span></a></sup> The plans depict a two-floor structure with external measurements of
                10.3 m by 8.2 m. The structure is divided centrally by a narrow corridor that
                terminates in a turret on the south aspect. Either side of the corridor is a wing
                that is subdivided into rooms. The ground-floor west wing comprises two rooms, a
                kitchen on the southern aspect, measuring 5.4 m by 3.9 m and a storeroom on the
                northern aspect, measuring 4.2 m by 3 m. The east wing is also divided into two
                rooms, a dining room on the southern aspect, measuring 4.5 m by 3.9 m, and a
                workroom on the northern aspect, measuring 4.2 m by 3 m. </p>
            <p> The upper storey is also divided into two wings. The west wing comprises two
                bedchambers, the main bedchamber on the northern aspect and a smaller, secondary
                bedchamber on the southern aspect. There is also a closet, measuring 1.5 m by 1.8 m,
                located at the northern end of the central corridor. The majority of the central
                corridor, an area measuring 4.2 m by 1.8 m comprises the library, which occupies the
                entire east wing of the upper storey. The library measures 7.9 m by 3.9 m, which,
                including the recess of 4.2 m by 1.8 m, equates to 128.6 m<sup>2</sup> making it the
                largest room in the house. There are three doors leading from the library to the
                closet, the main bedchamber and the stairs. A door from the stairs leads to the
                smaller bedchamber. The library and the two bedchambers each contain fireplaces. The
                fireplace in the library is located on the north aspect. Thomas Alphonso made
                several sculptural busts for the library’s fireplace, including busts of Homer and
                    Milton.<sup><a class="footnote">13<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley letters, XXXII, fol. 24. Also see Hayley,
                        <i>Memoirs</i> 2:89, 354 and 359.</span></a></sup> The upper library also has four
                windows, three on the eastern aspect and one on the southern aspect. This design
                would allow more light to enter the library, particularly in the morning, than the
                earlier designs.<sup><a class="footnote">14<span>Throughout his correspondence with Bunce, Hayley is concerned
                    with the amount of light the library will receive. See Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley
                    letters, XXXII fol. 11.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.7" id="7">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">7. Samuel Bunce, <i>The Turret</i></p> Bunce to Hayley, 29
            July 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. <p><br/>Like the earlier plans, these revised
                plans include an internal staircase. The staircase is in a rectangular turret, which
                also forms part of the entrance and measures 2.1 m<sup>2</sup>. The doorway in the
                turret was constructed using three great stones, forming a trilithon. Bunce informs
                Hayley of the manner of construction: “There can be no better way than to lay other
                larger stones or rough flints up to the Trilithon to meet the arch”.<sup><a class="footnote">15<span>Fitzwilliam
                    Museum Hayley letters, XXXII, fol. 19.</span></a></sup> In the same letter, Bunce described
                the house as “the druidical seat”. Blake’s depiction of trilithons in <i>Milton</i>
                and <i>Jerusalem</i> may have been, in part, influenced by the entrance to Turret
                    House.<sup><a class="footnote">16<span>See <i>Milton</i> Copy A (https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/milton.a?descId=milton.a.illbk.04) and <i>Jerusalem</i> (https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/jerusalem.mpi?descId=jerusalem.mpi.illbk.27).</span></a></sup> During a visit to Hayley in 1811,
                William Godwin records his experiences climbing the turret: <blockquote>His house is
                    quite a toy. He has erected a turret on the top, with a corridor over that, for
                    the sake of the prospect, and to this corridor he climbs at least once everyday
                    by a ladder, which can only be descended by crawling backwards, and which, being
                    on the top of the house in the open air, looked to me frightful, but I escaped
                    without breaking either my neck or leg.<sup><a class="footnote">17<span>Godwin to Mary Jane Godwin, 31 Aug.
                        1811. Bodleian Library, Abinger Dep. c. 523 (unfoliated).</span></a></sup></blockquote>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.8" id="8">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">8. Samuel Bunce, <i>The Stained-Glass Window</i></p> Pencil on
            paper. Bunce to Hayley, 9 January 1798. Fitzwilliam Museum.<p><br/>The turret also
                housed a stained-glass window on the south aspect, with 1 metre diameter on the
                exterior and 1.05 m diameter on the interior, 0.6 m deep. With a south-facing
                aspect, the light that was refracted through the thick, multicoloured glass would
                have made entering the library a unique and possibly transcendent-like experience.
                The dazzling effects that this window produced, particularly on a sunny day, may
                have inspired Blake’s connection of Turret House to heaven in his poem addressed to
                “Anna Flaxman”: “The Ladder of Angels descends thro the air / On the Turret its
                spiral does softly descend” (Erdman page 709).</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.9" id="9">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">9. Samuel Bunce, <i>South aspect of Turret House</i></p>
            Pencil on paper. Bunce to Hayley 29 April 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum,
                Cambridge.<p><br/>Bunce’s sketch of the south aspect of Turret House depicts a
                two-floor structure with a three-storey tower. Bunce includes a balcony on the
                turret’s second floor supported by what appear to be columns. Thomas Alphonso laid
                the foundation stone for Turret House on 15 April 1797 watched by his father, Bunce,
                and George Romney.<sup><a class="footnote">18<span>Morchard Bishop, <i>Blake’s Hayley, the Life, Works, and
                        Friendships of William Hayley,</i> (London: Victor Gollancz, 1951)
                    212.</span></a></sup> While Turret House was demolished in the twentieth century,
                contemporaneous depictions by Blake and George Engleheart suggest that Bunce’s third
                design and this sketch of the south aspect were close to the final structure.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.10" id="10">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p stye="color: skyblue">10. William Blake, Landscape near Felpham ca. 1800.</p>Tate
                Britain.<p><br/>Blake’s unfinished pencil and watercolour sketch depicts the
            village of Felpham as viewed from the seashore. One of the few landscapes Blake ever
            created, the sketch shows one of Felpham’s two windmills in the left foreground.
            Hayley’s Turret House is visible in the center of the picture. A contemporary account of
            the village appears to describe the view that Blake painted:<blockquote>On the left the
                eye rests on a lengthened series of cornfields and meadows, extending from the
                village to the sea-side, bedecking the latter with a gay verdant mantle, even to the
                water’s edge. Behind those fields arise three or four excellent and commodious
                dwellings, shaded and embellished by clusters of trees; and what still enhances
                their merit, commanding a marine landscape in front, and an extensive land view in
                the rear.<sup><a class="footnote">19<span>J.B Davis, <i>The Origin and Description of Bognor or
                        Hothhampton,</i> (London 1807) 21.</span></a></sup></blockquote>
            </p><p>Blake’s cottage can be seen on the right of sketch, half hidden behind trees and
                illuminated by a shaft of sunlight. For Blake’s own depiction of his dottage, see <a
                    href="https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/milton.a?descId=milton.a.illbk.36"
                    target="_blank">Blake's cottage in <i>Milton</i></a></p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.11" id="11">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">11. Samuel Bunce, <i>The Coach house</i></p> Bunce to Hayley,
            28 June and 3 July 1798. Fitzwilliam Museum. <p><br/>In 1798 Bunce sent Hayley a series
                of sketches of a coach house and a colonnade adjoining Turret House. The 1876
                Ordnance Survey map, which was the first topographical survey of the village to use
                the 25-inch to one-mile scale, indicates that the colonnade was approximately 47
                meters long, running between the main house and a coach house.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.12" id="12">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">12. William Blake, <i>Sketch of Turret house on verso of self
                    portrait</i></p> c. 1800. Pencil on paper. Robert N. Essick collection.
                <p><br/>On the verso of Blake’s self portrait is a rough sketch that appears to
                depict Turret House and the colonnade. In the second image, Blake’s faint pencil
                lines have been traced in Ink. The sketch may be preparatory to a planned picture of
                Turret House that was never begun or is now lost.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.13" id="13">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">13. George Engleheart, drawing of Turret House</p> c. 1810.
            Pen and ink. From George C. Williamson and Henry L. D. Engleheart, George Engleheart,
            1750-1829, Miniature Painter to George III (London: George Bell &#38; Sons, 1902).
                <p><br/>The miniaturist George Engleheart was introduced to Hayley by their mutual
                friend, Jeremiah Meyer. Engleheart visited Felpham, painted miniatures of Hayley and
                his second wife and sketched Turret House.<sup><a class="footnote">20<span>Morchard Bishop, <i>Blake's Hayley:
                        The Life, Works, and Friendships of William Hayley</i> (London: Victor
                    Gollancz, 1951) 324.</span></a></sup> This sketch depicts the house from the south with a
                turret and two wings, and a single-storey structure adjoining the west aspect of the
                house. The colonnade runs to the foreground from the adjoining structure.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.14" id="14">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">14. George Engleheart, watercolor, pen and ink drawing of
                Turret House</p>c. 1810. From George C. Williamson and Henry L. D. Engleheart,
                <i>George Engleheart, 1750-1829, Miniature Painter to George III</i>, (London:
            George Bell &#38; Sons, 1902).<p><br/>Engleheart's watercolor drawing depicts the house
                from the south aspect and includes alphbetized labels to identify the rooms.
                Engleheart identifies the upper-storey east wing (labeled A and L) as the upper
                library, below which, on the ground floor (labeled B) is the dining room. The room
                on the southern aspect of the ground-floor west wing is deisgnated as the lower
                library (labeled C). In Bunce's third design (see fig. 6), this room was to be the
                kitchen. In Engleheart's watercolour sketch, the kitchen is located in the
                single-storey structure (labeled H) adjoining the west wing of the house. It is
                likely that after Thomas Alphonso's death, Hayley required more space to accommodate
                the books, paintings and sculptures he transferred to Felpham from Eartham.</p>
            <p>Engleheart's identification of rooms reveals that Bunce's third design, with the main
                library located on the upper floor and occupying the entire east wing, was probably
                the final design of Turret House and, as we shall see, the location of Blake's 18
                portrait heads.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.15" id="15">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">15. Samuel Bunce and William Hayley, <i>Plan of the Library
                    Decorations</i></p> Pen, ink, and pencil on paper. James Marshall and
            Marie-Louise Osborn Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New Haven.
                <p><br/>In an undated drawing by Bunce of a rectangular room with a fireplace and at
                least one window, Hayley has added a series of names of authors, sometimes in a
                contracted form, next to circles that run along each wall. The circles could denote
                roundel frames. Starting with Cowper on the lower right of the plan and proceeding
                clockwise, the authors Hayley lists are as follows: Spenser, Cowley, Cicero,
                Voltaire, Shakespeare, Dryden, Sappho, Tasso, Camöens, Anacreon, Pope, Euripides,
                Ariosto, Demosthenes, Horace, Livy, and Edward Gibbon. The exclusion of Thomas
                Alphonso from this plan and his inclusion in Blake’s eighteen portraits suggests
                that it was drafted before May 1800 and, therefore, before Blake arrived in Felpham.
                This sketch of the library does not include features such as the recess and three
                doors that we see in Bunce’s third design and appears to be based on the rectangular
                library in his second design. While some of the subjects differ from Blake’s series,
                this sketch with Hayley’s manuscript additions suggests pairings for eight
                portraits. It is likely that the sketch represents Hayley’s early, if not initial
                intensions regarding a positional arrangement for a series of portraits in roundels
                to decorate the upper library at Turret House.</p>
        </caption>
        <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.16" id="16">
            <title> </title>
            <caption>
                <p style="color: skyblue">16. Samuel Bunce, <i>Position of Decorations</i></p> James
                Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript
                Library, New Haven. <p><br/>An indication of where Blake’s portraits were hung is
                    suggested in Bunce’s letter to Hayley of 20 March 1798, where the architect
                    expresses his concern over the width of a proposed frieze to decorate the
                    Felpham library: “I hope you will not make the frieze so wide as you mention I
                    have therefore only increased it by ½ an inch”.<sup><a class="footnote">21<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley
                        letters, XXXII, fol. 24.</span></a></sup> Bunce appears to be referring to a continuous
                    frieze. A sketch on the verso of Bunce and Hayley’s undated plan for the
                    decorations in the upper library supports this notion of a frieze, with a series
                    of portraits were to occupy a position above the chairs, probably in an area
                    between the bookcases and the ceilings. While differing in length, Blake’s
                    portraits are of similar height, which indicates they were hung in an area of
                    uniform height, such as between the bookcases and the ceiling. It must be noted
                    that the exact dimensions of the paintings may have altered as they have been
                    relined at least once.<sup><a class="footnote">22<span>According to the conservators at the Manchester City
                        Art Gallery, Blake’s paintings were relined approximately 70 years ago.
                        Gilchrist described the paintings he saw in Mr Toovey’s bookshop as “cracked
                        and blistered”, which suggests that they were also relined and varnished
                        once they had been removed from Hayley’s library. See Gilchrist (1863)
                        166.</span></a></sup>
                </p>
                <p> In Britain, the tradition of decorating libraries with portraits of authors in
                    roundel frames as part of a larger frieze located above bookcases may be traced
                    to the Bodleian Library, Oxford. The Bodleian frieze was painted between 1616
                    and 1618 and consists of 202 portraits in roundels located in a cornice between
                    the bookcases and the ceiling.<sup><a class="footnote">23<span>J.N.L Myers, “The Painted Frieze in the
                        Picture Gallery” <i>BLR</i>, Vol. 3, No. 50, (Oct 1950) 82-91 and “Thomas
                        James and The Painted Frieze”, <i>BLR</i>, Vol. 4, No. I (April 1952)
                        30-51.</span></a></sup> Between each portrait are depictions of scrolls, books, inkpots
                    and quills. In some instances there are allegorical items associated with the
                    passage of time, such as hour-glasses and skulls. The use of portraits arranged
                    in a frieze was two-fold, to represent visually the classification of subjects
                    within large libraries and to confer authority onto the library and inspiration
                    to its readers.<sup><a class="footnote">24<span>Andre Masson, <i>The Pictorial Catalogue, Mural Decoration
                            in Libraries,</i> (Oxford 1981) 1-11 and 51.</span></a></sup> In 1661 Gabriel Naude
                    advocated the pictorial representation of learned men in libraries, declaring
                    that “good copies drawn from such as are most famous in the Profession of
                    letters [act as] a puissant spurre to excite a generous and well-born soul to
                    follow their track”.<sup><a class="footnote">25<span>Gabriel Naude, <i>Instruction Concerning Erection of a
                            Library,</i> (London 1661) 84/5.</span></a></sup> This was certainly one of the
                    aims of the frieze in the Bodleian Library. As well as providing intellectual
                    inspiration and subject classification, the decorations in domestic libraries
                    such as Hayley’s also offered visual signification of the tastes and social
                    status of the owner.</p>
            </caption>
        </image>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.17" id="17">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">17. George Steevens and William Hayley, <i>Mr Hayley’s list of
                    the Portraits of English Poets</i></p> Mark Crosby collection. <p><br/>An
                undated manuscript document co-written by Hayley and his friend, the Shakespeare
                scholar George Steevens, demonstrates Hayley’s interest in the portraits of English
                authors. This list may have functioned as a catalogue of portraits that Hayley
                either owned as prints, or that he wanted and that it was used by Steevens as a
                buying guide to locate portraits at print and art sellers in London that Hayley
                didn’t yet own. Some of the subjects, for example, are marked with an extended dash
                followed by the letter ‘w’, which may denote portraits that are wanted. The list
                includes the names of all the English authors who appear in Blake’s series with the
                exception of Alexander Pope.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.18" id="18">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 2: The Hanging Arrangement</p>
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">18. Anon. Fronticepiece engraving, <i>Marci Tullii Ciceronis
                    opera quae supersunt omnia</i>, volume 2 (1724)</p>
            <p><br/>Hayley’s commission of the 18 portrait heads to decorate his upper library
                follows a long tradition of adorning libraries with busts and friezes depicting
                celebrated authors. When Turret House was conceived as Thomas Alphonso’s seaside
                residence, Hayley advised his son to decorate his prospective library with busts by
                    Flaxman.<sup><a class="footnote">26<span>See Hayley, <i>Memoirs</i> 2:89, 354 and 359. For Flaxman's on
                    busts see British Library Add. MS 37538, fol. 3.</span></a></sup> Before his death, Thomas
                Alphonso sculpted busts of Homer and Milton to decorate the fireplace in the upper
                library at Turret House.<sup><a class="footnote">27<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley letters, XXXII, fol.
                    24.</span></a></sup> The inclusion of portraits of famous authors in libraries can be seen
                in this anonymous seventeenth-century engraving depicting Cicero’s library, with the
                heads framed in roundels surrounded by wreaths and located above the
                    bookcases.<sup><a class="footnote">28<span>Hayley owned several volumes containing this fronticepiece, see
                        <i>Cierconis Orationes in isim Delphini</i> (1684) auction cat #803, and
                        <i>Marci Tullii Ciceronis opera quae supersunt omnia, v. 2</i> (1724),
                    auction cat. #802</span></a></sup> These portraits should be, according to Gabriel Naude
                writing in 1661, “good copies drawn from such as are most famous in the Profession
                of letters".<sup><a class="footnote">29<span>Gabriel Naude, <i>Instruction Concerning Erection of a Library,</i>
                    (London 1661) 84-5.</span></a></sup> Hayley owned several books that offered models for
                depictions of classical figures in roundel frames, such the 1735 edition of <i>The
                    Lives and Characters of Ancient Greek Poets</i>.<sup><a class="footnote">30<span>1772 catalogue fol.
                    19r.</span></a></sup> As well as inspiration, such portraits were often used to provide a
                system of visual classification for the contents of the library. According to a
                manuscript catalogue dated 1772 and in Hayley’s hand and the 1821 auction catalogue
                of the Felpham libraries, Hayley owned approximately 22 editions relating to Milton,
                which equated to over 80 volumes; 12 editions relating to Homer, over 40 volumes; 10
                editions relating to Shakespeare, over 60 volumes; 13 editions of Cicero, over 20
                volumes; 10 editions relating to Dante, over 30 volumes; 10 editions relating to
                Pope, over 40 volumes; and 68 volumes on British poets.<sup><a class="footnote">31<span><i>A Catalogue of Books
                        Belonging to Wm Hayley 1772,</i> West Sussex Country Record Office and <i>A
                        Catalogye of the Very Valuable and Extensive Library of the Late William
                        Hayley, ESQ.</i> (London: Mr. Evans, 1821).</span></a></sup></p>
            <p> The original frames of Blake’s 18 portrait heads date to <i>circa</i> 1870. While we
                don’t know how the portraits were originally fixed to the space between the
                bookcases and the ceiling in Hayley’s upper library, we can speculate that they were
                either stretched on wooden frames in Chichester or were pasted directly to the wall
                in imitation of fresco. Blake’s execution of the portraits in his tempera medium may
                have been informed by how the paintings were mounted. In his annotations to Joshua
                Reynolds, Blake suggests that his version of fresco can use a wall as a support:
                “Fresco Painting is Like Miniature Painting; a Wall is a Large Ivory” (Erdman page
                653). Blake use of light grey and brown washes accentuated by various types of
                intensely coloured wreaths and subsidiary design, imbuing the portraits with a
                three-dimensional appearance similar to busts. We can surmise from the dimensions of
                Blake’s 18 portraits, their visual correspondences, and the orientations of the
                heads, that they were conceived and executed as a group to occupy a single room.
                This would have been the upper library as it is the only space large enough to
                accommodate all 18 paintings in a space between the bookcases and the ceiling. </p>
            <p> Kenneth Povey and William Wells identified most of the sources of Blake’s 18
                portrait heads.<sup><a class="footnote">32<span>Kenneth Povey, "Blake's Heads of the Poets", <i>Notes and
                        Queries,</i> Vol. 151, (24 July 1926), pp. 57-8 and William Wells,
                        <i>William Blake's "Heads of the Poets"</i> (Manchester, William Morris
                    Press, 1969)</span></a></sup> This gallery rehearses these sources, providing additional
                information on books containing portrait engravings in Hayley’s libraries that Blake
                consulted. Our knowledge of the contents of Hayley’s libraries primarily derives
                from his 1772 manuscript catalogue and the 1821 auction catalogue. While these two
                documents provide a reliable account of books Hayley owned at specific historical
                moments, we also know that Hayley sold and borrowed books throughout his life and by
                1800 had amassed what his friend, William Meyer, son of the miniaturist Jeremiah
                Meyer, describes as a collection of engraved “Poets Heads”.<sup><a class="footnote">33<span>Fitzwilliam Museum
                    Hayley Letters IV fol. 2.</span></a></sup> This collection included a portrait of Friedrich
                Gottlieb Klopstock. Drawing on these sources, Hayley’s correspondence, this gallery
                offers three newly identified sources for Blake’s portraits of Homer, Demosthenes,
                and Tasso. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.19" id="19">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">19. Hanging Arrangement</p> c. 1800-3. Pen and tempera on
            canvas. The City Art Gallery, Manchester. <p><br/> Based on Bunce’s third design for
                Turret House, the dimensions of the walls of the upper library can be calculated. In
                this design Bunce does not provide exact dimensions for the windows, so a degree of
                error must be allowed in the reconstruction of the upper library. Labeled
                alphabetically and beginning clockwise from the northern wall, the first two wall
                spaces, labeled A and B, are located either side of the fireplace and each measure
                1.2 m each. The fireplace measures 1.5 m and the chimney breast, which would have
                run continuously to the ceiling, was narrower, measuring approximately 1.1 m, giving
                a total of 3.9 m as indicated by Bunce’s revised plan.<sup><a class="footnote">34<span>Fitzwilliam Museum Hayley
                    letters, XXXII, fol. 23</span></a></sup>
            </p><p> The eastern wall, labeled C, measures 7.9 m and contains three windows,
                approximately 0.4 m wide, fitted with sliding shutters.<sup><a class="footnote">35<span>The height and width of
                    the windows has been approximated from Bunce’s plan, Engleheart’s drawings, and
                    measurements taken from the 1876 OS map.</span></a></sup> The southern wall, labeled D,
                contains one window and measures 3.9 m. The window may also have been approximately
                0.4 m wide, with the sections of wall either side of the window measuring 1.5 m.
                </p><p> The wall sections either side of the recess, E and I, measure 1.8 m. The
                recess comprises three walls, with a door in each wall. The doors are approximately
                1.2 m wide and 1.7 m high. The wall on the southern aspect of the recess, labeled F,
                measures 1.8 m and contains a door leading to the turret. The longer wall on the
                western aspect, labeled G, measures 4.5 m and contains a door leading to the main
                bedchamber. The northern wall in the recess, labeled H, measures 1.8 m, and contains
                a door leading to the closet. </p><p> The tonality of the background and subsidiary
                scenes in the paintings that occupy walls A, B, C and D enhance the statuesque style
                of the main portrait and make the painting easier to view when not in direct
                sunlight. Contemporary advice on painting suggests that: “if the Picture be set in a
                Place which receives little light the colors must be very clear, as on the contrary
                very brown if the Place be strongly enlightened”.<sup><a class="footnote">36<span>Thomas Page, <i>The Art of
                        Painting,</i> (1720) 84.</span></a></sup> The position of the paintings on these walls
                would have been out of direct sunlight and therefore would have necessitated them
                being clear and more distinct tonally. There are several darker portraits, which
                probably occupied positions opposite the windows in direct sunlight. </p><p> In this
                reconstruction of the hanging arrangement, I have discounted the possibility of any
                portraits being located on walls F and H because the height of the door leading to
                the turret stairs was 1.7 m, which would preclude a portrait with a width of 40-45
                cm occupying the area above the doorframe. Also, due to the door's position, a
                bookcase would not have been built to occupy the 30 cm gap either side of the doors
                on walls F and H. This hanging arrangement has the heads of each subject facing in
                the same orientation when viewed sequentially except for the portrait of Milton.
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.20" id="20">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">20. William Blake, <i>Homer</i> (40 x 84 cm) and <i>Milton</i>
                (40.1 x 90.9 cm).</p>Pen and tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery.
            <p><br/> The portrait of Homer may have occupied the area on wall D, between wall C and
                the window. The portrait of Milton, which faces left, may have occupied the area on
                wall D, between the window and wall E. This placement situates the portraits facing
                inwards towards the window and opposite walls A and B, thereby complementing the
                corresponding busts of Homer and Milton by Thomas Alphonso decorating the fireplace.
                Both portraits have corresponding wreaths of bay leaves, suggesting that they were
                designed to complement each other. </p>
            <p> Blake’s main source for the Milton portrait was George Vertue’s engraving after
                William Faithorne that was published in the 1732 edition of <i>Paradise Lost</i>,
                edited by Richard Bentley (a copy of which was in Hayley’s library during Blake’s
                time in Felpham).<sup><a class="footnote">37<span>See Crosby, “A Copy of Richard Bentley’s Edition of Paradise
                    Lost in William Hayley’s Library, c. 1802” <i>Blake</i> 57:3 (Winter 2023-24).
                </span></a></sup> Blake probably also consulted Giovanni Battista Cipriani‘s engraving of a
                bust of Milton, derived from Faithorne, that was published in <i>Memoirs of Thomas
                    Hollis</i> (1780). A presentation copy of Hollis’s <i>Memoirs</i> is listed in
                the 1821 auction catalogue.<sup><a class="footnote">38<span>1821 auction catalogue #1443.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
            <p> The main source for Blake’s treatment of Homer may have been Carlo Gregori’s 1741
                engraving of the Farnese bust after Giovanni Domenico Campiglia. Blake may have also
                consulted the frontispiece engraving of the Farnese bust in Alexander Pope’s
                translation of <i>The Iliad</i> (1720) which Hayley owned<sup><a class="footnote">39<span>1772 catalogue f. 21 r
                    and 1821 auction catalogue #1557.</span></a></sup> and the portrait engraving on the title
                page of John Flaxman’s outline illustrations of the <i>Iliad</i> (1793). There are
                numerous editions of Homer listed in Hayley’s 1772 manuscript catalogue and the 1821
                auction catalogue, including Chapman’s famous edition although none contain
                Gregori’s engraving which may have been part of Hayley’s collection of “Poets
                    Heads”.<sup><a class="footnote">40<span>1821 auction catalogue #1240.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.21" id="21">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">21. Carlo Gregori after Giovanni Domenico Campilgia, <i>Omero</i>
            </p> 1741. Engraving. <p><br/> If Blake used Gregori’s engraving as a model, he altered
                the orientation of the head, retained the blank eyes, denoting blindness, the pursed
                lips, curly hair and beard, and the headband. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.22" id="22">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">22. William Blake, <i>Cowper</i>, 41.9 x 83.6 cm</p> c. 1800-03.
            Pen and tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery. <p><br/> The area between the third
                window and wall D was 1.2 m and could accommodate one portrait, such as Homer or
                Cowper. Both heads face to the right, thereby keeping the orientation of the heads
                uniform on wall C. In this configuration, the portrait of Cowper may have occupied
                this wall rather than the longer portrait of Homer. </p><p> Blake’s source for this
                portrait head was Romney’s pastel drawing of Cowper (1792). In a letter to Lady
                Harriet Hesketh of 22 July 1800, Hayley describes having Romney’s portrait of Cowper
                adorning “the Library of my marine Turret”.<sup><a class="footnote">41<span>British Library Add. MS 30803 A.
                    fols. 35-6.</span></a></sup> Blake copied Romney’s sketch for two portrait miniatures, a
                pen and ink drawing, a pencil sketch, <a
                    href="https://blakearchive.org/copy/bb468.1?descId=bb468.1.comeng.01">
                    target="_blank”>and an engraving</a> for the first volume of Hayley’s <i>The
                    Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William Cowper</i> (1803). </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.23" id="23">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">23. William Blake, <i>Pope</i> (40.2 x 79.4 cm) and <i>Dryden</i>
                (40.3 x 80.8 cm)</p> c. 1800-03. Pen and tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery
                <p><br/> The area between the second and third window was also 1.8 m. The portraits
                of Dryden and Pope are of similar lengths and face to the right. In the Osborn plan,
                these two portraits face each other but the orientation of the heads in the extant
                portraits suggest they were next to each other. </p><p> Blake’s source for Pope
                derives from Jean-Baptiste van Loo’s portrait, which was copied by numerous
                engravers during the eighteenth century, including Jacobus Houbraken, whose version
                was published in Thomas Birch’s <i>Heads of Illustrious Persons of Great Britain</i>
                (1741). Hayley’s 1772 ms catalogue and the 1821 auction catalogue do not include
                Birch’s publication. There are 6 editions of Pope’s works listed in the 1772 ms
                catalogue and 10 editions listed in the 1821 catalogue.<sup><a class="footnote">42<span>1772 catalogue fols. 13v
                    and 21r and 1821 auction catalogue #156-7.</span></a></sup> While none of these editions
                contain an engraving after van Loos, Hayley also owned John Bell’s 68-volume <i>The
                    Poets of Great Britain</i>, which includes an engraving after van Loo signed
                Cook and dated 12 January 1778.<sup><a class="footnote">43<span>1821 auction catalogue #270. Different editions
                    of Bell’s publication contain prints after van Loos by different engravers, such
                    as Sharpe.</span></a></sup>
            </p><p> Blake’s portrait of Dryden derives from George Vertue’s engraving of Godfrey
                Kneller’s portrait of Dryden. A copy of this portrait is in Trinity College,
                Cambridge, which Hayley attended. Vertue’s engraving after Kneller is in <i>The
                    Dramatick Works of John Dryden</i> (1725), which Hayley owned.<sup><a class="footnote">44<span>1772
                    catalogue fol. 25r and 1821 auction catalogue #552.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.24" id="24">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">24. William Blake, <i>Camõens</i> (41.5 x 56.2 cm), <i>Ercilla</i>
                (41.8 x 51.7 cm), and <i>Thomas Alphonso Hayley</i> (41 x 50.3 cm)</p> c. 1800-03.
            Pen and tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery. <p><br/> The area between the first
                and second windows was 1.8 m and could accommodate more than one portrait. It is
                possible that the portraits of Camõens, Ercilla and Thomas Alphonso occupied this
                area. These are the three smallest portraits and face to the right. The similarity
                of sizes between Ercilla and Thomas Alphonso portraits, as well as their depiction
                in profile, suggest they complement each other. The central location may also have
                influenced the choice of these portraits. This area of wall C would have been
                immediately viewable from the doorway leading to Hayley’s bedchamber and the doorway
                leading to the turret staircase. Therefore, Hayley would have seen Blake’s portrait
                of his son as soon as he entered the library, either from his bedchamber or from the
                stairs. </p><p> The source for Camõens was the anonymous frontispiece to the 1655
                edition of <i>The Lusiad</i>, translated by Richard Fanshaw, which depicts the
                Portuguese poet with his left eye closed to signify blindness.<sup><a class="footnote">45<span>1821 auction
                    catalogue #623.</span></a></sup> In all the reproductions of Blake’s portrait published in
                the twentieth century, however, Camõens is depicted with both eyes open, with the
                left eye slightly larger than the right.<sup><a class="footnote">46<span>See Thomas Wright, <i>The Heads of The
                        Poets by William Blake</i> (Olney 1925); Wells 33, Butlin Cat. #343.6 and
                        <i>Panorama: Revista Portuguesa De Arte E Turismo</i>, No. 29 (Marco de
                    1969) 5. </span></a></sup> The removal of varnish and oil-based paint by conservators at
                the Manchester City Art Gallery reveals that in the original tempera Camõens was
                depicted the left eye closed. This confirms that Blake’s source for the portrait was
                the 1655 edition of <i>The Lusiad</i> and that another hand had used oil paint to
                amend the portrait. The repainting of Camõens probably occurred between 1863 and the
                sale of the 18 portrait heads to the Manchester City Art Gallery in 1885. In his
                catalogue of Blake’s paintings appended to the second volume of the first edition of
                Gilchrist’s biography (1863), William Michael Rossetti describes Camõens as
                “Undisguisedly one-eyed”.<sup><a class="footnote">47<span>Gilchrist (1863) 2:205.</span></a></sup> The second edition
                (1880) reprints Rossetti’s description from the first edition. By the time the
                series was sold to the Manchester Art Gallery, Camõens had both eyes open. </p><p>
                The source for Ercilla was Manuel Salvador Carmona's engraved bust published in the
                second volume of <i>Parnaso Español</i>, 9 vols (1768-78). Hayley owned the first
                seven volumes and in <i>An Essay on Epic Poetry</i> (1781) provides the first
                English translation of a section from Ercilla’s poem, <i>Araucana</i>.<sup><a class="footnote">48<span>1821
                    auction catalogue auction #1718. Hayley also owned the 1586 and 1610 editions of
                        <i>Araucana</i> (1772 catalogue fol. 29r and 30r).</span></a></sup>
            </p><p> The source for Thomas Alphonso Hayley was John Flaxman’s medallion portrait of
                his pupil. The <a
                    href="https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/bb467.1?descId=bb467.1.comeng.03">
                    target=_blank>medallion</a> was sketched by Henry Howard and engraved by Blake
                to illustrate Hayley’s <i>Essay on Sculpture</i> (1800). </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.25" id="25">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">25. William Blake, <i>Dante</i> (42.5 x 87.8 cm)</p> c. 1800-03.
            Pen and tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery. <p><br/> The first painting on wall C
                would have been another long portrait also facing to the right, such as the head of
                Dante, occupying the area above the bookcase between wall B and the first window.
                Blake’s portrait of Dante derives from Raphael’s <i>Disputa</i> (1509-10) and
                possibly <i>Il Parnaso</i> (1509-11). Engravings of these frescos were in
                circulation during the period and the 1821 auction catalogue records several
                editions of the <i>Divine Comedy</i>, including the 1791 three-volume edition
                published in Rome with an engraved vignette on the title page depicting Dante in
                profile sporting laurels.<sup><a class="footnote">49<span>1821 auction catalogue #1022.</span></a></sup> In his notes to
                    <i>An Essay on Epic Poetry</i>, Hayley provides one of the earliest known
                English translations of the first three cantos of the <i>Inferno</i> and refers to
                the famous Paolo and Francesca and Ugolino episodes. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.26" id="26">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">26. Marcantonio Raimondi after Raphael, <i>Il Parnaso</i></p>
            Engraving (ca. 1517-20). Mark Crosby Collection. <p><br/> Raimondi’s engraving is after
                an early drawing of <i>Il Parnaso</i> prior to Raphael’s completion of the fresco in
                the Vatican. Apollo occupies the center of the composition surrounded by the nine
                muses. To the left, Dante and Virgil stand either side of Homer, an arrangement that
                invokes canto 4 of <i>The Inferno</i>. While there are other figures in the
                composition sporting laurel crowns, they aren’t clearly identifiable in this early
                version. In the finished fresco, as Giorgio Vasari observed, Raphael incorporates
                “all the most famous and modern poets who ever lived or were still
                    alive”.<sup><a class="footnote">50<span>Giorgio Vasari, <i>The Lives of the Artists</i>, trans. and with an
                    introduction by Julia Conway Bondanella and Peter Bondanella, (Oxford: Oxford
                    University Press, 1991) 316.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.27" id="27">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">27. William Blake, <i>Cicero</i> (41.5 x 103 cm) and
                    <i>Demosthenes</i> (42 x 106.6 cm)</p> c. 1800-03. Pen and tempera on canvas.
            Manchester Art Gallery. <p><br/> The two longest portraits, Cicero and Demosthenes,
                would have occupied the area above the bookcases on walls A and B, either side of
                the chimney breast. Both heads face the same direction, to the right. </p><p>
                Blake’s portrait of Cicero derives from the frontispiece engraving by M. Burg after
                Rubens in <i>Aeschines et Demosthenes de Corona</i> (1715). Hayley owned several
                editions of this publication including the 1715 edition.<sup><a class="footnote">51<span>1821 auction catalogue
                    #62.</span></a></sup> This edition also includes an engraving of the bust of Demosthenes by
                Berg but Blake based his portrait on D. Beyet’s 1789 engraving. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.28" id="28">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">28. D. Beyet, <i>Demosthenes</i>
            </p> 1798. Österreichische Nationalbibliothek. Public Domain. <p><br/> Blake closely
                follows Beyet’s engraving, depicting Demosthenes facing leftward, with blank eyes,
                curly beard and hair. Based on the similarities between the engraving and Blake’s
                portrait, it is likely that Beyet’s print was part of Hayley’s collection of “Poets
                Heads”. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.29" id="29">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">29. William Blake, <i>Klopstock</i> (43 x 79.8 cm) and
                    <i>Otway</i> (40.5 x 76.2 cm)</p> c. 1800-03. Pen and tempera on canvas.
            Manchester Art Gallery. <p><br/> Blake’s portraits of Otway and Klopstock would have
                occupied positions along wall I, opposite the window in wall C. Both portraits face
                to the left, continuing the orientation scheme of the portraits on walls A, B, and
                C. </p><p> Blake’s source for Klopstock was Johann Gerhard Huck’s mezzotint after
                Anton Hickel. William Meyer spent much of Fall 1800 in Germany, conveying Hayley’s
                “tribute” to Klopstock and sending Hayley “a recent print of Klopstock which I hope
                you will do me the honour to add to your collection of Poets Heads” in October
                    1800.<sup><a class="footnote">52<span>Fitzwillian Museum Hayley Letters IV fols. 1-2. Also partially quoted
                    in Wells, 26.</span></a></sup> This print may have been Huck’s mezzotint. </p><p> Blake’s
                source for Otway was I. Miller’s portrait engraving after Mary Beale in <i>The Works
                    of Thomas Otway</i> (1757). Hayley owned several copies of Otway’s <i>Works</i>
                including the 1757 edition.<sup><a class="footnote">53<span>1821 auction catalogue #1521.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.30" id="30">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">30. William Blake, <i>Tasso</i> (41.2 x 83.1 cm), <i>Voltaire</i>
                (41.9 x 79.4 cm), and <i>Shakespeare</i> (41 x 79.5 cm)</p> c. 1800-03. Pen and
            tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery. <p><br/> At least three portraits would have
                been located on wall G. The area between wall F and the door to the main bedchamber
                in wall G was 1.5 m in length. This area could accommodate both the Shakespeare and
                Voltaire portraits, which face left and therefore maintain the orientation pattern.
                There is perhaps some irony in a hanging arrangement that places France’s most
                famous eighteenth-century critic next to the subject of some of his more
                inflammatory strictures, with the suggestion that Voltaire’s attacks and
                (mis)translations fail to harm the bard. The area between the bedchamber door and
                wall H is also 1.5 m, which would allow a portrait such as Tasso, again with the
                head orientated to the left, to occupy this space. </p><p> Blake based his portrait
                of Tasso on the engraving by N. Depuis after Seeman that appears as the frontispiece
                to Jacob Tonson’s two-volume <i>Gierusalemme Liberata</i> (1724). A copy of this
                publication was in Hayley’s library.<sup><a class="footnote">54<span>1821 auction catalogue #2535.</span></a></sup>
            </p><p> For the head of Voltaire, Blake drew on one or more of the numerous engravings
                after Maurice Quentin de Latour’s portrait. While Hayley owned several editions of
                Voltaire’s letters and writings, none contain a portrait engraving. It is likely
                that a portrait engraving of Voltaire after Latour was in Hayley’s collection of
                “Poets Heads”. </p><p> For the head of Shakespeare, Blake followed the famous
                frontispiece engraving by Martin Droeshout published in the first folio (1623).
                According to Hayley’s manuscript list of Portraits of English Poets, he owned a
                portrait of Shakespeare. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.31" id="31">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">31. N. Depuis after Seeman, <i>Tasso</i></p> Frontispiece
            engraving, <i>Gierusalemme Liberata</i> (1724). <p><br/> Blake closely follows the
                Depuis engraving, depicting Tasso with a forelock of hair, beard and a broad white
                collar. As with a number of the sources, Blake alters the orientation of the head so
                that Tasso faces left thereby keeping with the overall orientation scheme of the
                group. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.32" id="32">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">32. William Blake, <i>Spencer</i> (42 x 84 cm) and <i>Chaucer</i>
                (42.5 x 63.7 cm)</p> c. 1800-03. Pen and tempera on canvas. Manchester Art Gallery.
                <p><br/> The portraits of Chaucer and Spenser would fit the area above the bookcases
                on wall E. The orientation of the heads, facing to the left, would ensure that apart
                from the Milton portrait, there would be a continuous pattern of leftward
                orientation in all the portraits. </p><p> Blake’s portrait of Spencer derives from
                George Vertue’s engraving in his series “Twelve Celebrated English Poets”. Spencer
                is listed in Hayley’s Portraits of English Poets, which suggests Vertue’s portrait
                engraving was part of Hayley’s collection of ‘Poets Heads”. </p><p> Blake’s source
                of Chaucer was Vertue’s engraved portrait in <i>The Works of Geoffrey Chaucer</i>
                (1721), which was present in Hayley’s library.<sup><a class="footnote">55<span>1821 auction catalogue
                    #432.</span></a></sup> Blake closely follows Vertue's engraving, including the orientation
                of the head, but adds a third button to Chaucer's tunic. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.33" id="33">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">33. George Vertue, <i>Geoffrey Chaucer</i></p> 1717. Line
            engraving. <p><br/> Blake closely follows Vertue’s engraving, including the orientation
                of the head, but adds a third button to Chaucer’s tunic. </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.34" id="34">
        <title> </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">34. William Blake, <i>Edward III,</i> c. 1774-1779.</p>
            <i>Edward III,</i> c. 1777-9. Copperplate. Bodleian Library, Oxford. <i>Edward III,</i>
            c. 1777-9. Line engraving. Published in Richard Gough, <i>Sepulchral Monuments in Great
                Britain</i> (1786-96). <p>
                <br/> Hayley’s commission to decorate his library with roundel portraits suggests
                that he was confident in Blake’s ability to create life-size portraiture. While
                there was little evidence that Blake could execute such portraits in his two
                previous commissions for Hayley, the three engravings for <i>Essay on Sculpture</i>,
                and the relief-etched broadside ballad, <i>Little Tom the Sailor</i>, the Turret
                House libraries contained a volume that may have informed Hayley’s decision: Richard
                Gough’s <i>Sepulchral Monuments in Great Britain</i> (1786-96).<sup><a class="footnote">56<span>1821 auction
                    catalogue #1042. Hayley also owned Gough's <i>British Topography</i> (1780),
                    1821 auction catalogue #1233.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
            <p> During his apprenticeship Blake made a series of preparatory drawings of the royal
                tombs in Westminster Abbey, many of which were engraved for the first volume of
                Gough’s <i>Sepulchral Monuments</i>. These drawings and their corresponding
                engravings include six oval portraits of monarchs taken from their effigies
                clustered around Edward the Confessor’s Chapel. To sketch the effigies, Blake had to
                climb up and, as Benjamin Heath Malkin recalls, stand “on the monument, […] viewing
                the figures from the top”. Malkin adds that Blake “considered” his heads of the
                effigies “as portraits” (<i>BR2</i> 563). </p>
            <p>Blake’s oval portraits were made between 1774-7 and capture the sculptural quality of
                the thirteenth-century effigies. The preparatory drawing and engraving of Edward
                III, depicted with blank eyes and long beard, and a possible visual source for
                Urizen, show that as early as his apprenticeship years Blake was more than capable
                of executing life-size portraiture. With the 18 portrait heads for the upper library
                at Turret House, Blake similarly imbues his subjects with a sculptural quality,
                complimenting the busts adorning fireplace, and providing “a puissant spurre to
                excite a generous and well-born soul to follow their track”.<sup><a class="footnote">57<span>Naude, 84-5.</span></a></sup>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
</exhibit>
