<exhibit id="absorbedbythepoets" title="&quot;Absorbed by the Poets&quot;" article="absorbedbythepoets.exhibit.html" composition_date_string="April 2024">
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.1" id="1">
        <title>
            <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 1: Reconstructing Hayley’s ‘Marine villa’ (Turret House)</p>
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">George Romney, <i>Flaxman Modeling the Bust of William Hayley</i></p>
            c. 1795-6. Oil on canvas. Yale Centre for British Art, New Haven.
            <p><br/>Hayley was an amateur physician, dispensing quack remedies to his friends and neighbours, and enthusiastically practicing and advocating sea-bathing as a cure-all treatment. Prompted by the frequent bouts of ill health suffered by his son in 1796 Hayley conceived of a dual-purpose residence near the coast:</p>
            <blockquote>I am finishing my little marine villa, in a comfortable hope that it will be singularly beneficial to the recovery of my dear artist, and we shall render it, I believe, so commodious, that it may even serve me for a winter residence.<sup><a class="footnote">5<span>See Elizabeth Johnston, <i>For Friendship’s Sake, William Blake and William Hayley</i>, (Manchester 1969).</span></a></sup></blockquote>
            <p>Thomas Alphonso was Hayley’s only child, born out of wedlock to the daughter of Hayley’s nursemaid, Sarah Betts. From a young age, Thomas Alphonso demonstrated an interest in art and became a pupil of both George Romney and John Flaxman. In this painting, Thomas Alphonso stands with his back to the viewer, assisting Flaxman in sculpting a gigantic bust of his father, who faces the viewer. Behind Hayley, Romney peers smirking above his easel. Thomas Alphonso’s contrapposto pose hints at the curvature of spine that contributed to his early death in May 1800.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.2" id="2">
        <title>
        </title>
        <caption>
<p style="color: skyblue">William Blake, <i>Thomas Alphonso Hayley</i></p>
            ca. 1800. Graphite on paper. Yale Center for British Art, New Haven.
            <p>
                <br/>This may have been a preparatory drawing for a more finished study or for an engraving. The drawing depicts Thomas Alphonso standing behind a table with a finger resting on his chin and holding a classical statue to signify the subject’s status as a sculptor. On the table is a scroll bearing “EPISTLES to John Flaxman Sculptor”. It is possible that Hayley wanted this image engraved for his poem, An Essay on Sculpture (1800), which was dedicated to Flaxman and contains three engravings by Blake, including a portrait of Thomas Alphonso in profile after Flaxman’s medallion of his pupil: https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/bb467.1?descId=bb467.1.comeng.03
                It is also conceivable that Blake made this drawing after the death of Thomas Alphonso to illustrate a biography that Hayley was writing during the first few years of the nineteenth century.
            </p>
            <p>
                Hayley selected Felpham for the location of Thomas Alphonso’s ‘Marine villa’ as it was close to his own home at Eartham and a short walk from the English Channel, allowing him to be both close to his son and for Thomas Alphonso to enjoy daily sea-bathing sessions. Hayley contacted Flaxman and the architect responsible for George Romney’s studio, Samuel Bunce, about the project, proposing a circular structure.
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.3" id="3">
        <title>
        
        </title>
        <caption>
<p style="color: skyblue">John Flaxman, <i>Marine villa</i></p>
            Pen on paper. Flaxman to Hayley, 11 September 1796. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.
            <p>
                <br/>In a letter to Hayley of 11 September 1796, Flaxman reports that he and Bunce, whom he refers to as “the man of Capitals &#38; Cornices”, had recently “held a council concerning your intended building”. Following Hayley’s suggestion, their initial proposal was a circular tower comprising three floors, a wraparound balcony on the first floor, and a vestibule leading to an internal staircase. In his letter, Flaxman includes three sketches depicting the front, “oblique, and plan perspectives of the tower and notes that “the circle ‘tho a beautiful figure is much better suited to many other Architectural purposes than the conveniences of a dwelling, yet according to your idea I think it may be well employed”.
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.4" id="4">
        <title>
        </title>
        <caption>
<p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>First Design</i></p>
            Bunce to Hayley, 31 March 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.
            <p>
                <br/>Writing to Hayley on 31 March 1797, Bunce optimistically states, “your building will not take more than between two &#38; three months.” The following month, Bunce sent Hayley a modified plan that of the ‘Marine villa’ that incorporates Flaxman’s circular tower and internal staircase. This plan indicates that the new house was designed around the library, a circular room that was perhaps modelled after Horace Walpole’s at Strawberry Hill. The proposed library is located on the upper floor and was to be subdivided into two floors. A side elevation shows that there would be six windows on each floor, with a fireplace on the northern aspect of the room and chimneybreasts on both floor. This early plan also indicates that the remainder of the house would comprise three ground-floor rooms, a kitchen and parlour, with the third room under the library left for Hayley to decide upon. Whether it was due to expense or taste, this plan was rejected.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.5" id="5">
        <title>
        
        </title>
        <caption>
<p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>Second Design</i></p>
            Bunce to Hayley, 29 April 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.
            <p>
                <br/>Bunce sent a series of revised plans to Hayley a month later. These plans are drawn on the verso of a sheet of paper included with Bunce’s letter to Hayley of 29 April 1797 and demonstrate the importance of the library in the overall design of the dwelling. The redesigned ‘Marine villa’ was a rectangular structure with a rectangular library again located on the second floor. The first sketched plan situates the library running the entire length of the northern aspect of the house. It is the largest room in the house and contains a fireplace opposite the only door. There is a window in each aspect.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.6" id="6">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>Third Design</i></p>
            Bunce to Hayley, 29 April 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.
            <p><br/>In the same packet, Bunce sent a second set of plans labeled ground floor and upper floor. These plans include measurements and room designations. The plans depict a two-floor structure with external measurements of 10.3 m by 8.2 m. The structure is divided centrally by a narrow corridor that terminates in a turret on the south aspect. Either side of the corridor is a wing that is subdivided into rooms. The ground-floor west wing comprises two rooms, a kitchen on the southern aspect, measuring 5.4 m by 3.9 m and a storeroom on the northern aspect, measuring 4.2 m by 3 m. The east wing is also divided into two rooms, a dining room on the southern aspect, measuring 4.5 m by 3.9 m, and a workroom on the northern aspect, measuring 4.2 m by 3 m.
            </p>
            <p>
                The upper storey is also divided into two wings. The west wing comprises two bedchambers, the main bedchamber on the northern aspect and a smaller, secondary bedchamber on the southern aspect. There is also a closet, measuring 1.5 m by 1.8 m, located at the northern end of the central corridor. The majority of the central corridor, an area measuring 4.2 m by 1.8 m comprises the library, which occupies the entire east wing of the upper storey. The library measures 7.9 m by 3.9 m, which, including the recess of 4.2 m by 1.8 m, equates to 128.6 m<sup>2</sup> making it the largest room in the house. There are three doors leading from the library to the closet, the main bedchamber and the stairs. A door from the stairs leads to the smaller bedchamber. The library and the two bedchambers each contain fireplaces. The fireplace in the library is located on the north aspect. Thomas Alphono made several sculptural busts for the library’s fireplace, including busts of Homer and Milton.22 The upper library also has four windows, three on the eastern aspect and one on the southern aspect. This design would allow more light to enter the library, particularly in the morning, than the earlier designs.
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.7" id="7">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>The Turret</i></p>
            Bunce to Hayley, 29 July 1797. Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.
            <p><br/>Like the earlier plans, these revised plans include an internal staircase. The staircase is in a rectangular turret, which also forms part of the entrance and measures 2.1 m<sup>2</sup>. The doorway in the turret was constructed using three great stones, forming a “trilithon”. Bunce informs Hayley of the manner of construction: “There can be no better way than to lay other larger stones or rough flints up to the Trilithon to meet the arch”. In the same letter, Bunce described the house as “the druidical seat”. Blake’s depiction of trilithons in Milton and Jerusalem may have been, in part, influenced by the entrance to Turret House. During a visit to Hayley in 1811, William Godwin records his experiences climbing the turret:
                <blockquote>His house is quite a toy. He has erected a turret on the top, with a corridor over that, for the sake of the prospect, and to this corridor he climbs at least once everyday by a ladder, which can only be descended by crawling backwards, and which, being on the top of the house in the open air, looked to me frightful, but I escaped without breaking either my neck or leg.</blockquote>
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.8" id="8">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>The Stained-Glass Window</i></p>
            Pencil on paper. Bunce to Hayley, 9 January 1798. Fitzwilliam Museum.
            <p><br/>The turret also housed a stained-glass window on the south aspect, with 1 metre diameter on the exterior and 1.05 m diameter on the interior, 0.6 m deep. With a south-facing aspect, the light that was refracted through the thick, multicoloured glass would have made entering the library a unique and possibly transcendent-like experience. The dazzling effects that this window produced, particularly on a sunny day, may have inspired Blake’s connection of Turret House to heaven in his poem addressed to “Anna Flaxman”: “The Ladder of Angels descends thro the air / On the Turret its spiral does softly descend” (E 709).</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.9" id="9">
        <title>
        </title>
        <caption>
                        <p style="color: skyblue">William Blake, <i>Landscape near Felpham</i></p>
            ca. 1800. Tate Britain.
            <p><br/>Bunce’s sketch of the south aspect of Turret House depicts a two-floor structure with a three-storey tower. Bunce includes a balcony on the turret’s second floor supported by what appear to be columns. Thomas Alphonso laid the foundation stone for Turret House on 15 April 1797 watched by his father, Bunce, and George Romney. While Turret House was demolished in the twentieth century, contemporaneous depictions by Blake and George Engleheart suggest that Bunce’s third design and this sketch of the south aspect were close to the final structure.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.10" id="10">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>The Coach house</i></p>
            Bunce to Hayley, 28 June and 3 July 1798. Fitzwilliam Museum.
            <p><br/>Blake’s unfinished pencil and watercolour sketch depicts the village of Felpham as viewed from the seashore. One of the few landscapes Blake ever created, the sketch shows one of Felpham’s two windmills in the left foreground. Hayley’s Turret House is visible in the centre of the picture. A contemporary account of the village appears to describe the view that Blake painted:
                <blockquote>On the left the eye rests on a lengthened series of cornfields and meadows, extending from the village to the sea-side, bedecking the latter with a gay verdant mantle, even to the water’s edge. Behind those fields arise three or four excellent and commodious dwellings, shaded and embellished by clusters of trees; and what still enhances their merit, commanding a marine landscape in front, and an extensive land view in the rear. </blockquote>
                Blake’s cottage can be seen on the right of sketch, half hidden behind trees and illuminated by a shaft of sunlight. For Blake’s own depiction of his cottage, see https://www.blakearchive.org/copy/milton.a?descId=milton.a.illbk.36</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.11" id="11">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>The Coach house</i></p>
            Bunce to Hayley, 28 June and 3 July 1798. Fitzwilliam Museum.
            <p><br/>In 1798 Bunce sent Hayley a series of sketches of a coach house and a colonnade adjoining Turret House. The 1876 Ordnance Survey map, which was the first topographical survey of the village to use the 25-inch to one-mile scale, indicates that the colonnade was approximately 47 meters long, running between the main house and a coach house.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.12" id="12">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue">William Blake, <i>Sketch of Turret house on verso of self portrait</i></p>
            c. 1800. Pencil on paper. Robert N. Essick collection.
            <p><br/>On the verso of Blake’s self portrait is a rough sketch that appears to depict Turret House and the colonnade. The sketch may be preparatory to a planned picture of Turret House that was never begun or is now lost. The miniaturist, George Engleheart executed a pencil sketch and a watercolour of Turret House during a visit to Hayley. For a comparison of Engleheart’s two pictures and Blake’s sketch, see https://bq.blakearchive.org/41.2.crosby</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.13" id="13">
        <title>
        </title>
        <caption>
                        <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce and William Hayley, <i>Plan of the Library Decorations</i></p>
            Pen, ink, and pencil on paper. James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New Haven.
            <p><br/>In an undated drawing by Bunce of a rectangular room with a fireplace and at least one window, Hayley has added a series of names of authors, sometimes in a contracted form, next to circles that run along each wall. The circles could denote roundel frames. Starting with Cowper on the lower right of the plan and proceeding clockwise, the authors Hayley lists are as follows: Spenser, Cowley, Cicero, Voltaire, Shakespeare, Dryden, Sappho, Tasso, Camöens, Anacreon, Pope, Euripides, Ariosto, Demosthenes, Horace, Livy, and Edward Gibbon. The exclusion of Thomas Alphonso from this plan and his inclusion in Blake’s eighteen portraits suggests that it was drafted before May 1800 and, therefore, before Blake arrived in Felpham. This sketch of the library does not include features such as the recess and three doors that we see in Bunce’s third design and appears to be based on the rectangular library in his second design. While some of the subjects differ from Blake’s series, this sketch with Hayley’s manuscript additions suggests pairings for eight portraits. It is likely that the sketch represents Hayley’s early, if not initial intensions regarding a positional arrangement for a series of portraits in roundels to decorate the upper library at Turret House.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.14" id="14">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
                        <p style="color: skyblue">Samuel Bunce, <i>Position of Decorations</i></p>
            James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New Haven.
            <p><br/>An indication of where Blake’s portraits were hung is suggested in Bunce’s letter to Hayley of 20 March 1798, where the architect expresses his concern over the width of a proposed frieze to decorate the Felpham library: “I hope you will not make the frieze so wide as you mention I have therefore only increased it by ½ an inch”. Bunce appears to be referring to a continuous frieze. A sketch on the verso of Bunce and Hayley’s undated plan for the decorations in the upper library supports this notion of a frieze, with a series of portraits were to occupy a position above the chairs, probably in an area between the bookcases and the ceilings. While differing in length, Blake’s portraits are of similar height, which indicates they were hung in an area of uniform height, such as between the bookcases and the ceiling. It must be noted that the exact dimensions of the paintings may have altered as they have been relined at least once.
            </p>
            <p>
                In Britain, the tradition of decorating libraries with portraits of authors in roundel frames as part of a larger frieze located above bookcases may be traced to the Bodleian Library, Oxford. The Bodleian frieze was painted between 1616 and 1618 and consists of 202 portraits in roundels located in a cornice between the bookcases and the ceiling. Between each portrait are depictions of scrolls, books, inkpots and quills. In some instances there are allegorical items associated with the passage of time, such as hour-glasses and skulls. The use of portraits arranged in a frieze was two-fold, to represent visually the classification of subjects within large libraries and to confer authority onto the library and inspiration to its readers. In 1661 Gabriel Naude advocated the pictorial representation of learned men in libraries, declaring that “good copies drawn from such as are most famous in the Profession of letters [act as] a puissant spurre to excite a generous and well-born soul to follow their track [sic]”. This was certainly one of the aims of the frieze in the Bodleian Library. As well as providing intellectual inspiration and subject classification, the decorations in domestic libraries such as Hayley’s also offered visual signification of the tastes and social status of the owner.
            </p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.15" id="15">
        <title>
            
        </title>
        <caption>
                        <p style="color: skyblue">George Steevens and William Hayley, <i>Mr Hayley’s list of the Portraits of English Poets</i></p>
            Mark Crosby collection.
            <p><br/>An undated manuscript document co-written by Hayley and his friend, the Shakespeare scholar, George Steevens, demonstrates Hayley’s interest in the portraits of English authors. This list may have functioned as a catalogue of portraits that Hayley either owned as prints, or that he wanted and that it was used by Steevens as a buying guide to locate portraits at print and art sellers in London that Hayley didn’t yet own. Some of the subjects, for example, are marked with an extended dash followed by the letter ‘w’, which may denote portraits that are ‘wanted’. The list includes the names of all the English authors who appear in Blake’s series with the exception of Alexander Pope.</p>
        </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="absorbedbythepoets.16" id="16">
        <title>
                        <p style="font-size: 16px;">Gallery 2</p>
        </title>
        <caption>
            <p style="color: skyblue"></p>
        </caption>
    </image>
</exhibit>