<exhibit id="authenticatingblake" title="Authenticating Blake: Lifetime Impressions, Posthumous Prints, and Forgeries"
    article="authenticatingblake.exhibit.html" composition_date_string="July 2021">

    <image dbi="fb.2" id="1">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption>
We will start our survey by defamiliarizing the first plate of the two-plate poem “Spring,” noting what it is and isn’t. Our impression was printed c. 1804 from a relief-etched copperplate executed in 1789 and is in a copy of Songs of Innocence designated Q. We derive this information about the design and copy contextually, from a body of knowledge about Blake’s illuminated books and not from the image, which does not reveal itself as a print. It resembles a drawing or an illustrated manuscript, and Blake’s contemporaries would have experienced it as such. 
<br/>
<br/>
In place of graphic codes—the kind of marks left by burins, needles, stipplers, and roulettes—we see water color washes, pen and ink outlining, and an under drawing in yellow ochre, with parallel line hatching in the dress characteristic of drawing. We see the same yellow ochre in the text and note that the letter forms vary, ruling out type and signaling a quill, the nib of which was cut to produce thin and wide strokes. We see signs of painting, drawing, and calligraphy; we do not see signs of a machine (printing press or metal tools). 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.3" id="2">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption>
Nevertheless, we suspect that the image may be a print because of its rectangular form and specifically because the form is misaligned on the leaf. Moreover, the paper is wove, not laid, as in letterpress and manuscripts. The reproduction on the left is how illuminated prints are usually represented in books and the Blake Archive, trimmed to the image to reduce printing costs and file size, respectively. While aesthetically pleasing, designs so trimmed hide information. For example, this impression of “Spring” is very poorly registered, slanting towards the spine and falling on the page. Yet Blake finished it along with the other impressions forming this copy of Innocence. It was presumably printed by Catherine Blake, who knew how to print relief and intaglio plates. She may have held it up to show Blake, who apparently was not alarmed, which is to say, the Blakes had a very low threshold for acceptance, an aspect of their practice that William Muir, a facsimilist of illuminated books in the late 19th c., referred to as “artful carelessness.”
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.4" id="3">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption>
We turn the leaf over to see that, like a print, its image is on the recto only; the leaf serves as a page in a book, but because it has no image on its verso, the book lacks facing pages, an essential feature of the codex format. The second part of the design is on a separate leaf, and it too was poorly registered (not an uncommon sight in illuminated books); we notice also that the two parts making up the poem are not the same size.  Indeed, all the Innocence plates differ in size, which means that Catherine had to register paper to plate by eye and not to a shared underlying template that marked the plate’s and paper’s positions. Because of this mode of registration and the variation among plate sizes, the pages comprising a copy of Innocence cannot have uniform margins. The absence of exact uniformity among pages is another feature of Blake’s illuminated books that counters book convention and reinforces the illusion of manuscript.
<br/><br/>
So, what kind of images are these? The designs appear to combine outlines transferred from matrices and finished in watercolors and pen and ink. The matrices, however, do not reveal themselves as such, leaving no noticeable emboss or platemarks or edges. We hold the small leaves in our hands, experience them sensually and intimately, as a new hybrid, an oxymoronic “printed manuscript” (Essick, Language of Adam 170). 
<br/><br/>
The leaves of this particular copy of Innocence were bound with 27 other leaves by string that was passed through stab holes along the inner margin. Blake used this temporary mode of binding leaves of copies, knowing that buyers would have their copies professionally bound and trimmed, as they would any copy of any book, because books were at this time bought in uncut sheets. Blake’s simple mode of binding also allowed owners to present the leaves as drawings, storing them in portfolios. 
 </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.5" id="4">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption> 
When we see other copies of the design, our suspicion that “Spring” is some kind of print is confirmed. Multiple impressions of the design reveal that “Spring” was repeatable, but also that Blake ignored print and book paradigms of exact repeatability. Each impression of the design and each copy of the book is unique, not only because the impressions were hand colored, but because the Blakes treated the printed outline as an under drawing to be finished anew each time. Colored prints were not uncommon, but the colors in such prints followed models, with colorists applying one or two colors before passing a print to the next colorist. This mode of coloring prints ensured consistency, whereas the Blakes’ mode of finishing designs independent of one another and without a model ensured variations among impressions, even those colored in the same sessions. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.6" id="5">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption>
We can trace the 37 year printing history of the design, from first printings in 1789 to last printings in 1827, for clues to its technique. The first copies of Innocence had 31 plates, with copies U, V, and W printed in black ink on one side of the leaf. Blake soon moved from this book of prints format to the more conventional book of poems by printing the plates on both sides of the leaf. He printed 17 copies in 1789 in green, yellow-ochre, and sienna ink; he wiped the ink from the edges of plates, which removed the shape of the matrices and reinforced the illusion of a design drawn, not printed, on paper. He lightly washed the vignettes but left the texts uncolored. 
<br/><br/>
In 1794, Blake reduced Innocence to 28 plates by moving two plates to Experience, his new collection of poems, and combined copies of Innocence printed in 1789 with copies of Experience to create Songs of Innocence and of Experience copies B, C, and D. In 1794, Blake also began printing illuminated books on one side of the leaf and most of them in colors. By the end of 1795 Blake had concluded his first, or early, period of illuminated printing; between 1796 and 1817 he printed only one new illuminated book (Milton a Poem, c. 1811) and a handful of copies of the earlier works. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.7" id="6">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption>
When he returned to illuminated printing in 1818, he moved two more Innocence plates to Experience, reducing Innocence to 26 plates, and he established the plate order, from plate 1 to 54. “Spring” was now numbered 22 and 23. The plate order in all copies of Innocence and Songs printed before 1818 was unique, presumably the result of Blake printing numerous impressions per plate and copies being compiled from loose impressions at the time of sale. Late copies were printed per copy, often with one copy commissioned providing the opportunity for printing a second copy for stock.
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.8" id="7">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption> 
He changed his printing and finishing styles dramatically. He printed in bright orangish and reddish inks and finished impressions like miniature paintings, often using shell gold. He printed the plate’s borders and emphasized its rectangular form with frame lines or floral decorations. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.9" id="8">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Introduction</p></title><caption>
Tracing the design’s 37 year printing history reveals the evolution of Blake’s printing and finishing styles, which in turn provide clues for dating copies of illuminated books.  More specifically, it reveals the evolution of Innocence, from a collection of 31 to 26 plates sequenced uniquely per copy until 1818. Moreover, it reveals that on the last seven impressions of the design, at the bottom right of the vignette, Blake added a sheep (slides 7, 8, 9). The design’s printing history does not, however, reveal how the design was made. 
</caption>
    </image>

	<image dbi="fb.10" id="9">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
Woodcut printed with text and “Spring” from Innocence copy U
The flatness and autographic marks of pen and brush suggests lithography, originally known as polyautography, which transferred drawings from the surface of fine grain limestone to paper. In effect, lithography--or planographic printing--multiplied drawings executed in specially made ink or crayon. Lithography, however, was not invented till 1798, leaving Blake just two options for making printable designs: creating the design as a relief wood block or as an intaglio copper plate. 
<br/><br/>
The ink in “Spring” lies flat on the paper and the matrix did not emboss the paper, features characteristic of woodcuts, wood engravings, and other relief prints. But the outline in woodcuts are defined indirectly, by cutting away the whites to leave the outline standing in relief; in wood engraving, the design is defined by a combination of white lines made directly with the burin and black lines and shapes cut away with knives. Moreover, while woodcuts and wood engravings can be set and printed with type on a platen press, image and text present themselves as independently made and discrete units of the design. Such tools and techniques cannot produce the pen and brush marks and integral designs of Blake’s illuminated books. Nor can the tools used to make intaglio prints.
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.11" id="10">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
In intaglio printing, designs are incised in copper plates by metal tools, such as burins, stipplers, roulettes, and needles. Each set of tools defines a particular technique and each technique has a recognizable character and look. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.12" id="11">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
Reproductive engraving, the technique in which Blake was trained, was a combination of etching and engraving. The design’s outline was first transferred on a waxy film covering the plate, traced with needles to expose the metal, and etched into the plate with acid. These preliminary etched lines were gone over and finished with various tipped burins. This overlapping of techniques, known as “mixed method” engraving, gave engraved lines both flexibility and strength. Engraving’s tapering lines and dot-and-lozenge methods of hatching (aka banknote engraving) distinguishes it from the pen like lines created by needles scratching through a thin film. Intaglio printing also includes techniques that reproduce the tonal effects of wash drawings (aquatint), oil paintings (mezzotint), and chalk drawings (chalk engraving). 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.13" id="12">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
The contemporary taste for drawings and sketches led to their codes being imitated in print facsimiles by ingenious combinations of intaglio techniques and novel uses of their tools. Cipiani, for example, using specially cut needles, recreated many pen and ink drawings by Bartolozzi; brush marks could also be imitated, but, as with pen lines, the marks, upon close inspection, reveal that they were carefully reconstructed by many fine lines. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.14" id="13">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
Blake’s brush and pen marks look genuine, unlike those in etched facsimiles of drawings, because they are. Instead of imitating such marks, Blake executed text and image using the tools and methods of writing and drawing, that is, he actually wrote and drew with pens and brushes.  He took the standard “stop-out” varnish used in etching to protect areas from acid and used it as an impervious ink. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.15" id="14">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
Blake executed text and image together and etched them into printable relief. Blake had created “relief etching,” though he called his invention “illuminated printing.” 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.16" id="15">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
Intaglio facsimiles of drawings also reveal themselves as prints because of their platemarks—the embossment of plate into paper—and the printing ink lying slightly raised on the paper. These features are the result of a rolling press, the machine all intaglio plates use to transfer ink from plate to paper. The intaglio design is filled with ink, the plate’s surface is wiped clean, and the plate is printed on dampened paper, which the press forces into the incised lines and areas. 
Blake used a rolling press to print illuminated plates, but he used light pressure and left no pronounced platemark. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.17" id="16">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: 18th-century Print Technologies</p></title><caption>
Blake’s authentic pen and brush marks combined with the absence of metal tools and printing press—the signs of reproduction—gave his illuminated prints the look of manuscript, drawings, and paintings. 
</caption>
    </image>

	<image dbi="fb.18" id="17">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
Innocence copy T, “Spring”
Like post 1794 copies of illuminated books, Innocence copy T comprises impressions  printed on one side of the paper and, like the last copies (1818-1827), its impression of “Spring” has the added sheep. However, its impressions were printed in a black ink, not the bright red and orange inks of late copies; it has a light wash behind the text, but no plate borders or frame lines. 
<br/><br/>
The impression was unquestionably printed from Blake’s relief-etching. But where does this copy belong in the history of Innocence or Songs? Was it printed by Blake? Is it Blake’s coloring? If not printed by Blake, then by whom? Catherine Blake? Frederick Tatham? 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.19" id="18">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
We have a problem. The coloring of the vignette in our newly discovered impression is too close to Innocence copy B, from 1789, as the band of three colors in the sky demonstrates. Blake and Catherine did not copy themselves in these ways. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.20" id="19">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
Something is wrong with this picture. I go to Innocence copy T’s “The Little Black Boy” to compare it to the impression in Innocence copy B. In copy T, the mother’s hair bun has been cut off, an alteration present only in posthumous copies of Songs. To verify whether copy T’s impression is posthumous, I measure it. If posthumously printed, it should be slightly larger than life-time impressions, because it was printed on dry paper, a feature true in all verified posthumous copies and prints—those printed on paper watermarked 1831 and 1832--, whereas the Blakes printed on damp paper, which shrinks 2 to 4%.  The copy T impression is slightly larger than known lifetime impressions.
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.21" id="20">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
“The Little Black Boy” in Innocence copy U, from 1789, and Songs copy O, from 1795, show the mother’s bun as drawn on the copper plate; Innocence copy B shows how Blake could reshape the mother’s back and hair by wiping ink from them and by coloring, rather than trimming the metal relief lines that formed them. 
<br/><br/>
Innocence copy T is from Blake’s relief-etched plate, but the copperplate has been altered and brought to a new state; this second state of the plate is clearly posthumous, as is evinced by its presence in Songs copy h, which is on paper watermarked 1831 and 1832, and by its absence in the last copies of Songs known to have been printed and finished by Blake. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.22" id="21">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
Innocence copy T has 29 plates, which also raises red flags, because all copies of Innocence printed on one side of the leaf have 28. More troubling, it has plates 34, 35, and 36 (“Little Girl Lost” and “Little Girl Found”), the three plates that Blake moved to Experience in 1794 and are only in copies of Innocence with 31 plates, i. e., copies printed in 1789. Equally troubling, Innocence copy T follows the plate order of copy B, which is very suspicious given how Catherine and Blake compiled the early copies and all other copies before 1818 had unique plate orders. Innocence copy T comprises recto only impressions, but it is imitating the unique plate order of a recto/verso early copy.
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.23" id="22">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
Innocence copy T is a forgery imitating the coloring and structure of Innocence copy B. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.24" id="23">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy T</p></title><caption>
Innocence copy T was derived from a copy of Songs posthumously printed by Tatham on Whatman paper in black ink, c. 1831-32. The copy initially had 53 plates, missing plates 15 and 53, but probably including “A Divine Image” (pl. b). It was one of six complete copies of Songs that Tatham had abridged to 40-42 plates, c. 1832-40, by extracting a cluster of 12 to 14 Experience plates (see Viscomi, “Posthumous Blake”). 
<br/><br/>
Someone, probably a dealer, acquired the abridged copy and extracted the remaining Experience plates to transform it into a near complete copy of Innocence and had the impressions colored and ordered in imitation of Innocence copy B. Subtracting impressions to make a complete looking copy of Innocence was easier than finding and adding the missing Experience impressions to build a complete copy of Songs, and, in turn, a complete colored copy of Innocence was more lucrative financially than an incomplete copy of Songs, let alone one recognized as posthumous. 
<br/><br/>
The dealer may have assumed that the impressions were life-time; nevertheless, the actions performed on the copy were done with the intent to deceive, which makes the copy a forgery and not merely an abridged copy of Songs posthumously printed by Tatham and posthumously colored by a second hand. The forgery is detected by its incoherent mix of printing and finishing styles and plate order and presence of a known second state of “The Little Black Boy.” Ironically, the forger’s adherence to models and the lack of variation in the plate order reveals the copy as a forgery.
<br/><br/>
The provenance of Innocence copy B is unknown between 1834, at the death of Clarke, its first known owner, and 1906, when it was sold anonymously at Sotheby’s to the book dealer Robson. Innocence copy T was unknown until 1910, when it sold anonymously at Hodgson’s as “coloured by Blake.” The coloring and compiling of copy T was most likely pre-1906.  Copy T was given to Princeton University Library in 1950 as a life time copy and unmasked in 1993 (see Viscomi, Blake and the Idea of the Book). 
</caption>
    </image>
	
	<image dbi="fb.25" id="24">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
Pierpont Morgan bought a composite copy of Songs in 1901 from James Toovey, a well-known and respected book dealer. It comprised 40 impressions printed in sepia, designated copy e, and 14 impressions printed in brown ink from a copy designated K. The two sets of impressions were colored but did not match.
</caption>
    </image>
	<image dbi="fb.26" id="25">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
The sepia ink of Songs copy e, as demonstrated by “The Little Black Boy,” is smooth and flat, noticeably different than the brown ink of Songs copy K, as demonstrated by “To Tirzah.” The sepia is a relief ink, which is made with a boiled linseed oil that enables the ink to transfer with light pressure. The brown is an intaglio ink, which is made with a viscous burnt linseed oil that enables the ink to stay in intagliate lines when the surface is wiped clean; consequently, when printed with light pressure, the ink reticulates. The different kinds of ink represent different materials, practices, and printers. Blake, a trained engraver, printed on damp paper with intaglio ink; Tatham printed on dry paper with relief inks. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.27" id="26">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
Blake did not print in sepia colored inks or relief inks. However, Tatham printed copies of Songs, America, Europe, and Jerusalem in a sepia relief ink. The examples from America copy P, Europe copy M, and Jerusalem copy I demonstrate the quality of Tatham’s printing and the ink’s range of hue, from a reddish brown to a brownish red. These impressions, printed on dry paper, are a few mm. larger than life-time impressions and have flat, smoother ink surfaces. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.28" id="27">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
The texture and color of the ink of Songs copy e raises suspicions that a comparison to Songs copy Y immediately confirm: Songs copy e is a forgery. The coloring closely imitated the coloring of Songs copy Y. These are not things that Pierpont Morgan or his agents could have recognized when they acquired copy e in 1901. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.29" id="28">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
Songs copy e was posthumously printed by Tatham on Whatman paper in sepia, c. 1831. It originally had 54 plates. As he had with five other complete copies of Songs—including the one that was used to form Innocence copy T—, Tatham extracted a cluster of Experience plates by 1832-40, reducing this sepia copy to 40 plates. It was acquired by an unknown collector and sold as part of their large Blake collection at Sotheby’s in 1862. All or nearly all of the Blake works in this collection once belonged to Tatham, which raises the likelihood that Songs copy e was acquired directly from Tatham.  Toovey acquired it uncolored, presumably believing it was an incomplete but original copy. 
<br/><br/>
Toovey, or possibly an unknown collector to whom he sold it, had the 40 impressions of Songs copy e colored in imitation of Songs copy Y, which Blake printed c. 1826, apparently for Edward Calvert, one of the young artists who surrounded Blake in his last years and in whose family it remained till 1893. The coloring of copy e probably occurred before 1893, when Songs copy Y was acquired by a new collector. 
<br/><br/>
How long Songs copy e was in this transformed condition is not known. Toovey owned the copy in the 1890s, when he combined it with impressions from Songs copy K. Whether he re-acquired copy e already transformed or held onto it and was the one who had it transformed is also not known. If Toovey re-acquired the 40-plate copy colored in imitation of copy Y, he would have assumed the copy was original and not have recognized it as the uncolored copy he acquired in 1862. 
<br/><br/>
The idea that anyone would color what they believed to be uncolored impressions printed by Blake strikes us as audacious, if not an outright act of vandalism (for that, see Songs copy M). Admittedly, Victorian standards for editing texts and images—for respecting the integrity of original art objects—were lower than today’s. Nevertheless, the person responsible for transforming what they thought was printed by Blake into a late copy colored by Blake committed fraud. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.30" id="29">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
By the time Morgan acquired Songs copy e, it had grown to 54 plates. Sometime in the 1890s, Toovey had acquired 28 uncolored impressions of Experience, all printed by Blake, as their measurements and reticulated inks attest. Toovey or his son Charles extracted 14 impressions from this set of impressions, now designated Songs copy K, and had them colored to complete Songs copy e. The colorist of the copy K impressions, though, did not use a model and did not try to match the coloring style or technique, as exemplified by “To Tirzah,” to the faux copy Y impressions.  While completing books with leaves from other books was not uncommon, selling the coloring of the life time impressions as Blake’s was fraud. Unravelling posthumous printing and coloring of the once combined copy e/K was first demonstrated in Viscomi’s Blake and the Idea of the Book, 1993. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.31" id="30">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy e/K</p></title><caption>
Pierpont Morgan’s composite copy of Songs comprised life time and posthumous impressions, all of which were posthumously colored. It was the product of four hands: Tatham printed the 40 sepia impressions, c. 1831-32; Blake printed the brown impressions, c. 1795; a colorist finished Tatham’s impressions after Songs copy Y, between 1862 and c. 1890; a colorist finished Blake’s impressions, between c. 1890 and 1901, without a model or attempting to match the work of the first colorist.
</caption>
    </image>
	
	<image dbi="fb.32" id="31">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orangered">Gallery V: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy f/j</p></title><caption>
The impressions making up Songs of Innocence and of Experience copy j are well printed and professionally colored, but neither printing nor coloring was by Blake. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.33" id="32">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orangered">Gallery V: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy f/j</p></title><caption>
Songs copy U is a very beautiful copy, elaborately colored and finished in pen and ink, with frame lines presenting the design as a miniature painting. Songs copy j was carefully colored in Blake’s late style, with light washes behind texts. The colors in the vignette, however, especially in the tree, are thicker and laid in more heavily than was characteristic of Blake’s style of finishing. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.34" id="33">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orangered">Gallery V: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy f/j</p></title><caption>
Comparing “The Little Black Boy” from Songs copy j to the impression in Songs copy U, a beautiful copy printed and colored by Blake in 1818, reveals that the copy j impression is posthumous.  The mother’s hair bun was trimmed, the ink lays unreticulated and flat, and the design—and all the other designs of Songs copy j—is slightly larger than the copy U impression. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.35" id="34">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orangered">Gallery V: <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy f/j</p></title><caption>
Like Innocence copy T and Songs copy e, Songs copy j began as a complete 54-plate uncolored copy of Songs printed by Tatham in sepia c. 1831-32. It was not, however, abridged. Copy j is probably the uncolored 54 plate copy that was acquired in 1836 by a collector who had it bound by 1869 and which subsequently disappeared. It reappeared in 1919, colored in the style of a late copy and sold as an origin to the owner of Songs copy U, which Blake printed and colored in 1818 and which may have served loosely as the model for the coloring styles. It was acquired as an original copy by 00, given to Princeton University Library in 00, and unmasked in 00. 
</caption>
    </image>
	
	<image dbi="fb.36" id="35">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:turquoise">Gallery VI: <i>For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</i></p></title><caption>
Catherine was a fine printer in her own right. She knew how to ink and print intaglio plates, skills that enabled her, in 1805, to print Blake’s two engravings for Hayley’s biography of Cowper in an edition of 500 copies, which amounted to 1000 impressions (E 726). She and Tatham were the only people with access to Blake’s press and plates after the artist died, 27 August 1827. By mid-September 1827, Catherine had moved herself and Blake’s plates, press, art works, and all of their belongings to the Fitzroy Square studio of John Linnell. She stayed till early Spring, 1828, by which time she appears to have printed a few copies of Blake’s Canterbury Pilgrims engraving, a portrait of 00, and copies F, G, H, and I of For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise (Viscomi, “Posthumous Blake”). These were the first of Blake’s works posthumously produced and demonstrate her ability to print Blake’s plates on her own. 
</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="fb.37" id="36">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:sienna">Gallery VII: <i>America a Prophecy</i> Copy Q</p></title><caption>
Catherine also knew how Blake printed relief etchings, presumably from handling the press and paper while Blake inked the plates and brought them to the press bed. In c. 1829. she printed America a Prophecy copy Q, which follows the pattern of Innocence copy T, Songs copy e, and Songs f/j, in that it was printed soon after Blake died and colored much later by a third party with intention to pass it as a life time copy. She also printed America copy N and Europe copies I and L. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.38" id="37">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:sienna">Gallery VII: <i>America a Prophecy</i> Copy Q</p></title><caption>
America a Prophecy, dated 1793, was the first of Blake's "Continental Prophecies," followed by Europe a Prophecy in 1794, executed in the same style and size but usually colored, and, in 1795, "Africa" and "Asia," two sections making up The Song of Los. Blake described America as folio in the 1793 Prospectus and, along with Europe, in his 1818 letter to Dawson Turner. All lifetime copies were folio in size—approximately 37 x 27 cm., which are quarters of Imperial sheets—except America Copy O and Europe Copy K, the last copies that Blake printed, in 1821 for John Linnell, which are quarto in size, at 30 x 24 cm. Catherine Blake appears to have used these late copies as her model, printing America copy Q and Europe copy L as matching quartos, at 29.5 x 22.1 cm., c. 1829 on Ruse and Turner laid paper dated 1812. She also printed America copy N and Europe copy I as matching quartos, at 32.6 x 23.6 cm., on T. Stains wove paper dated 1813. 
<br/><br/>
America comprises eighteen major text and design plates and a small plate (e) bearing the word "Preludium" and printed above the design on plate 3. Ten of the fourteen life time extant copies of America were printed in 1793 on both sides of leaves in bluish and greenish black inks and left uncolored. The last five lines of plate 4 were masked and did not print, and plate 13 was printed in its first of two states. Catherine Blake printed plate 4 unmasked, plate 13 in its final state, and did not print plate e. She printed on one side of the leaf and left the impressions uncolored. Her impressions are closer in appearance and feel to Blake’s impressions than Tatham’s. She printed in black intaglio ink on dampened paper, resulting in reticulated surfaces; she touched up impressions in light washes and numbered them in the top right corner. These features are characteristic of Blake’s practice and differentiate her books from all the posthumous illuminated books printed by Tatham. 
<br/><br/>
The impressions of plate 4 from America copies Q and N share accidentals and traces of ink printed from the shallows (which washes cover up in copy Q), evidence that Catherine printed America copy N and copy Q back to back in the same session. With Tatham acting as intermediary, Catherine sold America copy N to James Ferguson, who also bought Europe copy I, which she printed, and Visions of the Daughters of Albion copy N, which Blake had printed in 1818. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.39" id="38">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:sienna">Gallery VII: <i>America a Prophecy</i> Copy Q</p></title><caption>
America Copy Q was acquired between 1913 and 1918 by Walter T. Spencer, who had it colored in imitation of copy A, which Blake printed and colored in 1795. Spencer’s colorist, however, did not use Blake’s original; he used William Muir’s 1887 lithographic facsimile of America Copy A, which was based on tracings. Using a facsimile as the model allowed the colorist to work undetected. Copy Q was first recognized as posthumously colored in 1939, when exhibited in Philadelphia. The status of the coloring was confirmed by Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf in their 1953 Census. The possibility that copy Q was also posthumously printed was first suggested by G. E. Bentley Jr., in his 1977 Blake Books.
<br/><br/>
The original owner of America copy N and early curators at the Auckland Library where the book now resides assumed that this copy was printed by Blake. The paper is dated 1812 and 1813. The first owners of copy Q may have thought the same, and that includes Spencer.  Nevertheless, coloring copy Q in imitation of a life time copy was fraud. 
</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="fb.40" id="39">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:steelblue">Gallery VIII: <i>Europe a Prophecy</i> Copy L</p></title><caption>
Europe a Prophecy, dated 1794, is the second of Blake's "Continental Prophecies," following America a Prophecy of 1793 and preceding “Africa” and “Asia,” the two sections of The Song of Los, of 1795. Europe presents in mythopoeic form the conflict between liberty and tyranny, the fundamental philosophical issues of Blake's revolutionary era. Blake etched Europe's eighteen plates in relief, with considerable white-line work in some designs, on the versos of America’s eighteen plates. The posthumous copies are missing plate 3, a whimsical prefatory statement—present only in Copies H and K—about a "Fairy [who] sat upon the table, and dictated Europe." Blake paired Europe and America but did not print them together until 1821, when he produced Europe Copy K and America Copy O for John Linnell, which are smaller than earlier copies and appears to have been Catherine Blake’s model for printing Europe Copy L and America Copy Q as matching quartos, at 29.5 x 22.1 cm., on Ruse and Turner laid paper dated 1812. 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.41" id="40">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:steelblue">Gallery VIII: <i>Europe a Prophecy</i> Copy L</p></title><caption>
Europe copies I and L were printed by Catherine Blake in the same printing session. The traces of ink printed from the shallows are covered in copy L by washes that were laid in by the same colorist who finished America copy Q, between 1913 and 1918, and with the same intent to deceive. Coloring the book greatly increased its value; whether the dealer recognized that the printing was posthumous is irrelevant to their selling this copy off as original.
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.42" id="41">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:steelblue">Gallery VIII: <i>Europe a Prophecy</i> Copy L</p></title><caption>
Europe copy L follows the same pattern as America copy Q. It was acquired between 1913 and 1918 by Walter T. Spencer, who had it colored in imitation of Europe copy A, which Blake printed and colored in 1795. Spencer’s colorist, however, did not use Blake’s original; he used William Muir’s 1887 lithographic facsimile of Europe, which was made from tracings of a copy of Europe and most impressions hand colored in imitation of copy A. Working from facsimiles rather than originals allowed the colorist to work undetected. Europe copy A’s coloring was first recognized as posthumous by Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf in their 1953 Census. However, they did not report posthumous printing for Europe copy L, a possibility first suggested by G. E. Bentley, Jr., in his 1977 Blake Books and confirmed by Robert N. Essick in his 1985 catalogue of the Huntington collection. The identity of Catherine Blake as printer of Europe Copy L (as well as America Copy Q) is demonstrated in Joseph Viscomi’s “Posthumous Blake.” 
<br/><br/>
The original owner of Europe copy I and early curators at the Auckland Library where the book now resides assumed that this copy was printed by Blake. The paper is dated 1813. The first owners of copy L may have thought the same, and that includes Spencer.  Nevertheless, coloring copy L in imitation of a life time copy and selling it as Blake’s work was fraud. 
</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="fb.43" id="42">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:springgreen">Gallery IX: Photolithographs, Keriographs</p></title><caption>
America copies B and F, plate 4
America copy B was printed by Blake in 1795, along with copy A, as part of a deluxe set of illuminated books apparently commissioned by George Romney. By 1868, when copy B entered the collection of Dew-Smith, it was missing plates 4 and 9.  To complete the copy, Dew-Smith replaced these missing plates with photolithographic facsimiles, which he appears to have executed himself.  An independently wealthy collector of romantic literature who had trained at Cambridge in physiology, Dew-Smith owned a company that provided photolithographic facsimiles to publishers of maps and old texts. Though apparently executed as facsimiles to complete his copy of America, not as forgeries to deceive, the facsimiles were taken as originals after copy B was sold in 1870 and were not discovered as copies until 1978 (see Viscomi, “Forgery or Facsimile”). Nothing in the images gives them away; comparing plates 4 and 9 in copy B to life-time impressions would not reveal that they were fakes. Making that determination required examination of the physical object.
<br/><br/>
My suspicion of them was based on the paper, which was stiffer and harder than the other 16 leaves in the copy. The paper was not like any I knew Blake to have used, but it was like a German etching paper that I was using at the time in my own printing. With suspicions raised, I measured the image: height and width were the same as life-time impressions, but diagonally it was elongated, the result of a convex lens projecting the image onto a photosensitized zinc plate. The faint embossments of the relief-etched plates were put in by hand, the paper scored slightly with a beveled ruler to create the illusion of plate into paper as opposed to plate on paper (see Viscomi, “Two Fake Blakes Revisited”).   
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.44" id="43">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:springgreen">Gallery IX: Photolithographs, Keriographs</p></title><caption>
Dew-Smith used America copy F, in the British Museum, as his model for plates 4 and 9. Blake printed copy F in 1793 and masked the five lines of text under the vignette so that they did not print. Blake’s intaglio ink printed lighter than the lithographic ink, which was mixed with a magnesium powder to increase its opacity.
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.45" id="44">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:springgreen">Gallery IX: Photolithographs, Keriographs</p></title><caption>
The Book of Job reproductions in Gilchrist’s Life of Blake, 1863, were the first photolithographic reproductions of works by Blake. They were produced at the urging of Dante Rossetti, who, with his brother William Michael, assisted Anne Gilchrist in completing the biography. William Linton, who designed and provided over 100 illustrations for the Life, did not like the photolithographs because they were too dark and wanted to reproduce them as wood engravings, the medium of which he was a master. Linton, a very Blakean figure in his own right, was an illustrator, printmaker, poet, and inventor. For the Life, he had invented “keriography,” a process that enabled him to trace Blake’s designs and print them as line blocks with letterpress. He used this method to produce the Experience title plate, the original plate of which was missing among the ten plates—some etched on both sides of the copper—from Songs that Tatham had lent Gilchrist for the purpose of making electrotypes and printing them as facsimiles in the Life (see Viscomi, “Blake after Blake”). 
</caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="fb.46" id="45">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:springgreen">Gallery IX: Photolithographs, Keriographs</p></title><caption>
There is No Natural Religion, c. 1788, existed in twelve extant copies comprising different  plates and different number of plates, which made editing this tiny series of emblems and precepts impossible. In 1989, six of the twelve copies were discovered to be forgeries. Once they were removed from the canon, the remaining genuine impressions revealed that Blake had abridged the originally 20 plate No Natural Religion to twelve plates from the book’s a and b series. Around 1794, he color printed enough impressions to form six copies (A, B, C, D, G, and M); the following year, he printed copy L, which comprised only the b series of plates and was part of his deluxe set of illuminated books (see Viscomi, BIB chapters 21 and 22). 
<br/><br/>
The 1862 Sotheby auction in which posthumous Songs copy e was sold included 50 impressions of No Natural Religion. In 1890, another pile of impressions, of eight designs, was discovered. They were compiled into six incomplete copies of No Natural Religion, which were missing a few plates from the first pile of impressions. The set of impressions comprising the second pile, however, were forgeries—or at least became so when assumed to be by Blake and sold as original copies. Stoppard Brooks, the person who found them, had no reason to assume they were not genuine. The designs were clearly printed into the paper from relief plates and were on paper watermarked 1811. They appear to have been part of an aborted facsimile project, produced, perhaps, by keriography, c. 1870. They were not detected as facsimiles/forgeries until 1989. 
<br/><br/>
Ironically, two of the six fake copies of No Natural Religion were acquired by Thomas Wise and Buxton Forman, both of whom were to be unmasked as forgers of first editions by Shelley and Keats by Carter, in one of the great bibliographic detectives stories, An Enquiry into some Nineteenth Century Pamphlets, 1933. Before the fake Blake impressions were unmasked, however, they had entered esteemed collections, including Library of Congress, British Library, and Morgan Library, which provided the last institution with duplicate impressions of the book. Years later, the Morgan Library de-accessioned and auctioned off their duplicates; they kept the cleaner impressions, printed on 1811 paper, and sold the originals. 
<br/><br/>
Mistaking 19th c. facsimiles of illuminated prints for originals was not uncommon. In addition to Linton’s keriographs, hand-colored lithographs by John Camden Hotten, illustrator of Swinburne’s Critical Essay on Blake, 1863; photolithographic facsimile of Jerusalem published by John Pearson, 1870; and, occasionally, hand-colored lithographs by William Muir, in the 1880s, were mistaken for Blake’s work.
<br/><br/>
Detecting fakes cleans the historical record.
</caption>
    </image>
	
</exhibit>
