<exhibit id="canterburypilgrims" title="William Blake's Canterbury Pilgrims" article="canterburypilgrims.exhibit.html">

		<image dbi="ESXVI.1.3I.SP" id="1.1">

      <title>The Engraving</title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Reeve Chaucer Clerk of Oxenford Cook 1-4" id="1.2">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Reeve">
          The last rider in the procession at the far left, the reeve has short, light hair, one visible large, long ear, a prominent angular browline and rectangular forehead, large somewhat hooked nose, closed lips that may be turned slightly into a smile (though the expression is somewhat ambiguous), and a round chin with no facial hair. He looks forward following the procession of pilgrims to the right. He wears a vertically striped garment with a prominent cylindrical collar, which may alternatively be a hood. He is framed by the architectural portal in a gothic style. In comparison with the other pilgrims, the Reeve is smaller in size, which also creates the appearance that he is deeper in the space and further removed from the viewer.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Chaucer">
          The second pilgrims from the left, Chaucer is shown in full profile facing right but with head turned slightly right and toward the viewer. He wears head covering that falls just past his shoulders and appears to be made of a light textile. His hair beneath is either light or gray as is his facial hair (which may have a more specific name from Renaissance styles). His forehead is high and relatively rounded with arched, prominent eyebrows. His nose is narrow and pointed, and his eyes are large and completely open, though his gaze appears to be absent and somewhat vacant, as if engrossed in something other than the physical particularities of the scene. His lips are closed and slightly downturned. He wears an elaborately decorated gown that Blake renders with ample crosshatching. The collar, bottom hem, and edges of the sleeves are decorated with what appears to be lace in spiral and somewhat vegetative designs. He wears stockings and shoes with a low, flat heel and prominent spurs. The body beneath the garment seems rather portly, particularly in the abdominal region. The upturned, wrinkled hem at the lower left of the gown indicates movement, as if the fabric is swishing forward with the movement of the horse, which is dark in color and holds its left front leg up at a right angle with the ground. In his left hand, which is gloved, Chaucer holds the horse’s reins and perhaps the glove absent from his right hand, which holds a string of balls, perhaps rosary beads. A circular pillow or blanket is rolled up behind his back, and his overall posture is slightly slumped forward, which perhaps references his occupation as a writer/scholar rather than a man well acquainted with equestrian pursuits.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Clerk of Oxenford">
          The third pilgrim from the left and much more erect than Chaucer to his left, the Clerk of Oxenford has long light hair that falls freely down his back from beneath a square hat, which appears to be a pre-cursor to the mortarboard now associated with academic graduations. Wide-eyed, he stares directly forward and to the right. He has thin, horizontal eyebrows and a thin, somewhat downturned nose. His lips are small and tightly closed, creating a rosebud shape. He has sparse dark facial hair in a mustache and small goatee. His neck is long, thick, and columnar. He wears a garment that is similar in color and texture to Chaucer’s, though the Clerk appears to wear an undershirt and the decoration on the edges of his overcoat is more regularized and triangular. The majority of his lower body is obscured by the horse that Chaucer rides, but the Clerk’s horse is lighter in color and appears more haggard, though it also raises its right forward leg prominently.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Cook">
          The fourth pilgrim from the left, the cook rides in the background so that only his upper torso, head, and raised hands are visible. Facing right in profile, the cook tilts back his head to drink from the frothy beverage he raises to his lips with his left hand. He wears a white cloth head covering that is tied with a dark ribbon above his forehead, and no hair is visible beneath the hat. He browline curves outward, protruding sharply above his eyebrows, and his nose is similarly upturned away form his face, making his flared right nostril apparent. In contemporary physiognomy, a heavy brow ridge such as the cook’s was often associated with human groups often were thought to be less advanced than others and associated with the facial types of primates in particular. The cook’s eyes are heavily lidded, perhaps from the effects of alcohol already consumed, and his mouth is open slackly, giving him a rather slovenly appearance, which is heightened by his fat neck. Although most of his attire is obscured by the other pilgrims, he wears a garment with a moderately tall collar and the ends of his sleeves are ruffled, perhaps with lace.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Miller Wife of Bath Merchant 5-7" id="1.3">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Miller">
          The fifth pilgrims from the left, the miller is one of the few pilgrims shown with noticeably dark skin. He turns forward in a three-quarter view and stares out with large, open eyes. His hair is dark, plentiful, and curly, and his sports a sizable beard and mustache, both of which flare outward (perhaps indicating the increased stiffness of his hair’s texture). His forehead is small but thick eyebrows arch over his eyes, and his nose is wide and downturned. With his noticeably large right hand, he holds a musical pipe of some sort to his lips, and the shaft appears to extend both downward in front of him and rises again into a horn behind his left shoulder. His garment appears relatively simple: a long-sleeved tunic or overcoat with horizontal strips or threading is clasped below his neck with a single button, which supports a tall collar or perhaps a hood.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Wife of Bath">
          The sixth pilgrim from the left, the Wife of Bath rides sidesaddle with her whole body facing forward, knees spread slightly. Turning to look slightly right, her head is round and adorned with several layers of coverings and hats, including a knitted bonnet that covers her hair (although some curls may escape at the sides) and two elaborate hoods, one of which bends forward to touch the crown of her forehead. A pointed triangle stands erect on the outermost collar or hat and may indicate a hood. Her eyebrows are thin above almond-shaped eyes that are partially lidded. The ridge of her nose is thin and arched, pointing downward slightly. Her mouth, turned up at the corners into a smile, is open, revealing two prominent, somewhat uneven front teeth. Her chin below protrudes noticeably.
          <br />
          In addition to the long earrings dangling beside her face, three strands of pearls hang around her neck and bare chest; the middle strand supports a crucifix and the longest strand has a heart-shaped ornament in the middle. Her breasts, with visible nipples, swell out of her dress, which is made of a loose fabric that clings to her torso and legs. The garment also includes a sizable, spiky collar that fans outward to circle her shoulders. She sports white gloves, which extend from her elbow, and stockings cover her legs. A heavily patterned blanket with fringe covers her lap. She wears pointed-toe t-strap heels, and her right shoe includes a prominent spiked spur.
          <br />
          In her right hand, the Wife of Bath holds a stemmed glass filled with a dark liquid, perhaps wine. The horse’s reins, which are decorated with small bells, dangle over her left hand, which may also hold another long cylindrical object, maybe a riding crop. Additional small bells and bows decorate her horse’s mane.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Merchant">
          The seventh rider from the left, the merchant faces forward, turning his head slightly left, as if to look in the Wife of Bath’s direction. His face is long and gaunt, particular on the left cheek. His dark hair peeks from beneath a hat that is composed of two parts: a large round base and a smaller circular cap, perhaps reminiscent of styles associated with “oriental” traders. His eyebrows are similarly dark and raised in the middle, as if he is rather shocked by the sight of the Wife of Bath before him. His eyes, however, are less spirited and nearly halfway lidded, which coupled with his gauntness, give him an exhausted appearance. His nose is large and glaringly hooked—an attribute that Blake may employ to connote his Jewish heritage, which would be an unsurprising characteristic considering his economic occupation. His facial hair extends along his cheeks, tapering to two pointed tuffs below his round chin, following by a thick neck. Only his upper torso is visible, but his overcoat appears to have a stiff, possibly braided, collar and covers an undershirt with a minimally embellished hem. Part of his horse’s face, which is also facing forward, may be visible to the right of the parson.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Parson Man of Law and Plowman 8-10" id="1.4">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Parson">
          The eighth pilgrim from the left, the Parson is shown in direct profile on his right side as he rides forward. Unlike many of his companions, his posture is starkly erect, and he seems engrossed in the forward progress and ultimate aims of the pilgrimage. Although his hair and beard are extremely long and white, the parson’s face is relatively unlined. Thin brows arch over open, clear eyes, followed by a straight, small nose and closed lips. He wears a dark hat, which appears to be circular and somewhat floppy. His gown is also dark and unadorned; long sleeves are turned up at the hem, and the garment terminates just above his visible right ankle. His shoes are dark with white laces. Geared in a simple saddle and bridle, the Parson’s horse is light in color with shaggy hair and a short tail; it lifts its back left hoof and front right hoof, both of which have distinct metal shoes. The horse’s ears are turned back and its eyes heavily lidded.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Man of Law">
          The ninth pilgrim from the left, the Man of Law sits facing right but tilts his shoulders and head to face the viewer in three-quarter view. He has an oval face with shaggy whitish-gray hair seen beneath a triangular cap with two distinct layers, from which two tassels dangle behind his head. His gray eyebrows are bushy over open eyes that stare forward. His mustache and beard are similarly shaggy, appearing course. His nose is straight and protrudes forward over closed lips and a rosebud-shaped mouth. His neck is columnar, and he appears to wear several layers of clothes, including an overcoat with split sleeves, a woven shirt, and what may be a short lace collar. Although the Parson’s horse obscures the majority of his lower body, the Man of Law’s right knee and leg, covered in drapery, are visible by his horse’s side. His horse has dark, open eyes and a dark coat with perky ears; the animal’s bit and reins are simple and unadorned.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Plowman">
          The tenth pilgrim from the left, the Plowman rides to the right in strict profile, staring sternly at the path before him. His skin is tanned from performing agricultural labor outside. His face is angular with a high forehead, distinct cheekbones, and a rectangular chin, though the skin above his neck sags slightly. The arch of his nose is straight and protrudes foreword above tightly pursed, small lips. He wears a light-colored, woven hat with a wide, loose brim, likely worn to protect his skin further from the sun’s rays. His hair falls loosely on his neck, touching the edge of his garment, which is a simple shirt with a single button in the center. A vein protrudes prominently on the right side of his neck. He rides a light-colored horse that appears haggard from overwork—the animal’s ears fall to the side, its mouth is slackly open, and with heavily lidded eyes, the horse turns its head limply to the right. The tiredness of the horse stands in stark contrast to the alertness and forward-looking resolve of its rider, the Plowman.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image4" id="1.5">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Physician">
          The eleventh rider from the left, the Physician faces forward in a three-quarter view, and he is the leftmost figure in a closely spaced group of four pilgrims. His face is long, with a high forehead, downturned nose, and open eyes above slightly dark, sagging bags. No hair is visible beneath his hat, which Blake elaborately renders with a dark circular upper portion ringed by what appears to be white fur attached to descending sides that cover the Physician’s ears. He sports a two-part mustache and somewhat straggly facial hair that tapers into two points below his chin. Like his hat, the Physician’s overcoat has white fur trim attached to what appears to be woven material. The garment underneath has a lightly colored collar and a geometric pattern on the shirt itself. He rides a darkish horse with a shaggy mane that turns its head to the right in the direction of the three-horse group. The horse’s reigns appear to be slightly decorated, which aligns with the opulence of the Physician’s attire.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Franklin">
          The twelfth rider from the left, the Franklin is also the second figure from the left in a closely spaced group of four pilgrims. Though his horse is not visible, he rides immediately behind the Physician, causing only his head and left side torso to be seen. The Franklin’s hair is prominent—white and voluminous, it covers part of his forehead and extends outward in a sizeable, perhaps curly, beard. Barely visible, his eyebrows are thin, and his eyes, though open and looking upward, sag slightly at the outer edges. His nose is straight and relatively wide above thick, closed lips. He wears a cap with a dark, rounded top with a large jewel in the front topped by two white curved feathers. The hat’s elaborateness most likely attests to the Franklin’s wealth as a landowner. His left arm is bent at the elbow, and he holds the reins in a gloved hand in front of his chest. His garment appears to be decorated with an intricate pattern on the sleeves.
      </caption>

      <caption title="2 Citizens">
          The thirteenth and fourteenth riders from the left and the pair composing the rightmost figures in the small group of four pilgrims, the two citizens ride in the background of the composition, and only their heads and very upper torsos are visible. The citizen on the left looks in front of him to the right, with slightly parted lips and bushy facial hair that tapers into a single clump below his chin. His nose is arched and hooked, and the lapel of his shirt obscures his neck. Both citizens wear identical hats that have rounded tops and upturned brims with a large semi-circular opening in the front middle. The second citizen’s clothes are more visible; he wears a coat with a similarly high collar that has two buttons on the left side. Unlike his companion, this citizen turns to look to his right, staring past the other pilgrims directly out toward the viewer. His almond-shaped eyes are open and topped by heavy, dark brows. His nose is long and flares out at the base over tightly pursued lips. Like the other citizen, he wears a full mustache and beard, which touches the lapels of his coat.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Shipman">
          The fifteenth figure from the left, the Shipman is one of the only figures who twists his body nearly 180 degrees to look behind him, to the left. His gaze may meet with the direct forward stare of the Plowman, as the pair operates almost as a mirror image since both are shown in stark profile. The shipman’s complexion is dark, perhaps deeply tanned, and he scowls with heavy brows lowered over his eyes. His nose is straight and of average size; his mouth is closed though his somewhat fleshy lips protrude from his face. His chin juts forward sharply, and his long, dark beard continues this forward-slanting line. He wears a particularly designed hat that appears to have a thick layer of tufts of light fur around its circumference below a fitted, rounded cap that is netted or woven. His long-sleeved garment appears simple, made of thick woven threads with little adornment. He rests his left hand, which appears to be gloved, on the rump of his horse, and his right arm is extended, perhaps holding the reins, which are out of view. Three of four legs of his horse are visible below the belly of the Host’s horse, with one of the front hooves lifted in preparation for a step.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image5" id="1.6">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          The sixteenth pilgrim from the left occupying the processional space closest to the viewer, the Host commands attention for his central placement, hefty size, and grandiose gesture. He turns his entire torso to face forward and extends his arms perpendicular with slightly bent elbows in a cruciform posture. His oval-shaped face merges with a fat, sagging neck. He wears a hat similar to the Franklin’s that is round with a large central jewel with two tall feathers. His hair, visible beneath his hat, is white or light in color and curly; however, he has no facial hair. His eyes are average size and open, allowing him to gaze to his right and slightly behind him, and his gray brows are wavy, causing his expression to vacillate somewhere between pleasure and concern. His rosebud-shaped mouth is closed above a prominent small but cleft chin. His long-sleeved garment is incredibly tight, highlighting his portliness, especially in his midsection. He wears a wide ruffled collar that is deep, exposing some of the flesh of his chest. At least four clasps and a belt, from which a sword or dagger hangs, hold the garment together as he reclines against a rolled blanket or cylindrical pillow similar to the one used by Chaucer. Riding boots with prominent spurs rise up to his right knee. In his right hand, the Host brandishes a lengthy whip or riding crop that seems to blow up and to the right with the wind; in his left, he grasps his horse’s reins between his thumb and palm. It is unclear whether he wears gloves. He rides a dark horse, which his size makes appear to seem small though composed of beautiful serpentine curves in its neck and gently flowing mane. The equestrian equipment, including a saddle, blanket, stirrups, reins, and bridle is simple, and the horse lifts only its rear left foot slightly off the ground.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image6" id="1.7">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Summoner">
          The seventeenth pilgrim from the left, the Summoner turns his torso to face the viewer (and the Pardoner) in three-quarter view. His complexion is dark, in stark contrast to his light clothing, and his face is round. Heavy, dark brows lie over thin eyes that are set back into his head, and a wide nose dominates the space of his face above smiling thick lips. A bump or pimple is visible on his left cheek, and his facial hair is minimal—only a thin strip of dark hair winds around the bottom half of his face. He wears what appears to be a floral wreath or garland on his head, which obscures his hair. A similar garland-like accoutrement hangs low around his neck, although this may also be fur trim on his garment, which is long-sleeved with horizontal bands of woven material. His left hand is not visible, and his right arm, bent in a right angle at the elbow, reaches toward the body of the Pardoner, and his fingers, which may be gloved, disappear behind the Pardoner’s waist in a sexually suggestive position. In this hand, he may also hold some type of horn or musical instrument, the shaft of which extends back toward his right shoulder where the mouthpiece is visible. Only the rump of his horse immediately behind the Summoner’s hips is visible, but the animal appears to be light in color.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Manciple">
          Only visible above the shoulders, the Manciple is the eighteenth pilgrim from the left, and he rides in the background of the composition. He turns his neck sharply to look to the right and slightly behind him, and he tilts his chin and gaze up. His face is oval-shaped atop a columnar neck, and his hair is white, both on his head and in his bushy beard and mustache. He wears a small, circular cap with vertical stripes from which at least two feathers rise in the back. He has a low forehead and thin, downturned brows cover almond-shaped inquisitive eyes. His nose is incredibly long and thin, terminating above tightly set lips. His left ear, which should be visible, is not clearly delineated. He appears to wear a garment with a light colored collar and perhaps an undershirt with a smaller lace collar as well.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Pardoner">
          The nineteenth figure from the left, the highly feminized Pardoner rides to the right in the foreground but twists his torso to the left so that his face is rendered in a left profile. His long white hair falls in sections down his back, and he has a straight forehead over an open left eye, prominent triangular nose, closed mouth, and receding chin, which causes the skin to sag above his throat. He wears a hat with a dark band around the base and a long trailing hood that falls onto his right shoulder. His long-sleeved gown is relatively simple except for the large decorative cross that covers the entire backside of the garment. He also wears intricately patterned gloves, placing his left hand on his horse’s haunches for support and holding a large jeweled crucifix out with his right hand. A loose bag also decorated with a cross is worn over his left shoulder, and a belt circles his waist. His gown falls in folds above his right foot, which is covered in an intricately rendered shoe with an upward curving pointed toe, small heel, and prominent spur.
          <br />
          He rides a dark horse that is also adorned with a cross on its bridle. Twisting to the right in the opposite direction of its rider, the horse bends its head forward, perhaps trying to grasp the bit, which has become slack as the Pardoner does not hold the reins as the other pilgrims do. The horse’s mane is flame-like, and it is the only animal to be shown with all four hooves on the ground, completely stopped.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Monk">
          The eleventh pilgrim from the right side of the composition, the monk stares directly ahead, and the viewer observes him in right profile. The majority of his body is obscured by the Pardoner’s horse, but his head is large and round, set on a squat, thick neck. He is nearly completely bald, though his head is ringed by the last vestiges of white, curly hair. His dark brows cover open eyes that look forward and are slightly upward. His nose is triangular, and his chin recedes so that it merges with his sizeable jowls; he has no facial hair. Like the Friar beside him, the Monk wears a dark habit with a circular hood that stands stiff against his back. He positions his left arm to his chest, holding his horse’s reins in his hand. His horse is obscured all save for a small portion of its dark mane, which may have bells braided in it as adornments.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Friar">
          The tenth pilgrim from the right, the Friar turns to his right to face forward, looking slightly behind him in the direction of the Monk beside him. Only his shoulders and head are visible behind the neck of the Monk’s horse. Like the Monk, the crown of his head is bald, with only a garland-like ring of curly dark gray hair circling his head. His head is round with thin arching brows over almond-shaped eyes and a downward-hooked nose. His lips, though closed, are plump and deeply colored. His chin sags above a thick, tall neck. His attire echoes the Monk’s: a circular collar stands stiffly behind his head and neck. His left hand, which may be gloved, is visible directly above the mane of the Monk’s horse, and the Friar points to the left with his index finger in the direction of the Monk.
      </caption>

      <caption title="A Citizen">
          The ninth rider from the right, a male citizen rides behind the clerical pair and is shown in direct right profile. His appearance and attire is nearly indistinguishable from the two citizens riding behind him in the procession. Like the earlier pair, he wears a hat with upturned side brims, and light shaggy hair extends from beneath his hat; similarly colored hair composes his beard and perhaps also a mustache. His eyes are set deeply in his head, and his visible right brow is knitted over the bridge of his long, angular nose, perhaps in contemplation of the journey ahead. His fleshy lips are set firmly over a protruding chin and long neck. His garment, similar to the attire of the other two citizens, has tall lapels. His horse is not visible.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image7" id="1.8">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Lady Abbess">
          The eighth pilgrim from the right and rendered clearly in the foreground of the composition, the Lady Abbess rides sidesaddle with her legs on the left side of her horse, and her torso faces right in the direction of the procession while she turns her head slightly to the right. With smooth, pale skin and a serene expression, she is both beautiful and outwardly composed—a figure in stark contrast with the brazen dress and expression of the female rider behind her, the Wife of Bath.
          <br />
          Her heart-shaped face has delicate, slightly arched brows over almond eyes and a petite, linear nose. Her lips are small and closed tightly above a slightly receding chin and long neck. Her hair is light in color and long, falling loosely (or perhaps in braids) over both shoulders. She wears the sign of the cross on the crown of her head, which is covered by the black veil, which frames her face against the background foliage. The upper part of her garment is light and conceals her shoulders and bosom (though the thin material accentuates their shape), and below dark fabric of the habit covers her arms and other visible parts of her lower body. She wears minimally decorated gloves on her hands, and the left lightly holds her horse’s reins while the right grasps the shaft of a long, thin riding crop, which dangles down the right side of her horse. Rosary beads hang from her right wrist, and these contain a ribbon tied into two bows, a circular medallion with the words, “Amor Vincit Omnia,” and another cross. She rides in a dark saddle over at least two decorated pads or blankets, and her horse’s body is draped with a net or veil-like covering, and its reins are also draped with additional material. The top of the bridle forms a triangle or diamond shape around the animal’s two upright ears. Like the Pardonner’s horse behind it, the Lady Abbess’ horse has a vibrantly flowing, flame-like mane over a thick neck twisted slightly to the right in a serpentine curve. Echoing the femininity of its rider, the horse has wide, glistening eyes and noticeable thick eyelashes. It picks up its left front and back right hooves, and two greyhounds play in the space between its legs. The closer dog strides forward, and the second jumps upward, pawing at the belly of the horse. Present in Chaucer’s original texts, these dogs also link the Lady Abbess with the mythological Diana, a connection Warren Stevenson notes in his 1977 article.[1]
      </caption>

      <caption title="Nun">
          The seventh pilgrim from the right, the Nun rides to the left of the Lady Abbess and turns her head to the right to look directly out at the viewer. Appearing much older than her female companion, the Nun has a round face with thick curly hair, thin brows over eyes with heavy lids and slightly downturned outer corners. Her nose is crooked to the right, and her lips are set in a straight line. Her neck is completed covered by a white wimple that is also slightly visible near the crown of her head. Like the Lady Abbess, she wears the black veil, which also covers her shoulders and clasps in the middle of her chest. The portion of her torso that is visible is clothed in a light-colored garment, and a long, glove, decorated on the back of her hand, covers her right hand, with which she gestures in the direction of the three priests riding to her left. The head of her horse is visible immediately in front of the Lady Abbess’ horse. Like its rider, the horse turns its head to the right to look out with wide eyes at the viewer; its ears are pressed back against its head, and its nostrils are flared.
      </caption>

      <caption title="3 Priests">
          The group of three priests constitute the fourth, fifth, and sixth riders from the right side of the composition. The leftmost figure in the group of three, the priest closest to the viewer rides immediately to the left of the Nun, who gestures toward him with her right hand. He is shown in three-quarter view and looks up and slightly to the right with a contemplative gaze. His head is round with short, curly hair and a high forehead. His eyebrows are thin and straight over eyes with slightly descending lids, giving his gaze a somewhat entranced or dreamy appearance. His lips are thin and set in a straight line above a cleft chin and slightly sagging throat. The habit he wears is light in color and appears to be woven in vertical lines with at least four buttons in the middle of his chest. His hood is raised, and its circularity emphasizes the roundness of his head.
          <br />
          The middle priest has a much darker complexion than his companion to the left. His face is oval-shaped, and a tuft of dark hair appears from beneath his hood, which is dark in color with a white edge. He has a tall forehead with thin, severe brows over somewhat rectangular eyes and a prominent nose with a slightly hooked ridge. His lips are tightly set, and shadows on his right cheek emphasize his gauntness and stoic seriousness. He has a sizeable dark beard that tapers to two small points below his chin. Like his hood, his garment is dark with a lightly colored edge that may be braided. He may look in the direction of the Squire’s Yeoman riding in front of him.
          <br />
          The rightmost priest, set the furthest in the background, is shown in right profile with his head tilted slightly downward. His face is long, and no hair is visible beneath his dark hood, which like the priest to his left, is lined with white material. His eyes are heavily lidded, his nose is hooked, and the corners of his mouth are similarly downturned—all features underscore the downward sag of his overall appearance. His beard is white and bushy, further aging the figure. The majority of his body is obscured by the other pilgrims, but his garment is light in color and clasped with a button below his chin. His horse may be faintly visible in the space between the Squire’s Yeoman and the Knight riding in front of him. The animal appears to be light in color, and its ears are upright though turned to face the left.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image8" id="1.9">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          The third pilgrim from the right, the Squire’s Yeoman faces right but turns his head to look out at the viewer, tilting his head slightly back. His complexion is darker than the majority of the pilgrims. He stares out with large eyes, and his right lid droops slightly, giving him a somewhat tired appearance. His brows are thin, and his nose is of average size above a closed rosebud mouth, sagging chin, and noticeably thick, long neck. Thick, curly, dark hair is visible beneath his hood with white edging, and he also has a two-piece mustache and perhaps some stubble on his cheeks, though it may be a shadow. His hood appears to attach to his long-sleeved garment with a large brooch or gem in the front. He wears an elaborate glove, which may be made of chain mail, on his right hand with which he holds a large bow that extends upward in a serpentine curve far above his head.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image9" id="1.10">

      <title></title>

      <caption title="Knight">
          The second pilgrim from the right, the Knight rides in the foreground unobstructed by the bodies and horses of other pilgrims. He twists his torso to the right so that his chest faces the viewer, and he turns his head further to the right so that his face is shown in three-quarter view. His oval-shaped head is covered with chainmail, though his gray hair and bushy beard protrude from the armor. His brows are thin and slightly arched above large, dark eyes, and a straight, strong nose. His lips are pressed together, and the corners turn up in a slight smile, strengthening his appearance as a knowing, self-confident man.
          <br />
          With the exception of his face, the Knight’s entire body is covered in clothing. The chainmail encircling his head and neck connects to a breastplate that comes to a point below his sternum below which another layer of chainmail extends over his hips and down his arms. Both hands are gloved; with palm open and turned to face the viewer, the Knight gestures to the left with his right hand, and with his left, he grasps his horse’s reins. A scarf or fabric is draped around his shoulders, and the right end flutters actively in the unseen wind. He is also decorated with a sash that supports the emblem of the cross in the middle of his chest, and another sash crosses his torso diagonally down to his left hips. Beside his left hand and below the cross, a design of a horse and rider is visible, which may be another decoration or possibly the hilt of a sword that is tucked in his armor. His right leg is covered in plated armor with intricate designs on the knee and shin plates, and he wears a flat, pointed-toe shoe with a sizable spur. He rides a light-colored horse that, in contrast to his own stillness, is extremely active: its tail and mane billow wildly, its mouth is open, and it lefts its front right leg high, pushing to step forward. A large jewel accents the horse’s bridle below its right ear, which is raised and forward. The harness and saddle are minimally adorned (though there is some patterning on the blanket and billet or girth strap. Like the lady Abbess’ horse, the Knight’s horse also wears a netted or veil-like decoration over its rear haunches. Directly beneath and behind the front legs of the Knight’s horse treads a fierce looking black mastiff, with mangy hair, thick collar, and a perfectly spherical right eye, which stares directly at the path before the pilgrims.
      </caption>

      <caption title="Squire">
          The first pilgrim leading the party forward on the right side of the composition, the Squire (with the added height of his hat’s plumes) sits taller than his companions and turns his shoulders to the right to face the viewer nearly straight on. He gazes at a diagonal to the right and forward, perhaps surveying the path ahead. His oval-shaped head is covered with small gray curls and topped with an extravagant head from which two voluminous feathers extend and wave in the wind. His eyebrows are delicately thin over large eyes with slightly drooping lids and an average sized nose. He has no facial hair other than a thin mustache with a large gap in the middle. His lips are closed, and his overall appearance is youthful, even Apollonian in the phrasing of Stevenson.[1] A collar, perhaps made of lace, covers the base of his long neck, and a highly decorated overcoat comes together in a clasp in the middle of his chest. Neither of his hands or the majority of his body are visible, which limits his activity and increases his perceived stoicism. His horse, however, is the most active of the animals in the procession, raising both of its front legs off the ground in a dramatic gallop forward. The animal turns its head to the right to look directly at the viewer with wide, dark eyes and dramatically flared nostrils. The curve formed by the horse’s raised front legs (and echoed by the raised leg of the Knight’s horse immediately behind it) creates a kind of a parenthesis that demarcates the beginning of the procession behind it. Its flame-like mane blows backward, and it wears a scalloped bridle and chest ornamentation decorated with loops and tassels. The horse’s shoes are prominent on its front hooves, and its back hooves and flowing tail are visible beneath the belly of the Knight’s horse behind the mastiff.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image10" id="1.11">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image11" id="1.12">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image12" id="1.13">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image13" id="1.14">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image14" id="1.15">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image15" id="1.16">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image16" id="1.17">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image17" id="1.18">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image18" id="1.19">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image19" id="1.20">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image20" id="1.21">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Stothard.CP.Heath" id="2.1">

      <title>The Rivals</title>

      <caption>
          
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page0" id="2.2">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          In his Descriptive Catalogue, Blake lambasts Stothard’s portrayal of the Wife of Bath, a detail of which is seen here at right juxtaposed against Blake’s own version of the notorious female pilgrim at left. Blake discusses her character explicitly at two points in the text. In the first, he positions her in a binary relationship with the Lady Prioress as the representatives of the two classes of women. He asserts:
          <br />
          Are not these leaders of the ages of men? The lady prioress, in some ages, predominates; and in some the Wife of Bath, in whose character Chaucer has been equally minute and exact; because she is also a scourge and a blight. I shall say no more of her, nor expose what Chaucer has left hidden; let the young reader study what he has said of her: it is useful as a scare-crow. There are of such characters born too many for the peace of the world.[1]
          <br />
          Blake adorns his Wife of Bath with many signifiers to mark her loose sexuality, false piety, and preoccupation with worldly materials and power. Some of these signifying accoutrements include the cross necklace suspended between exposed breasts, the star-shaped spur visible above her right heel, the cock-headed riding crop clutched in her left hand, her sidesaddle riding position with legs at right and spread in the direction of the viewer, and her fickle beauty, revealed in a careful inspection of her buck teeth, sagging chin, and prominently hooked nose.
          <br />
          Stothard’s Wife of Bath stands in stark contrast to Blake’s. Although she also rides sidesaddle with legs toward the viewer, her clothing is more conservative and understated in its solid patterning and style. A long skirt and long sleeves hide her limbs, while a wimple and hat cover her head, hair, and chin—a notable instance in which Stothard remains faithful to Chaucer’s description of the wimpled Wife of Bath and Blake departs from the text. Stothard’s Wife of Bath appears both young and her face quite comely as she looks playfully over her left shoulder at the pilgrims riding behind her. Her shirt, though modest in its coverage, accentuates her thin waist. Her youthful appearance incenses Blake, who rages in the Descriptive Catalogue about Stothard and his reviewer John Hoppner’s foolishness in both scholarship and art:
          <br />
          In this manner he has jumbled his dumb dollies together, and is praised by his equals for it; for both himself and his friend are equally masters of Chaucer’s language. They both think that the Wife of Bath is a young beautiful blooming damsel; and H[oppner] says, that she is the Fair Wife of Bath, and that the Spring appears in her Cheeks. Now hear what Chaucer has made her say of herself, who is no modest one,
          <br />
          ‘But Lord when it rememberth me

          Upon my youth and on my jollity,

          It tickleth me about the heart root.

          Unto this day it doth my heart boot,

          That I have had my world as in my time;

          But age, alas, that all will envenime,

          Hath me bereft, my beauty and my pith

          Let go; farewell: the devel go therewith,

          The flower is gone, there is no more to tell.

          The bran, as best, I can, I now mote sell;

          And yet, to be right merry, will I fond,

          Now forth to tell of my fourth husband.’[2]
          <br />
          Instead of positioning her as a “scarecrow” for the edification of viewers as Blake does, Stothard portrays the Wife of Bath with no external markers of her flawed internal character, situating her instead in “a common scene” as described by Hoppner, which Blake hails as the most dangerous disguise possible for such a woman.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page1" id="2.3">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          In the Descriptive Catalogue accompanying the exhibition, Blake begins his detailed descriptions of the pilgrims with the Knight and the Squire, the two rightmost figures in his composition, a detail of which is visible here at left. His placement echoes Chaucer’s, he argues, who “has also placed them first in his prologue.”[1] Blake then launches into a laudatory account of the pair’s characters:
          <br />
          The Knight is a true Hero, a good, great, and wise man; his whole length portrait on horseback, as written by Chaucer, cannot be surpassed. He has spent his life in the field; has ever been a conqueror, and is that species of character which in every age stands as the guardian of man against the oppressor. His son [the Squire] is like him with the germ of perhaps greater perfection still, as he blends literature and the arts with his warlike studies. Their dress and their horses are of the first rate, without ostentation, and with all the true grandeur that unaffected simplicity when in high rank always displays.[2]
          <br />
          In accordance with Chaucer’s text, Blake depicts the mounted Knight in a full-length portrait in which the pilgrim wears the armor and accoutrements appropriate for a man who has spent his life conquering on the battlefield. In contrast, Stothard’s Knight (the second pilgrim visible from the left in the right detail) is crowded among other pilgrims and wears stylish civilian attire with a prominent large, black hat. Whereas Stothard’s Knight is shown in profile riding to the left, Blake’s Knight turns his torso back and to the left in the direction of the other pilgrims and extends his right hand toward them, perhaps in an instructive gesture to follow his lead. His posture is erect and stable, with only the slight fluttering of his scarf to suggest that he is moving forward. Behind him, the more youthful Squire gazes forward and slightly right, most likely in direct concentration on the path ahead.
          <br />
          Stothard positions his Knight and Squire as the seventh and ninth pilgrims, respectively, in his procession with the Reeve riding between them. Blake highlights what he believes to be Stothard’s erroneous departure from Chaucer’s text, asserting, “nothing need be done but to examine my rival’s prospectus. The two first characters in Chaucer, the Knight and the Squire, he has put among his rabble; and indeed his prospectus calls the Squire the fop of Chaucer’s age.”[3] Blake then quotes three sections of Chaucer’s introduction in which he lists various honorable qualities of the Squire and asks rhetorically after each: “Was this a fop?”[4]
          <br />
          Earlier in the Descriptive Catalogue, Blake observes that “Chaucer makes every one of his characters perfect in his kind, every one is an Antique Statue; the image of a class, and not of an imperfect individual.”[5] This particularity of Blake’s approach is evident in his treatment of the Squire whom he associates with Apollo. Unlike Stothard’s Squire who leans diagonally backward with torso turned to his right, hair blowing in the wind, as his horse lurches wildly beneath him, Blake’s Squire appears secure and even statuesque in his saddle as the horse below him charges forward with both front legs raised.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page2" id="2.4">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          In both compositions, Stothard and Blake position the Plowman on the more distant side of the procession from the viewer, obscuring all but the figure’s head and shoulders. Both Plowmen are shown in profile (though from opposite sides) with focused gazes directed at the path before them. Both are similarly attired: Blake’s Plowman on the left wears a wide-brimmed hat and a simple woven shirt while Stothard’s pilgrim sports an almost identical hat but also wears a protective neck covering that extends over his unadorned shirt. Although both Plowmen ride in the background, Blake delineates his figure with intricate linear detail, exemplified in the visible veins running up the Plowman’s neck in the engraving seen here, whereas Stothard’s Plowman is much less defined in his original painting and also faint in the later engraved reproduction.
          <br />
          In the Descriptive Catalogue, Blake chastises Stothard’s Plowman for two primary reasons: Stothard’s characterization of him as an old man and his reliance on color over line in the construction of his figure’s form. Blake first lays out the text informing his own depiction of the Plowman from Chaucer, stating:
          <br />
          The Plowman is simplicity itself, with wisdom and strength for its stamina. Chaucer has divided the ancient character of Hercules between his Miller and his Plowman. Benevolence is the plowman’s great characteristic, he is thin with excessive labour, and not with old age, as some have supposed.
          <br />
          ‘He would thresh and thereto dike and delve

          For Christe’s sake, for every poore wight,

          Withouten hire, if it lay in his might.’[1]
          <br />
          True to his description, Blake emphasizes the gauntness of the Plowman’s cheeks as well as the leathery texture of his skin from excessive hours toiling under the sun. He critiques Stothard’s equation of hard work with old age as another departure from Chaucer’s intent in the original text. He writes that Chaucer,
          <br />
          has respected his True Pilgrims, who are a majority of his company, and are not thrown together in the random manner that Mr. S[tothard] has done. Chaucer has no where called the Plowman old, worn out with age and labour, as the prospectus has represented him, and says, that the picture has done so too. He is worn down with labour, not with age.[2]
          <br />
          Blake’s peculiar insistence on this point that the Plowman is worn out with labour and not old age is related to his equally particular emphasis on the relationship he describes earlier in the Descriptive Catalogue between Chaucer’s Plowman and Hercules. Blake elaborates:
          <br />
          The Plowman of Chaucer is Hercules in his supreme eternal state, divested of his spectrous shadow; which is the Miller, a terrible fellow, such as exists in all times and places, for the trial of men, to astonish every neighborhood, with brutal strength and courage, to get rich and powerful to curb the pride of Man.[3]
          <br />
          Several scholars have argued that Blake’s prolonged defense of the Plowman suggests not only elevated respect for this particular pilgrim but also a personal identification with the Plowman. Karl Kiralis first highlighted a physical likeness between the Plowman and Blake’s own portrait (though he does not cite a specific work).[4] Similarly, Warren Stevenson points out that the Plowman’s wide-brimmed hat is somewhat similar to the hat Blake wears in John Linnel’s drawing of him for the frontispiece to Mona Wilson’s Life of William Blake.[5] Lastly, Alexander Gourlay highlights the similar physiognomy between Blake’s Plowman and James Deville’s life mask of Blake from 1823.[6] Gourlay argues that “by portraying himself in this role Blake becomes the genuine hero ignored in these and Chaucer’s times: the starved and neglected Plowman, the man who does the difficult and productive work in the society, contrasts dramatically with the sleek, honored, parasitic drones who dominate the procession and the culture as a whole.” Thus, Blake’s self-association with the Plowman emphasizes their shared marginalization from societies, both past and present, who do not recognize their efforts or genius.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page3" id="2.5">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          Although Blake takes issue with Stothard’s loose interpretation of Chaucer’s text throughout his Descriptive Catalogue, he addresses this problem specifically in relation the Monk. In Stothard’s version at right, the Monk rides in front of the Friar, who sits slightly back and to the right. In Blake’s engraving at left, the Monk, whose face is shown in profile, rides behind the Friar, who turns his head back toward his companion. Blake emphasizes Stothard’s literary incompetence when depicting these two pilgrims:
          <br />
          He [Stothard] has done all by chance, or perhaps his fortune, money, money. According to his prospectus he has Three Monks; these he cannot find in Chaucer, who has only One Monk, and that no vulgar character, as he has endeavoured to make him. When men cannot read they should not pretend to paint. To be sure Chaucer is a little difficult to him who has only blundered over novels and catchpenny trifles of booksellers. Yet a little pains ought to be taken even by the ignorant and weak.[1]  
          <br />
          Although Stothard only includes a single Monk in his final composition, Blake still critiques this Monk’s “vulgar” character, a judgment likely resulting from Stothard’s decision to place the Monk and Friar behind the Wife of Bath in the procession. The round-faced, chubby religious figures gaze in her direction and sport somewhat ridiculous smiles that compromise the assumed seriousness of their positions.
          <br />
          In contrast to this perceived baseness of character, Blake outlines his alternative interpretation of the Monk:
          <br />
          For the Monk is described by Chaucer, as a man of the first rank in society, noble, rich, and expensively attended: he is a leader of the age, with certain humourous accompaniments in his character, that do not degrade but render him an object of dignified mirth, but also with other accompaniments not so respectable.[2]
          <br />
          Alexander S. Gourlay highlights the Monk’s resemblance to the standard position of profile heads minted on coins, underscoring the traditional dignity with which the Monk is portrayed. However, to explain in part Blake’s characterization of the Monk as an “object of dignified mirth,” Gourlay also suggests the pilgrim’s specific resemblance to King George III and points to coins of the period and to a particularly striking caricature of George as a tonsured priest as evidence.[3] He points to Blake’s further characterization of the Monk to support his point, in which the artist details the complexities of the pilgrim, stating: “Though a man of luxury, pride and pleasure, he is a master of art and learning, though affecting to despise it. Those who can think that the proud Huntsman, and noble Housekeeper, Chaucer’s Monk, is intended for a buffoon or burlesque character, know little of Chaucer.”[4] Whether Blake intended the Monk to represent the English king, the very possibility of it, coupled with his extended textual description of the pilgrim, emphasizes the extent to which Blake, too, altered or at least added to the original characterization of the pilgrims outlined by Chaucer in The Canterbury Tales.
          <br />
          Blake continues with a lengthy description of the Friar and, quoting Chaucer’s text often, explains the Friar was:
          <br />
          a character also of a mixed kind. ‘A friar there was, a wanton and a merry.’ [B]ut in his office he is said to be a ‘full solemn man:’ eloquent, amorous, witty, and satyrical; young, handsome, and rich; he is a complete rogue; with constitutional gaiety enough to make him a master of all the pleasures of the word. ‘His neck was white as the flour de lis, Thereto strong he was as a champioun.’[5]
          <br />
          And Blake does portray his Friar as handsome, with a thick, columnar neck and fleshy, rosy lips—a stark contrast to the multitude of chins that Stothard includes on his buffoon-like Friar. However, Blake also may gesture toward the Friar’s unstable solemnity through his positioning. Unlike the Monk, who stares intensely forward toward, one would imagine, the religious object of their travel, the Friar turns away from the pilgrims in front of him and shifts his eyes slightly back. He also points to the left with his left hand, visible above the mane of the Monk’s horse. He may gesture toward the Pardonner riding immediately behind the Monk, who also turns to the left, or perhaps to the Host in the center, who may be in the throws of launching his call for the story-telling competition. With any of these situations, the Friar certainly attempts to redirect the Monk’s stoic, fixed gaze back to the realm of baser human activity.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page4" id="2.6">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          Arguably the most prominent figure in Blake’s engraving, the Host, Henry Baillie (seen here at left), rides in the middle of the procession at the center of the compositional space. Turning his torso to his right, he extends both arms so that his overall body position assumes a cruciform posture. Although he faces the viewer, his gaze is somewhat vacant and directed slightly left of center. Tight clothing emphasizes his corpulent body, and the objects in his hand—the horse’s reins in his left and a riding crop in his right—draw attention to his long fingers topped with pointed nails. His horse appears diminutive in relation to his heaviness and certainly does not exert the wild energy characteristic of many other animals along the procession.
          <br />
          Despite the Host’s rather uncomely outward appearance, Blake extols the pilgrim’s internal character:
          <br />
          For the Host who follows this group, and holds the center of the cavalcade, is a first rate character, and his jokes are no trifles; they are always, though uttered with audacity, and equally free with the Lord and the Peasant, they are always substantially and weightily expressive of knowledge and experience; Henry Baillie, the keeper of the greatest Inn, of the greatest City; for such was the Tabarde Inn in Southwark, near London: our Host was also a leader of the age.[1]
          <br />
          He compares the Host to Silenus, the satyr in Greek mythology who was a companion of Dionysus and, though wise, was often drunk. The unfocused stare of Blake’s Host may suggest that he, too, like the Cook and the Wife of Bath who hold visible drinking glasses, has indulged in a “morning’s draught of comfort” before beginning the pilgrimage.[2] Nevertheless, the Host in Blake’s composition fulfills his entertaining duties as he unites both halves of the pilgrims through his outspread arms and his likely forthcoming proposition to begin the storytelling game.
          <br />
          Although riding near the front rather than the middle of the procession, Stothard’s Host (seen at right) is also depicted in an attention-drawing gesture, presumably to call for the start of the competition. Whereas Blake’s Host wears an vaguely Elizabethan style ruffed collar and tights, the Host in Stothard’s version wears clothing made of a heavier material that covers nearly his entire body. He rides left but has turned sharply to his left and faces the pilgrims behind him so that his head is visible only in profile. His mouth is clearly open, and he raises his left arm and holds an indistinguishable object in his hand that his displays to those following him. Like the Host in Blake’s composition, his body appears quite heavy and the skin below his chin sags. The Host’s turn rightward constitutes a bracket of sorts to contain the pilgrims behind him and thus excluding the Miller (who appears quite uninterested in the Host’s call for a game anyway) in front of him at left.
      </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page5" id="2.7">

      <title></title>

      <caption>
          Embodying what Blake calls the “spectrous shadow” of the Plowman, the Miller forms the other baser half of the ideal Herculean state that Blake discusses in his Descriptive Catalogue. Blake characterizes the Miller as an omnipresent, irredeemable figure:
          <br />
          The Plowman of Chaucer is Hercules in his supreme eternal state, divested of his spectrous shadow; which is the Miller, a terrible fellow, such as exists in all times and places, for the trial of men, to astonish every neighborhood, with brutal strength and courage, to get rich and powerful to curb the pride of Man.[1]
          <br />
          In Blake’s composition, the Miller (seen here at left) rides near the rear of the procession between the Wife of Bath and the Cook. He is shown with short, curly hair and a full beard that extends out from his face in flame-like tufts in all directions. He stares in the direction of the Wife of Bath with large, widely open eyes set above a broad, flat nose. He holds a musical instrument to his lips with his right hand, and the attached horn or pipe extends over his left shoulder and behind his head. His complexion is darker than most of the other pilgrims’ skin, perhaps to accentuate Blake’s characterization of him as a “shadow.”
          <br />
          Stothard’s Miller (seen at right) also prominently plays an instrument—here more clearly a bagpipe. In Stothard’s composition, the Miller leads the procession as the leftmost rider. His posture and appearance, however, contrast with his ostensible place of prominence. Slumped forward with heavily lidded eyes, the Miller plods forward, making no motion to turn in the direction of the Host who appears to speak behind him. Whereas most of the other pilgrims in Stothard’s composition animatedly interact with one another, the Miller stares ahead in profile, and the parenthesis-like curvature of the Host’s body behind him further emphasizes his separation from the rest of the pilgrims.
      </caption>

    </image>

</exhibit>