<exhibit id="canterburypilgrims" title="William Blake's Canterbury Pilgrims"
    article="canterburypilgrims.exhibit.html" composition_date_string="January 2019">


    <image dbi="but653" id="1">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Painting of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption> Blake, <i>Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the nine and twenty Pilgrims on their journey to
                Canterbury</i>, 1808(?), Butlin 653</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="bb36a" id="2">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Advertisement to the Exhibition</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Exhibition of Paintings in Fresco, Poetical and Historical Inventions</i>,
            1809, Bentley 36A</caption>

    </image>


    <image dbi="but654" id="3">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Pencil Drawing of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>The Canterbury Pilgrims: Sketch for the Engraving</i>, 1809, Butlin
            654</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="bb12a" id="4">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Advertisement for the Engraving</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Prospectus for the engraving of 'Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims'</i>, 15 May 1809, Bentley 12A</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="esxvi.1.3i.sp" id="5">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Engraving of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</i>, 1810, third state, impression 3I,
            Essick XVI.3I</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Stothard_painting" id="6">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Thomas Stothard's Painting of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption>Thomas Stothard, <i>The Pilgrimage to Cantebury</i>, 1807</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Stothard_engraving" id="7">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Engraving of Stothard's Painting</p></title>
        <caption>Stothard, <i>The Pilgrimage to Canterbury</i>, engraved by Luis Schiavonetti,
            Robert Cromek, Francis Engleheart, Niccolo Schiavonetti, James Heath, W. H. Worthington,
            1817</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="esxvi.1.3i.sp" id="8">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Engraving of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</i>, 1810, third state, impression 3I,
            Essick XVI.3I</caption>

    </image>


    <image dbi="Reeve Chaucer Clerk of Oxenford Cook 1-4" id="9">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="Reeve"> The Reeve appears at the far left of procession. His appearance
            makes him the most devious-looking in the group: his short hair is matted atop his
            prominent brow, he has a large hooked nose, his cheek is gaunt, and his lips are turned
            slightly upward in an ambiguous smile. His garment is vertically striped with a
            prominent collar or hood. He is framed by a Gothic-styled portal. The Reeve is smaller
            than the other pilgrims, thus furthest removed from the viewer. This also exaggerates
            the heft of Chaucer, riding in front of and to the right of the Reeve. </caption>

        <caption title="Chaucer"> Chaucer is second from the left. Although shown in full profile,
            his head is turned slightly right, toward the viewer. His head covering identifies him
            as Chaucer: it is worn in nearly all portraits of him. However, this covering is white
            instead of the usual black. He appears to be engrossed in something other than the scene
            in front of him: his large eyes are open although his gaze is vacant and unfixed, and
            his lips are closed and slightly downturned. Details suggest his prominence: the collar,
            bottom hem, and sleeve cuffs of his gown are elaborately decorated and his physical heft
            denotes strength. He also carries religious ornaments, such as the string of ten prayer
            beads in his bare right hand, and travel necessities, such as the mat or blanket rolled
            up behind his back. The hem of the gown is wrinkled or swishing, suggesting movement
            forward. Chaucer sits on a dark horse that holds its downturned face and front left leg
            at a right angle and directs its gaze toward the Clerk’s horse. </caption>

        <caption title="Clerk of Oxenford"> The Clerk of Oxenford appears third from the left. His
            long hair flows from beneath a dark, square cap. Like Chaucer, his wide, open eyes gaze
            forward, although his attention appears more fixed. His thin, straight eyebrows and
            tightly closed lips additionally suggest concentration. His gown mirrors the texture and
            color of Chaucer’s, although its decoration is more geometrical. He sits very erect on a
            light-colored horse. The horse appears haggard but its legs mirror those of Chaucer’s
            horse. </caption>

        <caption title="Cook"> The cook appears fourth from the left, although only his upper torso,
            head, and raised hands are visible. His face is in profile and tilted back to drink what
            is presumably beer; he raises the tankard with his left hand and supports its weight
            with his right. His white cap, tied with a dark ribbon, covers any possible hair. A tall
            collar and ruffled sleeves decorate his garment. The cook’s appearance is more
            caricature than portraiture: his protruding brow, heavy-lidded eyes, snub nose, flaring
            nostril, and thick, pouting lips emphasize inebriation. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Miller Wife of Bath Merchant 5-7" id="10">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="Miller"> The miller is fifth from the left and one of the few African
            pilgrims. He turns slightly right but faces the viewer with large, open eyes. He has
            dark skin; dark, thick, tightly coiled hair; and a thick beard and mustache that flare
            outward. His thick, arched eyebrows and wide nose are prominent facial features. He
            holds the mouthpiece of a bagpipe with his large right hand; the bass drone extends over
            his left shoulder. He wears a simple long-sleeved tunic with a tall collar or hood
            clasped at the neck with a single button. </caption>

        <caption title="Wife of Bath"> Sixth from the left, the Wife of Bath rides sidesaddle and
            her whole body faces the viewer. Her sexuality is emphasized through slightly spread
            knees and breasts, with visible nipples, that swell out of her dress. Her posture and
            expression suggest relaxed ease: she looks upward and to the right with an open-mouthed
            smile and leans back in the saddle. She holds her horse’s reins and riding crop (with a
            decorative top shaped like a cock’s head) in one hand and a glass presumably filled with
            wine in the other. Her dress showcases her wealth: several adornments cover her head
            including a knitted bonnet and three elaborate collars that create a halo effect. The
            cone-shaped hat atop the second collar mimics the flourishes of the large, spiky collar
            extending outward from her shoulders. She wears long earrings and three strands of
            pearls around her neck and bare chest; the middle strand holds a cross and the bottom
            strand holds a large heart. Her white dress clings to her torso and waist and her lap is
            covered by a patterned blanket. She wears stockings and white elbow-length gloves. Her
            horse’s reins and mane are decorated with small bows and bells. Blake's presentation of
            the Wife of Bath resembles his later depiction of the Whore of Babylon, a water color
            version of which is dated c. 1809 (Butlin 523). Similarities can be seen in the
            position, necklace with the heart, and chalice in the right hand of both figures. </caption>

        <caption title="Merchant"> Seventh from the left, the merchant observes the Wife of Bath. He
            appears exhausted: his long, gaunt face mirrors the taper of his thin, hooked nose and
            his eyes are nearly half closed. However, his raised eyebrows suggest surprise or alarm.
            His dark beard extends into two pointed tufts. He wears a wide-brimmed hat, an overcoat
            with a stiff, possibly braided collar, and a minimally embellished undershirt. Part of
            his horse’s face appears to the right of the parson. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Parson Man of Law and Plowman 8-10" id="11">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="Parson"> Eighth from the left, the Parson concentrates on the progress of
            the pilgrimage. He is in full profile facing right and stares directly ahead with open
            eyes and closed lips as he rides forward. His long, white hair and beard and his lined
            brow suggest age. He wears dark clothing including a circular hat with a small brim; a
            long, unadorned gown with upturned hems; and shoes with white laces. Simple bridling
            adorns his fairly shaggy, short-tailed horse, which slightly raises its back left and
            front right hoof, showing metal shoes. Its eyes are heavily lidded. </caption>

        <caption title="Man of Law"> Ninth from the left, the Man of Law partially faces the viewer.
            His large, open eyes stare forward toward a distant scene. He has a shaggy, coarse
            white-gray beard and mustache and his hair peaks beneath a triangular, narrow-brimmed,
            tasseled hat. He wears possibly three layers of clothes, including an overcoat with
            split sleeves, a woven shirt, and a short lace collar. Aside from a bit of his right
            knee and leg, his lower body is mostly obscured by the Parson’s horse. His dark horse’s
            eyes are large, bright, and open and its ears are perked; its bit and reins are simple. </caption>

        <caption title="Plowman"> The Plowman rides tenth from the left. Like the Parson, he stares
            ahead in full profile facing right. The Plowman has been compared by critics to Blake
            himself, a plowman in copper. The Plowman’s light-colored, woven hat has a wide, loose
            brim similar in style to the one worn by the traveler in plate 16 of For Children: the
            Gates of Paradise (1793). The Plowman’s shoulder-length hair falls out of his hat, his
            tan skin, angular face, and vein protruding on his neck all indicate outdoor labor. His
            haggard horse contrasts with the attentiveness of the Plowman and adjacent horses. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image4" id="12">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="Physician"> The Physician rides eleventh from the left, leftmost among four
            closely grouped pilgrims. His wide-open eyes and raised eyebrows express surprise as he
            faces forward in a three-quarter view. His elaborate hat is composed of a dark circular
            upper portion; a white fur brim; and two long ear flaps that mirror the long, columnar
            structure of his face and nose. His overcoat has a white fur trim and his undershirt has
            a geometric pattern. Although shaggy, his horse’s decorated rein matches the opulence of
            the Physician’s attire. It looks toward the Plowman’s horse. </caption>

        <caption title="Franklin"> The Franklin rides twelfth from the left, second among the four
            closely grouped pilgrims. Unlike most of the other pilgrims, he gazes up. His horse and
            much of his body are obscured by the Physician but his wealth as a landowner is
            apparent: his voluminous white hair extends into an ample, well-trimmed beard; he wears
            a cap decorated with a large jewel and two white feathers; and his garment is decorated
            with an intricate pattern. His gloved hand holds the reins closely to his chest. </caption>

        <caption title="Two Citizens"> Riding in the background, the thirteenth and fourteenth
            riders form a pair among the group of four pilgrims. Only their heads and upper torsos
            are visible. Both wear identical hats with rounded tops and upturned brims and, although
            more of the right citizen’s clothes are visible, both appear to wear a similar
            high-collared coat. However, their expressions differ: the leftmost citizen looks
            forward with raised brows and slightly parted lips while the rightmost citizen stares
            toward the viewer with slightly furrowed brows and pursed lips. </caption>

        <caption title="Shipman"> Fifteenth from the left, the Shipman is the only figure to twist
            his body to look behind him. His gaze appears to meet that of the Plowman; together,
            they frame the group of four pilgrims. His left hand rests on his horse’s rump to
            support his body while the other extends, perhaps to hold reins. He has a dark, deeply
            tanned complexion; a long, dark beard; and dark, heavy brows that accentuate his scowl.
            He wears a round, fur-trimmed cap and a simple, woven garment. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image5" id="13">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Host</p></title>

        <caption> Sixteenth from the left, the Host commands attention for his central placement,
            hefty size, and grandiose gesture. He leans back against a rolled blanket (similar to
            Chaucer’s), turns his torso to face the viewer, and extends his arms perpendicularly in
            a cruciform posture. His oval-shaped face, double-chin, and form-fitting garment
            accentuate his portly physique. Like the Franklin, he wears a round hat with a central
            jewel and two feathers. Curly, light-colored hair is visible beneath. His raised brows
            and pursed lips ambiguously express either pleasure or concern as he gazes over his
            right shoulder. A wide ruffled collar, four clasps, and a belt holding a sword or dagger
            adorn his garment. He wears riding boots and holds a riding crop in his right hand and
            reins in the left. His dark, graceful horse lifts only its rear left hoof off the
            ground. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image6" id="14">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="Summoner"> Seventeenth from the left, the Summoner turns in a three-quarter
            view to face the Pardoner. He has a dark complexion; heavy, dark brows turned upward;
            and a smile that accentuates his rounded face. A floral wreath or garland covers his
            head and a similar garland (or fur trim) is draped over his garment. His right arm bends
            at the elbow to reach toward the Pardoner; the fingers disappear behind the Pardoner’s
            waist in a sexually suggestive position. The shaft of a musical instrument extends from
            his right hand towards his right shoulder, where a mouthpiece is visible. Only the rump
            of his horse is visible. The Summoner may be a caricature of the Whig politician Charles
            James Fox (1749-1806). </caption>

        <caption title="Manciple"> Riding in the background and only visible above the shoulders,
            the Manciple appears eighteenth from the left. His neck is turned sharply to look over
            his right shoulder and his gaze turns slightly upward. Downturned brows and tightly set
            lips suggest inquisitiveness. A circular feathered cap covers white hair that extends
            into a beard and mustache; the hair obscures his left ear. A lace collar shows beneath
            his garment. </caption>

        <caption title="Pardoner"> Nineteenth from the left, the Pardoner twists his torso to the
            left to look behind him. Highly feminized details characterize his face, rendered in
            profile. He has long, light-colored hair that falls down his back; no facial hair; a
            small, triangular nose; a high forehead; and a receding chin. A long hood trails from
            his cap. His gown fits loosely, except for the sleeves. In addition to the cross on the
            back of his gown, on his bag, and on his horse’s bridle, he holds a large jeweled cross
            in his right hand. He places his left hand on his horse’s rump for support. The horse
            twists its head to the right, an opposite movement from that of its rider. The
            Pardoner’s horse is the only one to be shown with all four hooves on the ground,
            completely stopped. The Pardoner may be a caricature of William Pit the Younger
            (1759-1806), Tory politician and Prime Minister. </caption>

        <caption title="Monk"> Twentieth from the right, the monk is seen in profile as he stares
            directly ahead and slightly upward. His head is large and round and his chin recedes
            into prominent jowls. White, curly hair circles his head, which is either nearly bald or
            tonsured. Like the Friar he wears a dark habit with a stiff circular hood; the rest of
            his body is obscured by the Pardoner’s horse. His left hand holds his horse’s reins
            tightly to his chest. Only his horse’s mane, decorated with bells, is visible. </caption>

        <caption title="Friar"> The Friar, tenth from the right, turns toward the Monk on his right.
            Only his shoulders and head are visible. Like the Monk, he is bald or tonsured; his face
            is round and his chin recedes into his neck; and he wears a dark habit with a stiff
            circular hood. Unlike the Monk, he has a slight smile. He points with his left index
            finger toward the Monk or Pardoner. </caption>

        <caption title="A Citizen"> Ninth from the right, a male citizen is shown in direct right
            profile. He resembles the two citizens riding behind him: he wears a hat with an
            upturned brim and a garment with tall lapels, and his shaggy hair extends into a beard
            and mustache. His brow is knitted, perhaps in contemplation of the journey ahead. His
            horse is not visible. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image7" id="15">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="Lady Abbess"> The Lady Abbess is prominently featured in the foreground
            eighth from the right. She gazes slightly to the right with tightly closed lips. Her
            serene expression, delicate features, and elegant posture contrast with the female rider
            behind her, the Wife of Bath. Her light, long hair falls loosely down her back and she
            wears a crown with the sign of the cross that supports a long black veil. The white
            upper portion of her garment cinches at her upper arms and below her bosom, and a dark
            habit covers the rest of her body. Rosary beads decorated with ribbon and a medallion
            with the words “Amor Vincit Omnia” hang from her right wrist. She holds a riding crop in
            her right hand. Her horse is elaborately decorated: aside from the net covering draped
            over its body, the reins and bridle top are attractively detailed. Her horse’s elegant
            stride and gaze echo the composure of its rider. Two greyhounds play underneath: one
            strides forward in a gait that mirrors the horse’s while the other jumps up to paw at
            the horse. Present in Chaucer’s original texts, these dogs also link the Lady Abbess
            with the mythological Diana, as noted by Warren Stevenson.<sup><a class="footnote"
                            >1<span>Warren Stevenson. “Interpreting Blake’s Canterbury Pilgrims.” Colby Library Quarterly, Volume 13, no. 2, June 1977, p. 115-126, 121.</span></a></sup></caption>

        <caption title="Nun"> The nun rides seventh from the right and turns her head directly
            toward the viewer. Older than her female companion, she has a round face, thick curly
            hair, and downturned eyes with heavy lids. A white wimple completely covers her neck and
            is also visible near the crown of her head. She wears a light-colored garment and, like
            the Lady Abbess, a black veil; it covers her shoulders and clasps over her chest. Her
            gloved right hand gestures toward the three priests to her left. Her horse’s head
            appears directly to the right of the Lady Abbess’ horse. Like its rider, it turns its
            head to look toward the viewer. </caption>

        <caption title="Three Priests"> The group of three priests ride fourth, fifth, and sixth
            from the right. The leftmost of the group is shown in a three-quarter view and gazes
            upward with an entranced or contemplative expression. The raised circular hood of his
            habit emphasizes his round head. He has short, curly hair and a youthful appearance. The
            middle priest appears sterner: his face is gaunt and his dark hair, sizable beard,
            severe brows and tightly set lips create a stoic expression. He may be looking toward
            the Squire’s Yeoman. The rightmost in the group appears oldest and most dejected. Shown
            in right profile, his heavily lidded eyes, hooked nose, and downturned mouth emphasize
            the downward sag of his appearance. He has a white, bushy beard. The leftmost and
            rightmost priests have lightly colored, woven habits while the center priest has a dark
            habit with a light, braided edge. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image8" id="16">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Squire's Yeoman</p></title>

        <caption> The Squire’s Yeoman rides third from the right. His head is tilted back and turned
            sharply to the right to look at the viewer. He has a tan complexion and thick, curly
            hair. His large eyes, drooping lids, beard stubble, and sagging chin give him a tired
            appearance. His raised hood is attached to a garment that has a large brooch or gem in
            the front. His right hand, elaborately gloved with, perhaps, chainmail, holds a long,
            curved bow. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image9" id="17">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p></title>

        <caption title="The Knight"> The Knight rides in the foreground second from the right. He
            twists his torso so his chest faces the viewer; his head is turned further to the right
            and shown in a three-quarter view. Although his face is covered with chainmail, his gray
            hair and beard are visible. He appears knowing and self-confident: he sits straight, his
            brows are slightly arched, and his lips are pressed together in a slight smile. The
            chainmail encircling his head and neck connects to a breastplate; below the breastplate,
            more chainmail extends over his hips and down his arms, and plated armor covers his
            right leg. Fabric is draped around his shoulders. Two more sashes cross his body: one
            across his chest supports a cross and another extends diagonally across his torso. The
            image of a horse and rider below the cross may be an additional emblem or it may be the
            hilt of his sword. His left hand holds his horse’s reins and his right hand gestures to
            the left with an open palm. His horse is minimally adorned except for the large jewel on
            its bridle and the netted covering over its haunches. Left of the horse a fierce, mangy
            black dog treads forward and stares directly ahead. </caption>

        <caption title="Squire"> The Squire, first on the right side of the composition, leads the
            party. He sits taller than his companions and gazes slightly right of the viewer,
            perhaps surveying the path ahead. He wears a hat with two voluminous feathers over his
            tightly curled hair. He has a slight smile and a thin mustache above his lips. Stevenson
            describes his youthful appearance as “Apollonian”(Stevenson, 119). A decorated overcoat clasps at his
            neck and a lace collar shows underneath. Although the rider appears stoic, his horse is
            the most active of the procession: both of its front legs are raised off the ground in a
            forward gallop and its head is turned to face the viewer directly. Its front legs appear
            furthest to the right of the composition and demarcate the beginning of the procession.
            </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image10" id="18">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Family Group</p></title>

        <caption> In the lower left corner of the engraving, six unnamed figures – one adult male,
            one adult female, a presumably male infant, and three children – are probably a family
            group. They are not present in Chaucer’s original <i>Canterbury Tales</i>. Their
            rightward gazes and gestures direct the viewer toward the pilgrims, while their
            stability contrasts with the motion of the procession. In the back of the group, the
            adult man looks down at the infant. Just above the infant’s head, his right index finger
            points toward the pilgrims, as if directing the infant’s attention. The infant’s right
            hand echoes this gesture, while his left hand extends toward the man and holds what may
            be a toy. The man’s long, white hair and beard and wrinkled forehead show his age. He
            strongly resembles portrayals of Urizen in Blake’s illuminated books. To his right, the
            adult woman holds the infant. Shown in profile, she concentrates on the pilgrims. Her
            nose is straight, reminiscent of the idealized form in ancient Greek sculpture. The
            closeness of the children around her contrasts her with the women in the pilgrimage, who
            are not depicted as maternal figures. The tallest of the three standing children is a
            male with short curly hair and a round chin. Although all other family members wear long
            flowing gowns, he wears a buttoned shirt with pants. He looks forward and slightly left
            of the other two children and gestures toward the pilgrims. To his left a child of
            indeterminate gender looks toward the pilgrims, shown in profile like the adult woman.
            The child has long wavy hair and holds a stick possibly used for the game of hoop
            rolling. The shortest standing child, presumably female, has her back to the viewer and
            looks up with fascination toward the nearest pilgrims. She clutches a doll that appears
            to wear a gown </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image11" id="19">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Female Child Walking</p></title>

        <caption> In the foreground of the design’s left half, between Chaucer and the Wife of Bath,
            a young figure walks forward with bare feet. The figure has his or her back to the
            viewer to look at the pilgrims and is perhaps the object of Chaucer’s gaze. The figure’s
            gender is indeterminate: a comb pulls back the figure’s hair and he or she wears a long,
            simple sleeveless gown that reveals a muscular right arm. A pouch – either a water
            bladder or a shepherd’s purse – is held in the right hand. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image12" id="20">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Boy with keg</p></title>

        <caption> Below the horses of the Parson, the Man of Law, and the Plowman a second unmounted
            youth stands in contrapposto facing left. His left profile contrasts with the rightward
            procession of the pilgrims and suggests that he is not part of the pilgrimage. He has
            very curly hair and an intricate outfit. The shirt has a plunging neckline with a
            prominent, stiff collar that exposes his pectoral muscles; long sleeves ruffed at the
            shoulders; and a ruffled hem. His breeches are cinched just above the knee. His right
            hand holds a pitcher by the handle and his left hand holds the strap of a wooden cask or
            keg. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image13" id="21">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Five figures behind the Squire</p></title>

        <caption> Groups of tiny, sparsely detailed figures populate the landscape behind the main
            riders. Behind the Squire at the far right, five figures – four adults and one child –
            stand on the crest of a hill between two clumps of vegetation. They all appear to wear
            gowns except for the middle figure, who possibly wears pants and a broad-brimmed hat.
            The child possibly extends a hand toward the adjacent adult and they all look away from
            the procession and over the vast landscape. Like the group of six figures in the lower
            left of the engraving, they may represent a family or community. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image14" id="22">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Figures behind the Host</p></title>

        <caption> Groups of tiny, sparsely detailed figures populate the landscape behind the main
            riders. Behind the Host’s raised left arm, an adult and child stand to the left of a
            small cottage. Above and to the left of this pair, a second pair of figures stands or
            walks on the downward slope of a hill. Because they are further away, they are smaller
            and less detailed and blend into the vegetation. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image15" id="23">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Statue of Bishop in Gothic portal</p></title>

        <caption> Sculptural figures adorn the arched portal on the left side of the plate. The
            largest of these figures stands inside a hexagonal niche of a tabernacle pinnacle on the
            left side of the arch. These niche spaces are typical of Gothic architecture and often
            contain representations of saints, angels, and other religious figures. The figure in
            this engraving is a Catholic bishop, identified by his mitre, ornately decorated robes,
            and crosier. The bishop’s left hand is raised with finger extended, as if blessing the
            pilgrims below who are beginning their journey. To the left of the bishop, a sculptural
            decoration shows two figures kneeling and facing each other. Either wings or the hoods
            of their gowns are visible as they bend their arms up in prayer. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image16" id="24">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Doves and Church Spires</p></title>

        <caption> Three white, dove-like birds sit on the eaves of the right side of the Tabard Inn
            while two similar birds fly above nearby church spires. The two lowest birds touch
            beaks. Stevenson suggests that these birds may collectively symbolize the five senses of
            man through which one may enter eternity, which Blake references in <i>Europe A
                Prophecy</i> (Stevenson, 118). </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image17" id="25">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Flock of black birds</p></title>

        <caption> A flock of four black birds – possibly ravens – fly with outstretched wings to the
            right of the white birds. The leftmost bird stretches its neck downward while the others
            appear to ascend. According to Damon, priests and the Church view ravens as symbols of
            Death. However, he also cites <i>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</i> to re-contextualize
            Death as the dawn of a new day: “Let the Priests of the Raven of dawn, no longer in
            deadly black, with hoarse note curse the sons of joy” (Damon, 341).</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image18" id="26">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Greyhounds</p></title>

        <caption> Two greyhounds stride in the foreground alongside the Lady Abbess’s horse. The
            greyhounds, present in Chaucer’s original texts and mentioned explicitly in Blake’s
                <i>Descriptive Catalogue</i> for the 1809 exhibition, associate the Abbess with the
            chaste goddess Diana. The closest dog strides forward with head erect and left paw
            raised in a posture that mirrors many of the surrounding horses. The second dog rears
            upward to paw at the underbelly or decorative saddle of the Lady Abbess’s horse. The
            juxtaposition of the light greyhounds to the left of the dark dog echoes the pairing of
            the engraving’s two groups of birds in which the lighter animals are also on the left. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image19" id="27">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Black Dog</p></title>
        <caption> Directly beneath the Knight and the Squire at the front of the pilgrimage, a
            stocky black dog marches forward and stares with its right eye completely open. Although
            the dog wears a collar its coat is unkempt, giving it a mangy, bestial appearance. The
            juxtaposition of the lighter greyhounds on the left with the dark dog on the right
            echoes the pairing of the engraving’s two groups of birds in which the darker animals
            are also on the right. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Image20" id="28">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Gallery I: Blake’s Pilgrims and Selected Figures</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Façade of Tabard Inn with Inscriptions</p></title>

        <caption> The largest architectural component of the composition is the Tabard Inn at far
            left from which the pilgrims emerge through a pointed arch supported by columns. The
            text on the gable and spandrels above the portal identify the building and the subject
            of the engraving. The left spandrel reads “THE TABARDE INNE BY HENRY BAILLY”; the right
            side of the gable reads “THE LODGYINGE HOUSE FOR PILGRIMS”; and the right spandrel reads
            “WHO JOURNEY TO SAINT THOMASS SHINE AT CANTERBURY”. The Gothic elements that decorate
            the façade are unusual in order and placement. The two wooden beams that form the roof
            of the portal are decorated with scalloped eaves. The rectangular divisions below and to
            the left of the building’s peak contain four windows possibly with stained glass panes;
            a tabernacle pinnacle containing the sculpture of the bishop; either lancet windows,
            buttresses, or niches; and at least one additional area with sculpted decorations to the
            left of the bishop figure. The interior portion of the Tabard Inn that is visible
            through the portal shows an inner right wall decorated with three wide, arched windows
            separated by columns. A sculpted saint or angel tops the central column. The three
            arches frame the heads of the Reeve, Chaucer, and the Clerk of Oxenford, a correlation
            that underscores how precisely Blake integrated all of the forms of the engraving into a
            cohesive program. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="but653" id="29">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Painting of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption> Blake, <i>Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the nine and twenty Pilgrims on their journey to
                Canterbury</i>, 1808(?), Butlin 653</caption>

    </image>



    <image dbi="Stothard_painting" id="30">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Thomas Stothard's Painting of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption>Thomas Stothard, <i>The Pilgrimage to Cantebury</i>, 1807</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="esxvi.1.3i.sp" id="31">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Engraving of the Pilgrims</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</i>, 1810, third state, impression 3I,
            Essick XVI.3I</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="bb12a" id="32">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Advertisement for the Engraving</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Prospectus for the engraving of 'Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims'</i>, 15 May 1809, Bentley 12A</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="Stothard.CP.Heath" id="33">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Engraving of Stothard's Painting</p></title>
        <caption>Stothard, <i>The Pilgrimage to Canterbury</i>, engraved by Luis Schiavonetti,
            Robert Cromek, Francis Engleheart, Niccolo Schiavonetti, James Heath, W. H. Worthington,
            1817</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page0" id="34">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Wife of Bath</p></title>

        <caption> Blake and Stothard create starkly different portrayals of the Wife of Bath.
            Blake’s version is informed by what he perceives as a binary relationship between the
            Wife of Bath and the Lady Prioress, representatives of the two classes of women. He
            asserts: <blockquote> Are not these leaders of the ages of men? The lady prioress, in
                some ages, predominates; and in some the Wife of Bath, in whose character Chaucer
                has been equally minute and exact; because she is also a scourge and a blight. I
                shall say no more of her, nor expose what Chaucer has left hidden; let the young
                reader study what he has said of her: it is useful as a scare-crow. There are of
                such characters born too many for the peace of the world.<sup><a class="footnote"
                            >1<span>DC, VIII, 24.</span></a></sup>
            </blockquote> Blake’s Wife of Bath signifies loose sexuality, false piety, and
            preoccupation with worldly materials and power, characterized by the cross necklace
            suspended between exposed breasts; the star-shaped spur above her right heel; the
            cock-headed riding crop in one hand and wine in the other; prominently spread legs
            facing the viewer; and an appearance compromised by buck teeth, a sagging chin, and a
            hooked nose.<br/><br/>In contrast, Stothard’s Wife of Bath wears plain, modest clothing and
            a wimple and hat covering her hair, head, and chin. The wimple is included in Chaucer’s
            original description but is notably disregarded by Blake. Stothard’s Wife of Bath is
            portrayed as attractive, young, and comely, as she looks playfully over her left
            shoulder toward the pilgrims behind her. Blake lambasts the design in his <i
                >Descriptive Catalogue</i>, deriding both Stothard and his reviewer John Hoppner:
                <blockquote> In this manner he has jumbled his dumb dollies together, and is praised
                by his equals for it; for both himself and his friend are equally masters of
                Chaucer’s language. They both think that the Wife of Bath is a young beautiful
                blooming damsel; and H[oppner] says, that she is the Fair Wife of Bath, and that the
                Spring appears in her Cheeks. Now hear what Chaucer has made her say of herself, who
                is no modest one, <br/><br/> ‘But Lord when it rememberth me <br/> Upon my youth and
                on my jollity, <br/> It tickleth me about the heart root. <br/> Unto this day it
                doth my heart boot, <br/> That I have had my world as in my time; <br/> But age,
                alas, that all will envenime, <br/> Hath me bereft, my beauty and my pith <br/> Let
                go; farewell: the devel go therewith, <br/> The flower is gone, there is no more to
                tell. <br/> The bran, as best, I can, I now mote sell; <br/> And yet, to be right
                    merry, will I fond, <br/> Now forth to tell of my fourth husband.’<sup><a class="footnote"
                        >2<span>DC, VIII, 30-31.</span></a></sup> </blockquote>
            Stothard portrays the Wife of Bath with no external markers of her flawed internal
            character instead of as a “scare-crow” for the edification of viewers, as Blake does.
            Blake hails that situating her in a “common scene” like Hoppner describes is the most
            dangerous disguise for such a woman. </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page1" id="35">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Knight and Squire</p></title>

        <caption> Blake begins the <i>Descriptive Catalogue</i> with descriptions of the
            Knight and the Squire, the two rightmost figures in his composition. He argues that his
            placement echoes Chaucer’s, who “has also placed them first in his prologue.”<sup><a class="footnote"
                >1<span>DC, III, 11.</span></a></sup> Blake
            then launches into a laudatory account of the pair’s characters: <blockquote> The Knight
                is a true Hero, a good, great, and wise man; his whole length portrait on horseback,
                as written by Chaucer, cannot be surpassed. He has spent his life in the field; has
                ever been a conqueror, and is that species of character which in every age stands as
                the guardian of man against the oppressor. His son [the Squire] is like him with the
                germ of perhaps greater perfection still, as he blends literature and the arts with
                his warlike studies. Their dress and their horses are of the first rate, without
                ostentation, and with all the true grandeur that unaffected simplicity when in high
                rank always displays.<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >2<span>DC, III, 11.</span></a></sup> </blockquote> The full-length portrait of the mounted
            knight accords with Chaucer’s text: he wears the armor and accouterments expected of a
            life of conquest on the battlefield. His posture and gesture also suggest leadership.
            <br/><br/>This depiction contrasts with Stothard’s Knight at right, the second visible
            pilgrim from the left. Stothard’s Knight is shown in profile crowded among the other
            pilgrims and wears stylish civilian attire, including a large black hat. Stothard places
            the Knight and the Squire seventh and ninth, respectively, in the procession, with the
            Reeve between them. Blake highlights this placement as an erroneous departure from
            Chaucer’s text, asserting, “nothing need be done but to examine my rival’s prospectus.
            The two first characters in Chaucer, the Knight and the Squire, he has put among his
            rabble; and indeed his prospectus calls the Squire the fop of Chaucer’s age.”<sup><a class="footnote"
                >3<span>DC, III, 28.</span></a></sup> Blake
            then quotes three sections of Chaucer’s introduction in which he lists various honorable
            qualities of the Squire and asks rhetorically after each: “Was this a fop?”<sup><a class="footnote"
                >4<span>DC, III, 28.</span></a></sup><br/><br/>
            Blake observes that “Chaucer makes every one of his characters perfect in his kind,
            every one is an Antique Statue; the image of a class, and not of an imperfect
            individual.”<sup><a class="footnote"
                >5<span>DC, III, 20.</span></a></sup> This particularity of Blake’s approach is evident in his statuesque
            depiction of the Squire, whom he associates with Apollo. Stothard’s Squire, in contrast,
            leans back as his horse lurches wildly beneath him.</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page2" id="36">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Plowman</p></title>

        <caption> Both Blake and Stothard distance the Plowman from the viewer, obscuring all but
            the pilgrim’s head and shoulders. Both depictions are in profile and both are similarly
            attired in a wide-brimmed hat and simple shirt. Stothard’s Plowman also wears a
            protective neck covering. Blake’s depiction, however, is more intricately detailed,
            exemplified by the visible veins on the Plowman’s neck. <br/> In his <i
                >Descriptive Catalogue</i>, Blake chastises Stothard for depicting his Plowman as
            aged and for a reliance on color over line. Blake first compares his depiction to
            Chaucer’s text: <blockquote> The Plowman is simplicity itself, with wisdom and strength
                for its stamina. Chaucer has divided the ancient character of Hercules between his
                Miller and his Plowman. Benevolence is the plowman’s great characteristic, he is
                thin with excessive labour, and not with old age, as some have supposed. <br/><br/>
                ‘He would thresh and thereto dike and delve <br/> For Christe’s sake, for every
                poore wight, <br/> Withouten hire, if it lay in his might.’<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >1<span>DC, III, 21.</span></a></sup> </blockquote> True to
            the text, the gaunt cheeks and leathery skin of Blake’s Plowman are associated with
            outdoor labor. He criticizes Stothard for departing from the text by associating hard
            work with old age. He writes that Chaucer, <blockquote> has respected his True Pilgrims,
                who are a majority of his company, and are not thrown together in the random manner
                that Mr. S[tothard] has done. Chaucer has no where called the Plowman old, worn out
                with age and labour, as the prospectus has represented him, and says, that the
                picture has done so too. He is worn down with labour, not with age.<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >2<span>DC, III, 32.</span></a></sup> </blockquote>
            Earlier in the <i>Descriptive Catalogue</i>, Blake relates Chaucer’s Plowman
            to Hercules. Blake elaborates: <blockquote> The Plowman of Chaucer is Hercules in his
                supreme eternal state, divested of his spectrous shadow; which is the Miller, a
                terrible fellow, such as exists in all times and places, for the trial of men, to
                astonish every neighborhood, with brutal strength and courage, to get rich and
                powerful to curb the pride of Man.<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >3<span>DC, III, 22.</span></a></sup> </blockquote> Several scholars have argued
            that Blake’s prolonged defense of the Plowman suggests not only elevated respect, but
            also a personal identification. Karl Kiralis first highlighted a physical likeness
            between the Plowman and Blake – though he does not cite a specific portrait.<sup><a class="footnote"
                >4<span>Kiralis, “William Blake as an Intellectual and Spiritual Guide to Chaucer’s
                    Canterbury Pilgrims,” 147.</span></a></sup> Warren
            Stevenson points out that the Plowman’s wide-brimmed hat is somewhat similar to the hat
            Blake wears in John Linnell’s drawing of him.<sup><a class="footnote"
                >5<span>Stevenson, “Interpreting Blake’s Canterbury
                    Pilgrims,” in <i>Chaucer Illustrated: Five Hundred Years of the Canterbury
                        Tales in Pictures</i>, 208. For a reproduction of Linnell’s drawing, see Keynes,
                    <i>The Complete Portraiture of William &amp; Catherine Blake</i>, illus.
                    33 and p. 139.</span></a></sup> Lastly, Alexander Gourlay highlights
            the similar physiognomy of Blake’s Plowman and James Deville’s life mask of Blake from
            1823.<sup><a class="footnote"
                >6<span>Gourlay, “Idolatry or Politics,” 116-7.</span></a></sup> Gourlay argues that “by portraying himself in this role Blake becomes the
            genuine hero ignored in these and Chaucer’s times: the starved and neglected Plowman,
            the man who does the difficult and productive work in the society, contrasts
            dramatically with the sleek, honored, parasitic drones who dominate the procession and
            the culture as a whole.” Blake’s self-association with the Plowman emphasizes their
            shared marginalization in past and present societies that failed to recognize their
            efforts or genius.</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page3" id="37">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Monk and Friar</p></title>

        <caption> Blake takes particular issue with Stothard’s loose interpretation of Chaucer’s
            text in relation to the Monk. In Stothard’s version at right, the Monk rides slightly in
            front of and to the left of the Friar, whereas in Blake’s version the Friar rides in
            front, turning his head back toward his companion. Blake targets Stothard’s literary
            incompetence to account for the difference: <blockquote> He [Stothard] has done all by
                chance, or perhaps his fortune, money, money. According to his prospectus he has
                Three Monks; these he cannot find in Chaucer, who has only One Monk, and that no
                vulgar character, as he has endeavoured to make him. When men cannot read they
                should not pretend to paint. To be sure Chaucer is a little difficult to him who has
                only blundered over novels and catchpenny trifles of booksellers. Yet a little pains
                ought to be taken even by the ignorant and weak.<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >1<span>DC, III, 29.</span></a></sup> </blockquote> Stothard includes
            a single Monk in his final composition, but Blake critiques this Monk’s “vulgar”
            character, suggested by his placement behind the Wife of Bath. Their exaggeratedly round
            faces and somewhat ridiculous smiles compromise the assumed seriousness of their
            positions. <br/> Blake outlines his alternative interpretation of the Monk:<br/><br/> For
            the Monk is described by Chaucer, as a man of the first rank in society, noble, rich,
            and expensively attended: he is a leader of the age, with certain humourous
            accompaniments in his character, that do not degrade but render him an object of
            dignified mirth, but also with other accompaniments not so respectable.<sup><a class="footnote"
                >2<span>DC, III, 13.</span></a></sup><br/><br/>
            Alexander S. Gourlay notes that Blake’s Monk resembles profile heads minted on coins,
            underscoring traditional dignity. Specifically, Gourley notes a resemblance to King
            George III in coins of the period and to a particularly striking caricature of George as
            a tonsured priest. He supports this comparison through Blake’s characterization of the
            Monk’s complexities.<sup><a class="footnote"
                >3<span>See Alexander S. Gourlay, “‘Idolotry or
                    Politics:’ Blake’s Chaucer, the Gods of Priam, and the Powers of 1809.”</span></a></sup> Blake states, “Though a man of luxury, pride and pleasure, he is a
            master of art and learning, though affecting to despise it. Those who can think that the
            proud Huntsman, and noble Housekeeper, Chaucer’s Monk, is intended for a buffoon or
            burlesque character, know little of Chaucer,”<sup><a class="footnote"
                >4<span>DC, III, 16.</span></a></sup> Whether Blake intended the Monk to
            resemble the English king, the possibility of it, coupled with his extended description
            of the pilgrim, emphasize the extent to which Blake, too, altered or added to Chaucer’s
            original characterization. <br/> Blake continues with a lengthy description of the
            Friar, integrating Chaucer’s text to explain that he was <blockquote> a character also
                of a mixed kind. ‘A friar there was, a wanton and a merry.’ [B]ut in his office he
                is said to be a ‘full solemn man:’ eloquent, amorous, witty, and satyrical; young,
                handsome, and rich; he is a complete rogue; with constitutional gaiety enough to
                make him a master of all the pleasures of the word. ‘His neck was white as the flour
                de lis, Thereto strong he was as a champioun.’<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >5<span>DC, III, 13.</span></a></sup> </blockquote> The thick yet
            graceful columnar neck and rosy lips of Blake’s Friar contrasts with the multitude of
            chins on Stothard’s buffoonish Friar. However, the movements of Blake’s Friar might also
            suggest the pilgrim’s unstable solemnity. Unlike the Monk, who stares forward toward,
            most likely, the religious object of their travel, the Friar shifts his gaze slightly
            back and points to the left, toward either the Pardoner or the Host. He attempts to
            redirect the Monk’s stoic gaze back to the realm of baser human activity.
            
          </caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page4" id="38">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Host</p></title>

        <caption> The Host, Henry Baillie, is depicted prominently in both Blake and Stothard’s
            engravings. Blake centers the Host within the procession and compositional space. His
            body assumes a cruciform position as he twists his torso and extends his arms. Despite
            the Host’s rather uncomely, corpulent appearance, Blake extols the pilgrim’s internal
            character: <blockquote> For the Host who follows this group, and holds the center of the
                cavalcade, is a first rate character, and his jokes are no trifles; they are always,
                though uttered with audacity, and equally free with the Lord and the Peasant, they
                are always substantially and weightily expressive of knowledge and experience; Henry
                Baillie, the keeper of the greatest Inn, of the greatest City; for such was the
                Tabarde Inn in Southwark, near London: our Host was also a leader of the age.<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >1<span>DC, III, 16.</span></a></sup>
            </blockquote> He compares the Host to Silenus, the satyr in Greek mythology who was a
            companion of Dionysus and, though wise, was often drunk. The unfocused stare of Blake’s
            Host may suggest that he, like the Cook and the Wife of Bath who hold visible drinking
            glasses, has indulged in a “morning’s draught of comfort” before beginning the
            pilgrimage.<sup><a class="footnote"
                >2<span>DC, III, 8.</span></a></sup> Nevertheless, the Host in Blake’s composition fulfills his entertaining
            duties: he unites both halves of the pilgrims through his outspread arms and his likely
            forthcoming proposition to begin the storytelling game.<br/><br/> Stothard’s Host, at right,
            rides near the front rather than middle of the procession. He also gestures to draw
            attention, presumably to call for the start of the competition. Unlike the ornate ruffed
            collar and tights worn by Blake’s Host, Stothard’s Host wears heavier, simpler clothing
            that fully covers his body – although like Blake’s Host, he appears quite heavy. He
            turns sharply to face the pilgrims behind him, his mouth open while displaying an
            indistinguishable object in his raised left hand. The Host’s turned horse and body act
            as a sort of bracket to contain the pilgrims, although excluding the Miller, who appears
            quite uninterested in the Host’s call for a game.</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="page5" id="39">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: The Pilgrims Compared</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Miller</p></title>

        <caption> The Miller embodies what Blake calls the “spectrous shadow” of the Plowman,
            forming the baser half of the ideal Herculean state that Blake discusses in his <i>Descriptive Catalogue</i>. Blake characterizes the Miller as an
            omnipresent, irredeemable figure: <blockquote> The Plowman of Chaucer is Hercules in his
                supreme eternal state, divested of his spectrous shadow; which is the Miller, a
                terrible fellow, such as exists in all times and places, for the trial of men, to
                astonish every neighborhood, with brutal strength and courage, to get rich and
                powerful to curb the pride of Man.<sup><a class="footnote"
                    >1<span>DC, III, 22.</span></a></sup> </blockquote> Blake’s Miller rides near the
            rear of the procession between the Wife of Bath and the Cook. Characterized through
            thick, curly hair and a flame-like beard, his large eyes stare toward the Wife of Bath
            while he holds a musical instrument to his lips. His complexion may be darker than the
            other pilgrims to accentuate Blake’s characterization of him as a “shadow.”<br/><br/> In
            Stothard’s depiction at right the Miller’s instrument is more clearly shown to be a
            bagpipe. Stothard places the Miller at the front of the procession, but his posture and
            appearance contrast with his ostensible place of prominence. Slumped forward with
            heavily lidded eyes, the Miller plods forward and pays no attention to the Host, who
            appears to speak behind him. Unlike Stothard’s other pilgrims, his Miller does not
            interact with others. He stares ahead. The Host’s turned body further accentuates the
            Miller’s separation.</caption>

    </image>


    <image dbi="bb11a.1" id="40">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: Blake’s Chaucer: An Original Engraving by him from his Fresco Painting</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Leaflet Describing the Engraving, Page 1</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Blake's Chaucer: An Original Engraving</i>, 1810, Bentley 11A, page
            1</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="bb11a.2" id="41">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: Blake’s Chaucer: An Original Engraving by him from his Fresco Painting</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Leaflet Describing the Engraving, Page 2</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Blake's Chaucer: An Original Engraving</i>, 1810, Bentley 11A, page
            2</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="bb11a.3" id="42">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: Blake’s Chaucer: An Original Engraving by him from his Fresco Painting</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake's Leaflet Describing the Engraving, Page 3</p></title>
        <caption>Blake, <i>Blake's Chaucer: An Original Engraving</i>, 1810, Bentley 11A, page
            3</caption>

    </image>


    <image dbi="image45" id="43">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Francis Douce</p></title>
        <caption>From <a href="https://archive.org/details/illustrationssh01doucgoog"
            ><i>Illustrations of Shakespeare and of Ancient Manners</i></a> (1807): “Mr.
            Stothard, with every claim to superior merit, has recently finished a Painting of the
            Procession of <i>Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</i>, which may be classed among the
            choicest morsels of its kind. The <i>attention to accuracy of costume</i> which it
            displays, has <i>never been exceeded</i>, and <i>but very seldom so well directed</i>”
            (285). Yet according to J. B. Mertz, Douce demonstrated his preference for Blake’s
            design by purchasing a print of Blake’s engraving and not one of Stothard’s design
            (75).</caption>
        
    </image>

    <image dbi="image48" id="44">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">John Hoppner</p></title>
        <caption>From a 10 May 1807 letter to Richard Cumberland, quoted in Cromek’s prospectus and
            in <i>Carey’s Critical Description</i>: “The features of each individual are touched
            with the most happy discrimination of character, and prove the Painter to have studied
            the human heart with as much attention, and not less successfully, than [sic] the Poet.
            This intelligent group is rendered still more interesting by the charm of colouring,
            which, though simple, is strong, and most harmoniously distributed throughout the
            picture.” The painting “is wholly free from that vice which painters term manner” and
            “bears no mark of the period in which it was painted, but might very well pass for the
            work of some able artist of the time of Chaucer.” It has “a primitive simplicity and the
            total absence of all affectation, either of colour or penciling” (Carey 13).</caption>
        
    </image>





    <image dbi="image46" id="45">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Robert Cromek</p></title>
        <caption>From his 1808 <a target="_blank" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=cD9aAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                >prospectus</a>: “These tales are the most pleasing of Chaucer’s works. It is the
            characters which are described in <i>the general Prologue</i> to them which Mr. Stothard
            has now transferred to the Canvas; and with so much truth and sprightliness, and in a
            manner so agreeable, that the Poet’s humor may, with truth, be said to be revived in the
            Painter. It is the particular merit of this piece, that the story is immediately brought
            home to the Spectator. He becomes instantly one of the group, and sees them move before
            him, marked by their distinctive habits, characters, and sensations, in the same manner
            as Chaucer has drawn them. The idea of the Poet is impressed at the first view,—a humor
            unforced, agreeable, and comic; <i>a pleasurable Tour; sanctified by the name of
                Pilgrimage</i>. The covert ridicule on these eccentric excursions, which Chaucer
            intended, is very happily preserved in his face; the quiet indifference of one of the
            Monks, the hypocrisy of another, and the real piety of a third, are with equal
            excellency portrayed. The gay levity of the Wife of <i>Bath</i>, and the countenance of
            the old Ploughman, worn down with age and labour, are finely rendered. The Miller is an
            admirable character; and his Horse is as much in character as himself. The <i>Fop of
                Chaucer’s Age</i> is exhibited as making a display of his riding; and the Sea
            Captain bestrides his Nag with the usual awkwardness of the Sailor. The pale and
            studious countenance of the Oxford Scholar; the stateliness of the Lady-Abbess; the
            facetiousness and homely humour of the Host, as contrasted with the Segeant at Law, and
            the Doctor of Physic;—all these peculiarities of character are very finely and
            delicately expressed. The costume of each Person is correct with an antiquarian
            exactness; and the whole Group is so well distributed, that each character is
            sufficiently seen, and in his due place” (39-40).</caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="image47" id="46">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">William Paulet Carey</p></title>
        <caption>From <a target="_blank" href="https://books.google.com/books?id=aadbAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA9&amp;lpg=PA9&amp;dq=A+Critical+Description+of+the+Procession+of+Chaucer%27s+Pilgrims+to+Canterbury&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=byICT0qaM6&amp;sig=FAgGRiZI6lwOr0zECro_JgE9Vc4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=7VM8U8erOJPNsQTTq4D4Dw&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                >Critical Description of Chaucer’s Pilgrims</a>: (1808) contains a detailed and
            admiring description of Stothard’s painting. “Connoisseurs talk only of the beauties of
            the composition, and of the triumph of the Artist” (11).</caption>

    </image>

    <image dbi="image44" id="47">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Robert Hunt</p></title>
        <caption>From <i>Examiner</i> (1809): “These he calls an Exhibition, of which he has
            published a Catalogue, or rather a farrago of nonsense, unintelligibleness, and
            egregious vanity, the wold effusions of a distempered brain" (BR2, 283).</caption>
        
    </image>

    <image dbi="image49" id="48">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Robert Bowyer, bookseller</p></title>
        <caption>From a 20 June 1810 letter to Lord Earl Spencer: “Mr. Bowyer begs leave to acquaint
            Lord Spencer that the Plate of which the enclosed is a prospectus is Engraving in the
            line manner &amp; of which W: B: has already a very fine Etching &amp; he [Bowyer]
            has reason to believe it will be one of the finest Engravings which has been seen in
            this country for some Years” (BR2 300). </caption>
    </image>
    <image dbi="image50" id="49">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Lady's Monthly Museum</p></title>
        <caption> From the only known review of Blake’s painting, as exhibited in the Associated
            Painters in Water Colours, appeared in the June 1812 <i>The Lady’s Monthly Museum</i>:
            “Sir Geoffrey Chaucer and the Pilgrims, by Blake is a picture of mongrel excellence; yet
            has such a repulsive appearance, that we doubt most of our fair readers will scarcely
            view it with pleasure, unless they should be well acquainted with <i>Aunciente</i>
            tapestrye, to enter into its merits. That it is the work of genius, no one will deny; it
            possesses all the truth, the costume, and manners of the times; and the artist is
            perhaps worthy of the highest commendation for his industry, research, and correctness;
            but for our parts, we feel ourselves so perfectly satisfied with the same subject, as
            treated by Stothard, that we wish not to possess a picture whose greatest merit seems to
            be an imitation of the arts in their degraded state” (BR2 313-314).</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="image51" id="50">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Thomas Frognall Dibdin</p></title>
        <caption> From an 1816 entry: “When Blake entered the arena with Stothard, as a rival in
            depicting the <i>Dramatis Personae</i> of Chaucer’s Canterbury Tales, he seems to have
            absolutely lost his wits; his pencil was as inferior to that of the former, as his burin
            was to that of <i>Cromek</i> [i.e., Schiavonetti], who engraved Stothard’s immortal
            picture” (BR2 328).</caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="image52" id="51">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Charles Lamb</p></title>
        <caption>From a 15 May 1824 letter to Bernard Barton: “His Pictures, one in particular the
            Canterbury Pilgrims (far above Stothard’s)[,] have great merit, but hard, dry, yet with
            grace. He has written a Catalogue of them, with a most spirited criticism on Chaucer,
            but mystical and full of Vision” (BR2 394).</caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="image53" id="52">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">J.T. Smith</p></title>
        <caption>From Nollekens and His Times (1828): “I entertain a high respect for the talents of
            both persons concerned” (BR2 613).</caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="image54" id="53">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Allan Cunningham</p></title>
        <caption>From <i>Lives of British Painters</i> (1830): “The chief attraction [of Blake’s
            1809 exhibition] was the Canterbury Pilgrimage, not indeed from its excellence, but from
            the circumstance of its origin, which was well known about town, and pointedly alluded
            to in the catalogue. The picture is a failure. Blake was too great a visionary for
            dealing with such literal wantons as the Wife of Bath and her jolly companions. The
            natural flesh and blood of Chaucer prevailed against him. He gives grossness of body for
            grossness of mind,—tries to be merry and wicked—and in vain” (BR2 644).</caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="image55" id="54">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Barron Field</p></title>
        <caption>From the conclusion of an anonymous and unpublished review of Chaucer Modernized,
            ed. Thomas Powell &amp; R.H. Horne (1830): “Have any of our readers ever seen the
            print of the Canterbury pilgrims by William Blake, the mad artist, whose biography may
            be read in Mr. Allan Cunningham’s Lives? He painted it, he says, before Mr. Stothard’s
            picture on the same subject, and nearly thirty years ago he exhibited it publicly, in
            opposition to that elegant composition. Mr. Stothard’s picture is Chaucer modernized—the
            horses are all barbs, from the Elgin Marbles, and the riders, refined and softened, in
            stage-dresses. Mr. Blake’s picture is Chaucer in the old rough verse—“in his habit as he
            lived”—bad in drawing, but true and vivid in expression. His horses are wooden toys, and
            his dogs pigs; but the individual character is in every human face, and look and dress.
            Mr. Blake understood Chaucer, like Mr. Wordsworth, profoundly. Mr. Stothard read him
            like Mr. Horne, superficially. Together with his Exhibition, Mr. Blake gave you, for yr.
            shilling, a printed description of his Pictures, in contrast with Mr. Stothards’. This
            contained a little madness about painting, and a great deal of abuse of Mr. Stothard;
            but it was prefaced by some Observations on Chaucer’s Poem, of so striking and original
            a kind, that, as the pamphlet is now as good as MS. (few people being in the habit of
            preserving their Exhibition Catalogues) we shall conclude this article by quoting them.
            [quotes from <i>Descriptive Catalogue</i>] Poor William Blake! He was
            certainly a man of a genius kindred to that of Chaucer” (BR2 534-535).</caption>

    </image>
    <image dbi="image56" id="55">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: Selection of Contemporary Comments</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Arnolds Magazine of the Fine Arts</p></title>
        <caption>From “On the Genius of Stothard, and the Character of his Works,” <i>Arnolds
                Magazine of the Fine Arts</i>, NS, III (March 1834), 440: Blake’s engraving “might
            in its character and execution have passed for a performance or work of Art,
            contemporary with the times of Chaucer” (BR2 228).</caption>

    </image>







</exhibit>
