<tei.2 id="glossary"><teiheader/><text><front/><body><div1 type="document"><div2 type="preface"><head>AN EMERGENCY ONLINE GLOSSARY OF TERMS, NAMES, AND CONCEPTS IN BLAKE</head><p>By Alexander S. Gourlay</p><p>The following is a revised and expanded version of "A Glossary of Terms, Names, and Concepts in Blake" in <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</title>, ed. Morris Eaves (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003), pages 272-87.  This resource is best used when Blake is making you dizzy, but as soon
as you regain your equilibrium, you should return to reading Blake on his
own terms.  Blake's names are particularly likely to inspire vertigo, but
if he wanted us to depend heavily on glossaries, dictionaries, and other learned
devices he would have provided them.  That he did not suggests that he wanted
his readers to trust him and trust themselves rather than "experts," though
he seems to have overestimated how well most us would know the Bible and the
other traditions to which he alludes.  Many of his characters correspond roughly
to more familiar beings from various mythologies, but by renaming them Blake
indicated that we should start afresh with them as characters, before someone
has told us what they mean.  At the same time, most of his characters are
multivalent allegorical beings corresponding simultaneously to such things
as mental faculties, emotions, psychological categories, political figures
or positions, geographical entities, body parts and so forth.  Don't ignore
the various polyglot etymologies that have been proposed for their names elsewhere,
for these often appear to contribute to Blake's own conception of characters,
though most names are primarily puns in English with echoes of familiar mythic
names.  Bear in mind that Blake's characters may change in radical fashion,
especially when separated from their emanations, and characters from one context
may be presented from a very different perspective elsewhere, even in the
same work, and may be known by several different names; these complexities
are greatly oversimplified here.</p><p>This glossary silently incorporates suggestions and discoveries by Morris
Eaves, Michael Ferber, John E. Grant, Cate McClenahan, E. B. Murray, G. A.
Rosso, Daniel Stempel, and of course S. Foster Damon, who did it all first;
when this glossary fails, try Damon's <title level="m">Blake Dictionary</title>.  This is a work in progress: please send corrections and propose additional entries to agourlay@risd.edu.</p></div2><div2 type="glossary"><list type="gloss"><item><label id="g1">Abel</label> Abel is the second child of Adam and Eve,
 murdered by his brother <ref target="g18">Cain</ref> in Genesis 4.  Blake referred to the voice calling for vengeance in 4:10 as the <title level="j">Ghost of Abel,</title> a phrase he used as the title
of a late etched work (1822) inspired by Byron's <title level="m">Cain</title> and
Gessner's <title level="m">Death of Abel</title>.  Elsewhere Blake treated
this incident as the origin of the law of retribution rather than forgiveness.</item><item><label id="g2">Adona</label> Adona is the name of a river in <title level="j">The Book of Thel</title>; it appears
to be a feminized version of "Adonis," who in classical myth is a beautiful youth with whom Venus
was smitten, as told in Ovid, <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> 10; she
mourns his early death, then transforms him into the short-lived windflower,
the anemone, the species of flower shown on the title page of <title level="m">Thel</title>.</item><item><label id="g3">Ahania</label> Ahania is an emanation of Urizen.  Her
name suggests Urania, the muse associated with astronomy and the heavens (and
an epithet of celestial Venus), and also the surprised laughter of discovery:
"Aha!"  She is associated with pleasure (Urizen calls her "sin") and also
charity, and her twelve sons correspond to the signs of the zodiac.</item><item><label id="g4">Albion</label> Albion is a traditional name for England
and also a mythical English giant.  In Blake, the giant Albion is the country
and its inhabitants, but is also identified as the fallen personification of
 all humankind, the Eternal Man.  <ref target="g64">Jerusalem</ref> is his emanation and his Daughters
are the women of England.</item><item><label id="g5">Albion's Angel</label> Albion's Angel is Blake's designation
in <title level="m">America</title> for the British politician (someone like
Lord Bute), who debates the thirteen colonial angels, represented by Boston's
Angel (someone like Samuel Adams).</item><item><label id="g6">Ariston</label> Called the "king of beauty" in <title level="m">America</title>, Ariston also appears briefly in <title level="m">The
Song of Los</title> and <title level="m">The Four Zoas</title>.  The name,
which is related to a Greek root meaning "best," may have come from Herodotus.</item><item><label id="g7">Ark</label> Arks are vessels that preserve the divine
against the dangers of the fallen world, such as Noah's ark and that in which
Moses was found among the bulrushes.  The Ark of the Covenant (an elaborate
chest wrought by the artists Bezaleel and Aholiab) held Moses' broken tablets
of the Law, Aaron's rod, and a pot of manna; it was kept in the innermost
sanctuary of a tabernacle (see <ref target="g129">veil</ref>).  Blake's uses
of arks reflect several interpretive traditions.</item><item><label id="g8">Augury</label> Roman augurers made prophecies by observing
birds in flight; an augury can be any kind of divination, usually based upon
signs in nature.</item><item><label id="g9">Ball</label>  See <ref target="g50">globe</ref>.</item><item><label id="g10">Bard</label>  Bards were ancient prophets and poets
of Britain, often associated in Blake's day with the Druids and with native
 opposition to invading <ref target="g53">Romans</ref> or Normans, as in Thomas Gray's <title level="j">The
Bard</title> (1757).  The Bard of <title level="m">Songs of Experience</title> has
a presiding role paralleling that of the Shepherd in <title level="m">Songs of Innocence</title>.</item><item><label id="g11">Behmen</label>  See <ref target="g14">Boehme</ref>.</item><item><label id="g12">Beulah</label> Beulah ("married") is the happy country
with which the Lord is delighted, according to Isaiah 62.  Blake's Beulah
land is a dreamy paradise in which the sexes, though divided, blissfully converse
in shameless selflessness.  Beulah is available through dreams and visions
to those in Ulro, the utterly fallen world.</item><item><label id="g13">Bird/Birds</label> Like his references to <ref target="g44">flowers</ref>, Blake's representations of birds often draw upon myth and folklore as well as behavioral characteristics of particular species.  See for instance <ref target="g28">Dove</ref> and <ref target="g66">Lark</ref>.</item><item><label id="g14">Boehme</label>  Jacob Boehme or Behmen (1575-1624) was
an engaging mystical philosopher whose works, as translated into English by
William Law, profoundly influenced Blake's thinking throughout his career.
 Like <ref target="g115">Swedenborg</ref>, Boehme interpreted the Bible in a radical spirit.</item><item><label id="g15">Boston's Angel</label>  See<ref target="g5"> Albion's
Angel</ref>.</item><item><label id="g16">Bromion</label> Bromion evokes "Bromius," an epithet
for the Greek god Dionysus meaning "roarer." As a character in <title level="m">Visions
of the Daughters of Albion</title>, he sometimes acts like another roaring
rapist, Boreas, the North Wind, as in Ovid, <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> 6.
 See also <ref target="g92">Palamabron</ref>.</item><item><label id="g17">Butterfly/moth</label>  Moths and butterflies were both
called "flies" in the eighteenth century, and are treated very similarly (but
distinguishably) by Blake, who followed the classical tradition of associating
moths and butterflies with the soul.  See also <ref target="g136">worm</ref>.</item><item><label id="g18">Cain</label> Cain, the first murderer, causes the initiation
of the law of retribution that is supplanted by Jesus' law of forgiveness. See <ref target="g1">Abel</ref>.</item><item><label id="g19">Cart</label>  A cart that accompanies a <ref target="g94">plow</ref> carries
dung as fertilizer.</item><item><label id="g20">Chafer</label>  The cockchafer is a large beetle that
navigates by light, and thus tends to fly into lamps at night.  Its larval
stage is spent underground.</item><item><label id="g21">Classes</label>  Milton's Puritan theology distinguishes
between the Elect, saints for whom salvation is guaranteed; the Redeemed,
those saved by Jesus Christ; and Reprobates or Transgressors, who are damned.
 In Blake's <title level="m">Milton</title> Jesus is a Transgressor who challenges
the stuffy Elect.</item><item><label id="g22">Contrary</label>  Contraries are mirroring entities
or principles that are mutually essential to each other though in apparent
opposition: justice and mercy, innocence and experience, etc.  See also <ref target="g84">negation</ref>.</item><item><label id="g23">Converse/conversation</label>  Like most people in his
day, Blake used the word "conversation" to include all kinds of interactions,
especially intimate ones, between individuals.  In law, "criminal conversation"
was adultery, but in Blake the word is always positive in connotation.</item><item><label id="g24">Covering Cherub</label>: Blake's term for dangerous
false versions of the divine, especially those calling for human sacrifice.</item><item><label id="g25">Devil</label>  Blake's Devil is a satirical foil who
argues against conventional piety in <title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven
 and Hell</title>; he is not the same as <ref target="g103">Satan</ref>.</item><item><label id="g26">Dinah</label> Dinah is a form of <ref target="g37">Erin</ref>.  In Genesis 30-34
Dinah is the daughter of Jacob and Leah; her rape or seduction is deceitfully
and brutally avenged by her brothers.</item><item><label id="g27">Divided Man</label>  When fallen, Man is divided into
 the humanity, the <ref target="g33">emanation</ref>, the <ref target="g109">shadow</ref>, and the <ref target="g112">spectre</ref>.</item><item><label id="g28">Dove/Pigeon</label>  Doves and pigeons are notable among
birds in that (unlike robins) they are happy to inhabit shelters that
humans build for them.</item><item><label id="g29">Druid</label>  Druidism, the religion of pre-Christian
Britain, featured nature-worship and human sacrifice, but also had a place
for Bards.  Blake regarded Druidism as a universal proto-religion.</item><item><label id="g30">Eden</label>  Eden is a state of mind as well as a place.</item><item><label id="g31">Edom</label>  The arrival of the "dominion of Edom"
in <title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title> suggests that
hairy, primitive Esau ("Edom") will reclaim his birthright as the elder son,
of which he was defrauded by his smoother twin Jacob ("Israel"); see Genesis
27.</item><item><label id="g32">Elect</label>  See <ref target="g21">classes</ref>.</item><item><label id="g33">Emanation</label>  An emanation is a feminine counterpart
that has separated from an integrated masculine entity, as when Eve was created
out of Adam and given a will and consciousness of her own.  But this separation
is itself a stage or an aspect of a fall, as it leads to conflict between
the formerly undivided aspects.  Many of Blake's female characters have emanated
from male characters, and their relationships often resemble that between
Adam and Eve.  In <title level="m">Jerusalem</title>, where the concept of
emanations is developed most fully, both male and female emanations exist
even within the integrated beings in eternity.  See also <ref target="g112">spectre/spectrous</ref>, <ref target="g109">shadow</ref>, <ref target="g27">divided man</ref>.</item><item><label id="g34">Enitharmon</label> Enitharmon is the beautiful emanation
 of <ref target="g70">Los</ref>, the Poet, and her name is probably intended to suggest "Harmony" and
 a combination of <ref target="g116">Tharmas</ref> and <ref target="g35">Enion</ref>.  In <title level="m">Europe</title> Enitharmon
is the church, offering a religion of chastity, guilt, and retribution that
lasts eighteen hundred years.</item><item><label id="g35">Enion</label> As the emanation of <ref target="g116">Tharmas</ref>, the body,
Enion personifies bodily or maternal impulses.  See also <ref target="g34">Enitharmon</ref>.</item><item><label id="g36">Eno</label> Eno, an anagram of "eon," is an "ancient
mother" who represents the seven thousand years of human history in the fallen
world.  See also <ref target="g37">Erin</ref>.</item><item><label id="g37">Erin</label> Erin is Ireland.  Her forms include the
maiden harp, a traditional symbol of Ireland and its arts (a harp incorporating the
form of a woman/fish/bird), the rape victim Dinah of Genesis 30-34, and the
"old woman," or Shan van vocht, traditional personification of Ireland in
tribulation.</item><item><label id="g38">Eternal Great Humanity Divine</label> The Eternal Great
 Humanity Divine is Jesus as perceived by the <ref target="g61">imagination</ref>, all humanity in
one man.</item><item><label id="g39">Eternals</label>  See <ref target="g47">Four Zoas</ref>.</item><item><label id="g40">Eternity</label> For Blake (and Milton), eternity was
not simply an infinite amount of time but rather the absence of sequential
time—from an eternal perspective, all events are simultaneous and all space
is the same place.  The vertigo that one experiences when reading Blake's
prophecies subsides when one recognizes that they offer something like an
eternal perspective.</item><item><label id="g41">Experience</label>  See <ref target="g62">innocence
and experience</ref>.</item><item><label id="g42">Female Will</label>  See <ref target="g135">will</ref>.</item><item><label id="g43">Fiber</label>  Blake knew that nerve cells were fibers,
and because the sensations of the body are conducted by fibers, bodily existence
has an essentially fibrous quality.  See also <ref target="g133">weave/weaving/woven</ref>, <ref target="g129">veil</ref>, <ref target="g127">Vala</ref>.</item><item><label id="g44">Flowers</label> Flowers in Blake represent transient
beauty and femininity, especially the female genitalia, but one should also
pay attention to the species of each flower he mentions or depicts, since
many of his flower images draw upon myths, folklore, poetic conventions, and/or
t<?Pub Caret?>he humanized botanical narratives in Erasmus Darwin's <title level="m">The Botanic Garden</title> (1789-91).  See <ref target="g13">Birds</ref>.</item><item><label id="g45">Fly</label>  See <ref target="g17">butterfly/moth</ref>.</item><item><label id="g46">Four/fourfold</label>  Blake adapted the mystical habit
of thinking in terms of sets of four that correspond to compass points, seasons,
humors, bodily organs, and so forth.</item><item><label id="g47">Four Zoas</label>  Revelation 4 describes four "zoa,"
Greek for living creatures or beasts; Blake appropriated the term for his
 fourfold division of the aspects of humanity.  The four are <ref target="g70">Los</ref>/<ref target="g126">Urthona</ref> (imagination),
 <ref target="g125">Urizen</ref> (intellect), <ref target="g71">Luvah</ref>/<ref target="g90">Orc</ref> (passion), and <ref target="g116">Tharmas</ref> (instinct).</item><item><label id="g48">Generation</label> Generation is the cycle of birth
and death through which living things survive in the fallen world.</item><item><label id="g49">Genius</label> Genius once meant a personifying or epitomizing
spiritual being rather than a brilliant person.  See <ref target="g95">Poetic
Genius</ref>.</item><item><label id="g50">Globe</label> Objects such as the earth or the human
heart, viewed from ordinary (fallen) perspectives, appear to be globes, folded
in on themselves rather than infinite.  See also <ref target="g131">vortex</ref>.</item><item><label id="g51">Gold</label> As a literal metallic substance, especially as coins, gold is usually represented by Blake as one of the roots of evil, but he used "shell gold" and gold leaf in his art and in general goldenness is a positive attribute when not in the form of guineas.</item><item><label id="g52">Golgonooza</label> Golgonooza is a city representing
 the human body as seen by the <ref target="g61">imagination</ref>.</item><item><label id="g53">Greeks/Romans</label> Blake admired the work of many individual Greek and Roman authors, especially Ovid, and, though he suggested that much of it was copied from older originals, Greek and Roman art.  But he saw Greek and Roman culture as a whole as being poisoned by militarism, materialism, slavery and sexual aggression.</item><item><label id="g54">Har</label>  In two early poems, Har and Heva are an
aged Adam and Eve in a (neo)classical garden world; in <title level="m">The
Book of Thel</title>, the vales of Har seem to be a special version of Arcadia,
traditionally a land of pastoral simplicity populated by amorous idle shepherds.</item><item><label id="g55">Harrow</label>  In agriculture, the harrow breaks up
 the earth turned over by the plow.  The harrow is the tool of <ref target="g92">Palamabron</ref>.
 The roller follows the harrow.</item><item><label id="g56">Harvest</label> The Harvest is the culmination of Blake's
agricultural master-metaphor, un-creating the created world at the end of time; it
 includes the <ref target="g67">Last Judgment</ref>.</item><item><label id="g57">Hayley</label>  William Hayley was a famous, successful
and shallow poet who patronized Blake, setting him up in a cottage at Hayley's
seaside country estate at Felpham.  Blake included the intellectual and spiritual
struggle with Hayley in his epic <title level="m">Milton</title>, in which
Hayley appeared as <ref target="g103">Satan.</ref></item><item><label id="g58">Hell</label> Blake's Hell is mostly a state of mind.  As Dante reported in <title level="m">Inferno</title>, a mighty earthquake accompanied the Harrowing of Hell.</item><item><label id="g59">Heva</label>  See <ref target="g54">Har</ref>.</item><item><label id="g60">Holy Thursday</label> Holy Thursday is not the Thursday before Easter (which is called Maundy Thursday in England), but rather Ascension Day, the sixth Thursday after Easter.  In Blake's adult lifetime there was a procession each year on a late spring Thursday (not actually Holy Thursday) in which all the charity-school children of London were marched in variously colored uniforms from their schools to a church, usually St. Paul's Cathedral, where they heard sermons about how lucky they were, and sang thanks to God, King, and Country.</item><item><label id="g61">Imagination</label> Imagination is the faculty that
perceives the divine, even is the divine.  See <ref target="g70">Los</ref>, <ref target="g38">Eternal Great Humanity Divine</ref>.</item><item><label id="g62">Innocence and Experience</label> Innocence and Experience
 are <ref target="g22">contrary</ref> states, ways of seeing and dwelling in the world.  Individuals
in Innocence are sustained by confidence in the redemptive presence of the
divine, perceived as both sympathetically human (often like a loving parent)
and somehow nearby, though they may also be aware of the darker aspects of
life.  Those in Experience are profoundly conscious of the limitations of
fallen life and its sorrows; for them the divine may seem inhuman, inscrutable,
impossibly distant, and cruel, though experienced visionaries, like the Bard,
may be indignantly or transcendently aware of the infinite and eternal.</item><item><label id="g63">Jealousy</label>  Jealousy is a fearful reaction of
 the <ref target="g104">selfhood</ref>; Blake rejected the "jealous God" of Exodus 20.</item><item><label id="g64">Jerusalem</label> Jerusalem is the emanation of the
 giant <ref target="g4">Albion</ref>, though she is also the city of the same name and has an assortment
of symbolic attributes and associations.  She is Blake's true church, the
"Divine Vision," and Liberty itself.  See <ref target="g34">Enitharmon</ref>.</item><item><label id="g65">Joseph of Arimathea</label> Joseph of Arimathea buried
Jesus in a tomb he built, according to legends, and later founded the first
Christian church in England (at Glastonbury); he was for Blake an archetypal
Christian and English artist.</item><item><label id="g66">Lark/skylark</label>  The lark responds ecstatically
to the morning, and unlike most birds it sings while flying.  It can fly so
high that one may hear it singing when it is not readily visible.</item><item><label id="g67">Last Judgment</label>  A last judgment definitively
separating truth from error is scheduled for the end of time, but is also
possible whenever one achieves an eternal perspective.  See <ref target="g40">eternity</ref>.</item><item><label id="g68">Leutha</label>  In <title level="m">Visions of the Daughters
of Albion</title> "Leutha's vale" seems to designate the female genitalia;
in <title level="m">Milton</title> Leutha is something like the character
Sin in Milton's <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title>, Book 2.  In <title level="m">The Four Zoas</title> she is the emanation of <ref target="g16">Bromion</ref>, and as sin
or sexual guilt she is associated with several other characters.</item><item><label id="g69">Limits</label> Limits might suggest impediments to reaching
the eternal and infinite, but in Blake the word itself usually refers to a
merciful limit upon various kinds of falling, as in the Limits of Opacity
(blindness) and Contraction.</item><item><label id="g70">Los</label> Los is one of the Eternals or Four Zoas,
the imagination, and his work as a blacksmith is to form poetry with creative
beating.  He is the temporal manifestation of Urthona, his emanation is Enitharmon,
and as the spirit of revolution he is the father of Luvah/Orc, passion and
revolutionary energy respectively.</item><item><label id="g71">Luvah</label> Luvah suggests "lover," and in <title level="m">The Book of Thel</title> and elsewhere in Blake he is an amorous
Christ-like figure, sometimes associated with the sun, but in his most ardent
 form he is <ref target="g90">Orc</ref>.  He is the third of the Four Zoas.  See also <ref target="g70">Los</ref>.</item><item><label id="g72">Lyca</label> Lyca suggests "wolf-girl," perhaps reflecting
her sojourn among wild animals.</item><item><label id="g73">Marygold</label>  The marigold grows new flowers when
old ones are plucked, and in poetry it is associated with renewable virginity.</item><item><label id="g74">Memory</label>  See <ref target="g78">Mnemosyne</ref>.</item><item><label id="g75">Mill/Miller</label>  A grinding mill processes the fruit
of the plow and other agricultural tools; it is also a complex but dead mechanism,
and became Blake's figure for Newton's materialist model of the universe.
 The Miller not only grinds but also buys and sells the produce of the Plowman.</item><item><label id="g76">Milton, John (1608-1674)</label> Milton was for Blake
his most important creative predecessor, though he objected to Milton's theology—the satirical <title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title> and
the epic <title level="m">Milton</title> indicate both Blake's admiration
and his reservations.  Blake illustrated <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title>, <title level="m">Paradise Regained</title>, <title level="m">Comus</title>, <title level="j">On the Morning of Christ's Nativity,</title> and <title level="j">L'Allegro</title> and <title level="j">Il Penseroso,</title> and Blake's poetry and art in general owe
almost as much to Milton as to the Bible.</item><item><label id="g77">Mne Seraphim</label> Mne Seraphim suggests a hybrid
of the classical mother of the muses Mnemosyne and the angelic, inspirational
Seraphim of the Bible.  Thel's older sisters, the other Daughters of Mne Seraphim,
are active shepherdesses like the Heliades of classical myth, who tend the
flocks of Helios, the sun.  See also <ref target="g71">Luvah</ref>, <ref target="g79">Mnetha</ref>.</item><item><label id="g78">Mnemosyne</label>  Mnemosyne or Memory was the mother
of the Greek Muses, who inspired poetry inferior to imaginative, prophetic
poetry like that of the Bible.</item><item><label id="g79">Mnetha</label> Mnetha, whose name evokes both Mnemosyne
and a scrambled Athena, the Greek goddess of learning and warfare, sustains
the degenerate Har and Heva in their neoclassical Eden.</item><item><label id="g80">Moth</label>  See <ref target="g17">butterfly/moth</ref>.</item><item><label id="g81">Mundane Egg/Shell</label>  The material world and its
universe constitute the mundane egg; the mundane shell is the sky.  See <ref target="g131">vortex</ref>, <ref target="g50">globe</ref>.</item><item><label id="g82">Nameless Shadowy Female</label> The Nameless Shadowy
 Female is a daughter of <ref target="g126">Urthona</ref> and consort of <ref target="g90">Orc</ref>; she is a fallen <ref target="g83">Mother Nature</ref>, somewhat like <ref target="g127">Vala</ref>.</item><item><label id="g83">Nature</label> Nature is an illusory projection of the
 fallen <ref target="g106">senses</ref> for Blake; individuals perceive the connection of nature with
themselves and with the divine through the imagination.</item><item><label id="g84">Negation</label> A negation is the absence of a positive
principle, as cruelty is the negation of mercy; justice, by contrast, is the
 <ref target="g22">contrary</ref> of mercy.  </item><item><label id="g85">Newton, Isaac (1642-1727)</label> Newton was not just
a mathematician and scientist, but was also important as a philosopher; Blake
charged him with narrow-minded mechanistic materialism.</item><item><label id="g86">Nobodaddy</label> The silliest-sounding of Blake's gods,
Nobodaddy is a comical reduction of imaginary, abstract, paternal sky-gods
on the model of Zeus, Jupiter and other scary and punitive God-the-Fathers.</item><item><label id="g87">Of</label> As a word that occurs in many of Blake's
titles and other critical phrases, "of" should be considered carefully—does it mean "pertaining to," "composed of," "composed by," "derived from,"
"owned by," "based on," "characterized by," a combination of these, or something
else?</item><item><label id="g88">Ololon</label> Ololon, whose name suggests "all-alone,"
 "ululation," or "alleluia," is <ref target="g76">Milton</ref>'s "Sixfold Emanation" (his three wives
and three daughters); also, a river, the river-dwellers, a mountain range,
and a lonely twelve-year-old girl.</item><item><label id="g89">Oothoon</label> In <title level="m">Visions of the Daughters
of Albion</title>, Oothoon is "the soft soul of America," and in Blake's later
works she plays various roles as a woman frustrated in love.  Her name evokes
James Macpherson's Ossianic heroine, Oithona, who fought back after being
raped.  See also <ref target="g26">Dinah</ref>.</item><item><label id="g90">Orc</label> Orc in Blake embodies revolutionary energy,
 an aspect of <ref target="g71">Luvah</ref> or passion.  The so-called "Orc Cycle" in which rebel and
tyrant eternally overthrow each other is not really Blakean.  Outside of Blake an
orca or orc is a killer whale or, on land, a humanoid monster.</item><item><label id="g91">Ox</label>  The powerful patient masculine (if neutered)
ox is the antithesis of tiny, aggressive "Jenny" wren.  When they were too
old for labor, oxen were often tortured for entertainment and to tenderize
their work-toughened muscle tissue so it could be eaten.</item><item><label id="g92">Palamabron</label> Palamabron is the son of <ref target="g34">Enitharmon</ref>
  and <ref target="g70">Los</ref>.  Like his brother <ref target="g101">Rintrah</ref> he emerges in response to oppression, but
he is "mild &amp; piteous" rather than loud and angry, and is distinguished
as well from Bromion and Theotormon.  In <title level="m">Milton</title>,
  Palamabron struggles with the <ref target="g75">Miller</ref>/<ref target="g103">Satan</ref>.  His tool is the <ref target="g55">harrow</ref>.</item><item><label id="g93">Piper</label>  The shepherd-poet of Arcadia traditionally
whiles away his days playing a homemade panpipe and making up songs of love,
loss, and the natural world.</item><item><label id="g94">Plow/Plowman</label>  A Plowman does the assigned masculine
work of the fallen world, as specified in Genesis 3; women (the "distaff"
 side) <ref target="g133">weave</ref> or spin.  Blake thought of engraving as a kind of plowing and
himself as Chaucer's Plowman, but in his poetry plowing can also be a metaphor
for the disruptive aspects of revolution or even the processes of mutability.
 Various characters use plows, including <ref target="g125">Urizen</ref>, <ref target="g70">Los</ref>, <ref target="g101">Rintrah</ref>, and others.
 In Isaiah 2:4, the destructive alternative to the plow is the sword.  See
also <ref target="g55">harrow</ref> and <ref target="g75">mill/Miller</ref>.</item><item><label id="g95">Poetic Genius</label> The Poetic Genius is Blake's term
 for the ultimate <ref target="g61">imaginative</ref> entity, at once God and the "true Man."  See
also <ref target="g49">genius</ref>.</item><item><label id="g96">Polypus</label> A polypus is a cuttlefish, octopus or tumor, with additional 
characteristics in Blake's work suggesting a jellyfish, squid, or sponge; it usually represents vegetative institutions such as religions and governments.</item><item><label id="g97">Prophecy</label> A prophecy is a visionary account of
reality, future, past, and present, not a prediction.  See <ref target="g61">Imagination</ref>.</item><item><label id="g98">Rahab</label>  Blake's Rahab, who has the name of both
a (usually redeemed) harlot and an allegorical dragon of Empire in the Bible,
represents false Religion, hid in War.</item><item><label id="g99">Ratio</label>  Blake punned on "ratio," in the modern
sense, meaning "fraction," and the word as used in older philosophy, meaning
"reason," which in Blake's terms apprehends only a fraction of reality.</item><item><label id="g100">Redeemed/Reprobate</label>  See <ref target="g21">classes</ref>.</item><item><label id="g101">Rintrah</label> Rintrah appears first in <title level="m">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>, personifying revolutionary wrath.  Later
books represent him as the son of Los and Enitharmon and group him with Bromion,
Palamabron, and Theotormon, each of whom represents a different response to
oppression/repression.</item><item><label id="g102">Romans</label> See <ref target="g53">Greeks</ref>.</item><item><label id="g103">Satan</label> Satan is Error, the accuser of sin, who
 blinds the mind to the divine.  He is not the same as the <ref target="g25">Devil</ref>, a satiric
character.  See also <ref target="g57">Hayley</ref>.</item><item><label id="g104">Selfhood</label> The selfhood is the perception of oneself
as being essentially separate from the divine and from other beings, leading
to self-centeredness and selfishness.  Blake probably found the concept in
 the writings of <ref target="g14">Boehme</ref>.  See also <ref target="g112">spectre/spectrous</ref>.</item><item><label id="g105">Self-Annihilation</label> Self-annihilation is abandonment
of the selfhood, which may seem like suicide from erroneous perspectives.</item><item><label id="g106">Sense/Senses</label> The fallen senses are the narrow inlets through which we dimply perceive the infinite—their limitations make us believe that we inhabit a material body.</item><item><label id="g107">Sexes</label> Sexes are a consequence of the Fall.
 See also <ref target="g33">emanation</ref>, <ref target="g12">Beulah</ref>.</item><item><label id="g108">Seraphim</label> The seraphim are an order of angels
who inspire prophecy.  See also <ref target="g77">Mne Seraphim</ref>.</item><item><label id="g109">Shadow</label> The shadow is the aspect of the divided
man that results when desire is repressed.</item><item><label id="g110">Shepherd</label>  In the Golden Age shepherds lived
without the comforts and commodities (and compromises) of civilization; Blake's
good shepherds are often typologically related to Jesus; a shepherd has it
easier than a Plowman.  See also <ref target="g93">Piper</ref>.</item><item><label id="g111">Sin</label> Sin is a form of erroneous thinking rather
than acting for Blake, and sin and disease are closely related, as if all
diseases are manifestations of misplaced guilt about sin.</item><item><label id="g112">Spectre/Spectrous</label>  The <ref target="g104">selfhood</ref> of the divided
man generates the Spectre, a parodic version of the self characterized by
self-defensive rationalization, especially in opposition to an emanation.</item><item><label id="g113">Spinning</label>  See <ref target="g133">weave/weaving/woven</ref>.</item><item><label id="g114">States</label> States are stages of error or partial
 consciousness associated with particular times in one's life, such as <ref target="g62">Innocence</ref>
and Experience.  States persist but apply only temporarily to any given individual.
 See also <ref target="g21">classes</ref>.</item><item><label id="g115">Swedenborg, Emanuel (1688-1772)</label> Swedenborg
was a scientist, mining engineer, and mystical philosopher.  Blake briefly
joined and then repudiated a Swedenborgian alternative church as a young man,
but his thought and writings were strongly influenced by Swedenborg's writings
even after he left the New Church.  See also <ref target="g14">Boehme</ref>.</item><item><label id="g116">Tharmas</label> Tharmas is the self governed by instinct,
 and one of the <ref target="g47">Four Zoas</ref>.</item><item><label id="g117">Thel</label> "Thel" is often glossed as an obscure reference
to a Greek root meaning "will" or "wish," but it is more likely that this
name was suggested to Blake by the title of a controversial book by Martin Madan, <title level="m">Thelyphthora</title> (1780),
which means "destruction of the female," in which case the name, if it means anything, means "female."</item><item><label id="g118">Theotormon</label> Theotormon suggests "god-tormented";
the autobiographical narrative of a mercenary who fought half-heartedly to
suppress a slave revolt may have inspired his character in <title level="m">Visions
of the Daughters of Albion</title>.  In later books Theotormon is grouped
with Rintrah, Palamabron, and Bromion.</item><item><label id="g119">Tiriel</label> Tiriel is the son of Har and Heva in
Blake's <title level="m">Tiriel</title>.</item><item><label id="g120">Tirzah</label> Tirzah figures in a late addition to <title level="m">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title> as the "mother of [the
speaker's] Mortal part"; she is more closely related to the sexual torturer
Tirzah in <title level="m">The Four Zoas</title>, <title level="m">Milton</title>,
and <title level="m">Jerusalem</title> than to a woman and a city of the same
name in the Bible.  Blake may have chosen the name because it sounds Biblical
and yet suggests "tears" and "teaser."  See also <ref target="g133">weave/weaving/woven</ref>.</item><item><label id="g121">Transgressors</label>  See <ref target="g21">classes</ref>.</item><item><label id="g122">Tyburn</label> Tyburn was the site for public hangings
in London throughout most of the eighteenth century.  Blake saw the "Tyburn
Procession" of doomed men and women as a vestige of Druid ceremonies of human
sacrifice.  Tyburn was rarely used after 1780, but executions continued at
a somewhat reduced rate elsewhere.</item><item><label id="g123">Tyger</label>  In the eighteenth century tigers epitomized
bloodthirstiness.</item><item><label id="g124">Ulro</label> Ulro is the dreariest form of the fallen
material world, where the happiness of Beulah can only be glimpsed in dreams
and visions.</item><item><label id="g125">Urizen</label> Urizen is one of the Eternals or <ref target="g47">Four Zoas</ref>; he is associated with the intellect and with various forms of rationalism,
literalism, and materialism.  Urizen is usually tyrannical or at least wants
to be so, but he is often weak and pathetic, and occasionally heroic.  The
name suggests the Greek god of the heavens, Uranus, and a pun on "Your Reason"
and "Horizon," which is  the limit on perception imposed in this world by
Your Reason.  Not all the old men with beards in Blake are Urizen, and Urizen
is not always the bad guy.</item><item><label id="g126">Urthona</label> Urthona is the original manifestation
 of <ref target="g70">Los</ref>, one of the <ref target="g47">Four Zoas</ref>.  The name suggests "earth-owner," and like Los
(and Hephaestus/Vulcan) he is a blacksmith, associated with the Imagination;
 he forges the <ref target="g94">plow</ref>, making him an artificer if not an artist.</item><item><label id="g127">Vala</label> Vala is <ref target="g83">Nature</ref>, and the emanation of <ref target="g71">Luvah</ref>.
 The name is like that of a Scandinavian earth-spirit, but punningly suggests
both "vale" and "veil," associating her with both the natural world and seductively
coy beauty.  See also <ref target="g129">veil</ref>, <ref target="g133">weave/weaving/woven</ref>.</item><item><label id="g128">Vegetable/vegetative</label> Vegetable or vegetative
is Blake's term for the state of ordinary material being, slow growing and
merely temporal and temporary.  See also <ref target="g96">Polypus</ref>.</item><item><label id="g129">Veil</label> In Blake the veil is typologically related
to the temple veil between the holy of holies and the worshippers, traditionally
rent at the moment of Jesus' death on the cross.  Veils are also associated
with coyness, blindness, selfishness, self-enclosure, the body, and the hymen.
 See also <ref target="g127">Vala</ref>, <ref target="g133">weave/weaving/woven</ref>.</item><item><label id="g130">Vision</label> Vision is a term encompassing ordinary
"single vision," mere optical reality in sequential time, and higher forms
that perceive things prophetically, metaphorically, imaginatively, and eternally.</item><item><label id="g131">Vortex</label>  The philosopher Rene Descartes (1596-1650)
describes a vortex as a whirling object appearing as a sun or star in space,
throwing off light centrifugally as it spins.  A vortex can also be a whirlpool
or whirlwind, and thus can suck things beyond itself to another dimension.
 For Blake, the vortex was a way of explaining how a "Wild Flower" can open
up to be "a Heaven" (E 490).  Everything has its own vortex and appearance
as one approaches it; as one passes through, it unfolds progressively on the
other side like a globe or a sky or a man.  In <title level="m">The Four Zoas</title> Urizen
constructs a mechanistic heaven of Cartesian vortices.</item><item><label id="g132">War</label>  In this world human energies are perversely
 consumed in physical warfare, but in <ref target="g40">Eternity</ref> warfare is an intellectual and
creative struggle.</item><item><label id="g133">Weave/weaving/woven</label>  The traditional work of
Eve in the fallen world is spinning or weaving, as opposed to Adam's work,
plowing or digging (see <ref target="g94">plow/Plowman</ref>).  Blake often
represents the material body as having been woven; <title level="m">Auguries
of Innocence</title> says it is woven of alternating threads of joy and woe.  See also <ref target="g43">fiber</ref>.</item><item><label id="g134">Wheels</label>  Most of the many wheels in Blake are
associated at some level with the gears of a clockwork, suggesting a mechanism
like an orrery, but some are charged with other references, such as the eyed
 wheels described in Ezekiel's account of the creatures Blake called the <ref target="g47">Four Zoas</ref>, or with the spinning wheels of <ref target="g34">Enitharmon</ref> (see <ref target="g133">weave/weaving/woven</ref>).</item><item><label id="g135">Will</label>  The will is the impulse of the <ref target="g104">selfhood</ref>.
 The female will is the impulse to self-protection and resistance to reintegration
of the emanated feminine aspect.  See <ref target="g33">emanation</ref>.</item><item><label id="g136">Worm</label>  Anything from a caterpillar to a maggot,
a cankerworm or an earthworm; some of Blake's characters refer to Man as a
worm of sixty winters or of seventy inches.</item><item><label id="g137">Wren</label>  See <ref target="g91">ox</ref>.</item><item><label id="g138">Zoa</label>  See <ref target="g47">Four Zoas</ref>.</item></list></div2></div1></body></text></tei.2><?Pub *0000037185?>