<exhibit id="biblicalillustrations" title="William Blake's Biblical Illustrations"
    article="biblicalillustrations.exhibit.html" composition_date_string="March 2021">

    <image dbi="BUT474" id="1">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">Gallery II: [by Jennifer Michael]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Christ in the Carpenter's Shop</p></title>
        <caption>[caption]</caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="BUT490" id="2">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Gallery III: [by Naomi Billingsley]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The Hymn of Christ and the Apostles (c. 1805). Watercolor, 37.7 x 32.2 cm. Collection of Robert N. Essick.</p></title>

        <caption>The subject of this watercolor is taken from a verse that appears in the Gospels of Matthew and Mark. At the end of their accounts of the Last Supper (a subject Blake depicts in a <a href="http://www.blakearchive.org/copy/biblicaltemperas?descId=but424.1.pt.01" target="_blank">tempera painting</a> for Butts), they state of Jesus and his disciples: “And when they had sung an hymn, they went out into the mount of Olives” (Matthew 26:30, Mark 14:26).<br></br><br></br>

        This fleeting reference to the singing of a hymn is a highly unusual subject in art. I have not identified any precedents of this as a standalone subject, but it does appear in composite images of the events leading to Jesus’s death. The very choice of subject here is innovative and could reflect the interests of both artist and patron.<br></br><br></br>

        As Mary Lynn Johnson has discussed, Butts’s father, Thomas Butts, Sr., had compiled the Methodist hymnbook Harmonia-Sacra (c. 1753), making the subject of Jesus and his disciples singing a hymn appropriate for the patron (“Newfound Particulars” n2). Blake himself may have been exposed to the strong Moravian culture of hymn singing by his mother (see Davies and Schuchard). The subject probably also appealed to the artist as one that places Jesus and his disciples in an act of creative expression.<br></br><br></br>

        The references in Matthew and Mark imply that the hymn was sung in the room where the Last Supper took place, and then Jesus and his disciples went to the Mount of Olives. Blake plays with this chronology, depicting the event taking place outside—presumably on the Mount of Olives. While the Bible has this as a private moment shared by Jesus and his disciples, Blake’s relocation of the act makes it public.<br></br><br></br>

        As Johnson has discussed, Blake’s company of disciples is more inclusive than the traditional title The Hymn of Christ and the Apostles suggests. The apostles were the twelve male principal disciples of Jesus, but Blake’s group includes two women, perhaps Martha and Mary of Bethany (“Blake’s Mary and Martha” 100-01). The biblical text allows for the presence of the women, stating that the twelve were at the Last Supper, but not explicitly stating that no others were present.<br></br><br></br>

        Jesus is seen here as the center of a creative community. Alighting on this subject that only fleetingly appears in the Bible, Blake finds a fitting subject for the conclusion of Jesus’s public ministry.
        </caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="Memorandum" id="3">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: [by Sarah Jones]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Memorandum of Job agreement</p></title>
        <caption>[caption]
        </caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="Yaleproof" id="4">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: [by Sarah Jones]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Yale proof</p></title>
        <caption>[caption]
        </caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="BMproof" id="5">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:orange">Gallery IV: [by Sarah Jones]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">BM proof</p></title>
        <caption>[caption]
        </caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="SefiroticTree" id="6">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:turquoise">Gallery V: [by Sheila Spector]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;"><i>Sefirotic</i> Tree</p></title>
        <caption>[caption]
        </caption>
    </image>

    <image dbi="Ginsburg" id="7">
        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:turquoise">Gallery V: [by Sheila Spector]</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Ginsberg, <i>Kabbalah</i></p></title>
        <caption>[caption]
        </caption>
    </image>

</exhibit>
