<tei.2 n="biography"><teiheader><filedesc><titlestmt><title>Biography</title></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Carolina Digital Library and Archives</publisher><pubplace>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</pubplace><availability><p>Available from: The William Blake Archive</p><p>URL: http://www.blakearchive.org</p></availability><date>©2003-2010</date></publicationstmt><sourcedesc><p>HTML files developed for the William Blake Archive c. 1998.  XML migration 2006.</p></sourcedesc></filedesc></teiheader><text><front><titlepage><doctitle><titlepart><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">William Blake </name><date value="1757-1827">(1757-1827)</date></titlepart></doctitle></titlepage></front><body><div1 type="section" id="d1"><head>Youth and Apprenticeship, 
		  <date>1757-1778</date></head><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">William Blake </name><figure entity="K.35.WD.100" id="K.35.WD.100"><head><title>Self-Portrait of William Blake</title></head><figdesc>Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1802. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> was born in London on 28 November 1757 and was christened on 11 December in St. James’s Church. His mother, born Catherine Wright, was married twice. Evidence has recently emerged that she and her first husband, a hosier named Thomas Armitage, were members of the Moravian Church (Davies and Schuchard), and some readers have detected echoes of Moravian hymns in Blake’s poems. After Armitage died, Catherine left the Moravians and married James Blake, also a hosier. The Blakes kept a shop at <address><addrline>28 Broad Street</addrline></address> and were in their mid-thirties when 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">William </name> arrived. Of his
		brothers and sisters, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert </name><date value="1762-1787">(1762-87)</date> was 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> favorite.
		His eldest brother, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, James">James </name><date value="1753-1827">(1753-1827)</date>, and a sister, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">Catherine </name><date value="1764-1841">(1764-1841)</date>, also figured prominently in
		his later life. 
		</p><p>As a child, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake </name> viewed the world
		  in the light of what 
		  <name type="person" reg="Wordsworth, William">Wordsworth, </name>in his
		  
		<title level="a">Ode: Intimations of Immortality</title>, would later
		call a “visionary gleam.” When he was about nine, he told his
		parents he had seen “a tree filled with angels” on one of his
		walks; he later reported a similar vision of “angelic figures
		walking” in a field among workers as they gathered in the hay 
		<bibl>(Gilchrist 1: 7)</bibl>. Unlike the child in 
		<name type="person" reg="Wordsworth, William">Wordsworth’s </name>
		poem, however, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake </name> never outgrew
		these visions. He was past fifty when he described seeing the rising sun as
		“an Innumerable company of the Heavenly host crying Holy Holy Holy is the
		Lord God Almighty” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 566)</bibl>.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> artistic
		  ability also became evident while he was still a child. At age ten he was
		  enrolled in 
		  <name type="person" reg="Pars, Henry">Henry Pars’s </name>
		  drawing school, where he learned to sketch the human figure by copying from
		  plaster casts of ancient statues. His father encouraged his interest and even
		  bought him some casts of his own. The influence of his early exposure to Greek
		  and Roman sculpture can be seen in 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> later
		  work. The Farnese Hercules, for example, is the model for the figure of Giant
		  Despair in 
		<title level="a">Christian and Hopeful Escape from Doubting
		  Castle</title>,  one of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		illustrations to 
		<name type="person" reg="Bunyan, John">Bunyan’s </name><title level="m">Pilgrim’s Progress </title><date value="1824-1827">(1824-27)</date>. In his last illuminated work, 
		<title level="m">Laocoön </title><date value="1826-1827" certainty="approx">(c. 1826-27)</date>, 
		<figure entity="laocoon.B.P1.100"><head><title>Laocoön</title>,  copy B</head><figdesc>Engraving, c. 1826-27. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> he surrounds a well-known classical sculpture with his own
		commentary on art, religion, and commerce.</p><p>Besides plaster casts, the young 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake </name> also began to
		  collect inexpensive prints from shops and auctions. His taste ran to 
		  <name type="person" reg="Raphael">Raphael, </name><name type="person" reg="Michelangelo">Michelangelo, </name><name type="person" reg="Romano, Giulio">Giulio Romano, </name><name type="person" reg="Durer, Albrecht">Albrecht Dürer, </name>and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Heemskerck, Maerten">Maerten Heemskerck,
			 </name>artists whose work was not widely appreciated at the time. He never
		  wavered in his conviction that they were superior to the more fashionable
		  painters of the Venetian and Flemish schools. In the catalogue for an
		  exhibition of his own work in 
		  <date value="1809">1809</date>, he accuses artists “who endeavour
		  to raise up a style against 
		  <name type="person" reg="Raphael">Rafael, </name><name type="person" reg="Michelangelo">Mich. Angelo, </name>and the
		  Antique” of attempting to destroy art  
		  <bibl>(Erdman 538)</bibl>.</p><p>In 
		  <date value="1772">1772</date>, having left 
		  <name type="person" reg="Pars, Henry">Pars’s </name> school, the
		  fourteen-year-old 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake </name> began his
		  apprenticeship under 
		  <name type="person" reg="Basire, James">James Basire, </name>engraver
		  to the 
		  <name type="organization" reg="Society of Antiquaries, The">Society of
			 Antiquaries </name> and the 
		  <name type="organization" reg="Royal Society, The">Royal Society.
			 </name><name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire </name> was best known
		  for his simple line engravings—a style many of his contemporaries
		  considered outdated, but one that fit well with 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		  preference for the firm outlines of artists like 
		  <name type="person" reg="Durer, Albrecht">Albrecht Dürer</name>.
		  <name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire’s </name> usual
		  subjects were antiquities and monuments, which he reproduced with austere
		  precision; although he occasionally took on higher-profile projects, such as 
		  <name type="person" reg="West, Benjamin">Benjamin West’s </name><title level="m">Pylades and Orestes</title>, these were the exception
		rather than the rule. Prominent artists like 
		<name type="person" reg="West, Benjamin">West </name> tended to prefer
		the services of 
		<name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire’s </name> rivals, 
		<name type="person" reg="Woollett, William">William Woollett </name> (who
		engraved 
		<name type="person" reg="West, Benjamin">West’s </name> best-known
		painting, 
		<title level="m">The Death of General Wolfe)</title> and 
		<name type="person" reg="Strange, Robert">Robert Strange. </name>Many
		years later, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>remembering the
		slight to his employer, would call these two men “heavy lumps of Cunning
		&amp; Ignorance” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 573)</bibl>.</p><p>In 
		  <name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire’s </name> shop at 
		<address><addrline>31 Great Queen Street</addrline></address> in 
		<name type="place">London, </name><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake </name> learned the craft
		of copy engraving as it was practiced in 
		<name type="place">England </name> at the end of the 
		<date certainty="approx">eighteenth century</date>. The standard method
		of preparing a copperplate for etching or engraving was time-consuming and
		labor-intensive. The original large sheet of copper had to be cut into
		appropriate sizes and the edges beveled to facilitate cleaning the ink off the
		plate and to prevent it from tearing the paper. The plate also had to be
		squared and its corners rounded, because the pressure of the printing press
		would leave an impression of the plate’s edges in the paper. Next, the
		surface had to be polished, cleaned, and covered with an acid-resistant film,
		or “ground,” which was then darkened with soot to contrast with the
		copper. Onto this ground the design was then transferred and traced with a
		needle to expose the plate’s surface to acid, which bit the design into
		the copper 
		<bibl>(Viscomi, 
		  <title level="m">Blake </title> 48-50)</bibl>. In a shop like 
		<name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire’s </name>, most of
		the tedious preparatory work was carried out by apprentices like 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake. </name></p><p>It is difficult to know which of the works produced in 
		  <name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire’s </name> shop
		  during this period 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> himself may have
		  engraved, because engravers’ apprentices were discouraged from developing
		  their own individual styles, and their work was usually signed by the master.
		  Among the projects in which modern scholars believe 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> probably had a
		  hand were 
		  <name type="person" reg="Bryant, Jacob">Jacob Bryant’s </name><title level="m">A New System, or, an Analysis of Ancient
		  Mythology </title><date value="1774-1776">(1774-76)</date> and 
		<name type="person" reg="Gough, Richard">Richard Gough’s </name><title level="m">Sepulchral Monuments in Great Britain</title>, Part I
		(published 
		<date value="1786">1786)</date>. These books represent two
		subjects—mythology and British history—in which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> never lost
		interest.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Bryant, Jacob">Bryant</name> was an
		  antiquarian and mythographer who, like many others in the 
		  <date certainty="approx">seventeenth</date> and 
		  <date certainty="approx">eighteenth</date> centuries, attempted to
		  reconcile pagan mythology with the biblical account of history. He theorized
		  that the original monotheism of the 
		<title>Old Testament </title> had degenerated after the Flood into various
		forms of sun worship, from which all the other pagan gods and heroes descended.
		His work had a lasting influence on 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>who as late as 
		<date value="1809">1809</date> cites the authority of  
		<name type="person" reg="Bryant, Jacob">“Jacob Bryant, </name>and
		all antiquaries” in support of his claim that “The antiquities of
		every Nation under Heaven” are equally sacred 
		<bibl>(Erdman 543)</bibl>.</p><p>The plates for 
		  <name type="person" reg="Gough, Richard">Gough’s </name><title level="m">Sepulchral Monuments </title> were engraved after pencil
		sketches 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> made of the tombs
		of kings and queens in 
		<name type="place">Westminster Abbey. </name><name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire</name> is said to have
		given him that assignment in order to get him out of the shop and away from the
		dissension that was brewing among the newer apprentices 
		<bibl>(Bentley, <title level="m">Blake Records </title> 422)</bibl>. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> probably engraved a
		number of the sketches himself, including the portraits of 
		<name type="person" reg="Henry III">Henry III, </name><name type="person" reg="Eleanor of Castile">Eleanor of Castile, </name><name type="person" reg="Edward III">Edward III, </name>and 
		<name type="person" reg="Richard II">Richard II. </name><figure entity="BB.461.P4.COM.100"><head><title>Portrait of Queen Eleanor from her Monument</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake for Richard Gough, 
			 <title level="m">Sepulchral Monuments</title>, 1786. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BB.461.P12.COM.100"><head><title>Portrait of Edward III. from his Monument</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake for Richard Gough, 
			 <title level="m">Sepulchral Monuments</title>, 1786. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Eleanor of Castile">Eleanor</name> in particular
		seems to have appealed to 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		imagination, for he returned to her as a subject for the historical print 
		<title level="m">Edward &amp; Elenor</title><figure entity="ESIV.1.1B.SP.100"><head><title>Edward &amp; Elenor</title></head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> and, much later, for one of his 
		<title level="a">Visionary Heads</title>.  
		<name type="person" reg="Edward III">Edward III, </name>meanwhile,
		reappears as the protagonist of a dramatic fragment in 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> first
		volume of poetry, 
		<title level="m">Poetical Sketches </title><date value="1783">(1783)</date>.</p><p>The earliest engraving that scholars can confidently attribute to 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> reflects his
		  interest in early British history and legend. He later reworked and reprinted
		  it with the title 
		<title level="a"><name type="person" reg="Joseph of Arimathea">Joseph of
			 Arimathea</name> among the Rocks of 
		  <name type="place">Albion</name></title><figure entity="ES.I.2D.SP.100"><head><title>Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion</title>, second
			 state</head><figdesc>Engraving, first state 1773, second state c. 1820. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> and dated it 
		<date value="1773">1773</date>, the second year of his apprenticeship.
		The young 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> technique
		in the first state of this work, though competent, does not reveal much about
		him as an artist; his distinctive imagination emerges only in the way he
		combines the compositional elements. He takes the pensive, muscular figure from
		
		<name type="person" reg="Michelangelo">Michelangelo’s </name><title level="m">Crucifixion of 
		  <name type="person" reg="St. Peter">St. Peter</name></title>, but
		places him against a spare, brooding background of sea and rocky coast that
		evokes a mood reminiscent of the bleak seascapes of Anglo-Saxon verse. On the
		later state of this engraving, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> identifies the
		figure as “One of the Gothic Artists who Built the Cathedrals in what we
		call the Dark Ages” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 671)</bibl>—an allusion to the legend that 
		<name type="person" reg="Joseph of Arimathea">Joseph of Arimathea</name>
		traveled to 
		<name type="place">Britain</name> and founded 
		<name type="place">Glastonbury Abbey</name>.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d2"><head>Artist and Engraver, 
		  <date>1779-1788</date></head><p>In 
		  <date value="1779">1779</date>, at age twenty-one, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> completed his
		  seven-year apprenticeship with 
		  <name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire</name> and became a
		  journeyman copy engraver, making his living by working on projects for 
		  <name type="place">London</name> book and print publishers like 
		  <name type="person" reg="Macklin, Thomas">Thomas Macklin, </name><name type="publisher" reg="Harrison and Co.">Harrison and Co.</name>,
		  and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Joseph Johnson. </name><name type="person" reg="Macklin, Thomas">Macklin</name> would later
		  launch the 
		<title>Poets’ Gallery </title><date value="1788">(1788)</date> and the 
		<title>Macklin Bible </title><date value="1790">(1790)</date>—commercial ventures aimed, like 
		<name type="person" reg="Boydell, John">John Boydell’s </name><title><name type="person" reg="Shakespeare, William">Shakespeare</name>
		  Gallery</title>, at orchestrating a profitable combination of paintings,
		engravings, and literature. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> earliest
		separate prints were stipple engravings for 
		<name type="person" reg="Macklin, Thomas">Macklin</name> of scenes by the
		French Rococo painter 
		<name type="person" reg="Watteau, Jean-Antoine">Jean-Antoine Watteau,
		  </name>whose work was known in 
		<name type="place">England</name> primarily through engravings. 
		<figure entity="ES.XXII.2F.SP.100"><head><title>Morning Amusement</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Jean-Antoine Watteau, 1782. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="ES.XXIII.2F.SP.100"><head><title>Evening Amusement</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Jean-Antoine Watteau, 1782. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> The stipple method, with its patterns of tiny dots, was well
		suited for reproducing his paintings, which emphasized color and tone over
		line. Although he never mentions 
		<name type="person" reg="Watteau, Jean-Antoine">Watteau</name> by name, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> later expresses
		contempt for this emphasis on color among painters of the Venetian school, of
		which 
		<name type="person" reg="Watteau, Jean-Antoine">Watteau</name> was a
		direct heir.</p><p>The summer of 
		  <date value="1780">1780</date> was an uneasy time in 
		  <name type="place">England. </name>In 
		  <date>June</date>, violent anti-Catholic demonstrations, the 
		  <name type="event">Gordon Riots, </name>spread through 
		  <name type="place">London, </name>and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> may have
		  witnessed the destruction firsthand. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Gilchrist, Alexander">Alexander
			 Gilchrist</name> reports that on 
		  <date value="06-06-1780">6 June</date>, the third day of the riots, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was involuntarily
		  swept along before a large mob and watched as it stormed and burned 
		  <name type="place">Newgate Prison</name> (1: 35). Later that same
		  summer, a sketching trip with 
		  <name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Thomas Stothard</name> and
		  another friend on the 
		  <name type="place">River Medway</name> brought 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> afoul of the law
		  when the artists, mistaken for spies, were arrested for approaching too near to
		  the great naval base on the 
		  <name type="place">Medway</name> near 
		  <name type="place">Upnor Castle</name>.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Stothard</name> was a
		  versatile commercial artist and a prolific book illustrator, and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was one of
		  several engravers who helped to popularize his works during the 
		  <date certainty="approx">1780s</date>; others included 
		  <name type="person" reg="Heath, James">James Heath</name> and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Sharp, William">William Sharp. </name><title level="m">The Novelist’s Magazine</title>, published by 
		<name type="publisher" reg="Harrison and Co.">Harrison and Co.</name> in
		the 
		<date certainty="approx">early 1780s</date>, showcased 
		<name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Stothard’s </name>
		picturesque wash drawings, which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name><name type="person" reg="Heath, James">Heath, </name>and 
		<name type="person" reg="Sharp, William">Sharp</name> reproduced in a
		uniform technique that preserved the fashionable style of the originals. 
		<figure entity="BB.485.P2.COM.100"><head><title>Don Quixote</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Thomas Stothard for 			 
			 <title level="m">The Novelist's Magazine</title>, 1782. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> also engraved some
		of 
		<name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Stothard’s </name>
		illustrations for books published by 
		<name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Joseph Johnson</name>,
		including 
		<name type="person" reg="Enfield, William">William Enfield’s
		  </name><title level="m">The Speaker </title><date value="1780">(1780)</date>, 
		<figure entity="BB.453.COM.100"><head><title>Clarence’s Dream</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to Shakespeare’s 
			 <title level="m">Richard III</title>. Engraved by Blake after Thomas
			 Stothard for William Enfield, 
			 <title level="m">The Speaker</title>, 1780. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> the mathematician 
		<name type="person" reg="Bonnycastle, John">John Bonnycastle’s
		  </name><title level="m">Introduction to Mensuration </title><date value="1782">(1782)</date>, 
		<figure entity="BB.436.COM.100"><head><title>Introduction to Mensuration</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Thomas Stothard for John Bonnycastle,
			 <title level="m">An Introduction to Mensuration</title>, 1782. Second state, 1787. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<name type="person" reg="Ritson, Joseph">Joseph Ritson’s </name><title level="m">A Select Collection of English Songs </title><date value="1783">(1783)</date>.</p><p>A number of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> other
		  new friends in the 
		  <date certainty="approx">early 1780s</date> were professional or
		  amateur artists. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Flaxman, John">John Flaxman, </name>a
		  neoclassical sculptor whose illustrations of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Homer">Homer, </name><figure entity="BB.457.P1.COM.100"><head><title>Homer Invoking the Muse</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after John Flaxman for Flaxman, 
				<title level="m">The Iliad of Homer</title>, 1805. Essick
				Collection.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Aeschylus">Aeschylus, </name>and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Alighieri, Dante">Dante</name> would one day
		  spread his fame throughout 
		  <name type="place">Europe, </name>was then beginning his career as a
		  designer for 
		  <name type="person" reg="Wedgwood, Josiah">Josiah Wedgwood’s
			 </name> popular line of classically inspired pottery. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Hawkins, John">John Hawkins, </name>a
		  connoisseur, in 
		  <date value="1784">1784</date> tried unsuccessfully to raise enough
		  money to send 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> to 
		  <name type="place">Italy, </name>where he was to have completed his
		  education in drawing by studying firsthand the works of the ancient sculptors
		  and of Renaissance masters like 
		  <name type="person" reg="Michelangelo">Michelangelo</name> and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Raphael">Raphael. </name><name type="person" reg="Cumberland, George">George Cumberland</name>,
		  the author of 
		<title level="m">Thoughts on Outline </title><date value="1796">(1796)</date>, 
		<figure entity="BB.447.P6.COM.100"><head><title>Iron Age</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after George Cumberland for Cumberland, 
			 <title level="m">Thoughts on Outline</title>, 1796. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> was, like 
		<name type="person" reg="Flaxman, John">Flaxman, </name>dedicated to
		reviving the classical style. “I study your outlines,” 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> would write to him
		in 
		<date value="1799">1799</date>, “[. . .] just as if they were
		antiques” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 704)</bibl>.</p><p>At the same time that he was working on commercial engraving projects,
		  
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was also
		  preparing himself for a career as a painter. In 
		  <date value="1779">1779</date> he was admitted as a student to the 
		  <name type="organization" reg="Royal Academy of Art, The">Royal Academy
			 of Art’s </name><name type="school" reg="Royal Academy of Art's Schools of Design, The">Schools of Design</name>.
		  Founded in 
		  <date value="1769">1769</date> to promote English art and artists, the 
		  <name type="organization" reg="Royal Academy of Art, The">Royal
			 Academy</name> provided formal training and annual exhibitions. There 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> pursued his study
		  of drawing, gaining admission after a probationary period to the 
		  <name type="school" reg="Royal Academy of Art's Schools of Design, The">Schools’</name>
		  collection of plaster casts of antique sculpture. 
		  <figure entity="BUT71.1.1.PD.100"><head><title>Academy Study: A Naked Youth Seen from the Side, Perhaps
				  Robert Blake</title></head><figdesc>Black chalk, c. 1779-80. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BUT72.1.recto.PD.100"><head><title>Academy Study: Standing Male Nude Seen from
				  Behind</title></head><figdesc>Pencil, c. 1779-80. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> Even as a student, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> followed his own
		  taste in art. When the elderly 
		  <name type="person" reg="Moser, George">George Moser, </name>Keeper of
		  the 
		  <name type="organization" reg="Royal Academy of Art, The">Royal
			 Academy, </name>advised him to study 
		  <name type="person" reg="Vigee-Lebrun, Marie Louise Elisabeth">Lebrun</name> and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Rubens, Peter Paul">Rubens</name> instead of
		  the “stiff” and “unfinished” works of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Raphael">Raphael</name> and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Michelangelo">Michelangelo, </name>the young 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake balked</name>:
		  “These things that you call Finishd are not Even Begun,” he later
		  reported himself as having replied; “how can they then, be
		  Finishd?”
<bibl>(Erdman 639)</bibl>.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> not only studied
		  at the 
		  <name type="organization" reg="Royal Academy of Art, The">Royal
			 Academy</name> but exhibited his work there as well, beginning in 
		  <date value="1780">1780</date> with 
		<title level="m">The Death of Earl Goodwin</title>, 
		<figure entity="BUT60.1.1.WC.100"><head><title>The Death of Earl Goodwin</title></head><figdesc>Water color, c. 1779. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> one of a series of watercolor drawings on the early history of 
		<name type="place">England</name> that also included such subjects as 
		<title level="m">The Landing of Brutus</title>, 
		<title level="m">The Making of Magna Carta</title>, 
		<figure entity="BUT.62.WC.100"><head><title>The Making of Magna Charta</title></head><figdesc>Water color, c. 1779. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<title level="m">The Penance of Jane Shore</title>. In 
		<date value="1784">1784</date>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> exhibited a pair of
		thematically related works, 
		<title level="m">A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle and War
		  Unchaind by an Angel. Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</title>, 
		<figure entity="BUT.186.r.WD.100"><head><title>War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine
				Following</title></head><figdesc>Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1780. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> depicting the ravages of war. The following year, he exhibited
		four works: 
		<title level="m">The Bard, from Gray</title> and three drawings
		illustrating the biblical story of 
		<name type="person" reg="Joseph">Joseph</name> and his brothers, the
		latter reflecting an increasing interest in 
		<title>Old Testament</title> subjects. In all these drawings, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> adheres to the
		prevailing neoclassical style as interpreted by such contemporary artists as 
		<name type="person" reg="Barry, James">James Barry</name>.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> creative
		  activities were not confined to the visual arts during these years. The 
		  <date certainty="approx">early 1780s</date> also saw the private
		  publication of 
		<title level="m">Poetical Sketches </title><date value="1783">(1783)</date>, a collection of poems he had written
		over the previous fourteen years. These early efforts echo 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> English
		precursors from 
		<name type="person" reg="Spenser, Edmund">Spenser</name> to the 
		<date certainty="approx">eighteenth century</date> but also demonstrate
		his willingness to experiment with form and language. The series of four season
		poems that opens the volume suggests the range of influences the young poet had
		absorbed, drawing on sources as diverse as the 
		<title>Song of Solomon</title> and the northern sublime popularized by 
		<name type="person" reg="Macpherson, James">James Macpherson’s
		  </name> poems of 
		<title>Ossian</title>. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		independent views in both aesthetics and politics are evident even in his first
		book: 
		<title level="a">To the Muses</title> explicitly critiques contemporary
		verse, accusing the muses of turning their backs on poetry altogether, and the
		fragmentary historical drama 
		<title level="a">King Edward the Third</title> explores the problematic
		role of war and imperialism in English history.</p><p>The publication of 
		<title level="m">Poetical Sketches</title> was financed by 
		<name type="person" reg="Flaxman, John">Flaxman</name> and two of his
		friends, the 
		<name type="person" reg="Mathew, A. S.">Rev. A. S. Mathew</name> and his
		wife 
		<name type="person" reg="Mathew, Harriet">Harriet, </name>who hosted
		literary and artistic gatherings to which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had recently begun
		to be invited. One of those who attended frequently was 
		<name type="person" reg="Taylor, Thomas">Thomas Taylor, </name>whose
		lectures on Greek philosophy, soon to be followed by translations from 
		<name type="person" reg="Plotinus">Plotinus, </name><name type="person" reg="Proculus">Proclus, </name>and the Platonic
		dialogues, earned him the nickname 
		<name type="nickname">“the Platonist</name>.” 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> eventually became
		disillusioned with 
		<name type="group">the Mathew circle</name>; his unfinished satire 
		<title level="m">An Island in the Moon </title><date value="1784-1785" certainty="approx">(c. 1784-85)</date><figure entity="BB74.1.P8.MS.100"><head><title>An Island in the Moon</title></head><figdesc>Holograph manuscript by Blake, page 8, c. 1784. The
			 Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> is a lively sendup of their social ambitions and affectations.
		Under names like 
		<name type="character" reg="Inflammable Gass">“Inflammable
		  Gass</name>,” 
		<name type="character" reg="Sipsop the Pythagorean">“Sipsop the
		  Pythagorean</name>,” and 
		<name type="character" reg="Mrs. Nannicantipot">“Mrs.
		  Nannicantipot</name>,” 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> fellow
		guests gossip, philosophize, and show off their latest inventions, bursting
		frequently into song—and, at least once, into flame.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		  companion throughout these eventful years was 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">Catherine 
			 <name type="maiden" reg="Boucher">Boucher </name></name><date value="1762-1831">(1762-1831)</date>, whom he had married in 
		  <date value="1782">1782</date>. He had met his future wife, the
		  daughter of a market gardener, during a stay in 
		  <name type="place">Battersea. </name>Recently rejected by another
		  woman, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> told 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">Catherine</name> the story
		  of his unsuccessful courtship; she pitied him and in turn won his affection
<bibl>(Bentley, 
			 <title level="m">Blake Records</title> 517-18)</bibl>. The two were
		  married 
		  <date value="18-08-1782">18 August</date> at the 
		  <name type="place">church of 
			 <name type="person" reg="St. Mary">St. Mary</name></name> in 
		  <name type="place">Battersea</name> and moved to 
		<address><addrline>23 Green Street</addrline></address> in 
		<name type="place">London. </name>Their marriage was by all accounts
		happy; one of the few recorded exceptions occurred when 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">Catherine</name> quarreled
		with 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> beloved
		younger brother 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert, </name>and 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> insisted she kneel
		down and apologize to him 
		<bibl>(Gilchrist 1: 58-59)</bibl>.</p><p>In 
		  <date value="1784">1784</date>, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> set up a printing
		  and publishing partnership at 
		<address><addrline>27 Broad Street</addrline></address> with 
		<name type="person" reg="Parker, James">James Parker, </name>who had also
		worked as an apprentice under 
		<name type="person" reg="Basire, James">Basire. </name>The business
		apparently did not thrive. Only two prints, 
		<title level="a">Zephyrus and Flora</title><figure entity="ES.XXVI.2C.SP.100"><head><title>Zephyrus and Flora</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Thomas Stothard, 1784. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<title level="a">Calisto,</title><figure entity="ES.XXVII.2B.SP.100"><head><title>Calisto</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Thomas Stothard, 1784. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> separate plates on mythological themes engraved by 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> after 
		<name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Stothard, </name>are known to
		have been produced 
		<bibl>(Essick 141)</bibl>. The 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake-</name><name type="person" reg="Parker, James">Parker</name> partnership appears
		to have broken up by the end of 
		<date value="1785">1785</date>, and the 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name>s moved to 
		<address><addrline>28 Poland Street</addrline></address>. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> did little
		commercial engraving over the next two years, but 
		<date value="1788">1788</date> was busier, culminating in a commission
		from the 
		<name type="person" reg="Boydell, John">Boydell</name>s for 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> biggest
		commercial project of the decade: a large engraving of 
		<name type="person" reg="Hogarth, William">William Hogarth’s </name><title level="m">The Beggar’s Opera, Act III</title>. 
		<figure entity="BB.475.COM.100"><head><title>Beggar’s Opera, Act III</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after William Hogarth for 
			 <title level="m">The Original Works of William Hogarth</title>, 1790.
			 Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> The painting depicts a performance of 
		<name type="person" reg="Gay, John">John Gay’s </name> famous
		ballad opera, the story of the highwayman 
		<name type="character" reg="MacHeath">MacHeath. </name>The engraving took
		
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> nearly two years to
		complete.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d3"><head>Illuminated Printing and other Illustrated Books, 
		  <date>1789-1792</date></head><p>At the same time that he was working on these commercial projects, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was searching for
		  a better way to print and publish his own work. About 
		  <date value="1788" certainty="approx">1788</date>, he invented relief
		  etching, a process that was both more efficient and potentially more expressive
		  and autographic than traditional intaglio etching. In intaglio graphics, the
		  design must be transferred to the metal plate: either scratched lightly onto
		  the waxed surface and then deepened with an engraving tool, such as a burin, or
		  traced with a needle into an acid-resistant coating, the exposed pattern of
		  lines and dots then being bitten into the plate with acid. Blake’s
		  contemporaries usually tried to optimize quality and efficiency by combining
		  these techniques in “mixed-method” engraving. In relief etching, on
		  the other hand, the design is painted directly onto the copperplate using an
		  acid-resistant varnish. When acid is applied to the plate, the unpainted
		  surface, rather than the design itself, is eaten away, while the design is left
		  standing in relief to be inked and printed. Because the design is above rather
		  than below the surface of the plate, a relief etching also requires less
		  pressure to print than a conventional intaglio etching or engraving. The
		  printed version of a relief etching is, of course, a mirror image of the
		  original design; this means that any text to be included must be written
		  backwards. As a trained copy engraver, however, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had already had
		  an opportunity to practice this skill.</p><p>It was 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> late
		  brother 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert</name> who, according to
		  
		  <name type="person" reg="Smith, John Thomas">John Thomas Smith</name>,
		  directed 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> toward this
		  discovery. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert</name> had died in 
		  <date value="02-1787" certainty="approx">February 1787</date>; 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>who had remained
		  constantly at his bedside for two weeks and reportedly collapsed into a
		  continuous sleep for three days and nights after his death
<bibl>(Gilchrist 1: 59)</bibl>, continued to see his brother in visions. The
		  following year, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert</name> appeared to him
		  in such a vision and instructed him in a new method of printing his works
		  without “the expense of letter-press”
<bibl>(Bentley, 
			 <title level="m">Blake Records</title> 460)</bibl>. Appropriately,
		  one of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> first
		  experiments in this medium was 
		<title level="a">The Approach of Doom,</title><figure entity="ESIII.1.1.SP.100"><head><title>The Approach of Doom</title></head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching, c. 1788. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> a print based on one of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert’s </name> drawings. 
		<figure entity="BUTR2.1.1r.WD.100"><head>Robert Blake, 
			 <title level="m">The Approach of Doom</title></head><figdesc>Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1786? The British
			 Museum.</figdesc></figure> The real importance of relief etching for 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>however, was not
		economic but aesthetic: unlike other methods of printing texts and designs
		available at the end of the 
		<date certainty="approx">eighteenth century</date>, it did not separate
		invention from production. The need to keep these two activities united became
		one of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> central
		tenets as an artist.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> continued to
		  employ relief etching in his first two illuminated books, 
		<title level="m">All Religions are One</title> and 
		<title level="m">There is No Natural Religion</title> (both 
		<date value="1788" certainty="approx">c. 1788)</date>. 
		<figure entity="aro.A.P2.100"><head><title>All Religions are One</title>, copy A, plate 2 (title
			 page)</head><figdesc>Relief etching with pen and ink additions. Etched c. 1788,
			 printed 1795. The Huntington Library.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="nnr.G.P2-a2.100"><head><title>There is No Natural Religion</title>, copy G, plate a2 (title
			 page)</head><figdesc>Relief etching with rudimentary color printing. Etched c.
			 1788, printed 1794. The Pierpont Morgan Library.</figdesc></figure> His decision to present their texts in the form of aphorisms
		(or “Principles,” as he calls them in 
		<title level="m">All Religions are One</title>) may have been inspired
		partly by the English translation of 
		<name type="person" reg="Lavater, Johann Caspar">Johann Caspar
		  Lavater’s </name><title level="m">Aphorisms on Man </title><date value="1788">(1788)</date>, 
		<figure entity="BB.480.COM.100"><head><title>Aphorisms on Man</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Henry Fuseli for John Caspar Lavater, <title level="m">Aphorisms on Man</title>, 1788. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> for which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> engraved the
		frontispiece. The two tractates are part of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> lifelong
		quarrel with the philosophy of 
		<name type="person" reg="Bacon, Francis">Bacon, </name><name type="person" reg="Newton, Isaac">Newton, </name>and 
		<name type="person" reg="Locke, John">Locke. </name>Rejecting the
		rational empiricism of 
		<date value="approx">eighteenth-century</date> deism or “natural
		religion,” which looked to the material world for evidence of God’s
		existence, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> offers as an
		alternative the imaginative faculty or “Poetic Genius.”</p><p>Much better known is 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> next
		  illuminated book, 
		<title level="m">Songs of Innocence </title><date value="1789">(1789)</date>, 
		<figure entity="s-inn.B.P2-3.100"><head><title>Songs of Innocence</title>, copy B, plate 2 (title
			 page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring, 1789.
			 Rosenwald Collection, The Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure> a collection of short lyric poems and their accompanying
		designs. Deceptively simple at first reading, the 
		<title level="m">Songs</title> have affinities with 
		<date certainty="approx">eighteenth-century</date> children’s
		literature but go beyond the traditional children’s book to question some
		of the unexamined assumptions of adult society. “Every child may joy to
		hear” such songs 
		<bibl>(Erdman 7)</bibl>, but some adults in 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> audience
		might well have been uncomfortable with the social critique implicit in such
		poems as 
		<title level="a">The Chimney Sweeper, </title><title level="a">Holy Thursday,</title> or 
		<title level="a">Night.</title> The nature of illuminated printing
		allowed the 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name>s 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">(Catherine</name> assisted with
		the printing and hand coloring) to maintain control over the entire process of
		producing and marketing 
		<title level="m">Songs</title> and subsequent illuminated books.</p><p>Later in the same year 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> produced 
		<title level="m">The Book of Thel</title>, 
		<figure entity="thel.O.P1-2.100"><head><title>The Book of Thel</title>, copy O, plate 1 (title page)</head><figdesc>Relief etching with hand coloring. Etched 1789, printed c.
			 1818. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure> an illuminated poem in unrhymed lines of fourteen syllables.
		Numerous allegorical interpretations have been suggested for this story of a
		young shepherdess who receives advice from a lily, a cloud, and a clod of clay,
		only to flee in the end from a “voice of sorrow” that rises from
		“her own grave plot” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 6)</bibl>. The designs present her as a pale and slender
		figure, clothed in a wispy gown, conversing with her anthropomorphic mentors in
		a world defined by delicate watercolor washes.</p><p>A very different kind of illuminated book grew out of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		  disillusionment with 
		  <name type="person" reg="Swedenborg, Emanuel">Emanuel Swedenborg, </name>a Swedish
		  mystic in whose work he had begun to take an interest. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> read and
		  annotated at least three of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Swedenborg, Emanuel">Swedenborg’s </name> books, and
		  he and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">Catherine</name> attended a
		  meeting of the 
		  <name type="person" reg="Swedenborg, Emanuel">Swedenborg</name>ian 
		  <name type="organization" reg="New Jerusalem Church">New Jerusalem
			 Church</name> in 
		  <date value="04-1789" certainty="approx">April 1789</date>. By 
		  <date>1790</date>, however, interest had turned to opposition. 
		<title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell </title><date value="1790">(1790)</date><figure entity="mhh.I.P1.100"><head><title>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>, copy I, plate 1
			 (title page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1790,
			 printed 1827. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> apparently began as a four-page 
		<name type="person" reg="Swedenborg, Emanuel">anti-Swedenborgian</name> pamphlet 
		<bibl>(Viscomi, 
		  <title level="a">Lessons</title> 173)</bibl>, but it quickly grew into
		a full-blown satire flexible enough to accommodate a mixture of prose and
		verse, with settings spanning heaven and hell and a cast of characters that
		includes angels and devils, 
		<title>Old Testament</title> prophets, 
		<name type="person" reg="Milton, John">John Milton, </name>and 
		<name type="person" reg="Swedenborg, Emanuel">Swedenborg</name> himself. The section
		titled 
		<title level="a" type="section">Proverbs of Hell</title> contains some of
		
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> best-known
		aphorisms, such as “The road of excess leads to the palace of
		wisdom” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 35)</bibl>.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> apparently
		  intended to publish his narrative poem 
		<title level="m">Tiriel </title><date value="1789" certainty="approx">(c. 1789)</date><figure entity="BUT198.1.1.WD.100"><head><title>Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana and Cursing His
				Sons</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to Blake’s poem, 
			 <title level="m">Tiriel</title>. Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1789.
			 Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BUT198.1.4.WD.100"><head><title>Har Blessing Tiriel While Mnetha Comforts Heva</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to Blake’s poem, 
			 <title level="m">Tiriel</title>. Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1789.
			 The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> in conventional letterpress with intaglio engravings, but it
		remained in manuscript accompanied by twelve wash drawings. 
		<name type="character" reg="Tiriel">Tiriel, </name>a tyrant who curses
		his own children, has affinities with both 
		<name type="person" reg="Sophocles">Sophocles’s </name><name type="character" reg="Oedipus">Oedipus</name> and 
		<name type="person" reg="Shakespeare, William">Shakespeare’s
		  </name><name type="character" reg="King Lear">King Lear. </name>The poem’s
		echoes of Greek tragedy and the designs’ strong classical associations
		may initially strike readers as derivative, but despite its traditional
		elements, 
		<title level="m">Tiriel</title> is noteworthy as one of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> earliest
		experiments in constructing his own mythic world.</p><p>Another letterpress project that was never completed, 
		<title level="m">The French Revolution </title><date value="1791">(1791)</date>, progressed as far as the page proofs of
		the first book, printed for 
		<name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Joseph Johnson. </name>Although
		the title page announces “A Poem, in Seven Books,” only 
		<title level="a" type="book">Book the First</title> is known to exist.
		Based on the events of 
		<date value="1789">1789</date>, it mixes fact with fiction, though the
		proportion of history to myth is much higher than in later prophetic poems like
		
		<title level="m">America</title><figure entity="america.O.P2.100"><head><title>America a Prophecy</title>, copy O, plate 2 (title
			 page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1793,
			 printed 1821. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<title level="m">Europe</title>. 
		<figure entity="europe.K.P2.100"><head><title>Europe a Prophecy</title>, copy K, plate 2 (title page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1794,
			 printed 1821. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure></p><p>In addition to his own manuscripts and illuminated books, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> continued during
		  the 
		  <date certainty="approx">1790s</date> to engrave illustrations for 
		  <name type="place">London</name> booksellers, particularly 
		  <name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Joseph Johnson. </name>To the
		  third volume of 
		<title level="m">The Antiquities of Athens </title><date value="1794">(1794)</date>, 
		<figure entity="BB.500.P4.COM.100"><head><title>Battle of the Centaurs and Lapithae</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after William Pars for James Stuart and
			 Nicholas Revett, 
			 <title level="m">The Antiquities of Athens</title>, vol. 3 (1794).
			 Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Stuart, James">James Stuart</name> and 
		<name type="person" reg="Revett, Nicholas">Nicholas Revett’s
		  </name> monumental work on classical architecture, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> contributed four
		engravings after 
		<name type="person" reg="Pars, W.">W. Pars</name> of sculptures from the 
		<name type="place" reg="Temple of Theseus, The">Temple of Theseus</name><bibl>(Bentley, 
		  <title level="m"> Blake Books</title> 624)</bibl>. For 
		<name type="person" reg="Darwin, Erasmus">Erasmus Darwin’s </name>
		scientific poem 
		<title level="m">The Botanic Garden </title><date value="1791-1806">(1791-1806)</date>, he engraved designs after 
		<name type="person" reg="Fuseli, Henry">Fuseli </name><title level="a">(Fertilization of Egypt</title> and 
		<title level="a">Tornado)</title><figure entity="BB.450.P1.COM.100"><head><title>Fertilization of Egypt</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Henry Fuseli for Erasmus Darwin, 
			 <title level="m">The Botanic Garden</title>, 1791. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BUT173.1.1Fuseli.PD.100"><head>Henry Fuseli, 
			 <title level="m">Fertilization of Egypt.</title></head><figdesc>Pencil, c. 1791. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BB.450.P6.COM.100"><head><title>Tornado</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Henry Fuseli for Erasmus Darwin, 
			 <title level="m">The Botanic Garden</title>, 3rd ed., 1795. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> and illustrations of the famous 
		<name>Portland Vase. </name><name type="person" reg="Darwin, Erasmus">Darwin’s </name> poem and its
		copious notes probably suggested some of the biological and geological imagery
		that appears in 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		illuminated books of the 
		<date certainty="approx">mid-1790s</date>.</p><p>While engraving 
		  <name type="person" reg="Stedman, John Gabriel">John Gabriel
			 Stedman’s </name> designs for his 
		<title level="m">Narrative, of a Five Years’ Expedition, Against
		  the Revolted Negroes of Surinam </title><date value="1796">(1796)</date>, a firsthand account of a slave
		rebellion, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> became a close
		friend of the author. Though not an abolitionist, 
		<name type="person" reg="Stedman, John Gabriel">Stedman</name> deplored
		the inhuman conditions to which Africans were subjected on sugar and tobacco
		plantations. His graphic descriptions and depictions of the torture inflicted
		by the slave owners offended some contemporary readers, but critics praised the
		quality of the illustrations. 
		<figure entity="BB.499.c.P2.COM.100"><head><title>A Negro hung alive by the Ribs to a Gallows</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after John Gabriel Stedman for Stedman, 
			 <title level="m">Narrative, of a Five Years’ Expedition,
				Against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</title>, 1796. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BB.499.c.P8.COM.100"><head><title>Flagellation of a Female Samboe Slave</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after John Gabriel Stedman for Stedman,
			 <title level="m">Narrative of a Five Years’ Expedition, Against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</title>, 1796. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BB.499.c.P12.COM.100"><head><title>March thro’ a swamp or Marsh, in
				Terra-firma</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after John Gabriel Stedman for Stedman, 
			 <title level="m">Narrative, of a Five Years’ Expedition,
				Against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</title>, 1796. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure></p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> both composed and
		  engraved the six designs for 
		  <name type="person" reg="Wollstonecraft, Mary">Mary
			 Wollstonecraft’s </name><title level="m">Original Stories from Real Life </title><date value="1791">(1791)</date>, a work of didactic fiction that offers
		an alternative to the 
		<date certainty="approx">eighteenth-century</date> ideal of woman as an
		emotional creature of more sensibility than sense. Most of the illustrations
		depict the rational 
		<name type="character" reg="Mrs. Mason">Mrs. Mason’s </name>
		efforts to teach her two young female students the importance of charity and
		compassion by exposing them to scenes of poverty and suffering. 
		<figure entity="BB514.1.1.COM.100"><head><title>Look what a fine morning it is</title></head><figdesc>Designed and engraved by Blake as the frontispiece for Mary
			 Wollstonecraft, 
			 <title level="m">Original Stories from Real Life</title>, 1791.
			 Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BUT.244.4.WD.100"><head><title>Look What a Fine Morning It Is</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to Mary Wollstonecraft, 
			 <title level="m">Original Stories from Real Life</title>. Monochrome
			 wash drawing, c. 1791. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure></p><p>His work for 
		  <name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Johnson</name> during the 
		  <date certainty="approx">1790s</date> may have given 
		  meet some of the more prominent radical thinkers and writers in 
		  <name type="place">England. </name>Besides 
		  <name type="person" reg="Wollstonecraft, Mary">Wollstonecraft</name>,
		  whose 
		<title level="m">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman </title><date value="1792">(1792)</date> attacked contemporary notions about
		women’s education and role in society, the 
		<name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Johnson</name> circle included 
		<name type="person" reg="Godwin, William">William Godwin, </name>the author of 
		<title level="m">Political Justice </title><date value="1794">(1794)</date>; 
		<name type="person" reg="Holcroft, Thomas">Thomas Holcroft, </name>who
		was tried on charges of high treason in 
		<date value="1794">1794</date> along with 
		<name type="person" reg="Tooke, John Horne">John Horne Tooke</name>; 
		<name type="person" reg="Priestley, Joseph">Joseph Priestley, </name>the
		prominent chemist and radical; and 
		<name type="person" reg="Paine, Thomas">Thomas Paine, </name>author of 
		<title level="m">The Rights of Man </title><date value="1791-1792">(1791-92)</date>, who fled 
		<name type="place">England</name> in 
		<date value="1792">1792</date> to avoid arrest—tipped off, it was
		rumored, by 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> himself: 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">“Blake</name> advised him
		immediately to fly, for he said ’if you are not now sought I am sure you
		soon will be.’ 
		<name type="person" reg="Paine, Thomas">Paine</name> took the hint directly
		&amp; found he had just escaped in time” 
		<bibl>(Bentley, 
		  <title level="m">Blake Records</title> 530)</bibl>. The story may well
		be apocryphal, but it reveals the extent to which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> name was
		associated with those of the leading radical figures of the decade.</p><p>The member of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Johnson’s </name>
		  circle who played the most important role in 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> life,
		  however, was 
		  <name type="person" reg="Fuseli, Henry">Henry Fuseli, </name>a Swiss
		  artist who had emigrated to 
		  <name type="place">England. </name>He and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> greatly admired
		  each other’s work: 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> considered 
		  <name type="person" reg="Fuseli, Henry">Fuseli</name> a century ahead
		  of his time
<bibl>(Bentley, 
			 <title level="m">Blake Records Supplement</title> 80)</bibl>, while 
		  <name type="person" reg="Fuseli, Henry">Fuseli, </name>for his part,
		  pronounced 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> “<hi rend="italic">d----d good to steal from</hi>”
<bibl>(Gilchrist 1: 52)</bibl>. The two formed a close friendship, and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> engraved a number
		  of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Fuseli, Henry">Fuseli’s </name> designs,
		  both for book illustrations and as separate plates. 
		  <figure entity="ESXXXIV.1.1.SP.100"><head><title level="m">Falsa ad Coelum</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after Henry Fuseli, c. 1790. The British
				Museum.</figdesc></figure></p><p>When 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> returned to
		  illuminated printing in 
		  <date value="1793">1793</date> after a three-year hiatus, his new books
		  shared some themes prominent among the authors 
		  <name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Johnson</name> published. 
		  <name type="character" reg="Oothoon">Oothoon, </name>the victimized
		  heroine of 
		<title level="m">Visions of the Daughters of Albion </title><date value="1793">(1793)</date>, 
		<figure entity="vda.O.P2.100"><head><title>Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>, copy O, plate 2
			 (title page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1793,
			 printed c. 1818. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> adds her eloquent lament to the discourse on slavery and the
		rights of women. 
		<title level="m">America a Prophecy </title><date value="1793">(1793)</date>, the first of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name><name>Continental Prophecies, </name>treats the 
		<name type="event">American Revolution</name> as an event with
		mythological as well as historical dimensions. 
		<name type="person" reg="Paine, Thomas">Paine</name> makes an appearance here,
		as do 
		<name type="person" reg="Washington, George">Washington, </name><name type="person" reg="Franklin, Benjamin">Franklin, </name>and other
		American luminaries, but so do new figures from 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> personal
		mythology: 
		<name type="character" reg="Urizen">Urizen, </name><figure entity="america.O.P10.100"><head><title>America a Prophecy</title>, copy O, plate 10</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1793,
			 printed 1821. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> the wintry oppressor, and 
		<name type="character" reg="Orc">Orc, </name><figure entity="america.O.P12.100"><head><title>America a Prophecy</title>, copy O, plate 12</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1793,
			 printed 1821. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> the fiery revolutionary, who act out the conflict on a cosmic
		scale. 
		<title level="m">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</title>, 
		<figure entity="gates-child.D.P1.100"><head><title>For Children: The Gates of Paradise</title>, copy D, plate 1
			 (frontispiece)</head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of
			 Congress.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="gates-child.D.P2.100"><head><title>For Children: The Gates of Paradise</title>, copy D, plate 2
			 (title page)</head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of
			 Congress.</figdesc></figure> an emblem book comprising eighteen small intaglio etchings
		accompanied by brief inscriptions on the human condition, also appeared in 
		<date value="1793">1793</date>. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> later revised the
		work as 
		<title level="m">For the Sexes </title><date value="1820" certainty="approx">(c. 1820)</date>. 
		<figure entity="gates-sexes.D.P1.100"><head><title>For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</title>, copy D, plate 1
			 (frontispiece)</head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793, revised c. 1820, printed 1825. The Pierpont
			 Morgan Library.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="gates-sexes.D.P2.100"><head><title>For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</title>, copy D, plate 2
			 (title page)</head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793, revised c. 1820, printed 1825. The Pierpont
			 Morgan Library.</figdesc></figure><!--gates-sexes.D.P1, P2--></p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d4"><head>Illustrated Books and Separate Prints, 
		  <date>1793-1799</date></head><p>Besides illuminated books, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> designed and
		  executed a number of separate plates in 
		  <date value="1793">1793</date>. Although he produced many watercolor
		  drawings of subjects from British history, 
		<title level="m">Edward &amp; Elenor </title><date value="1793">(1793)</date><figure entity="ESIV.1.1B.SP.100"><head><title>Edward &amp; Elenor</title></head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> is his only known engraving in that genre. It commemorates the
		moment when, according to legend, the queen risked her own life to suck the
		poison out of her husband’s wound. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name><title level="m">Job </title><date value="1793">(1793)</date><figure entity="ES.V.1A.SP.100"><head><title>Job</title>, first state</head><figdesc>Engraving, 1793. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> grew out of drawings dating from the 
		<date certainty="approx">1780s</date>, and he revised the design for one
		of his Job watercolors of c. 
		<date value="1805" certainty="approx">1805</date>. 
		<figure entity="BUT550.1.P10.WC.100"><head><title>Job Rebuked by His Friends</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to The Book of Job. Water color, c. 1805-1806.
			 The Pierpont Morgan Library.</figdesc></figure> In 
		<title level="m">Albion rose </title><date value="1793">(1793)</date>, also known as 
		<title level="m">Glad Day</title> or 
		<title level="m">The Dance of Albion</title>, a triumphant young male
		nude stands with outstretched arms before a glorious sunburst. 
		<figure entity="BUT262.1.1.CPD.100"><head><title>Albion rose</title>, or 
			 <title level="m">The Dance of Albion</title>, or 
			 <title level="m">Glad Day</title>. From the 
			 <title level="m">Large Book of Designs</title>, copy A</head><figdesc>Intaglio etching/engraving color printed from the surface of
			 the plate with hand coloring, 1796. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> Contrasting with his open and unselfconscious posture are 
		<title level="m">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder </title><date value="1793">(1793)</date>, who, though armed, crowd stiffly
		together in fright. 
		<figure entity="BUT262.1.2.CPD.100"><head><title>The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</title>, or 
			 <title level="m">When the senses are shaken</title>, or 
			 <title level="m">Our End is come</title></head><figdesc>From the 
			 <title level="m">Large Book of Designs</title>, copy A. Intaglio
			 etching/engraving color printed from the surface of the plate with hand
			 coloring, 1796. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> Both these designs have affinities with the revolutionary
		themes of 
		<title level="m">America</title>: the vigorous young 
		<name type="character" reg="Albion">Albion</name> suggests the youthful
		revolutionary 
		<name type="character" reg="Orc">Orc, </name>while the title of the first
		state of 
		<title level="m">The Accusers</title> echoes the prediction in 
		<title level="m">America</title> that the tyrants’ “end
		should come” with 
		<name type="event">the French Revolution</name><bibl>(Erdman 57)</bibl>.</p><p>In his next 
		  <name>Continental Prophecy, </name><title level="m">Europe: a Prophecy </title><date value="1794">(1794)</date>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> continued to mix
		his personal mythology with history and the ongoing conflicts of his own times.
		The frontispiece design to this book is perhaps the most familiar of all 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> images: an
		old man, his long white hair and beard blown to one side, kneeling in an orb
		surrounded by clouds and reaching one arm down to apply a pair of compasses to
		some unseen realm below. 
		<figure entity="europe.K.P1.100"><head><title>Europe a Prophecy</title>, copy K, plate 1 (frontispiece, also
			 known as 
			 <title level="m">The Ancient of Days</title>)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched 1794,
			 printed 1821. The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> In the poem, the eighteen centuries of Christian history become
		a “female dream” of 
		<name type="character" reg="Enitharmon">Enitharmon</name><bibl>(Erdman 63)</bibl>, whose son 
		<name type="character" reg="Orc">Orc</name> illuminates “the
		vineyards of red France” with the light of revolution 
		<bibl>(Erdman 66)</bibl>.</p><p>In 
		  <date value="1794">1794</date>, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> produced a second
		  collection of lyrics, 
		<title level="m">Songs of Experience</title>, 
		<figure entity="songsie.C.P30-29.100"><head><title>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>, copy C, plate 30
			 (title page to 
			 <title level="m">Experience</title>)</head><figdesc>Relief etching with hand coloring, 1794. Rosenwald Collection,
			 The Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure> as a companion volume for his earlier 
		<title level="m">Songs of Innocence</title>. He intended the two sets of
		poems, which he combined as 
		<title level="m">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>, to
		illustrate “the Two Contrary States of the Human Soul” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 7)</bibl>. 
		<figure entity="songsie.AA.P1.100"><head><title>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>, copy AA, plate 1
			 (general title page)</head><figdesc>Relief etching with hand coloring. Etched 1794, printed 1826.
			 The Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> In one of the most anthologized poems in the English language, 
		<title level="a">The Tyger, </title><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> frames this
		opposition as a question of origins. When the child in 
		<title level="m">Innocence</title> asks, “Little Lamb who made
		thee” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 8)</bibl>, he is already sure of the answer, but the
		question the adult speaker of 
		<title level="m">Experience</title> poses to the Tyger— “Did
		he who made the Lamb make thee?” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 25)</bibl>—resists any such certainty.</p><p>The problem of origins is also central to the 
		  <name type="character" reg="Urizen">Urizen</name> Books, a series of
		  interrelated illuminated poems whose myths echo—and subvert— 
		<title>Genesis</title>, 
		<title level="m">Paradise Lost</title>, and other traditional creation
		narratives. In 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> version,
		the act of creation is itself a fall into the material world, where flawed
		creators struggle with each other and with the intractable elements of the
		cosmos. The most ambitious work in this series is 
		<title level="m">The [First] Book of Urizen </title><date value="1794">(1794)</date>, 
		<figure entity="urizen.F.P1.100"><head><title>The First Book of Urizen</title>, copy F, plate 1 (title
			 page)</head><figdesc>Relief etching, color printed with hand coloring, 1794. The
			 Houghton Library, Harvard University.</figdesc></figure> a poem in nine chapters generously illustrated with
		relief-etched designs. Two related poems, 
		<title level="m">The Book of Ahania</title><figure entity="ahania.A.P2.100"><head><title>The Book of Ahania</title>, copy A, plate 2 (title
			 page)</head><figdesc>Intaglio etching with color printing from the surface of the
			 plate and hand coloring, 1795. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of
			 Congress.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<title level="m">The Book of Los</title>, 
		<figure entity="b-los.A.P2.100"><head><title>The Book of Los</title>, copy A, plate 2 (title page)</head><figdesc>Intaglio etching with color printing from the surface of the
			 plate and hand coloring, 1795. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> followed in 
		<date value="1795">1795</date>. These are briefer and less lavishly
		illustrated than 
		<title level="m">Urizen</title>, and their texts are etched in intaglio
		rather than relief. In the same year, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> produced his final 
		<name>Continental Prophecy, </name><title level="m">The Song of Los</title>, 
		<figure entity="s-los.A.P2.100"><head><title>The Song of Los</title>, copy A, plate 2 (title page)</head><figdesc>Planographic color print, 1795. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> consisting of 
		<title level="a" type="section">Africa</title> and 
		<title level="a" type="section">Asia.</title> In these last three
		illuminated books, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was experimenting
		with color printing techniques he would employ in his next major graphic
		project.</p><p>The twelve large color-printed drawings of 
		  <date value="1795">1795</date> represent the culmination of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name>
		  experiments with a new color-printing technique using opaque, glue-based
		  pigments. The subjects of these designs range from the creation of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Adam">Adam</name> to the discoveries of Sir 
		  <name type="person" reg="Newton, Isaac">Isaac Newton, </name>and
		  include scenes from the 
		<title>Old Testament</title>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Shakespeare, William">Shakespeare, </name>and 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> own
		mythology. 
		<title level="m">Lamech and His Two Wives</title>, 
		<figure entity="BUT.298.CPD.100"><head><title>Lamech and His Two Wives</title></head><figdesc>Planographic color print with hand coloring, 1795. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> based on an obscure and infrequently illustrated passage in
		Genesis 4:23-24, pictures the destructive passions that lead to murder and
		regret in the fallen world. An equally dire fate awaits those who come to 
		<title level="m">The House of Death</title>, 
		<figure entity="BUT.322.CPD.100"><head><title>The House of Death</title></head><figdesc>Planographic color print with hand coloring, 1795. The
			 Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure> a design based on a passage in 
		<name type="person" reg="Milton, John">Milton’s </name><title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> also illustrated by Fuseli. 
		<title level="m">Nebuchadnezzar</title><figure entity="BUT302.CPD.100"><head><title>Nebuchadnezzar</title></head><figdesc>Planographic color print with hand coloring. Designed 1795,
			 printed 1804-1805. The Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</figdesc></figure> shows an even lower mental and physical state—the human
		reduced to the animalistic. It has been suggested recently that the color print
		traditionally titled 
		<title level="m">Hecate</title><figure entity="BUT318.P1.100"><head><title>Hecate</title>, or 
			 <title level="m">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</title></head><figdesc>Planographic color print with hand coloring, 1795. The
			 Huntington Library.</figdesc></figure> should actually be called 
		<title level="m">The Night of Enitharmon’s Joy</title>. Such a
		change in title shifts the subject of the print from the traditional witch and
		moon goddess 
		<name type="character" reg="Hecate">Hecate</name> to 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> own
		mythological representations of the natural world as a place of joyless
		repression. 
		<name type="character" reg="Enitharmon">Enitharmon, </name>as the
		reigning deity of such a world, separates and casts spells upon the youthful
		male and female behind her. Like the full-page designs for 
		<title level="m">The Song of Los</title>, 
		<title level="m">The Book of Los</title>, and 
		<title level="m">Ahania</title>, they were printed from a flat surface
		instead of a relief-etched plate.</p><p>In the same year, the bookseller and publisher 
		  <name type="person" reg="Edwards, Richard">Richard Edwards</name>
		  commissioned 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> to illustrate 
		  <name type="person" reg="Young, Edward">Edward Young’s </name><title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, a long didactic poem in blank
		verse that had achieved great popularity on the continent as well as in 
		<name type="place">England. </name>It was the biggest commercial project 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> would ever
		undertake. Within two years, he produced 537 watercolor designs to fit in large
		margins around rectangular blocks of 
		<name type="person" reg="Young, Edward">Young’s </name> text set in
		letterpress. 
		<figure entity="BUT330.1.78.WC.100"><head><title>Night Thoughts: Narcissa</title></head><figdesc>Water color illustration to Edward Young, 
			 <title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, fly-title to <title level="m">Night the Third</title>, c. 1795-97. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="BUT330.1.87.WC.100"><head><title>Night Thoughts: Night III</title></head><figdesc>Water color illustration to Edward Young, 
			 <title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, <title level="m">Night III</title>, page 12,  c. 1795-97. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> For this prodigious effort, he reportedly received only
		twenty-one pounds. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> engraved
		forty-three of his designs for the first of four projected volumes, which was
		also the last: 
		<name type="person" reg="Edwards, Richard">Edwards</name> went out of
		business not long after it appeared in 
		<date value="1797">1797</date>, and the project was abandoned. 
		<figure entity="BB515.1.24.COM.100"><head><title>Night Thoughts: Narcissa</title></head><figdesc>Designed and engraved by Blake as the fly-title to <title level="m">Night the
			 Third</title> in Edward Young, 
			 <title level="m">The Complaint, and the Consolation; or, Night
				Thoughts</title>, 1797. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></p><p>Meanwhile, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had begun work on
		  his own long poem, divided, like 
		  <name type="person" reg="Young, Edward">Young’s </name><title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, into nine “Nights.”
		Originally titled 
		<title level="m">Vala</title>, the epic evolved into 
		<title level="m">The Four Zoas</title>, an exploration of the fourfold
		division of fallen consciousness. It remained in manuscript, heavily revised
		and accompanied by designs that, like his 
		<title level="m">Night Thoughts</title> illustrations, surround the text.
		
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> eventually
		abandoned the poem, probably around 
		<date value="1807" certainty="approx">1807</date>, but used material from
		it in his two later epics, 
		<title level="m">Milton</title><figure entity="milton.D.P1.100"><head><title>Milton a Poem</title>, copy D, plate 1 (title page)</head><figdesc>White-line etching with hand coloring. Etched c. 1804-18,
			 printed 1818. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<title level="m">Jerusalem</title>. 
		<figure entity="jerusalem.E.P2.100"><head><title>Jerusalem</title>, copy E, plate 2 (title page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched c.
			 1804-20, printed 1821. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> work on 
		<title level="m">Night Thoughts</title> also influenced a project very
		different from 
		<title level="m">The Four Zoas</title>: his watercolor illustrations for
		the poems of 
		<name type="person" reg="Gray, Thomas">Thomas Gray, </name>which 
		<name type="person" reg="Flaxman, John">Flaxman</name> commissioned in 
		<date value="1797">1797</date> as a present for his wife, 
		<name type="person" reg="Flaxman, Ann">Ann. </name>By the following year 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had completed a
		series of 116 watercolor designs around the letterpress text of 
		<name type="person" reg="Gray, Thomas">Gray’s </name> poems. 
		<figure entity="but.335.7.100"><head><title>Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat</title>, title page</head><figdesc>An illustration to Thomas Gray, 
			 <title level="m">Poems</title>. Water color, c. 1797-98. Yale Center
			 for British Art.</figdesc></figure><figure entity="but.335.18.100"><head><title>Ode on a Distant Prospect of Eton College</title>, page
			 6</head><figdesc>An illustration to Thomas Gray, 
			 <title level="m">Poems</title>. Water color, c. 1797-98. Yale Center
			 for British Art.</figdesc></figure></p><p>After spending two years on the ill-fated 
		<title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had difficulty
		finding work as an engraver. “I am laid by in a corner as if I did not
		Exist,” he complained to 
		<name type="person" reg="Cumberland, George">Cumberland</name> in 
		<date value="1799">1799</date>; “Even 
		<name type="person" reg="Johnson, Joseph">Johnson</name> &amp; 
		<name type="person" reg="Fuseli, Henry">Fuseli</name> have discarded my
		Graver” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 704)</bibl>. As the decade drew to a close, he became
		increasingly dependent on private patrons. One of the most important of these
		was 
		<name type="person" reg="Butts, Thomas">Thomas Butts, </name><figure entity="BUT376.1.1.PT.100"><head><title>Portrait of Thomas Butts</title></head><figdesc>Miniature, water color on ivory, c. 1801. The British
			 Museum.</figdesc></figure> who, beginning about 
		<date value="1799" certainty="approx">1799</date>, commissioned paintings
		on biblical subjects in watercolors and in an experimental medium 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> called
		“tempera” or “fresco.” These commissions provided 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> with the creative
		latitude he craved and the financial support he needed: between 
		<date value="1803">1803</date> and 
		<date value="1810">1810</date>, they brought in some 400 pounds 
		<bibl>(Bentley, 
		  <title level="m">Stranger</title> 186)</bibl>, one of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> few
		reliable sources of income during those lean years.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d5"><head>Departure and Return, 
		  <date>1800-1808</date></head><p>In 
		  <date value="1800">1800 </date><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> left 
		  <name type="place">London</name> and moved to a cottage near the home
		  of another patron, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">William Hayley, </name>in 
		  <name type="place">Felpham, </name><name type="place">Sussex. </name><name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> was a popular
		  poet, the author of 
		<title level="m">Essays on Sculpture </title><date value="1800">(1800)</date>, for which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> engraved three
		plates, including a portrait of 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley’s </name> son 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, Thomas">Tom, </name>a student of 
		<name type="person" reg="Flaxman, John">Flaxman. </name><figure entity="BB.467.P3.COM.100"><head><title>Thomas Hayley</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after a medallion by John Flaxman for
			 William Hayley, 
			 <title level="m">An Essay on Sculpture</title>, 1800. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> The two found common ground in 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, Thomas">Tom’s </name> death in 
		<date value="05-1800" certainty="approx">May 1800</date>; 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>recalling his
		brother 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, Robert">Robert’s </name> death
		thirteen years earlier, wrote to 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> “with a
		brothers Sympathy” for his loss 
		<bibl>(Erdman 705)</bibl>. Two months later, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> visited 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> at 
		<name type="place">Felpham</name> and was soon making preparations to
		move there. Eager to leave 
		<name type="place">London</name> and full of optimism about his new life
		in 
		<name type="place">Sussex, </name>he wrote to 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> in 
		<date value="09-1800" certainty="approx">September</date>, “My
		fingers Emit sparks of fire with Expectations of my future labours” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 709)</bibl>.</p><p>The stay at 
		  <name type="place">Felpham</name> began auspiciously enough. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> found the place
		  “more Spiritual than 
		  <name type="place">London</name>,” as he wrote to 
		  <name type="person" reg="Flaxman, John">Flaxman</name> on his arrival:
		  “Heaven opens here on all sides her golden Gates [. . .] voices of
		  Celestial inhabitants are more distinctly heard &amp; their forms more
		  distinctly seen”
<bibl>(Erdman 710)</bibl>. The following 
		  <date value="05-1801" certainty="approx">May</date>, in a letter to 
		  <name type="person" reg="Butts, Thomas">Butts, </name>he was still
		  calling 
		  <name type="place">Felpham</name> “the sweetest spot on
		  Earth”
<bibl>(Erdman 715)</bibl>. 
		  <figure entity="milton.C.P39-36.100"><head><title level="m">Blakes Cottage at Felpham</title></head><figdesc>Detail of the illustration from <title level="m">Milton a Poem</title>, copy C, plate 39. Relief etching with hand coloring. Etched c. 1804-11,
				printed c. 1811. The New York Public Library.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> continued to work
		  on commissions for 
		  <name type="person" reg="Butts, Thomas">Butts, </name>while 
		  <name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> kept him busy
		  executing plates for his 
		<title level="m">Life of 
		  <name type="person" reg="Cowper, William">Cowper</name></title>, 
		<figure entity="BB.468.P1.COM.100"><head><title>William Cowper</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Blake after George Romney for William Hayley, 
			 <title level="m">The Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William
				Cowper</title>, 1803-1804. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> illustrating his 
		<title level="m">Ballads </title><date value="1802">(1802)</date>, 
		<figure entity="BB.466.P12.COM.100"><head><title>The Dog</title></head><figdesc>Designed and engraved by Blake for William
			 Hayley, 
			 <title level="m">Designs to a Series of Ballads</title>, 1802. Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure> and even decorating his library with portraits of poets.</p><p>As time went on, however, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> began to resent 
		  <name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley’s </name>
		  insistence that he spend his time on such projects at the expense of his own
		  artistic and poetic endeavors. He came to believe that, as he later wrote in 
		<title level="m">Milton</title>, “Corporeal Friends are Spiritual
		Enemies” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 98)</bibl>. 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> was certainly
		trying to be a corporeal friend, looking out for 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> financial
		interests, teaching him Greek and Latin, and worrying about his mental health.
		This last role was a familiar one for 
		<name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name>: eight years
		earlier, he had befriended the poet 
		<name type="person" reg="Cowper, William">William Cowper</name> and had
		tried unsuccessfully to intervene in his struggle with insanity. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>however, was not 
		<name type="person" reg="Cowper, William">Cowper. </name>Many years
		later, in his annotations to 
		<name type="person" reg="Spurzheim, Johann">Spurzheim’s </name><title level="m">Observations on Insanity </title><date value="1817">(1817)</date>, he recorded a vision in which 
		<name type="person" reg="Cowper, William">Cowper</name> told him,
		“You retain health &amp; yet are as mad as any of us all [. . .] mad as a
		refuge from unbelief—from 
		<name type="person" reg="Bacon, Francis">Bacon </name><name type="person" reg="Newton, Isaac">Newton</name> &amp; 
		<name type="person" reg="Locke, John">Locke</name>” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 663)</bibl>.</p><p>By 
		  <date value="1803">1803</date>, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had decided to
		  leave 
		  <name type="place">Felpham, </name>but before he could do so an
		  incident occurred that redoubled his distress. On 
		  <date value="12-08-1803">12 August</date>, he found a soldier, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Scolfield, John">John Scolfield, </name>in the
		  garden and insisted that he leave. The soldier refused, the two argued, and in
		  the end 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> evicted him by
		  force. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Scolfield, John">Scolfield</name> accused 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> not only of
		  assault but of sedition, claiming he had damned the king, and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was indicted on
		  the charges in 
		  <date value="10-1803">October</date>. The penalties for sedition in 
		  <name type="place">England</name> during the 
		  <name type="event">Napoleonic wars</name> were severe, and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> spent the fall of
		  
		  <date value="1803">1803</date> in anguish, uncertain of his fate. 
		  <name type="person" reg="Hayley, William">Hayley</name> hired a
		  barrister to defend him, and he was acquitted the following 
		  <date value="01-1804">January</date>. Meanwhile, he and 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, Catherine">Catherine</name> had moved
		  back to 
		  <name type="place">London, </name>renting rooms at 
		<address><addrline>17 South Molton Street</addrline></address>.</p><p><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> first
		  major commercial project after his return to 
		  <name type="place">London</name> was a set of illustrations for 
		<title level="m">The Grave</title>, a didactic blank-verse poem by 
		<name type="person" reg="Blair, Robert">Robert Blair. </name><figure entity="BB435.1.11.COM.100"><head><title>Death’s Door</title></head><figdesc>Engraved by Luigi Schiavonetti after Blake for Robert Blair, 
			 <title level="m">The Grave</title>, 1808. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> The publisher, 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Robert H. Cromek, </name>paid
		
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> a small sum in 
		<date value="1805">1805</date> for about twenty designs, with the
		understanding that he would engrave fifteen for publication. After seeing 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> etching of
		
		<title level="a">Deaths Door,</title><figure entity="ES.XIII.SP.100"><head><title>Deaths Door</title></head><figdesc>White-line etching, 1805. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure> however, 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Cromek</name> changed his
		mind. He saw the ruggedness produced by 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> innovative
		use of white-line etching as mere carelessness 
		<bibl>(Bentley, 
		  <title level="m">Blake Records</title> 172)</bibl> and decided to turn
		over the engraving of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> designs to
		the more fashionable 
		<name type="person" reg="Schiavonetti, Louis">Louis Schiavonetti</name>.
		As with 
		<name type="person" reg="Young, Edward">Young’s </name><title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had invested
		considerable effort and hope in a project that in the end seemed to have been
		pulled out from under him. 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Cromek</name> also rejected 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> dedicatory
		vignette 
		<title level="a">To the Queen,</title><figure entity="BUT620.1.1.WC.100"><head><title>Design for the Dedication to Blair’s
				Grave</title></head><figdesc>Water color, 1807. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure> but did include a portrait of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> himself engraved
		after 
		<name type="person" reg="Phillips, Thomas">Thomas Phillips. </name><figure entity="BB435-K8b.1.1.COM.100"><head><title>William Blake</title></head><figdesc>Frontispiece portrait engraved by Luigi Schiavonetti after
			 Thomas Phillips for Robert Blair, 
			 <title level="m">The Grave</title>, 1808. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure> To the extent that 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> name was
		known in the early 
		<date certainty="approx">nineteenth century</date>, it was largely as the
		artist of the 
		<title level="m">Grave</title> designs.</p><p>While 
		<title level="m">The Grave</title> was still in progress, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> began work on what
		was to become his largest original separate plate, a one-by-three-foot intaglio
		etching of 
		<title level="m">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</title>. <!--[INSERT IMAGE: BUT654*--><figure entity="ES.XVI.5GG.SP.100"><head><title>Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</title>, fifth state</head><figdesc>Engraving, first state 1810, fifth state c. 1820-23. Essick
			 Collection.</figdesc></figure><name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> later told 
		<name type="person" reg="Linnell, John">Linnell</name> that 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Cromek</name> had offered him
		twenty-one pounds for a painting of the subject, “with the understanding
		that the remuneration for the whole would be made adequate by the price to be
		paid to 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> for the Engraving
		which 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> stipulated he
		should execute” 
		<bibl>(Bentley, 
		  <title level="m">Blake Records</title> 464n)</bibl>. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> became suspicious
		of 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Cromek’s </name>
		intentions and refused to part with the painting; he later learned that 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Cromek</name> had
		commissioned a similar design from his friend 
		<name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Stothard. </name>Although 
		<name type="person" reg="Stothard, Thomas">Stothard</name> was probably
		unaware of 
		<name type="person" reg="Cromek, Robert H.">Cromek’s </name> prior
		arrangement with 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>both men became
		thieves in 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> eyes. 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> engraved and
		attempted to market his own design, but it did not sell well.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d6"><head>Exhibition and Illuminated Epics, 
		  <date>1809-1818</date></head><p>In 
		  <date value="1809">1809</date>, 
		  <name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> exhibited 
		<title level="m">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</title> along with fifteen
		other paintings in his brother’s shop at 
		<address><addrline>28 Broad Street</addrline></address>. The 
		<title level="m">Descriptive Catalogue</title> that he published to
		accompany the exhibit is as much an aesthetic manifesto as a catalogue. In it
		he defends his interpretation of 
		<name type="person" reg="Chaucer, Geoffrey">Chaucer’s </name>
		characters, presents his case against Venetian and Flemish painting, and argues
		that all great art must be based on the “distinct, sharp, and wirey [. .
		.] bounding line” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 558)</bibl>. Among the other works on display were 
		<title level="m">The Bard, from Gray</title>; 
		<title level="m">Satan Calling Up His Legions</title>; and a pair of
		temperas representing the “spiritual forms” of 
		<name type="person" reg="Nelson, Horatio">Nelson</name> and 
		<name type="person" reg="Pitt, William">Pitt. </name>By far the largest
		painting exhibited was 
		<title level="m">The Ancient Britons</title>, a ten-by-fourteen-foot
		canvas (now lost) depicting three survivors of “the last Battle of 
		<name type="person" reg="Arthur, King">King Arthur</name>” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 542)</bibl>. It had been commissioned by 
		<name type="person" reg="Pughe, William Owen">William Owen Pughe</name>,
		a Welsh antiquarian described by 
		<name type="person" reg="Southey, Robert">Robert Southey</name> as a
		“good simple-hearted, Welsh-headed man, [. . .] whose memory is the great
		storehouse of all Cymric tradition and lore of every kind” 
		<bibl>(Bentley, 
		  <title level="m">Blake Records</title> 226)</bibl>. The three surviving
		Britons in the painting, according to 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake, </name>represent
		“the human sublime,” “the human pathetic,” and
		“the human reason”: “They were originally one man, who was
		fourfold: he was self-divided, and his real humanity slain on the stems of
		generation” 
		<bibl>(Erdman 543)</bibl>. This division of the fourfold man was the
		subject of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> own epic
		poems: the abandoned 
		<title level="m">Four Zoas</title> manuscript and the two illuminated
		books, 
		<title level="m">Milton</title><figure entity="milton.D.P1.100"><head><title>Milton a Poem</title>, copy D, plate 1 (title page)</head><figdesc>White-line etching with hand coloring. Etched c. 1804-18,
			 printed 1818. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure> and 
		<title level="m">Jerusalem</title>, 
		<figure entity="jerusalem.E.P2.100"><head><title>Jerusalem</title>, copy E, plate 2 (title page)</head><figdesc>Relief and white-line etching with hand coloring. Etched c.
			 1804-20, printed 1821. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure> that grew out of it.</p><p>The title page of 
		<title level="m">Milton a Poem</title> (c. 
		<date value="1804-1818" certainty="approx">1804-18)</date> is dated 
		<date value="1804">1804</date>, but it was not until c. 
		<date value="1811" certainty="approx">1811</date> that 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> produced the first
		three copies, and he continued working on the fourth until c. 
		<date value="1818" certainty="approx">1818</date>. The poem is divided
		into two parts: in the first, 
		<name type="character" reg="Milton">Milton, </name>inspired by a
		bard’s song, descends from heaven and returns to earth in order to
		correct the errors he had left behind; in the second, 
		<name type="character" reg="Milton">Milton’s </name> female
		“emanation,” 
		<name type="character" reg="Ololon">Ololon, </name>also returns to earth,
		and the poem culminates in their apocalyptic union. Throughout 
		<title level="m">Milton</title>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> manipulates time
		and space in unconventional ways, and his characters’ identities change
		with disconcerting ease. In the designs, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> experimented with
		new etching techniques that give the book a rough, primitive appearance. 
		<figure entity="milton.A.P38.100"><head><title>Milton a Poem</title>, copy A, plate 38</head><figdesc>White-line etching with hand coloring. Etched c. 1804-11,
			 printed c. 1811. The British Museum.</figdesc></figure></p><p><title level="m"><name type="character" reg="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</name>: The Emanation
		  of the Giant 
		  <name type="character" reg="Albion">Albion</name></title>, at 100
		plates 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> longest
		illuminated book, took even longer to complete. Also dated 
		<date value="1804">1804</date> on its title page, it was not printed in
		its entirety until about 
		<date value="1820" certainty="approx">1820</date>. By the end of his
		life, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> had hand-colored
		one copy, but he was unable to find a buyer for it. The poem tells of efforts
		to awaken the self-divided and sleeping giant 
		<name type="character" reg="Albion">Albion</name> and reunite him with
		his female portion (or emanation), 
		<name type="character" reg="Jerusalem">Jerusalem. </name><name type="character" reg="Albion">Albion’s </name> cruel sons and
		daughters and the nature goddess 
		<name type="character" reg="Vala">Vala</name> impose obstacles and
		temptations, but 
		<name type="character" reg="Los">Los</name> (the artist’s
		imagination) eventually triumphs, with the help of 
		<name type="character" reg="Jesus">Jesus, </name>who is more prominent
		here than in any of 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake’s </name> other
		illuminated books.</p><p>While writing his epic 
		<title level="m">Milton</title>, 
		<name type="person" reg="Blake, William">Blake</name> was also at work on
		several series of watercolor drawings illustrating 
		<name type="person" reg="Milton, John">John Milton’s </name> own
		poems. He had already produced a set of designs for 
		<title level="m">Comus</title> for the Rev. 
		<name type="person" reg="Thomas, Joseph">Joseph Thomas</name> in 
		<date value="1801">1801</date>. 
		<figure entity="BUT.527.P1.100"><head><title>Comus with His Revellers</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to John Milton, 
			 <title level="m">Comus</title>. Water color, c. 1801. The Huntington
			 Library.</figdesc></figure> Now he illustrated 
		<title level="m">Paradise Lost </title><date value="1807">(1807)</date><figure entity="BUT.529.P1.100"><head><title>Satan Calling Up His Legions</title></head><figdesc>An illustration to John Milton, 
