<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2005-09-23T16:48:33-04:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><!-- Step 2 Conversion to BAD DTD 2004 using modblake.pl Fri Sep 23 15:38:05 2005 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="bb125.1" type="ms" work="The Order in which the Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience ought to be paged &amp; placed" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="lc" catalog="bentley" catid="125"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Order in which the Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience ought to be paged &amp; placed, The"><main>The Order in which the Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience ought to be paged &amp; placed</main>
: electronic edition</title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; 
<name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and 
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Programmer/Analysts:</resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants:</resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Kari Kraus,</name><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the Library of Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software grants from Sun Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 475KB; 108 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) 
files ranging in size from 55KB to 820KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH<date>June 2006</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of two late copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, Copy V (Pierpont Morgan Library) and Copy Y (Metropolitan Museum), and a manuscript listing the order of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress). Both copies are here reproduced for the first time, and, like all the illuminated books in the Archive, their texts and images are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.<lb/><lb/>
                Blake printed Copy V in 1821 in light orange ink on large sheets of J. Whatman paper watermarked 1818. He and/or possibly his wife, Catherine, drew four lines in pen and ink over or beside pencil lines to form a frame of three bands around each image; washed the frame's wide central band in light pinks, blues, yellows, or greens; and numbered the pages in ink 1-54 just outside the outer framing line. Copy Y, printed in 1825 in bright orange ink on J. Whatman paper watermarked 1825, is framed more decoratively with vines, curtains, and other motifs and is also numbered in pen and ink 1-54.<lb/><lb/>
                Both copies are connected either visually or bibliographically to Copy R, previously published in the Archive (see the update for 14 December 1999). Nearly all of the impressions of Copy R were printed in 1795 along with those making up Copy A (forthcoming in the Archive), and then, by August 1819, were refinished and given four framing lines for Blake's patron, John Linnell. Copy R established the plate order for seven of the eight subsequent copies printed between 1818 and 1827, including Copy Y and Copies Z and AA, both previously published in the Archive. The exception is Copy V, whose plates were uniquely arranged according to a manuscript entitled "The Order in which the Songs of Innocence &amp; Experience ought to be paged &amp; placed," often called "The Order of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>." Our reproduction of this manuscript is the first to be published since William Muir's partial facsimile of 1885, and our transcription and notes provide the most thorough textual and bibliographic treatment of it in any medium.<lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible through the continuing support of the Library of Congress, the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the University of Virginia, by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and by the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2006</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
            granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This work copyright © 2006 William Blake Archive.
            </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>The Order in which the Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience ought to be paged &amp; placed</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author,</role><role>inventor,</role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1821">c. 1821 or later?<note>Copy V of *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*, the only copy with the plates arranged in the order presented by this manuscript, was printed in 1821.  Thus, 1821 is probably a *terminus a quo* for the composition of this manuscript, but Blake may have written it at a later date.  There is no evidence that this manuscript was ever bound or kept with Copy V of the *Songs*.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>27.1 x 19.6 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>2<note>The manuscript is a single sheet of paper, folded to create two leaves.  Blake's writing is on the verso of the first leaf and the recto of the second leaf.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>27.1 x 19.6 cm.</leafsize><medium>manuscript mostly in pen and ink on paper, with a few words in pencil</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><framelines>none</framelines><binding>disbound<note>The former binding in blue morocco was produced sometime between the manuscript's acquisition by George C. Smith (no earlier than 1924) and its sale from Smith's collection in 1938; see the provenance, below.</note></binding><stabholes>There are two sets of stab holes created when the manuscript was bound, c. 1853, and a second binding between 1924 and 1938.</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Library of Congress</name><date>1945</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Acquired c. 1853 by George A. Smith and bound by him into an album of works by Blake and the manuscript of Allan Cunningham's biography of Blake; the album sold by Smith at Christie's, 1 April 1880, lot 168 (£66 to the dealer Bernard Quaritch); after the removal of some works from the album, but with the *Order of the Songs* manuscript still present, offered by Quaritch in his 1887 *General Catalogue of Books*, vol. 2, item 10252 (£80); acquired by Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge by 1892; the album sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 1 July 1924, lot 133 (£345 to the dealer E. Parsons and Sons); the album offered in 1924 by Maggs Bros. (possibly on behalf of, or in partnership with, Parsons), catalogue 456, item 53 (£630); acquired by George C. Smith by 1927; the album broken up by Smith, who separately bound the *Order of the Songs* manuscript with 9 plates from *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*; the manuscript and its accompanying plates sold from Smith's collection, Parke-Bernet, 2 Nov. 1938, lot 18 ($550 to the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach acting on behalf of Lessing J. Rosenwald); given by Rosenwald to the Library of Congress in 1945.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Library of Congress</institution><addressline>101 Independence Avenue SE</addressline><addressline>Washington, D.C. 20540-4740</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 202-707-5434</addressline><addressline>Fax: 202-707-4142</addressline><addressline>E-mail: rbsc@loc.gov</addressline><addressline>URL: http://lcweb.loc.gov/rr/rarebook</addressline><department>Rare Book and Special Collections</department><collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">ms.no.7</repositoryid><repositoryid label="Catalog number">1800</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="bb125.1.ms.01" dbi="BB125.1.1.MS"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">page 1</title><title type="alt">The Order of the Songs, page 1</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>27.1 x 19.6 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Blake's writing is on the verso of the first leaf. The recto is inscribed, in an unidentified hand, possibly George A. Smith's, as follows: "The following nine plates [inserted with the manuscript] are it is believed, engraved by Blake, tho' three only bear his name; and this Manuscript Index to the Song [sic] of Innocence and Experience is supposed to be in Blake's Autograph.  The engravings may be regarded as specimens of those 'daily tasks' alluded to in Cunningham's Memoir, by which the artist maintained himself, and purchased leisure for the indulgence of more favourite pursuits."</p></objnote><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.01" justify="left" indent="10">The Order in which the Songs of Innocence &amp;</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.02" justify="left" indent="4">of Experience ought to be paged &amp; placed</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.03" justify="left" indent="10">Page</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.04" justify="left" indent="7">x<space extent="3"/>1<space extent="5"/>General Title<note>The two sequences of check marks and x marks preceding most of the numbered entries on both pages are written in a lighter ink than the rest of the manuscript and may have been written at a later date. These marks may be by Blake or by some other, unidentified writer. They may indicate alternative sequences for the plates, although no copy of *Songs of Innocence and of Experience* follows the left-hand series. The right-hand series (those closest to the numbers) corresponds to Copy F of *Songs of Innocence*, except that Copy F contains the second plate of "Night," number 23 in this manuscript. Copy F, however, was printed in 1789, long before Blake wrote this manuscript. Thus, the check marks may simply have been the writer's way of checking-off available impressions. There are as well very light diagonal strokes, rising from left to right and apparently in pen and ink, before many lines, most apparent on page 2 of the manuscript. These may be a continuation of the right-hand check marks or yet a third series of such marks. These very light strokes are not recorded in the transcription.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.05" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>2.<space extent="5"/>Frontispiece of Piper</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.06" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>3.<space extent="5"/>Title page <subst><del type="overwrite">of</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">to</add></subst> Songs of Innocence
                    </l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.07" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>4.<space extent="5"/>Introduction __ Piping down the Valleys &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.08" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>x<space extent="1"/>5<space extent="6"/>Ecchoing Green<note>In addition to the two marks, there is a very light diagonal stroke, rising from left to right and probably in pen and ink, at the beginning of this line. The bracket (here rendered on its own, unnumbered, line) links lines 8 and 9. Perhaps this indicates simply that these are the two plates of a single poem.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.XX" justify="left" indent="9">{</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.09" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>x<space extent="1"/>6<space extent="6"/>Ditto</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.10" justify="left">x<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="1"/>x 7.<space extent="6"/>The Lamb<note>The second "x" from the left may be a more substantial part of the very light horizontal lines preceding other lines.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.11" justify="left">x<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="3"/>8.<space extent="6"/>The Shepherd<note>The bracket (here rendered on its own, unnumbered, line) links lines 11 and 12. The reason for the bracket is uncertain. Unlike the other bracketed plates, lines 11 and 12 do not name the two plates of a single poem.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.XX" justify="left" indent="9">{</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.12" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>9.<space extent="6"/>Infant Joy</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.13" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>10.<space extent="4"/>Little Black Boy</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.14" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>11.<space extent="4"/>Ditto</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.15" justify="left">x<space extent="5.5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>12.<space extent="4"/>Laughing Song</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.16" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>13.<space extent="4"/>Spring<note>At the beginning of this and the next numbered entry (line 17) are very light diagonal strokes, rising from left to right and probably in pen and ink. The bracket (here rendered on its own, unnumbered, line) links lines 16 and 17. Perhaps this indicates simply that these are the two plates of a single poem.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.XX" justify="left" indent="9">{</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.17" justify="left">x<space extent="5.5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>14.<space extent="4"/>Ditto</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.18" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>15.<space extent="4"/>Cradle Song<note>The bracket (here rendered on its own, unnumbered, line) links lines 18 and 19. Perhaps this indicates simply that these are the two plates of a single poem.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.XX" justify="left" indent="9">{</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.19" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>16.<space extent="4"/>Ditto</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.20" justify="left">✓<space extent="9"/>17<space extent="4"/>Nurses Song<note>At the beginning of this and the next numbered entry (line 21) are very light diagonal strokes, rising from left to right and probably in pen and ink.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.21" justify="left">✓<space extent="9"/>18<space extent="4"/>Holy Thursday</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.22" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>19.<space extent="4"/>The Blossom<note>In addition to the two check marks, there is a very light diagonal stroke, rising from left to right and probably in pen and ink, at the beginning of this line.  Although extremely faint, such lines may also be at the beginning of all following lines on this page.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.23" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>20.<space extent="4"/>The Chimney Sweeper</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.24" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>21.<space extent="4"/>The Divine Image</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.25" justify="left">✓<space extent="5"/>✓<space extent="2"/>22.<space extent="4"/>Night</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.01.26" justify="left">✓<space extent="9"/>23.<space extent="4"/>Ditto</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb125.1.ms.02" dbi="BB125.1.2.MS"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">page 2</title><title type="alt">The Order of the Songs, page 2</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>27.1 x 19.6 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Blake's writing is on the recto of the leaf.  The pencil marks, possibly a number, in the top right corner are not by Blake.</p></objnote><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.01" justify="left" indent="8">page<note>The top of the word is trimmed off, indicating that the top edge of the leaf was trimmed after the manuscript was written.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.02" justify="left" indent="1">✓<space extent="3"/>✓<space extent="1"/>24.<space extent="4"/>A Dream<note>For the sequences of check marks, see the textual note on page 1, line 4.  In addition to the check marks transcribed here, there are extremely faint diagonal strokes, rising from left to right and probably in pen and ink, at the beginning of lines 2-5, 8-13, 15-18, 20-30, 32-34.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.03" justify="left" indent="1">✓<space extent="3"/>✓<space extent="1"/>25.<space extent="4"/>On <subst><del type="overwrite">a</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">A</add></subst>nothers Sorrow
                            </l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.04" justify="left">✓<space extent="4"/>✓<space extent="1"/>26.<space extent="4"/>The litle Boy Lost</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.05" justify="left">✓<space extent="4"/>✓<space extent="1"/>27.<space extent="4"/><subst><del type="overwrite"><unclear resp="ME">T</unclear><gap reason="illegible_inkblot" extent="2" unit="character"/><unclear resp="ME">to</unclear></del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">The</add></subst> Little Boy Found <note illus="bb125.2.5.note.jpg">The portion of this line overwritten by the word "The" is unclear, due in part to the fact that, at times within this line, the color of the ink constituting certain letters (note the "L" in "Little," for example) varies in intensity.  The first letter of the line appears to be a "T" (overwritten by another "T"), followed by two illegible characters and what appear to be the letters "t" and "o."  The first of the illegible characters may or may not contain a vertical stroke.  The "h" overwriting this character may simply be comprised of two different shades of ink (as in the case of the aforementioned "L")-- and therefore the illegible character is almost entirely obscured by the lower half of the "h"-- or the "h" is merely a partial overwrite, in which Blake makes use of the vertical stroke of the underwritten letter, adding the lower element (namely, the portion of the letter appearing in darker ink).  The second illegibale character (overwritten by the letter "e") contains a vertical stroke.  Bentley reads this line as "27. [Little (*?*) *del*] The Little Boy Found" (*Writings*, volume 2, page 1320).  Erdman (page 772) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 144) read "27. The Little Boy Found".</note></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.06" justify="left" indent="6">End of Songs of Innocence then Begins Songs of Experience</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.07" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>28<space extent="3"/>Frontispiece of Child on the Shepherds head</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.08" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>29<space extent="4"/>Title Page <subst><del type="overwrite">of</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">to</add></subst> Songs of Experience
                            </l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.09" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>30<space extent="5"/>Introduction __ Hear the Voice of the Bard &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.10" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>31<space extent="6"/>Earths Answer</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.11" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>32<space extent="6"/>Nurses Song</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.12" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>33<space extent="6"/>The Fly</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.13" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>34<space extent="6"/>The Tyger</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.14" justify="left" indent="1">✓<space extent="2"/>✓<space extent="1.5"/>35<space extent="6"/>Little Girl Lost<note>The bracket (here rendered on its own, unnumbered, line) links lines 14 and 15. Perhaps this indicates simply that these are the two plates of a single poem.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.XX" justify="left" indent="7">{</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.15" justify="left" indent="1">✓✓<space extent="2"/>✓36<space extent="6"/>Ditto</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.16" justify="left" indent="1">✓ ✓ ✓<space extent="1"/>37<space extent="6"/>Ditto<space extent="2"/><!--<instr type="pencil">-->the little girl found<!--</instr>--><note>The words "the little girl found" are written in pencil.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.17" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>38<space extent="6"/>The Clod &amp; Pebble</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.18" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>39<space extent="6"/>The Little Vagabond</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.19" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>40<space extent="6"/>Holy Thursday</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.20" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>41<space extent="6"/>A Poison Tree</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.21" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>42<space extent="6"/>The Angel</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.22" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>43<space extent="6"/>The Sick Rose</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.23" justify="left" indent="8.5">44<space extent="6"/>To Tirzah</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.24" justify="left">✓<space extent="4"/>✓<space extent="1"/>45<space extent="5"/>The Voice of the Ancient Bard</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.25" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>46<space extent="5"/>My pretty Rose Tree</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.26" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>47<space extent="5"/>The Garden of Love</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.27" justify="left" indent="8.5">48<space extent="5"/>A Little Boy Lost</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.28" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>49<space extent="5"/>Infant Sorrow</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.29" justify="left">✓<space extent="4"/>✓<space extent="1"/>50<space extent="5"/>The School Boy</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.30" justify="left">✓<space extent="7"/>51<space extent="5"/>London</l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.31" justify="left" indent="44">Page<note>Lines 31-34 are written sideways, rising from the bottom to the top, in the lower right corner of the page.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.32" justify="left" indent="44">52<space extent="3"/>A Little Girl Lost<space extent="2"/><!--<instr type="pencil">--><unclear resp="ME">Found secd</unclear><!--</instr>--><note>The final two words in line 32 are written in pencil and are slightly rubbed.  There may be another word at the end of the line.</note></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.33" justify="left" indent="40"><hi rend="superscript">✓</hi><space extent="2"/>53<space extent="3"/>The Chimney Sweeper . A little Black thing &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi></l><l n="bb125.1.ms.02.34" justify="left" indent="40"><hi rend="superscript">✓</hi><space extent="2"/>54<space extent="3"/>The Human Abstract</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>