<bad id="bb435.1" type="comdes" work="Robert Blair, The Grave" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="bentley" catid="435" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Grave, The"><main><author>Robert Blair</author>, The Grave</main>, : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the Library of
                    Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a software
                    grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software grants from Sun
                    Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 240KB; 36 JPEG
                (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 150KB to 2500KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH<date>October 2007</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt><lb/><b>May 2014</b><lb/><lb/>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. 
                <lb/><lb/><b>October 2007</b><lb/><lb/>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of the
                electronic edition of Blake's illustrations to Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The
                    Grave</hi>, accompanied by the related separate plate of <hi rend="i">Deaths
                    Door</hi>. Both are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the
                features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (our image annotation program).<lb/><lb/> The illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> are among Blake's most
                important commissions for commercially published book illustrations. The engraver
                and would-be publisher R. H. Cromek hired Blake to illustrate Blair's popular
                "Graveyard" poem in 1805. Blake produced one design, <hi rend="">Deaths Door</hi>,
                as a white-line etching, but Cromek found this so unsatisfactory that he quickly
                turned to the fashionable engraver Louis Schiavonetti to etch and engrave twelve of
                Blake's illustrations. These were published, along with a frontispiece portrait of
                Blake included in our electronic edition, in 1808. Blake's reputation as an artist
                through the first half of the nineteenth century was based largely on these images.<lb/><lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible through
                the continuing support of the Library of Congress, the Institute for Advanced
                Technology in the Humanities at the University of Virginia, by a major grant from
                the Preservation and Access Division of the National Endowment for the Humanities,
                by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and by the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2003</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © William Blake Archive</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Robert Blair, *The Grave*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>inventor</role></origination><origination>Thomas Phillips <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><origination>Luigi Schiavonetti <role>engraver</role></origination><imprint><publisher>R. H. Cromek</publisher><pubplace>London</pubplace><date>1808</date></imprint><compdate value="1805">c. 1805-08<note>c. 1805-08 (Objects 2-13) and 1807-08 (object
                        1)</note></compdate><note>Blake executed the designs for Objects 2-13, on which the engravings are
                    based, in the fall of 1805. Luigi Schiavonetti began to engrave the designs in
                    late 1805 or early 1806, but did not finish the plates until 1808, when the book
                    was published. The portrait of Blake, on which Object 1 is based, was painted in
                    oils by Thomas Phillips in 1807. Schiavonetti engraved the portrait in
                    1807-08.</note></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1808">1808</printdate><numberobj>13</numberobj><objorder>1-13</objorder><objsize>ranging between 14.1 x 12.0 cm. and 33.7 x 26.1 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>13</numberleaves><leafsize>35.7 x 28.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>etching and engraving</medium><printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>J Whatman 1808<note>In this copy, the watermark appears only on object
                        7.</note></watermark><etchednumbers>Facing page numbers are etched or engraved top right on Objects 3,
                    5-9, 11-13. See the Textual Transcriptions for these numbers.</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>loose</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1970</date><dealer>Heritage Book Shop</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>earlier history not known</note></provenance><repository><lb/><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline><lb/></repository></source><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.01" dbi="BB435.1.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">William Blake</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="K1">(Keynes 8b)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>33.1 x 23.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="730"/><objnote><p>The plate is based on an oil painting by Thomas Phillips. This impression is
                        in the first published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The image is based on a portrait of William Blake painted by
                        Thomas Phillips and engraved by Luigi Schiavonetti. Blake sits on a chair or
                        bench with only his upper body visible. He wears a coat, shirt, scarf, and
                        pants. His hair is short. Blake's eyes are raised and look up to the right.
                        Both arms are bent and cross at the wrist. He holds a pen, graphite pencil,
                        or etching needle in his right hand. His left hand rests on the arm of the
                        chair or bench; the fingers on his left hand are spread. There may be a
                        small leaf or other design on the back of the chair, to the right of Blake's
                        left arm.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Blake, William</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pen</characteristic><characteristic>graphite pencil</characteristic><characteristic>etching needle</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The image is based on a portrait of William Blake painted by
                            Thomas Phillips and engraved by Luigi Schiavonetti. Blake sits on a
                            chair or bench with only his upper body visible. He wears a coat, shirt,
                            scarf, and pants. His hair is short. Blake's eyes are raised and look up
                            to the right. Both arms are bent and cross at the wrist. He holds a pen,
                            graphite pencil, or etching needle in his right hand. His left hand
                            rests on the arm of the chair or bench; the fingers on his left hand are
                            spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>bench</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Blake sits on a chair or bench. There may be a small leaf or
                            other design on the back of the chair, to the right of Blake's left
                            arm.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.01.01" justify="left">Painted by T. Phillips R.
                                A.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.01.02" justify="right">Engraved by L. Schiavonetti
                                V. A.<note>The period after "L" is very faint.</note></l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.01.03" justify="center">William Blake<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.01.04" justify="center">London, Published by R. H. Cromek,
                        64, Newman S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808_<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.02" dbi="BB435.1.2-1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">THE GRAVE, A Poem.</title><title type="alt">The Skeleton Re-Animated</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 435.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>34.9 x 25.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="730"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state. The title for the design is
                        not inscribed on the plate, but is given in "Of the Designs," page 35 of the
                        letterpress text.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="but614r.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="bb515.1.comb.12" type="compare" copyid="bb515.1" bentley="B12"/><related objectid="but611.1.wc.01"/><related objectid="but612.1.wd.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male trumpeter hovers upside down in the right half of the
                        design. He may be a wingless angel descending to awaken the skeleton below.
                        His body faces forward with his genitals clearly visible. His head is bent
                        back and faces down; he likely looks at the skeleton below. His hair is
                        short and may also be curly. The figure's legs are together and extend up
                        and to the left. His arms are slightly bent and are raised vertically with
                        respect to his body. He holds and plays a trumpet with his hands together
                        and the fingers spread. A skeleton lies supine across the lower border of
                        the design, facing up. The figure's legs are together and bent to the left.
                        The skeleton's left arm rests at its side with the hand on the ground, palm
                        down. Its right arm is bent over its shoulder; the skeleton appears to hold
                        part of a cloth shroud with its right hand. The figure's head is up and bent
                        back with its mouth open and teeth clearly visible. A stone(?) structure,
                        perhaps part of a tomb or coffin, extends to the left of the skeleton. Fire
                        surrounds the skeleton and a large cloud of smoke rises above and to the
                        right.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male trumpeter hovers upside down in the right half of
                            the design. He may be a wingless angel descending to awaken the skeleton
                            below. His body faces forward with his genitals clearly visible. His
                            head is bent back and faces down; he likely looks at the skeleton below.
                            His hair is short and may also be curly. The figure's legs are together
                            and extend up and to the left. His arms are slightly bent and are raised
                            vertically with respect to his body. He holds and plays a trumpet or
                            musical horn with his hands together and the fingers
                            spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>skeleton</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent over shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A skeleton lies supine across the lower border of the design,
                            facing up. The figure's legs are together and bent to the left. The
                            skeleton's left arm rests at its side with the hand on the ground and
                            the palm down. Its right arm is bent over its shoulder; the skeleton
                            appears to hold part of a cloth shroud with its right hand. The figure's
                            head is up and bent back with its mouth open and teeth clearly
                            visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="C"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>coffin</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A stone(?) structure, perhaps part of a tomb or coffin,
                            extends to the left of the skeleton.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Fire surrounds the skeleton, and a large cloud of smoke rises
                            above and to the right.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="1"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.01" justify="center">THE</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.02" justify="center">GRAVE,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.03" justify="center">A Poem.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.04" justify="center">Illustrated by twelve
                                Etchings</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.05" justify="center">Executed</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.06" justify="center">BY</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.07" justify="center">LOUIS SCHIAVONETTI,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.08" justify="center">From the Original</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.09" justify="center">Inventions</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.10" justify="center">OF</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.11" justify="center">WILLIAM BLAKE.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.12" justify="center">1808.</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/></column><column/></columns><vspace extent="4"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.13" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.<note>The
                                    line is slightly curved, perhaps in response to the design above
                                    it.</note></l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.14" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                    Schiavonetti.<note>The line is slightly curved, perhaps in
                                    response to the design above it.</note></l></lg></column></columns><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.15" justify="center">London, Published May 1, 1808, by
                        R. H. Cromek, N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 64, Newman Street.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.02.16" justify="right">Subscribers' Copy.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.03" dbi="BB435.1.3-2.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Christ descending into the grave.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 435.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>26.0 x 12.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="590"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="but621r.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.02"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Christ stands in the center of the design, facing forward. He
                        descends a set of stairs or steps with his left leg and foot prominent and
                        his right leg bent back. Both feet are visible; his right foot is raised on
                        tiptoe. Christ is gowned and has long, curly hair and a beard. A halo of
                        light surrounds his head and shoulders, and beams of light radiate outward
                        around his body. His arms are raised at 45 degrees and he holds a large key
                        in each hand; these likely represent "The Keys of Hell and Death" mentioned
                        in the inscription below. Christ casts a shadow on the stairs to the left. A
                        wall with an open doorway is visible at the top of the stairs. A (hellish?)
                        fire burns along the lower border of the design; it appears to divide to the
                        left and right at Christ's approach. The setting is mid-way between heaven,
                        perhaps represented by the portal behind Christ, and the grave into which he
                        descends.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>key</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Christ stands in the center of the design, facing forward. He
                            descends a set of stairs with his left leg and foot prominent and his
                            right leg bent back. Both feet are visible; his right foot is raised on
                            tiptoe. Christ is gowned and has long, curly hair and a beard. A halo of
                            light surrounds his head and shoulders, and beams of light radiate
                            outward around his body. His arms are raised at 45 degrees and he holds
                            a large key in each hand; these likely represent "The Keys of Hell and
                            Death" mentioned in the inscription below. Christ casts a shadow on the
                            stairs to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><characteristic>hell</characteristic><characteristic>grave</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Christ descends a set or stairs or steps, probably made of
                            stone. A wall with an open doorway is visible at the top of the stairs.
                            The setting is mid-way between heaven, perhaps represented by the portal
                            behind Christ, and the grave into which he descends.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>dividing</characteristic><characteristic>hell</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A (hellish?) fire burns along the lower border of the design;
                            it appears to divide to the left and right at Christ's
                            approach.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.1.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.04" justify="center">Christ descending into the
                            Grave.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.05" justify="center">Eternal King! whose potent Arm
                            sustains<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.06" justify="center">The Keys of Hell and Death.<space extent="20"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.03.07" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.04" dbi="BB435.1.4-3.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The meeting of a Family in Heaven.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 435.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>25.4 x 13.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="590"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="but623.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.17"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Two gowned angels fly or hover above a family of seven. Their
                        wings may touch at the upper border of the design. The angels face towards
                        the center and look down at the figures below. A male and a female child
                        kneel or crouch furthest left. The female is seen from behind and faces
                        away. The male figure's arms are bent and wrap around the waist of the
                        female; her arms wrap around his neck and shoulders. The figures are
                        embracing and may also be kissing. A male and female adult couple stand
                        third and fourth from the left; they are probably the father and mother of
                        the children to the left and right. The father faces right with his head
                        turned down; the mother faces left with her head turned up. The couple are
                        embracing and kissing. His right arm is bent and wraps around the back of
                        the female; his left hand holds her buttocks. The female's arms are bent and
                        wrap around the male's neck; her right hand rests on the male's right
                        shoulder with the fingers slightly spread. A male child and female child
                        stand fifth and sixth from the left; only the male's upper body is clearly
                        visible. The male's arms are bent and wrap around the waist of the female
                        child; the figures are embracing and may be kissing. A male child stands
                        furthest right with his mouth open. He faces left with his right leg bent
                        back and his right foot raised on tiptoe; he may be walking or running. His
                        arms are raised at 135 degrees and extend to the left with the palms held
                        vertically; he may be reaching towards his mother and father. The scene is
                        set in heaven. Two vertical columns of clouds appear in the sky above the
                        figures.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned angels fly or hover above a family; the angels'
                            wings may touch at the upper border of the design. The angel to the left
                            faces right with its head down and looks at the figures below. The
                            angel's right leg is bent slightly and the right foot is visible. The
                            angel's right arm is bent with its hand resting on its left shoulder;
                            the figure's left arm is not pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned angels fly or hover above a family; the angels'
                            wings may touch at the upper border of the design. The angel to the
                            right faces left with its head down in profile and looks at the figures
                            below. The angel's left leg is bent slightly and the left foot is
                            visible. The left arm is bent with its hand resting on its right
                            shoulder; the figure's right arm is not pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>family</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A male and female child kneel or crouch furthest
                            left. The male kneels with his left knee on the ground and his right leg
                            bent forward. He wears short pants or breeches. The figure's arms are
                            bent and wrap around the waist of a kneeling female with his hands
                            together; the figures are embracing. The male figure's head is turned
                            down and to the left; only the figure's short, curly hair and left
                            eye(?) are visible. His head may rest on the female's right shoulder,
                            and they may be kissing. His right arm casts a shadow on his right
                            thigh.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A female child kneels second from the left. She is
                            seen from behind and faces away with her head turned slightly to the
                            right. She is gowned and has long hair. Her left knee rests on the
                            ground and her left foot is visible; her right leg is not clearly
                            pictured. The figure's arms are bent and wrap around the neck and
                            shoulders of the kneeling male; the figures are embracing and may be
                            kissing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A male with short curly hair stands third from the
                            left; he is likely the father of the children to the left and right. The
                            figure's left leg is bent slightly and his left foot raised on tiptoe.
                            The figure wears a shirt, breeches, stockings, and shoes. The figure
                            faces right with his head turned down; he embraces and kisses the female
                            to the right. His right arm is bent and wraps around the back of the
                            female figure to the right; his left hand holds the female's buttocks.
                            The figure's left leg is cast in shadow, and a shadow extends on the
                            ground to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A gowned female with long hair stands fourth from
                            the left; she is likely the mother of the children to the left and
                            right. The figure's left leg is bent slightly and her left foot raised
                            on tiptoe. The figure faces left with her head turned up. She embraces
                            and kisses the male to the left. Both arms are bent and wrap around the
                            male's neck; her right hand rests on the male's right shoulder with the
                            fingers slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A male child with short, curly hair stands fifth
                            from the left; only his upper body is clearly visible. He wears a gown
                            or shirt. The figure's arms are bent and wrap around the waist of the
                            female child to the right; the figures are embracing and may be
                            kissing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A gowned female child with long hair stands sixth
                            from the left. She is seen from behind and faces slightly left. Her
                            right leg is bent back slightly with her right foot raised on tiptoe.
                            Her left arm is visible only to the elbow and is apparently raised at 45
                            degrees; she is likely embracing the male child to the left. Her head is
                            turned up and she may kiss the male child. She casts a shadow to the
                            right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures in the lower portion of the design
                            represents a family. A male child with short, curly hair stands furthest
                            right. He faces left with his mouth open. The child wears a shirt,
                            breeches, stockings, and shoes. The figure's right leg is bent back with
                            the right foot raised on tiptoe; he may be walking or running. His arms
                            are raised at 135 degrees and extend to the left with the palms held
                            vertically, fingers spread; he may be reaching towards his mother and
                            father. A narrow shadow extends to the right from the child's left
                            foot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in heaven. Two vertical columns of clouds
                            appear in the sky above the figures standing on what may be a floor of
                            some sort.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.04.01" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.04.02" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.04.03" justify="center">The meeting of a Family in
                            Heaven.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.04.04" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.05" dbi="BB435.1.5-4.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Counseller, King, Warrior, Mother &amp; Child, in the
                    Tomb.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 435.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.3 x 22.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="530"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Five corpses lay supine in an ornate tomb. The ceiling of the tomb
                        arches above the central figures. The tomb is probably made of stone. The
                        figures lay horizontally on a woven mat; it may be made of straw. Their
                        heads rest on pillows to the left. The lowest figure is a gowned male with
                        long hair and a beard; he is identified in the inscription as the counselor.
                        His right arm rests at his side and he holds a partially unrolled scroll in
                        his right hand. A seal dangles from the lower end of the scroll. The second
                        figure from the bottom is a gowned male with long, curly hair and a short
                        beard. He wears a crown and is identified in the inscription as a king; his
                        right arm rests at his side and he holds a scepter with his right hand. The
                        third figure from the bottom is a male figure wearing armor and a plumed
                        helmet; he is identified in the inscription as a warrior, and may be a
                        knight or soldier. The warrior holds a sheathed sword with both hands. His
                        feet rest on the back and head of a sculpted animal, probably a lion. The
                        fourth figure from the bottom is a gowned female with long hair; she is
                        identified in the inscription as a mother. Her left arm rests at her side
                        with her hand resting on the child above. The child is gowned and has curly
                        hair. The left and upper walls of the tomb are lined with Gothic arches or
                        small niches, perhaps eighteen in all; at least four of these contain
                        statues. Two winged angel statues stand to the left and right of the oil
                        lamp, facing forward. Both angels are gowned and may have long hair. Their
                        arms are apparently down at their sides. The statue of a female(?) stands
                        along the left border of the design, left of the king's head. She has long
                        hair and wears a crown and a cloak or gown. Above and to the right stands a
                        statue of a gowned male. Both statues face right. Three Gothic arches appear
                        in the center of the upper wall, directly above the child; a shelf is
                        recessed behind the arches. An oil lamp burns above the figures on the
                        shelf; the lamp's handle forms a loop. Fourteen figures appear along the
                        upper and lower borders of the design; they may represent statues or
                        carvings on the tomb. Six winged angels appear above the arch of the
                        ceiling. The figures appear to lay prone against the arch; each has one arm
                        bent upward in front of its chest. Eight gowned figures appear along the
                        lower border of the image. The figures lay on their sides in a reclining
                        position. Each figure appears to rest its head on its hand. Vegetative
                        motifs, possibly leaves, appear in the upper corners of the
                        design.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>seal</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>counselor</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five corpses lay supine in an ornate tomb; the figures' bodies
                            extend horizontally across the design with their heads to the left. The
                            lowest figure is a gowned male with long hair and a beard. He is
                            identified in the inscription as a counselor ("Counseller"). The
                            figure's legs are together and both feet are visible. His right arm
                            rests at his side and he holds a partially unrolled scroll in his right
                            hand. A seal dangles from the lower end of the scroll. His eyes are
                            closed.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five corpses lay supine in an ornate tomb; the figures' bodies
                            extend horizontally across the design with their heads to the left. The
                            second figure from the bottom is a gowned male with long, curly hair and
                            a short beard. He wears a crown. The figure is identified in the
                            inscription as a king. His eyes are raised. The figure's legs are
                            together and extend to the right; he may wear shoes. His right arm rests
                            at his side and he holds a scepter, with a fleur-de-lis finial, in his
                            right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>knight</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>spurs</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>plume</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mustache</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>sheath</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>lion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five corpses lay supine in an ornate tomb; the figures' bodies
                            extend horizontally across the design with their heads to the left. The
                            third figure from the bottom is a male figure apparently wearing armor;
                            he is identified in the inscription as a warrior, and may be a knight or
                            soldier. The figure wears a helmet with a large plume. A belt or sash is
                            visible around his waist. His legs are crossed at the knees with the
                            left over the right; he may wear spurs. The warrior's right arm is bent
                            upwards and he grasps the hilt of a sheathed sword with his right hand;
                            his left arm is at his side and he holds the sheath with his left hand.
                            He has a mustache but is not bearded. His eyes are raised. His feet rest
                            on the back and head of a sculpted animal, probably a
                            lion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five corpses lay supine in an ornate tomb; the figures' bodies
                            extend horizontally across the design with their heads to the left. The
                            fourth figure from the bottom is a gowned female with long hair. She is
                            identified in the inscription as a mother. Her eyes are closed. The
                            figure's legs are together and extend to the right. She may wear shoes.
                            Her left arm rests at her side with her hand resting on the child above;
                            she is probably the child's mother.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five corpses lay supine in an ornate tomb; the figures' bodies
                            extend horizontally across the design with their heads to the left. The
                            uppermost figure is a gowned child with curly hair. He or she is
                            identified in the inscription as a child. The figure's eyes are closed.
                            The child's legs are together and extend to the right; both feet are
                            visible. The child's arms are not pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five figures lay in an ornate tomb. The left and upper walls
                            of the tomb are lined with Gothic arches or small niches, perhaps
                            eighteen in all. At least four of these contain statues. Three Gothic
                            arches appear in the center of the upper wall, directly above the figure
                            of the child; a shelf is recessed behind the arches. The ceiling of the
                            tomb arches above the figures. Several statues or decorative carvings
                            appear above and below the five central figures. The tomb is probably
                            made of stone.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>mat</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>bundle</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The five figures lay on a woven mat; it may be made of straw.
                            Their heads rest on pillows.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An oil lamp burns above the figures on a recessed shelf. The
                            lamp's handle forms a loop.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Vegetative motifs, possibly leaves, appear in the upper
                            corners of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A total of eighteen decorative figures appear within the tomb.
                            Two winged angel statues stand to the left and right of the oil lamp,
                            facing forward. Both angels are gowned and may have long hair. Their
                            arms are apparently down at their sides. The statue of a female(?)
                            stands along the left border of the design, left of the king's head. She
                            has long hair and wears a crown and a cloak or gown. Above and to the
                            right stands a statue of a gowned male. Both statues face right.
                            Fourteen figures appear along the upper and lower borders of the design;
                            they may represent statues or carvings on the tomb. Six winged angels
                            appear above the arch of the ceiling. The figures appear to lay prone
                            against the arch; each has one arm bent upward in front of its chest.
                            Eight gowned figures appear along the lower border of the image. The
                            figures lay on their sides in a reclining position. Each figure appears
                            to rest its head on its hand.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.05.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.11.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.05.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.05.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.05.04" justify="center">The Counseller, King, Warrior,
                        Mother &amp; Child, in the Tomb.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.05.05" justify="center"> London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.06" dbi="BB435.1.6-5.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Death of the Strong Wicked Man.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 435.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.1 x 26.1 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="530"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="but624r.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.08"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with an open window in the upper
                        left portion of the wall. The body of a muscular male figure lies partly
                        supine, partly on its side, in the lower half of the design; he is
                        identified in the inscription as "the Strong Wicked Man." He lies on a woven
                        matpossibly made of strawand a sheet or bundle of sheets. He is partly
                        nude with a loincloth or sheet covering his genitals. The figure's head is
                        bent back and rests on his left shoulder. The figure's legs are together and
                        extend to the left. Both arms are bent and rest at his side; he clutches at
                        a sheet with both hands. He is dying and may even be dead. A broken chalice
                        or goblet appears to the left of the corpse's left hand; liquid spills out
                        to the left. A nude, muscular male flies or hovers in the upper portion of
                        the design. This figure probably represents the spirit of the male figure
                        below. The spirit is surrounded by fire; the flames rise up and to the left
                        and may pass through the open window. The spirit is seen from behind and
                        rises up and to the left with his body nearly horizontal. His right leg is
                        extended down and to the right with his left leg bent and drawn up; the sole
                        of his left foot is turned out toward the viewer. The figure's head is
                        turned to the left in profile; his mouth is open and he wears an expression
                        of surprise or fear. The spirit's left arm is bent to the left with the palm
                        held vertically; his right arm is not clearly pictured, but his right hand
                        is also held vertically left of his head. A gowned female with long hair
                        kneels or lunges above the corpse with her body horizontal. Her mouth is
                        open and she looks down and to the right toward the corpse below; her
                        expression and posture suggest grief or despair. Her right leg is bent and
                        drawn up; her left leg extends to the left with her foot raised on tiptoe.
                        Both arms are bent with her hands positioned beside her head; her palms are
                        nearly vertical with respect to her head and her fingers are slightly
                        spread. A gowned female with long hair stands at the right border of the
                        design. She faces left in profile. Her left foot is visible below the hem of
                        her gown. The figure's head is turned down; her left arm is bent and she
                        covers her face with her left hand. Her posture suggests grief or
                        despair.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with an open window in the
                            upper left portion of the wall.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A mountain or series of mountains are visible through the open
                            window.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>mat</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>bundle</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>bench</characteristic><characteristic>chalice</characteristic><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dying man lies on a woven matpossibly made of strawand a
                            sheet or bundle of sheets. A broken chalice or goblet (possibly made of
                            glass) appears to the left of the corpse's left hand; liquid spills out
                            to the left. A chair or bench stands in shadow to the left of the
                            figures, just below the open window.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The body of a muscular male figure lies partly supine, partly
                            on its side, in the lower portion of the design. He is identified in the
                            inscription as "the Strong Wicked Man." He is partly nude with a
                            loincloth or sheet covering his genitals. The figure's head is bent back
                            and rests on his left shoulder; he has short, curly hair and his mouth
                            is open with teeth visible. The figure's legs are together and extend to
                            the left. Both arms are bent and rest at his side; he clutches at a
                            sheet with both hands. He is dying and may even be dead.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>ear</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude, muscular male flies or hovers in the upper portion of
                            the design. This figure probably represents the spirit of the dying male
                            below. The spirit is seen from behind and rises up and to the left with
                            his body nearly horizontal. His right leg is extended down and to the
                            right with his left leg bent and drawn up; the sole of his left foot is
                            turned out toward the viewer. The figure's head is turned to the left in
                            profile; his mouth is open and he wears an expression of surprise or
                            fear. His hair is short and curly. The spirit's left arm is bent to the
                            left with the palm held vertically; his right arm is not clearly
                            pictured, but his right hand is also held vertically left of his head.
                            His fingers are slightly spread; his left ear and buttocks are
                            prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The spirit is surrounded by fire; the flames rise up and to
                            the left and may pass through the open window.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands beside head</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair kneels or lunges above the
                            corpse with her body horizontal. Her mouth is open, teeth visible, and
                            she looks down and to the right toward the corpse below; her expression
                            and posture suggest grief or despair. Her right leg is bent and drawn
                            up. Her left leg extends to the left with her foot raised on tiptoe.
                            Both arms are bent with her hands positioned beside her head; her palms
                            are nearly vertical with respect to her head and her fingers are
                            slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair stands at the right border of
                            the design. She faces left in profile. Her left foot is visible below
                            the hem of her gown. The figure's head is turned down; her left arm is
                            bent and she covers her face with her left hand. Her posture suggests
                            grief or despair.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched"> P.12.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.03" justify="right">Engraved by L.
                                Schiavonetti</l></lg></column></columns><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.04" justify="center">Death of the Strong Wicked
                            Man.<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.05" justify="center">...............Heard you that
                            groan?<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.06" justify="center">It was his last.<space extent="25"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.06.07" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.07" dbi="BB435.1.7-6.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Soul hovering over the Body reluctantly parting with
                    Life.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley435.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>19.3 x 22.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="480"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="but625.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.09"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with a window in the upper left
                        portion of the wall. An arch is visible on the wall to the right of the
                        window. A series of mountains appear through the window. There may be water
                        in the lower left portion of the landscape, representing a lake, river, or
                        the sea. A sky with visible clouds is pictured above the mountains. The
                        corpse of a gowned male lays supine on a bier in the lower half of the
                        design. The bier is covered with a sheet and the corpse rests on a partially
                        rolled mat or cushion. His body is horizontal with his head to the right.
                        The figure has curly hair and his eyes are closed. A gowned female with long
                        hair hovers above the corpse; she likely represents the male figure's soul
                        or spirit. She leans or arches to the right above the corpse with her legs
                        extended together down and to the left. Her head is turned down and she
                        looks at the corpse below. Both arms are bent with her hands held beside her
                        head and the palms turned out towards the viewer; the fingers on both hands
                        are slightly spread.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with a window in the upper
                            left portion of the wall. An arch is visible on the wall to the right of
                            the window.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>lake</characteristic><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A series of mountains is visible through the window. There may
                            be water in the lower left portion of the landscape, representing a
                            lake, river, or the sea. A sky with visible clouds is pictured above the
                            mountains.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="C"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several buildings, including one with a tall spire, are
                            visible below the leftmost mountain. They may represent a distant
                            city.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a gowned male lays supine on a bier in the lower
                            half of the design. His body is horizontal with his head to the right.
                            The figure has curly hair and his eyes are closed. Both feet are visible
                            and rest on a partially rolled mat or cushion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>bier</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>mat</characteristic><characteristic>cushion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A corpse rests on a bier in the lower half of the design. The
                            bier is covered with a sheet. The corpse lays on a partially rolled mat
                            or cushion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hands beside head</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair hovers above the corpse; she
                            likely represents the male figure's soul or spirit. She leans or arches
                            to the right above the corpse with her legs extended together down and
                            to the left. Her head is turned down and she looks at the corpse below.
                            Both arms are bent with her hands held beside her head and the palms
                            turned out towards the viewer; the fingers on both hands are slightly
                            spread.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.16.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.04" justify="center">The Soul hovering over the Body
                        reluctantly parting with Life.<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.05" justify="center"> _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _How
                        wishfully she looks<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.06" justify="center">On all she's leaving, now no longer
                            her's!<space extent="15"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.07.07" justify="center">London, Published May 1. 1808, by
                        Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.08" dbi="BB435.1.8-7.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The descent of Man into the Vale of Death.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 435.7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>26.5 x 13.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="590"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.11"/><related objectid="but638.1.wc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a cave-like valley (the "Vale" of the
                        title inscription) strewn with large stones. Several stairs and a path wind
                        between the stones; twenty-two figures appear along the pathway. Several
                        dark shadows appear on the stones, particularly along the left and right
                        borders. Distant mountains are visible through the mouth of the cave in the
                        upper portion of the design. Clouds appear in the sky above the mountains.
                        Two gowned females(?) stand in the upper left portion of the design. The
                        figure closest to the viewer stands with her right leg bent back; the pair
                        likely walks to the right. Both figures are slightly hunched over. The
                        figure closest to the viewer has her head down; both arms are bent and she
                        covers her face with her hands. The figure furthest from the viewer holds a
                        walking stick in her right hand. A gowned, bearded old man kneels or crawls
                        at the top of a set of stairs in the upper portion of the design. The figure
                        is bent over with his left knee drawn up to his chest. His left foot is
                        visible below the hem of his garment. His arms are down and both hands are
                        on the ground with the palms down; he may be bracing or supporting himself.
                        A gowned female carries an infant below and to the right of the stairs; only
                        her upper body is visible. Her right arm is bent and she holds the infant
                        with both hands; she is likely the infant's mother. The child sits in the
                        female's arms, facing left. Both legs are bent and its left arm is bent
                        upward; the infant may reach for or hold onto the female. A male figure with
                        long hair appears to the right of the mother and child. He is visible only
                        from the knees up; he appears to be running or walking to the right. His
                        left arm is raised horizontally and his right arm is raised at 45 degrees;
                        both palms are turned out, away from the figure's body. The figure may wear
                        a shirt. Cloth or other drapery appears over his right arm. The head and
                        shoulders of a male figure appear in the upper portion of the design along
                        the right border, to the right of the running male. The figure faces right
                        and is hunched over with his head down and his face in shadow; he may have a
                        beard. A male figure with long hair runs to the left in the upper right
                        portion of the design. The figure's left leg is bent forward and his right
                        leg is bent back; his arms are raised horizontally with the palms turned
                        out, away from his body. He may look towards the figures to the left. A
                        gowned female and old male with long hair and a beard stand immediately left
                        of the running male. The female faces forward with her head turned up and
                        slightly right. Her arms are bent and she clutches at the side of her head
                        with both hands; her posture and gesture may suggest grief or despair. The
                        male figure faces left with his shoulders slightly hunched and his head
                        down. Both feet are visible below the hem of his garment; he may walk to the
                        left. His arms are down and he holds a crutch in each hand; he leans
                        slightly forward onto the crutches. A gowned female with long hair stands
                        below and to the left of the male with crutches. She faces forward with her
                        head turned to the left in profile. The figure's arms are bent in front of
                        her chest; her hands are held together with the palms down. Her head is down
                        slightly and may rest on her hands. A male figure with short hair stands in
                        the lower portion of the design directly below the male holding crutches. He
                        walks to the right with his right leg is bent and his right foot raised on
                        tiptoe. His arms are bent in front of his chest with the hands held together
                        and the palms vertical; he may be praying. A gowned female holds an infant
                        in the lower right portion of the design. Her right leg is bent back with
                        her right foot raised on tiptoe; she walks to the right. The figure is
                        slightly hunched over. Her left arm is raised at 135 degrees with the palm
                        held vertically and the fingers spread. Her right arm is bent and she holds
                        an infant to her chest; she is likely its mother. The infant faces left with
                        its left arm raised; it may reach for or touch the female. A gowned female
                        stands in the lower right portion of the design. She wears a veil or other
                        cloth drapery over her hair. The figure stands facing forward with her head
                        turned to the left; she looks down at the children to the left. Both arms
                        are bent with the palms turned out toward the viewer and the fingers on her
                        left hand are spread. Seven gowned children stand to the left and right of
                        the gowned female in the lower portion of the design.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>valley</characteristic><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a cave-like valley (the "Vale" of the
                            title inscription) strewn with large stones. Several stairs and a path
                            wind between the stones; twenty-two figures appear along the pathway.
                            Several dark shadows appear on the stones, particularly along the left
                            and right borders.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Distant mountains are visible through the mouth of the cave in
                            the upper portion of the design. Clouds appear in the sky above the
                            mountains.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>walking stick</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned females(?) stand in the upper left portion of the
                            design. Each apparently has her hair drawn back in a bun. The figure
                            closest to the viewer stands with her right leg bent back; the pair
                            likely walks to the right. Both figures are slightly hunched over. The
                            figure closest to the viewer has her head down; both arms are bent and
                            she covers her face with her hands. The figure furthest from the viewer
                            holds a walking stick in her right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>crawling</characteristic><characteristic>bending</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>hands on ground</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>bracing</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned, bearded old man kneels or crawls at the top of a set
                            of stairs in the upper portion of the design. The figure is bent over
                            with his left knee drawn up to his chest. His left foot is visible below
                            the hem of his garment. His arms are down and both hands are on the
                            ground with the palms down; he may be bracing or supporting
                            himself.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female carries an infant in the upper right portion
                            of the design; only her upper body is visible. The female stands facing
                            right in profile with her hair drawn back in a bun. The figure's head is
                            turned down slightly and may touch the head of the infant. Her right arm
                            is bent and she holds the infant with both hands; she is likely the
                            infant's mother. The child sits in the female's arms, facing left. Both
                            legs are bent and its left arm is bent up; the infant may reach for or
                            hold onto the female. The infant is nude and has short, curly
                            hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure with long hair appears in the upper right
                            portion of the design. He is visible only from the knees up; he appears
                            to be running or walking to the right. His left arm is raised
                            horizontally and his right arm is raised at 45 degrees; both palms are
                            turned out, away from the figure's body. The figure may wear a shirt and
                            possibly tights. Cloth or other drapery appears over his right
                            arm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of a male figure appear in the upper
                            right portion of the design just inside the right border, right of the
                            running male. The figure faces right and is hunched over with his head
                            down and his face in shadow; he may have a beard. The figure appears to
                            wear a gown or other clothing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizonally</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure with long hair runs to the left in the upper
                            right portion of the design. He wears breeches. The figure's left leg is
                            bent forward and his right leg is bent back. His arms are raised
                            horizontally with the palms turned out, away from his body. He may look
                            towards the figures to the left. The fingers of his right hand are
                            slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands beside head</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female stands in the upper portion of the design to
                            the left of the running male. She faces forward with her head turned up
                            and slightly right. Her arms are bent and she clutches at the side of
                            her head with both hands. Her posture and gesture may suggest grief or
                            despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>crutch</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned male stands in the upper portion of the design to the
                            left of the running male. He is old with long hair and a beard. The
                            figure faces left with his shoulders slightly hunched over and his head
                            down. Both feet are visible below the hem of his garment; he may walk to
                            the left. His arms are down and he holds a crutch in each hand; he leans
                            slightly forward onto the crutches.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair stands below and to the left of
                            the male with crutches. She faces forward with her head turned to the
                            left in profile. The figure's arms are bent in front of her chest; her
                            hands are held together with the palms down. Her head is down slightly
                            and may rest on her hands.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure with short hair stands in the lower portion of
                            the design directly below the male holding crutches. The figure wears a
                            shirt, breeches, possibly stockings, and shoes. He walks to the right
                            with his right leg is bent and his right foot raised on tiptoe. His arms
                            are bent in front of his chest with the hands held together and the
                            palms vertical; he may be praying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female appears in the lower right portion of the
                            design. She may be wearing a cap or cloth head-covering of some sort.
                            Her right leg is bent back with her right foot raised on tiptoe; she
                            walks to the right. The figure is slightly hunched over. Her left arm is
                            raised at 135 degrees with the palm held vertically and the fingers
                            spread. Her right arm is bent and she holds an infant to her chest; she
                            is likely its mother. The infant faces left with its left arm raised; it
                            may reach for or touch the female.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>shoe</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female stands in the lower right portion of the
                            design. She wears a veil or other cloth drapery over her hair. The
                            figure stands facing forward with her head turned to the left; she looks
                            down at the children to the left. Her mouth is slightly open. The
                            figure's right foot is visible below the hem of her gown; she may wear
                            shoes. Both arms are bent with the palms turned out toward the viewer
                            and the fingers on her left hand are spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Seven gowned children stand in the lower portion of the design
                            to the left and right of a gowned female. The child furthest left is a
                            female with long hair. She faces left in profile. To the right, a female
                            child stands with her head turned up and to the right; she looks towards
                            the adult female in the center of the group. Both children's arms are
                            bent with the palms held together vertically in prayer. To the right,
                            the head of a male(?) child with short hair faces left in profile. To
                            the right of the adult figure, a child stands facing forward with his or
                            her eyes raised. The heads of two children are visible to the right. The
                            uppermost figure has long hair and faces left in profile; the lower
                            figure has short, curly hair and faces slightly left. The child furthest
                            right stands facing forward with his head turned up to the left. His
                            right arm is bent in front of his chest with the palm turned
                            down.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.08.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.21.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.08.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.08.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                    Schiavonetti.<note>The letters "on" in "Schiavonetti" did not
                                    print well in this copy.</note></l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.08.04" justify="center">The descent of Man into the Vale of
                            Death.<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.08.05" justify="center">...............'Tis here all
                            meet!<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.08.06" justify="center">London Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.09" dbi="BB435.1.9-8.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Day of Judgment.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 435.8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>30.0 x 22.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="650"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.12"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Christ sits enthroned in heaven in the upper central portion of
                        the design above a series of steps or stairs; the structure may represent an
                        altar. A halo of light surrounds Christ's head with beams of light radiating
                        outward. His arms are bent and rest at his sides; he holds an open book
                        across his lap. Two gowned, winged angels kneel on stones or cushions to the
                        left and right of Christ. Both angels hold pens or quills and may write on
                        tablets or books resting on (stone?) pillars. Eight gowned male figures sit
                        to the left and right of the central throne or altar in the upper portion of
                        the design. Each has long hair and a beard and wears a crown; they may
                        represent kings. The four figures to the left face left and the four figures
                        to the right face right. The two figures closest to the center each has a
                        scoll resting on his lap. A pair of gowned angels flies or hovers above
                        Christ on outstretched wings; each figure holds and plays a harp. Eight nude
                        infants or putti sit on a cloud above and to the left of Christ, and the
                        heads and shoulders of four old figures appear above and to the right of
                        Christ. Three angels hover or fly in the upper left portion of the design;
                        their wings are covered with small eyes or other circular designs. The
                        central angel holds a tray carrying two loaves of bread and two goblets or
                        chalices. The heads and shoulders of six figures appear directly below the
                        three winged angels; they may be hovering or flying. Below, three gowned
                        males with long hair and beards kneel on a cloud. The central figure's arms
                        are bent with the palms held together vertically in prayer; the figures to
                        the left and right cross their arms in front of their chests. A group of
                        indistinct figures appears to the left; only their heads are visible and
                        they may be seen from behind. Etched lines across the group may suggest that
                        they are in shadow. A gowned couple appears below; the figures face each
                        other and embrace with their arms slightly bent and raised horizontally. Two
                        gowned figures with braided hair kneel or crouch on a cloud below the
                        embracing couple. The figure to the left grasps the upper corners of an open
                        book while the figure to the right supports it from the bottom with his or
                        her palms turned up. Two gowned angels with short, curly hair fly or hover
                        in the upper right portion of the design; their wings are covered with small
                        eyes or other circular designs. The angel to the right holds a large pitcher
                        with both hands; the angel to the left likely holds the second pitcher.
                        Liquid pours from both pitchers into a bowl held by at least one of the four
                        nude children or putti below; the child furthest left is positioned with his
                        legs spread and his left leg extended backward. Three gowned females kneel
                        on a cloud below the group of angels. The figure furthest left may have her
                        breasts exposed; a nude infant or child stands below the figure and reaches
                        upward with his or her arms raised vertically. The central female cradles a
                        swaddled infant with her left arm. The female furthest right wears a veil or
                        scarf over her head. Her left arm is extended downward and she may touch the
                        hip of a nude child to the right; the child stands facing left with his legs
                        bent and feet raised on tiptoe. Two nude children sit or kneel to the right
                        of the gowned females; the figures embrace and may kiss. A group of
                        indistinct figures appears above the embracing couple; only the figures'
                        heads are visible and they may be in shadow. A nude child with short hair
                        flies or hovers below the female figures; the figure is seen from behind
                        with its body nearly horizontal and its legs extended to the right. Two
                        gowned figures appear in the upper right portion of the design, below and to
                        the right of the kneeling females. The figures face each other and embrace
                        with their arms bent and wrapped around each other; they appear to be
                        kissing. Two gowned males with short hair kneel on a cloud below the
                        embracing couple; the figure to the right holds the upper corners of an open
                        book while the figure to the left supports it from the bottom with his palms
                        turned up. Two bearded males kneel on a cloud below and to the right of the
                        figures holding a book. Three nude angels stand on a stone in the lower
                        portion of the design, directly below Christ; they likely represent
                        seraphim. Fire surrounds the seraphim and extends upward to the base of
                        Christ's throne or altar. Flames are also visible among the stones or
                        mountains to the left and right. The central seraph has three pairs of
                        wings. His arms are bent upward and he holds and plays a trumpet with both
                        hands. Two additional trumpets appear above and to the left and right of the
                        central seraph, each held by a single disembodied hand; the bells of all
                        three trumpets are filled with fire. The seraphim to the left and right have
                        at least two pairs of wings and each hold a sheathed sword. Four males
                        appear below the three seraphim in the lower portion of the design; the
                        figures may be partially buried. Only the head of the figure furthest left
                        is visible. The figure to the right turns his head up and to the right; his
                        eyes are raised and his expression may suggest fear. The figure third from
                        the left is seen from behind; his arms are raised horizontally and his hands
                        rest on figures to the left and right. The figure furthest right crouches or
                        kneels with his body horizontal and his head down. Both arms are bent upward
                        and wrap around his head and his hands rest on the back of his head. The
                        heads of two figures appear within a cave in the lower right portion of the
                        design. A serpent, lizard, or dragon appears in the lower right corner of
                        the design; only its head and a single leg are visible. The animal faces
                        right with its mouth open and teeth visible. A nude female with long hair
                        kneels or crouches in a twisted posture in the lower right corner of the
                        design; her arms are bent and at least her left hand may clutch at her head.
                        Six figures, or a single figure with six heads, stands in the lower right
                        corner of the design, above the nude female; the figure is seen from behind
                        and is covered with scales. Only the head furthest left is clearly visible;
                        a large curved horn grows from its forehead. Two figures lay on stones above
                        and to the left of the multi-headed figure. The lower figure rests upside
                        down with his arms bent to either side of his head; the upper figure’s head
                        is down and the he appears to lie in a prone position on top of the lower
                        figure's left leg. A group of figures appears above the multi-headed figure,
                        extending from the right border towards the center of the design. Several
                        figures wear helmets and armor; they may be soldiers or knights. As many as
                        seven spears are visible, and a circular object directly above the
                        multi-headed figure may represent a shield. A gowned figure with long hair
                        stands third from the right. The figure's arms are bent upward with the
                        hands held beside his or her face; the figure's mouth is open and the
                        expression suggests fear. Further left, the figures become less distinctive
                        and only their heads are visible. A building with a domed roof appears in
                        shadow just left of the group. Eight nude males fall below and to the right
                        of Christ's throne; six of the figures are upside down, and five are seen
                        from behind. A snake is wrapped around the body of the lowest figure in the
                        group. The figure furthest right, probably a devil, hovers with his body
                        positioned horizontally and his head to the right. His right arm is wrapped
                        around the waist of the figure to the left; in his left hand he holds a
                        chain that may be attached to the other figure's head or neck. The upper
                        bodies of four figures appear in the lower left portion of the design, just
                        left of the seraphim; they may represent a family. A gowned female with long
                        hair appears furthest left; her right arm is bent and may rest on the rock
                        below. A gowned male with long hair and a beard appears to the right; he
                        embraces or touches the other three figures. Below, a nude figure of
                        indeterminate gender is seen from behind. To the right, a nude male faces
                        right with his left arm raised vertically. The heads of at least three
                        figures appear in the lower left corner of the design; all three face right
                        with their eyes raised. A nude couple sits or kneels on a stone in the lower
                        left portion of the design. The female (left) is seen from behind; her arms
                        are raised and likely wrap around her partner’s neck. The male (right) holds
                        the female’s left hip and right buttock. The figures’ heads are together and
                        they are likely kissing. The heads of at least three figures are visible to
                        the left of the embracing couple; they face forward and slightly right with
                        their heads turned up. A nude female with long hair hovers or stands on a
                        stone to the left of the seraphim. Her right arm is bent and she holds a
                        nude infant against her chest; the infant’s right arm is raised horizontally
                        and may reach upwards towards its mother's face or hair. The female figure's
                        left arm is raised at 135 degrees and her left hand touches a nude male to
                        the right. He is seen from behind and faces away with his head turned to the
                        left; he likely looks towards the female to the left. A gowned male with
                        long hair and beard stands or hovers between the two figures; his arms are
                        not visible, but the position of his hands suggests that they are raised at
                        45 degrees. Ten figures hover in the lower left portion of the design; they
                        may rise upward. A gowned female with her hair drawn back in a bun is seen
                        from behind and faces away with her head turned up and to the right; her
                        arms are raised vertically with the palms turned away from the viewer and
                        the fingers spread. Above, a nude male(?) with short hair holds his arms
                        down at his sides; his left hand may touch the female figure below. The head
                        and arms of a figure are seen from behind near the left border of the
                        design; his or her arms are raised vertically with the hands held together
                        in prayer. Above, a gowned female(?) with long hair is seen from behind; she
                        may be slightly hunched over with her head down. To the right, a nude male
                        with short, curly hair raises his right arm vertically with the palm turned
                        out toward the viewer; his left hand touches or embraces the left hip of the
                        female to the right. The female’s arms are bent with the palms held together
                        vertically; she may be praying. A gowned female with long hair raises her
                        right arm at 135 degrees with the palm turned slightly out toward the
                        viewer; her left arm is only partially visible and appears to be raised at
                        45 degrees. Two nude infants hover below and to the left of Christ's throne.
                        The infant to the left faces forward with his genitals exposed; the infant
                        to the right is seen from behind with his or her arms raised at 135 degrees
                        and the hands held together in prayer. A nude male with short hair hovers
                        below and to the left of Christ's throne; he is seen from behind and faces
                        away from the viewer with his head turned up and slightly right. Both arms
                        are raised at approximately 135 degrees and his hands are held together in
                        prayer.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least one column of clouds fills the upper left portion of
                            the design. The two figures holding a book sit or kneel on the lower
                            reaches of the cloud. Another cloud supports the infants or putti above
                            and to the left of Christ, and yet another supports the three bearded
                            men further to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least one column of clouds fills the upper right portion of
                            the design. The two figures holding a book sit or kneel on the lower
                            reaches of the cloud or on another cloud projecting horizontally from
                            the right margin of the design. Another cloud support the elders above
                            and to the right of Christ, and yet another supports the women and
                            children further to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>thorn</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Christ sits in the upper central portion of the design; he
                            faces forward with his head turned slightly to the left. He is gowned
                            and has long, curly hair and a beard. He may wear a vine-like crown (of
                            thorns?) on his head. A halo of light surrounds his head, with beams of
                            light radiating outward. Christ's right foot is visible below the edge
                            of his gown. His arms are bent and rest at his sides; he holds an open
                            book across his lap.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pen</characteristic><characteristic>quill</characteristic><characteristic>tablet</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>writing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned, winged angels kneel on cushions or stones to the
                            left and right of Christ. The figure to the left faces left; his left
                            leg is bent and left foot visible. He has short, possibly curly hair.
                            His left arm is bent and may rest on a short pillar to the left; he
                            holds a book or tablet in his left hand. His right arm is not visible,
                            but is likely bent; he holds a pen or quill in his right hand and may be
                            writing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pen</characteristic><characteristic>quill</characteristic><characteristic>tablet</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>writing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned, winged angels kneel on stones or cushions to the
                            left and right of Christ. The figure to the right faces right; his right
                            leg is bent and right foot visible. He may have his hair drawn back; a
                            single long lock falls down his neck and shoulder. The figure's right
                            arm is bent and he holds a pen or quill in his right hand; his hand
                            rests on a tablet or open book and he may be writing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="AB"><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><characteristic>throne</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>cushion</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>altar</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Christ sits enthroned in heaven above a series of steps or
                            stairs. The two angels to the left and right of Christ may kneel on
                            stones or cushions and they rest their arms on two small pillars. The
                            structures may represent altars.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight gowned male figures sit to the left and right of the
                            central altar in the upper portion of the design. Each has long hair, a
                            beard, and wears a crown; they may represent kings. The four figures to
                            the left face left and the four figures to the right face right. The two
                            figures closest to the center each has a scoll resting on his
                            lap.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>harp</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A pair of gowned angels flies or hovers above Christ on
                            outstretched wings. The tips of their wings may be touching. Each figure
                            holds and plays a harp. The figure to the left faces left and has long
                            hair; the figure to the right faces right and has short, possibly curly
                            hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>putto</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude infants or putti sit or kneel on a cloud above and
                            to the left of Christ. Several figures are partially obscured so that
                            only their heads are visible. The figure third from the left may point
                            downward with his right hand; his head is turned slightly up and he may
                            look at the winged angel above and to the right. To the right, a figure
                            faces left in profile. The infant or putto furthest right has his head
                            turned down and to the right; he may look at Christ. All the figures
                            appear to be bald.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>clothing</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The heads and shoulders of four figures appear above and to
                            the right of Christ; they may rest on a cloud. The three lower figures
                            are old, bearded males; they face right and wear gowns or other
                            clothing. The figure furthest left may have his mouth open. The central
                            figure has short hair, and the figure to the right has long hair. The
                            figure above is partially obscured and is of indeterminate
                            gender.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>chalice</characteristic><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three angels hover or fly above and to the left of Christ. Two
                            wings are visible to the left and right of the figures and two extend up
                            and to the right; the wings are covered with small eyes or other
                            circular designs. Only the head of the figure furthest left is visible;
                            he faces left in profile. The two angels to the right face forward with
                            their heads turned to the right. The central figure is visible from the
                            waist up. He is bearded and wears a gown. His arms are bent and his left
                            palm is turned up. He holds a tray or plate with both hands; two loaves
                            of bread and two goblets or chalices rest on the tray. The figure to the
                            right is partially obscured; only his head and left arm are visible. His
                            left arm is bent with the palm turned up; he holds a tray or
                            plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The heads and shoulders of six figures appear in the upper
                            left corner of the design, directly below the three winged angels; they
                            may be hovering or flying. The first and fourth figures from the left
                            have long hair; the other figures have short hair, and the figures fifth
                            and sixth from the left have curly hair. Below, three gowned males kneel
                            on a cloud. Each of the three figures has long hair and a beard. The
                            central figure's arms are bent upward with the palms held together
                            vertically in prayer. The figures to the left and right cross their arms
                            in front of their chests. All nine figures face right. A large group of
                            indistinct figures appears to the left; only their heads are visible and
                            they may be seen from behind. Etched lines across the group may suggest
                            that they are in shadow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned couple appears to the left of Christ; only their
                            upper bodies are clearly visible. Both figures have long hair. The
                            figure to the right is probably female; the figure to the left may be
                            male. The figures face each other and embrace with their arms slightly
                            bent and raised horizontally. They may kiss.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>braid</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned figures kneel or crouch on a cloud below an
                            embracing couple. Both figures, perhaps females, have long hair that may
                            be drawn back into braids. They face slightly left and may look at the
                            figures below. The right foot of the figure to the left and the left
                            foot of the figure to the right are visible. The figures hold an open
                            book in front of their chests, facing out towards the viewer. The figure
                            to the left grasps the upper corners of the book while the figure to the
                            right supports it from the bottom with his or her palms turned
                            up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pitcher</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>putto</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>bowl</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned angels with short, curly hair fly or hover in the
                            upper right portion of the design. Two wings are visible to the left and
                            right of the figures and two extend up and to the left; the wings are
                            covered with small eyes or other circular designs. The figures face left
                            with their heads turned slightly down; they may look downward. The angel
                            to the right holds a large pitcher with both hands; his right hand
                            grasps the handle while his left arm is bent and cradles the pitcher
                            from below. The angel to the left likely holds the other pitcher. Liquid
                            pours from both pitchers into a bowl held by at least one of the four
                            nude children below. The children or putti fly or hover below and to the
                            left of the winged angels. They face left with their heads turned up and
                            away from the viewer. The figure furthest left is positioned with his
                            legs spread and his left leg extended backward. His left arm is raised
                            horizontally and extends to the left; his left palm is turned up and
                            supports the bowl. The two infants or putti to the right also extend
                            their left legs backward; only the upper body of the figure furthest
                            right is visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>swaddled</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three gowned females kneel on a cloud in the upper right
                            portion of the design, below the group of angels. The figure furthest
                            left may have her breasts exposed. A nude infant or child stands below
                            the figure; the child is seen from behind and reaches upward with his or
                            her arms raised vertically. The central female cradles a swaddled infant
                            with her left arm. The female furthest right wears a veil or scarf over
                            her head. Her torso is twisted to the right and her left arm is extended
                            downward; she may touch the hip of a nude child to the right. Her left
                            hand is visible to the right of the child with the palm turned out
                            towards the viewer. The child stands facing left with his legs bent and
                            feet raised on tiptoe. His left arm is bent upward and his left hand may
                            touch the female's neck. The child has short, curly hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two nude children appear to the right of the three gowned
                            females. The figure to the left is seen from behind and may be sitting.
                            His or her right arm is raised at approximately 135 degrees and touches
                            or embraces the figure to the right. The figure to the right may be
                            kneeling with his or her left leg bent. The figure's left arm is raised
                            at approximately 45 degrees and touches or embraces the figure to the
                            left. Both figures have short hair. Their heads are together and they
                            may kiss. A group of indistinct figures appears above the embracing
                            couple; only the figures' heads are visible. Etched lines across the
                            group may suggest that they are in shadow. Only one figure clearly faces
                            forward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>putto</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horzontally</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><illusobjdesc> A nude child with short hair flies or hovers below the female
                            figures; it may represent a putto. The figure is seen from behind with
                            its body nearly horizontal and its legs (or at least its left leg)
                            extended to the right and its head turned in the same direction. The
                            figure's arms are raised horizontally with the left palm turned away
                            from the viewer and the right palm turned down. The fingers of the left
                            hand may be spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned figures appear in the upper right portion of the
                            design, below and to the right of the kneeling females with infants. The
                            figures face each other and embrace with their arms bent and wrapped
                            around each other. They appear to be kissing. The figure to the right,
                            with a curling lock of hair descending down the back, is probably
                            female; the figure to the left, with short hair, is probably
                            male.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned males kneel on a cloud to the right of Christ's
                            altar. Both figures have short hair and the figure to the left has a
                            beard. Each figure kneels with a single leg drawn up. The leftmost
                            figure's right arm is down and he holds or supports the bottom of an
                            open book with both hands. The rightmost figure holds the top corners of
                            the book with both hands. Both figures face forward with their heads
                            turned to the left. The figure on the left may be old.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bending</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two bearded males, both probably old, kneel on a cloud in the
                            central right portion of the design, below and to the right of figures
                            holding a book. Both figures are gowned and face left. The figure to the
                            right kneels with his legs spread apart and his body bent slightly
                            forward. The figure's head is turned up slightly. His right arm is bent
                            with his hand positioned in front of his chest; he may point to the
                            right with the extended index finger. His left arm is bent upwards with
                            the hand held above his hand and the palm down, fingers slightly spread.
                            The figure to the left raises his right arm horizontally with the hand
                            turned upside down and the palm nearly vertical. The figure's left hand
                            is pictured to the right of his companion, indicating that his left arm
                            is also raised horizontally, and with the right palm turned
                            down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three angels stand in the lower portion of the design,
                            directly below Christ; they likely represent seraphim. They are nude,
                            except for wings partly covering their loins. The central angel faces
                            forward with his head turned up and his eyes raised. The figure has
                            three pairs of wings; his central wings may touch those of the figures
                            to the left and right. His hair appears to be curly and perhaps slightly
                            flame-like; both feet are clearly pictured. His arms are bent upward; he
                            holds and plays a trumpet or musical horn with both hands. The fingers
                            on his right hand are slightly spread. Fire appears in the bell of the
                            trumpet.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two additional trumpets or musical horns appear above and to
                            the left and right of the central seraph, each held by a single
                            disembodied hand; the fingers on each hand are spread. The bells of the
                            trumpets are filled with fire.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>sheath</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three angels stand in the lower portion of the design,
                            directly below Christ; they likely represent seraphim. They are nude,
                            except for wings partly covering their loins. The leftmost angel faces
                            left with his upper body turned slightly away from the viewer. He may
                            have at least two pairs of wings; his upper wing may touch the wing of
                            the figure to the right. His left arm is down at his side and holds the
                            blade or sheath of a sword. His right hand rests on the sword's hilt
                            with the palm down. His hair is curly and his left foot is
                            prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>sheath</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three angels stand in the lower portion of the design,
                            directly below Christ; they likely represent seraphim. They are nude,
                            except for wings partly covering their loins. The rightmost angel faces
                            right. He may have at least two pairs of wings; his upper wing may touch
                            the wing of the figure to the left. His right arm is bent down and he
                            holds the hilt of a sword in his right hand. His left hand grasps the
                            sheath or possibly the blade of the sword. His hair is curly; both feet
                            are clearly pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>hell</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The three seraphim stand on a stone or mound in the lower
                            portion of the design. Other dark stones or mountains appear to the left
                            and right. Fire surrounds the seraphim and extends upward to the base of
                            Christ's throne or altar. Flames (of hell?) are also visible among the
                            stones to the left and right. The opening of a small cave is visible
                            below and to the right of the seraphim.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>buried</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four males appear below the three seraphim in the lower
                            portion of the design. Only the head of the figure furthest left is
                            visible; his body may be buried in the earth. He is bald and has a
                            beard. He faces forward and may look out towards the
                            viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>buried</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four males appear below the three seraphim in the lower
                            portion of the design. The figure second from the left is nude and has
                            short hair. He faces left with his head turned up and to the right; his
                            eyes are raised and his expression may suggest fear. The figure's left
                            leg is bent sharply upward and likely touches the figure to the right.
                            His left arm is at his side. He may be partially buried.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>buried</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four males appear below the three seraphim in the lower
                            portion of the design. The figure third from the left is nude and bald;
                            he is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer with his head
                            turned down and to the left. His body is slightly twisted with his hips
                            facing down and to the right, buttocks prominent. The figure's legs are
                            not visible; he may be partially buried. His arms are raised
                            horizontally with the palms turned down. His left hand rests on the head
                            of the bald figure to the left; his right hand rests on the back or
                            shoulder of the figure to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>buried</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four males appear below the three seraphim in the lower
                            portion of the design. The figure furthest right is nude and has short
                            hair. He crouches or kneels with his body horizontal and his head down.
                            The figure's right leg is bent; his left leg is not visible. Both arms
                            are bent upward and wrap around his head; his hands rest on the back of
                            his head. He may be partially buried.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>bending</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female with long hair kneels or crouches in the lower
                            right corner of the design. Both legs are bent and her right leg is
                            drawn up toward her chest. She faces right with her head turned up and
                            to the left; her torso is twisted forward with her breasts clearly
                            exposed. Her arms are bent and at least her left hand may clutch at her
                            head. Her right hand may be beside or behind her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>dragon</characteristic><characteristic>lizard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A serpent, lizard, or dragon appears in the lower right corner
                            of the design; only its head and a single leg are visible. The animal
                            faces right with its mouth open and teeth visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>heads, multiple</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Six figures, or a single figure with six heads, stand in the
                            lower right corner of the design. The figure is covered in scales or
                            wears scale-like armor. It is seen from behind with its torso twisted
                            away from the viewer and its heads turned up and to the left. Only the
                            head furthest left is clearly visible; a large curved horn grows from
                            its forehead. Its mouth is open and its eyes are raised; its expression
                            may suggest fear or surprise. The figure may run or flee to the right;
                            its right leg is bent with the right foot raised on tiptoe. The figure's
                            left arm is bent upward with the palm turned away from the viewer and
                            the fingers spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>hands beside head</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The heads of two figures appear within a cave in the lower
                            right portion of the design. The figure to the left faces right with its
                            head turned up. The figure has long hair and its mouth is open. Both
                            hands are raised beside the figure's head with the palms turned out
                            towards the viewer. The figure to the right faces slightly left. The
                            figure may have a beard.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms resting</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two figures lay on stones above and to the left of the
                            multi-headed figure. The lower figurea nude maleis upside down. His
                            arms are bent and rest on the stone to either side of his head; though
                            not clearly pictured, his hands may clutch at his head. His right leg is
                            twisted to the left and may be bent; his left leg is not pictured. Only
                            the head and shoulders of the upper figure are visible. His(?) head is
                            down and the figure appears to lay in a prone position on top of the
                            lower figure's left leg.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>knight</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>spear</characteristic><characteristic>shield</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands beside head</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of figures appears above the multi-headed figure,
                            extending from the right border towards the center of the design. The
                            figures first, second, and fourth from the right wear helmets and may be
                            soldiers or knights. The fourth and fifth figures from the right may
                            also to wear armor. Though their hands are not visible, the figures
                            likely hold the spears visible above; a circular object directly above
                            the multi-headed figure and behind his raised left hand may represent a
                            shield. A gowned figure with long hair stands third from the right. The
                            figure's arms are bent upward with the hands held beside his or her
                            face. The figure's mouth is open and the expression suggests fear. The
                            figures may be fleeing to the right. Further left, the figures become
                            less distinctive; at least one figure faces forward and to the
                            left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="D"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>church</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>dome</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>classical art</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The suggestion of a building with a domed roof appears in the
                            lower right portion of the design, to the right of the group of
                            seraphim. It may have a vertical element, such as a spire, at the top of
                            the dome. This may be a church, although the architecture also suggests
                            classical art.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure furthest left in the upper row is upside down and seen
                            from behind. He is partially obscured by the figure to the right. Both
                            legs are bent with the soles of his feet turned out towards the viewer.
                            His right arm is bent and wrapped around his head; he may clutch his
                            head with his right hand. His head is likely bent back as his face
                            points downward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure second from the left in the upper row is upside down
                            and faces forward. Both legs are bent and drawn up toward his chest. His
                            head is bent back and turned to the right. The figure's arms are both
                            bent and wrap around his head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure third from the left in the upper row is upside down
                            and seen from behind. He has long hair and his head is bent back. Both
                            of his arms are raised vertically with respect to his body and extend
                            downward; his palms are turned down with the fingers slightly spread.
                            The figure's right leg is bent; his left leg is not pictured. His
                            buttocks are prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure fourth from the left in the upper row falls in a
                            contracted position with his legs bent and his back hunched forward. He
                            faces slightly right with his head turned down. His hair is short. Both
                            arms are bent and his hands cover his face.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The upper body of the figure in the lower row, furthest left, is
                            surrounded by fire. The figure is upside down and seen from behind. He
                            falls diagonally down and to the right. Both arms are bent with the
                            hands clasped together and fingers interwined; he may be praying. His
                            hair is short.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>encircling</characteristic><characteristic>coil</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure second from the left in the lower row is upside down
                            and faces forward with his head bent back. His right leg is bent and his
                            left leg extends upward. Both arms are likely behind his back and may be
                            bound by a snake. The snake is coiled around the figure's left leg and
                            hips; its head faces up to the right of the figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>feet touching</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure third from the left in the lower row is upside down
                            and seen from behind, buttocks prominent. His legs are bent with his
                            hips twisted to the left; the soles of his feet face out towards the
                            viewer and may touch each other at the heels. His head is down. Both
                            arms are bent and wrap around his head. The figure may be chained; a
                            large chain with several links extends from the figure's head or neck to
                            the figure furthest right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>devil</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight nude males fall below and to the right of Christ's
                            altar. The figure furthest right falls or hovers with his body
                            horizontal and his head to the right. His right leg is apparently bent
                            and his left leg is extended to the left. Both arms are bent. His right
                            arm is wrapped around the waist of the figure to the left; in his left
                            hand he holds a chain that is likely attached to the other figure's head
                            or neck. He has short hair and his eyes are cast down; he likely looks
                            at the figure to the left. He may be a devil with slightly spiky
                            hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The upper bodies of four figures appear in the lower left
                            portion of the design, just left of the seraphim; they may represent a
                            family. A gowned female with long hair appears furthest left. She faces
                            right with her head turned up and her eyes raised; she may look up
                            towards Christ or the seraphim. Her right arm is bent and may rest on
                            the rock below. Her right hand may rest on her breasts.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>man</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>clothing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>encircling</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The upper bodies of four figures appear in the lower left
                            portion of the design, just left of the seraphim; they may represent a
                            family. A gowned old man with long hair and a beard is second from the
                            left. He faces right with his head turned up and his eyes raised; he may
                            look towards Christ or the seraphim. He embraces the other three
                            figures. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and he touches or holds
                            the female's right elbow; his left arm likely wraps around the male
                            figure to the right with his hand touching the back of the figure
                            below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The upper bodies of four figures appear in the lower left
                            portion of the design, just left of the seraphim; they may represent a
                            family. A nude figure, probably female, with long hair appears below the
                            bearded male. The figure is seen from behind and faces left with his or
                            her head turned up; the figure may look up toward the female to the
                            left. The figure's left arm is bent and rests on the rock below; the
                            right arm is raised at 135 degrees with the palm turned slightly up and
                            away from the viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The upper bodies of four figures appear in the lower left
                            portion of the design, just left of the seraphim; they may represent a
                            family. The figure furthest right is a nude male with short hair. He
                            faces right with his head turned up. His mouth is open and his eyes are
                            raised; he may look towards Christ or the seraphim. The figure's left
                            arm is raised vertically with the palm turned up; his right arm is not
                            visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The heads of at least three figures appear in the lower left
                            corner of the design. The lowest head is bearded and may have long hair.
                            All three face right and up with their eyes raised. The heads are
                            heavily shadowed. A fourth head may appear just left of the central
                            figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude couple sits or kneels on a stone in the lower left
                            portion of the design. The figure to the left is likely female; she is
                            seen from behind, buttocks prominent, and her hair is drawn back in a
                            bun. Her left leg is bent with her left foot raised on tiptoe. Her arms
                            are raised and likely wrap around the male figure's neck. She faces away
                            with her torso slightly twisted and her head turned up and to the right;
                            she kisses the male figure to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude couple sits or kneels on a stone in the lower left
                            portion of the design. The figure to the right is likely male; he faces
                            forward with his head turned down and to the left. He kisses the female
                            figure. He kneels with his left leg bent beneath him; his right leg is
                            not visible. Both arms are down; he holds the female's left hip and
                            right buttock.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The heads of at least three figures, but perhaps as many as
                            six, are visible in the lower left portion of the design, just left of
                            the embracing couple. The figures face forward and slightly right with
                            their heads turned up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female with long hair hovers just above, or stands on,
                            a stone to the left of the seraphim. She faces forward with her left
                            breast exposed. Her legs are together, with the right ankle crossing
                            over the left; her left leg is slightly bent. Her head is turned to the
                            right. The figure's left arm is raised at 135 degrees; her left hand
                            touches the right shoulder of the nude male to the right. Her right arm
                            is bent and she holds a nude infant against her chest. She may be the
                            infant's mother. The infant is seen from behind and has short, curly
                            hair. The infant's right leg is bent and its left leg extends downward.
                            His or her right arm is raised horizontally and may reach upwards
                            towards its mother's face or hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned old man with long hair and a beard stands or hovers
                            to the left of the seraphim. He faces forward, between the female
                            holding an infant and the male seen from behind. His eyes are raised.
                            His arms are not visible, but the position of his hands suggests that
                            they are raised at 45 degrees. His palms are turned slightly down,
                            perhaps with fingers slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>family</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short, curly hair stands or kneels on stones
                            to the left of the seraphim. He is seen from behind, buttocks prominent,
                            and faces away with his head turned to the left; he likely looks towards
                            the female to the left. The figure's right leg is bent, with his right
                            foot prominent, and his left leg is extended down and to the left. Both
                            feet are raised on tiptoe. His left arm is slightly bent and it is
                            positioned down at his side with the palm turned away from the viewer.
                            His right arm is raised vertically with the palm turned up. Taken
                            together, this figure, the old man, and the woman holding an infant may
                            be a family.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with her hair drawn back in a bun hovers along
                            the left border of the design. She may be rising upward. She is seen
                            from behind and faces away with her head turned up and to the right. Her
                            eyes are raised and she may look up towards the figures above. The
                            figure's legs are positioned together and both feet are visible below
                            the hem of her garment. Her arms are raised vertically with the palms
                            turned up and away from the viewer and the fingers
                            spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male(?) with short hair hovers along the left border of
                            the design. He may be rising upward. He faces forward with his head
                            turned up and to the right; his eyes are raised and he may look up
                            towards the figures above. The figure's right leg is bent. Both arms are
                            down at his sides. His left hand may touch the female figure below; his
                            right hand is in shadow and the fingers are spread. His feet are
                            prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>arm</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>prayer</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The head and arms of a figure are visible near the left border
                            of the design, behind and above the rising man and gowned female. The
                            figure is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer. His or her
                            arms are raised vertically with the hands held together and the palms
                            vertical as if in prayer. This figure may also be rising.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female(?) with long hair hovers along the left border
                            of the design, below and to the left of two figures holding an open
                            book. She may be rising upward. The figure is seen from behind and is
                            turned slightly to the right. Her right leg is bent and the right foot
                            is visible beneath the hem of her gown. Her right arm is bent and is
                            visible only to the elbow. The figure may be slightly hunched over with
                            her head down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short, curly hair hovers next to a gowned
                            female in the central left portion of the design. He may rise upward. He
                            faces forward with his genitals exposed. His head is turned up and to
                            the right with his eyes raised; he likely looks up toward Christ. The
                            figure's legs are together but apparently crossed at the ankles; only
                            his right foot is visible. His right arm is raised vertically with the
                            palm turned out toward the viewer. His left hand touches or embraces the
                            left hip of the female to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair hovers next to a nude male in
                            the central left portion of the design. She may rise upward. She faces
                            forward and right with her head turned up and her eyes raised; she may
                            look up toward Christ. The figure's legs are together and both feet are
                            visible below the hem of her gown. Her arms are bent with the palms held
                            together vertically; she may be praying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair hovers below and to the left of
                            Christ's altar. She may rise upward. She faces right with her head
                            turned to the left; she looks at the female figure to the left. The
                            figure's right arm is raised at 135 degrees with the palm turned
                            slightly out toward the viewer and the fingers spread. Her left arm is
                            only partially visible and appears to be raised at 45
                            degrees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two nude infants hover below and to the left of Christ's
                            altar. The infant to the left is male; he faces forward with his
                            genitals exposed. The figure's arms are raised at 135 degrees with the
                            palms turned up. His head is turned up and he has short, curly hair. The
                            figure may rise upward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two nude infants hover below and to the left of Christ's
                            altar. The infant to the right is seen partly from behind and faces to
                            the right. He or she has short, slightly curly hair. The figure may rise
                            upward. The figure's arms are raised at 135 degrees and extend to the
                            right with the hands held together in prayer. The infant may reach
                            toward Christ.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short hair hovers below and to the left of
                            Christ's altar. He is seen from behind, buttocks prominent, and faces
                            away from the viewer with his head turned up and slightly right. He may
                            rise upward. The figure's right leg is bent back with the sole of his
                            foot turned out toward the viewer. His right arm is slightly bent. Both
                            arms are raised vertically and extend up and to the right; his hands are
                            held together in prayer. The figure may reach toward
                            Christ.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.09.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.28.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.09.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.09.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.09.04" justify="center">The Day of Judgment.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.09.05" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.10" dbi="BB435.1.10-9.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Soul exploring the recesses of the grave.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber><objcode code="B9">(Bentley 435.9)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>26.0 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="590"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.20"/><related objectid="but629.1.penc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A cave or tomb of stone (the "Grave" of the inscription) dominates
                        the lower portion of the design. A shadow appears in the lower right corner
                        of the cave. A gowned female stands within the cave; the figure is
                        identified in the inscription as a representation of the soul. The figure is
                        seen from behind and faces away with her head turned to the right. Her hair
                        is drawn back in a braided bun. Both feet are visible and her left foot is
                        raised on tiptoe; she is probably walking away from the viewer. Her arms are
                        bent and she holds a candle in her right hand; the candle is burning and the
                        flame creates a halo of light. The figure casts a shadow below and to the
                        left. She may look down and to the right toward a corpse of a male(?)
                        figure. The corpse lies on the ground in a supine position, perhaps partly
                        sunk into a shallow grave; the body is horizontal with the head to the
                        right. The figure appears to be gowned or shrouded and wears a plumed
                        helmet; he may be a knight or soldier. The figure's eyes are closed. A fire
                        burns above the corpse. A male with short, curly hair stands above the cave.
                        The figure is partly nude and wears short pants. Both legs are bent and are
                        spread apart. His body faces forward with his head turned down to the left;
                        his torso is twisted and bends to the left. The figure's arms are bent to
                        the right with the palms held vertically. His eyes are cast down and he may
                        be looking at the ground or the figure below; his mouth is open and his
                        expression suggests fear or surprise. A series of distant mountains appears
                        to the left and right of the male figure. A group of buildings to the right
                        of the male figure's left foot suggests a distant city. The city may be
                        walled. Perhaps four windows are visible on the lowest building or wall. A
                        triangular spire or pyramid rises above the other buildings. A crescent moon
                        appears in the sky between the male figure's legs.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>grave</characteristic><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>grave</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A cave or tomb (the "Grave" of the inscription) of stone
                            dominates the lower portion of the design. A shadow appears in the lower
                            right corner of the cave. The body lying within the cave may be partly
                            sunk into a shallow grave.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>braid</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>candle</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female stands in a cave in the lower portion of the
                            design; the figure is identified in the inscription as a representation
                            of the soul. The figure is seen from behind and faces away with her head
                            turned to the right. Her hair is drawn back in a braided bun. Her left
                            leg is bent back and crosses behind her right. Both feet are visible and
                            her left foot is raised on tiptoe; she is probably walking away from the
                            viewer. Both arms are bent and she holds a candle in her right hand; the
                            candle is burning and the flame creates a halo of light. The figure
                            casts a shadow below and to the left. She may look down and to the right
                            toward a corpse.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>plume</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>knight</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a male(?) figure lies supine in the lower
                            portion of the design. The figure's body is horizontal with his head to
                            the right, perhaps sunk partly into a shallow grave. The figure appears
                            to be gowned or shrouded and wears a plumed helmet; he may be a knight
                            or soldier. The figure's eyes are closed.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A fire burns above the corpse in the lower half of the
                            design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>bending</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male with short, curly hair stands in the upper portion of
                            the design. The figure is partly nude and wears short pants. Both legs
                            are bent and are spread apart. His body faces forward with his head
                            turned down to the left; his torso is twisted and bends to the left. The
                            figure's arms are bent to the right with the palms held vertically,
                            fingers slightly spread. His eyes are cast down and he may be looking at
                            the ground or the figure below; his mouth is open, with teeth visible,
                            and his expression suggests fear or surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A series of distant mountains appears to the left and right of
                            the male figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>crescent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A crescent moon appears in the sky between the male figure's
                            legs.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="B"><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>triangle</characteristic><characteristic>pyramid</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of buildings to the right of the male figure's left
                            foot suggests a distant city. The city may be walled. Perhaps four
                            windows are visible on the lowest building or wall. A triangular spire
                            or pyramid rises above the other buildings.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.10.01" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.10.02" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.10.03" justify="center">The Soul exploring the recesses of
                        the Grave.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.10.04" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.11" dbi="BB435.1.11-10.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Death of The Good Old Man.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber><objcode code="B10">(Bentley 435.10)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.1 x 26.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="520"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.14"/><related objectid="but638.1.wc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with an open window on the right
                        portion of the wall. The floor is visible below the figures. A table with a
                        cloth draped over it stands just below the window. A plate with bread or
                        other food and a glass goblet or chalice appear on the table; a shadow on
                        the goblet indicates that it is partially filled with liquid. The body of a
                        male figure lays supine on a mat or bed in the lower portion of the design;
                        the body is horizontal with the head to the left. He is identified in the
                        inscription as the "Good Old Man"; he is either dying or may be dead. The
                        figure has long hair and a beard. His eyes are closed. He is gowned and a
                        cloth veil or other drapery rests on his head. The figure's right arm is at
                        his side and his right hand holds or touches an open book; the right page of
                        the book has a clearly visible text or inscription which reads, "THE NEW
                        TESTAMENT." Seven figures appear around the old man, four at the head and
                        three at the feet. A gowned female kneels in the lower left corner. She is
                        seen from behind and faces to the right with her head turned slightly down;
                        she looks at the old man below. Her right arm is bent upward and the palm
                        may be held vertically; although her left arm is not pictured, she may be
                        praying. The upper body of a gowned female appears directly above the old
                        man's head. She may be kneeling or sitting. The figure faces left with her
                        head turned down; she looks at the face of the old man below. Both arms are
                        bent in front of her chest; her hands are together with the palms held
                        vertically in prayer. Two additional figures are visible to the left of the
                        corpse; they may be female. Both figures are positioned with their heads
                        down and their faces obscured. The figure directly above the old man's head
                        rests her hands on a pillow or bundle with the palms turned down. A gowned
                        male with short, curly hair kneels to the right of the old man. The figure's
                        left leg is bent; his right leg is not visible. He faces left in profile
                        with his head down. Both arms are bent in front of his chest with his hands
                        held together and the palms vertical; he may be praying. Two additional
                        figures appear to the right of the old man; both are positioned with their
                        faces obscured. The figure to the left may be seen from behind. A gowned
                        male with long hair and a beard flies or hovers between two winged angels in
                        the upper portion of the design; he probably represents the soul of the dead
                        or dying man below. His head is turned up with his eyes raised and his mouth
                        slightly opened. His hands are positioned to the right of his head with the
                        palms held together vertically; he is probably praying. The angel to the
                        right is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer. The angel to the
                        left has long curly hair and looks to the right toward the male spirit; the
                        lower half of the angel's face is obscured. The figures may rest on a large
                        cloud extending horizontally across the upper portion of the design; it
                        appears to pass through the open window.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with an open window on the
                            right portion of the wall. The floor is visible below the
                            figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>table</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><characteristic>chalice</characteristic><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A table stands just below the window in the lower right
                            portion of the design. A cloth is draped over the table. A plate with
                            bread or other food and a glass goblet or chalice stand on the table; a
                            shadow on the goblet indicates that it is partially filled with
                            liquid.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The body of a male figure lays supine in the lower half of the
                            design; the body is horizontal with the head to the left. He is
                            identified in the inscription as the "Good Old Man"; he is either dying
                            or may already by dead. The figure has long hair and a beard. His eyes
                            are closed. He is gowned and a cloth veil or other drapery rests on his
                            head. The figure's right arm is at his side and his right hand holds or
                            touches an open book. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The old man's right hand rests on an open book; the right page
                            of the book has a clearly visible text or inscription which reads, "THE
                            NEW TESTAMENT."</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>mat</characteristic><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>bundle</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dying or dead old man lies on a bed or mat. His head rests
                            on a pillow or other bundle.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><characteristic>rope</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female kneels in the lower left corner of the design.
                            Her right leg is bent and her left leg is not visible. She is seen from
                            behind and faces to the right with her head turned slightly down; she
                            looks at the old man below. The figure has her long hair pulled back
                            with a small rope, string, or other tie. Her right arm is bent upward
                            and the palm may be held vertically; her left arm is not pictured. She
                            may be praying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><characteristic>rope</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The upper body of a gowned female appears directly above the
                            old man's head. She may be kneeling or sitting. The figure faces left
                            with her head turned down; she looks at the face of the old man below.
                            Her long hair is pulled back with a small rope, string, or other tie.
                            Both arms are bent in front of her chest; her hands are together with
                            the palms held vertically in prayer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The head and right shoulder of a female(?) figure are visible
                            above and to the left of the old man. She has long hair and wears a gown
                            or other clothing. The figure faces right with her head turned down; her
                            face is not visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The head and hands of a female(?) figure appear directly above
                            the old man's head. The figure has long hair and wears a gown or other
                            clothing. She faces left with her head turned down. Only part of her
                            head, neck, face, and hands are pictured. Her hands are together and
                            rest on a pillow or bundle with the palms turned down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned male with short, curly hair kneels to the right of
                            the old man. The figure's left leg is bent; his right leg is not
                            visible. He faces left in profile with his head down. Both arms are bent
                            in front of his chest with his hands are held together and the palms
                            vertical; he may be praying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two figures appear above the praying male in the lower right
                            portion of the design. The (male?) figure to the left is gowned and has
                            short, slightly curly hair. He may be seen from behind or he is facing
                            down and to the left; only the figure's upper body is visible. The
                            (female?) figure to the right has long hair and wears a gown or other
                            clothing. Only the figure's head and upper back are pictured. The figure
                            faces left and appears to have his or her head turned down; the figure's
                            face is not visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned male with long hair and a beard flies or hovers
                            between two angels in the upper portion of the design; he probably
                            represents the soul of the dead or dying man below. The figure's body is
                            horizontal with his head to the right. His head is turned up with his
                            eyes raised and his mouth slightly opened. His hands are positioned to
                            the right of his head with the palms held together vertically; he may be
                            praying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned and winged angels fly to the left and right of the
                            male spirit. The angels' bodies are horizontal with their heads to the
                            right. The angel to the right is seen from behind and faces away from
                            the viewer. The angel has long hair and its feet are visible. The angel
                            to the left has long curly hair and looks to the right toward the male
                            spirit; the lower half of the angel's face is obscured. Both feet are
                            visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The hovering or flying figures may rest on a large cloud
                            extending horizontally across the upper portion of the design; it
                            appears to pass through the open window.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P 30</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.02" justify="center"><space extent="5"/>THE<note>Lines 2-4 are inscribed on the right page of the
                            image of an opened book. Line 4 curves slightly in response to this
                            image.</note></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.03" justify="center"><space extent="5"/>NEW</l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.04" justify="center"><space extent="5"/>TESTAMENT</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.05" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.06" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.07" justify="center">The Death of The Good Old
                            Man.<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.08" justify="center">...............Sure the last
                            end<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.09" justify="center">Of the good Man is peace!<space extent="2"/>How calm His exit!<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.11.10" justify="center">London Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.12" dbi="BB435.1.12-11.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Death's Door.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A12">Object 12 </objnumber><objcode code="B11">(Bentley 435.11)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>28.0 x 13.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="640"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state. For Blake's own white-line
                        etching of "Deaths Door," click <xref targorder="u" doc="ESXIII.1.SPB.01" from="root" to="ditto">here</xref>.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.16"/><related objectid="esxiii.1.spb.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A tomb is built into a large stone or hill in the lower portion of
                        the design. The doorway is framed by two pillars supporting a lintel and a
                        single step below. There may be a path or road below the tomb, along the
                        lower border of the image. Leafy vegetation appears in the lower right
                        corner of the design along the right edge of the path or road. The door to
                        the tomb is open with a hinge visible along its right edge. Large straps,
                        possibly made of iron, secure the structure of the wooden(?) door. A
                        circular knocker or handle appears in the center of the door, and a keyhole
                        is visible below and to the left. The interior of the tomb is dark. A woven
                        matpossibly made of strawrests on a bed, bier, or raised platform in the
                        lower left corner of the tomb. An old man with long hair and a beard stands
                        in the lower portion of the design. The figure wears a belted gown and faces
                        left in profile. His left leg is bent with his left heel raised slightly.
                        His right leg is not pictured, but he likely steps up into the doorway. The
                        figure is hunched over and leans on a crutch positioned under his left arm.
                        The figure's left arm is bent at his side and he may hold or touch the
                        crutch with his left hand. The old man's long hair streams out to the left,
                        as though blown by a wind. A nude male with short curly hair sits or kneels
                        above the tomb. The figure faces forward with his head turned up and to the
                        right in profile. His mouth is open and his right eye is raised. Both legs
                        are bent; his left knee is on the ground and his right leg is drawn up. The
                        figure's left arm is at his side and is not visible below the elbow. His
                        right arm is bent back; his hand rests on the ground with the palm down and
                        he may be bracing or supporting himself. An aura surrounds the upper half of
                        the figure; beams of light radiate outward. Alternatively, the figure may be
                        positioned in front of the sun.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>lintel</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>iron</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>hinge</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>bier</characteristic><characteristic>mat</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>coil</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tomb is built into a large stone or hill in the lower
                            portion of the design. The doorway is framed by two pillars supporting a
                            lintel and a single step below. There may be a path or road below the
                            tomb, along the lower border of the image. The door to the tomb is open
                            with a hinge visible along its right edge, just above the old man's
                            back. A circular knocker or handle appears in the center of the door,
                            and a keyhole is visible below and to the left. Large straps, perhaps
                            made of iron, secure the structure of the wooden(?) door. The interior
                            of the tomb is dark. A woven matpossibly made of strawrests on a bed,
                            bier, or raised platform in the lower left corner of the tomb. The left
                            end of the mat is coiled.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Leafy vegetation appears in the lower right corner of the
                            design along the right edge of the path or road.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>crutch</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old male with long hair and a beard stands in the lower
                            portion of the design. The figure wears a belted gown and faces left in
                            profile. His left leg is bent with his left heel slightly raised. His
                            right leg is not pictured, but he likely steps up into the doorway. The
                            figure is hunched over and leans on a crutch positioned under his left
                            arm. The figure's left arm is bent at his side and he may hold or touch
                            the crutch with his left hand. His long hair streams out to the left, as
                            though blown by a wind.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>bracing</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short curly hair sits or kneels above the
                            tomb. The figure faces forward with his head turned up and to the right
                            in profile. His mouth is open and his right eye is raised. Both legs are
                            bent; his left knee is on the ground and his right leg is drawn up. The
                            figure's left arm is at his side and is not visible below the elbow, but
                            would appear to be drawn back. His right arm is bent back; his hand
                            rests on the ground with the palm down and he may be bracing or
                            supporting himself. An aura surrounds the upper half of the figure;
                            beams of light radiate outward. Alternatively, the figure may be
                            positioned in front of the sun.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines in the upper portion of the design represent
                            the sky. The sun may appear in the sky behind the nude male; beams of
                            light radiate outward.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.32.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.04" justify="center">Death's Door.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.05" justify="center">'Tis but a Night, a long and
                        moonless Night,<space extent="10"/></l><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.06" justify="center">We make the Grave our Bed, and then
                        are gone!<space extent="6"/></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.12.07" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb435.1.comdes.13" dbi="BB435.1.13-12.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Reunion of the Soul &amp; the Body.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A13">Object 13 </objnumber><objcode code="B12">(Bentley 435.12)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>26.7 x 17.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="640"/><objnote><p>This impression is in the second published state.</p></objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.15"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A partly nude male with short, curly hair kneels in the lower
                        portion of the design. The figure likely represents "the Body" mentioned in
                        the inscription. A cloth shroud or other drapery covers his legs, but leaves
                        his buttocks exposed. The figure is seen from behind. His left leg is bent
                        with the knee apparently on the ground; his right leg is extended back and
                        to the right. The figure's arms are raised almost vertically with the palms
                        turned up and the fingers spread. His head is bent back and he kisses a
                        female spirit, positioned above. A gowned female spirit flies or hovers
                        upside down above the partly nude male; she is seen from behind and may be
                        descending. The figure represents "the Soul" mentioned in the inscription.
                        Her left leg is bent with the sole of her foot turned out towards the
                        viewer; her right leg is extended upward and slightly right. Both arms are
                        bent and embrace the male figure around his neck; her head is bent back and
                        she kisses the male figure. A dark shadow below the male figure may indicate
                        an open grave. A tombstone appears to the left of the figures and a large
                        tomb or coffin appears to the right. Fire surrounds the tombstone and tomb.
                        Two columns of clouds or smoke extend upward toward the top left and right
                        corners of the design, forming a V-shape behind the two figures. Horizontal
                        lines representing sky appear between the two columns of clouds or
                        smoke.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A partly nude male with short, curly hair kneels in the lower
                            portion of the design. A cloth shroud or other drapery covers his legs,
                            but leaves his buttocks exposed. The figure is seen from behind. His
                            left leg is bent with the knee apparently on the ground; his right leg
                            is extended back and to the right. The figure's arms are raised almost
                            vertically with the palms turned up and the fingers spread. His head is
                            bent back and he kisses a female, positioned above. The figure likely
                            represents "the Body" mentioned in the inscription.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female spirit flies or hovers upside down above the
                            partly nude male; she is seen from behind and may be descending. The
                            figure represents "the Soul" mentioned in the inscription. Her left leg
                            is bent with the sole of her foot turned out towards the viewer; her
                            right leg is extended upward and slightly right. Both arms are bent and
                            embrace the male figure around his neck; her head is bent back and she
                            kisses the male figure. The spirit's hair is long.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>grave</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>coffin</characteristic><characteristic>tombstone</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark shadow below the male figure may indicate an open
                            grave. A tombstone appears to the left of the figures and a large tomb
                            or coffin appears to the right. Fire surrounds the tombstone and tomb.
                            Two columns of smoke or clouds extend upward toward the top left and
                            right corners of the design, forming a V-shape behind the figures.
                            Horizontal lines representing sky appear between the two columns of
                            smoke or clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.13.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="etched">P.32.</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="8"/><columns><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.13.02" justify="left">Drawn by W. Blake.</l></lg></column><column/><column><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.13.03" justify="right">Etched by L.
                                Schiavonetti.</l></lg></column></columns><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.13.04" justify="center">The Reunion of the Soul &amp; the
                            Body.<space extent="10"/></l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb435.1.comdes.13.05" justify="center">London, Published May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.<space extent="10"/></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>