<bad id="bb442.1" type="comeng" work="The Poetical Works of Geoffrey Chaucer, 1783" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="bentley" catid="442.1" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Poetical Works of Geoffrey Chaucer, 1783">
                    <main>The Poetical Works of Geoffrey Chaucer, 1783</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill </principal>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill,
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 13KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 150KB to
                410KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt> Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries <date>April
                    2023</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a Chaucer Omnibus, a selection of seven works by Blake on the subject of Geoffrey Chaucer.  
      <lb/>
                <lb/>The Archive has previously published works by Blake that are of a Chaucerian nature; these include five pages in the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, Objects 58, 67, and 119–21, in Manuscripts and Typographic Works, the tempera painting of <hi rend="i">Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty Pilgrims on their Journey to Canterbury</hi>, in Drawings and Paintings, and all four states of the engraving of the painting, in Separate Prints and Prints in Series. Both the engraving and painting can also be viewed in a multi-gallery presentation in Archive Exhibitions. The exhibition includes works in the Omnibus that are now also accessible in their genre categories:
      <lb/>
<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake’s Chaucer: The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, 1809, a single page prospectus for the engraving of his painting, which he refers to as a "Fresco Picture."
      <lb/>
<lb/><hi rend="i">Blake's Chaucer: An Original Engraving</hi>, 1810, an advertisement for and three-page leaflet describing the engraving.
      <lb/>
<lb/><hi rend="i">Exhibition of Paintings in Fresco, Poetical and Historical Inventions</hi>, 1809, an advertisement for Blake's exhibition with a one-page text on "The Invention of a portable Fresco," dated May 15, 1809 (in pen and ink). The sheet was folded to make an envelope addressed to "Ozias Humphry, Esq. / Sloan Street." Blake had enclosed "a ticket of admission" to his exhibition and a short letter asserting that "Florentine &amp; Venetian Art cannot exist together," claims he expounds upon in the exhibition’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, which includes Blake's lengthy description of his Chaucer painting.
      <lb/>
<lb/>These works are now available for study in Manuscripts and Typographic Works, as is the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>.
      <lb/>
<lb/>Another work in the Archive's digital exhibition on Chaucer now accessible in its genre category of Drawings and Paintings is
      <lb/>
<lb/><hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims: Sketch for the Engraving</hi>, 1809, a pencil drawing based on the painting but reducing its size to that of the engraving.
      <lb/>
<lb/>The Omnibus also includes two works in Commercial Book Illustrations:
      <lb/>
<lb/>An engraving after a design by Stothard, dated March 1783, that served as the frontispiece to volume XIII of <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of Geoffrey Chaucer</hi> in <hi rend="i">Bell’s Edition [of] the Poets of Great Britain</hi>.
      <lb/>
<lb/><hi rend="i">The Prologue and Characters of Chaucer's Pilgrims Selected from his Canterbury Tales</hi>, which comprises a frontispiece, dated Dec 26, 1811, and a tailpiece. The former reproduces, at a much reduced size, a portion of the left side of the large engraving; the latter is a vignette of Canterbury Cathedral.
      <lb/>
<lb/>Also included in the Omnibus is a
      <lb/>
<lb/>portrait of Chaucer from the series of <hi rend="i">Eighteen Heads of Poets</hi> that Blake painted in watercolor and pen and ink for William Hayley's library, c. 1800-1803, and now in the Manchester Art Gallery. It is the first of the series in the Archive (to be joined by the others in due course) and can be found under Drawings and Paintings.
      <lb/>
                <lb/>As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt> 
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict> Copyright © <date>2023</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only. <lb/>
            <lb/> This work copyright © 2023 William Blake Archive. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing, revisions, and publication</change>
                <date>September 2022-April 2023</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
                    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher Catanese, </name>
                    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>
                    <name>Mary Geisert, </name>
                    <name>HaiLee Hearburg, </name>
                    <name>Liam Kusmierek, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
                    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
                    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
                    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created, engraving transcribed, editorial notes composed</change>
                <date>September 2021-May 2022</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Ben Ami, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian, </name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green, </name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Ania Michas, </name>
                    <name>Angie (Quynh-Anh) Pham, </name>
                    <name>Rob Rich, </name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
                    <name>Iftekhar Uddin, </name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>*The Poetical Works of Geoffrey Chaucer, 1783*</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination> William Blake <role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>engraver, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination> Thomas Stothard <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>designer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination> Apollo Press <role>printer of the letterpress text</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher> John Bell </publisher>
                    <pubplace> London 
                    </pubplace>
                    <date>1783</date>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1783">1783</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1783">1783<note>The title-page of Volume XIII is dated 1782, but
                        the table of contents is dated 22 March 1783 and Blake's frontispiece is
                        dated 24 May 1783, thus the real date is 1783.</note></printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>10.7 x 6.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>12.5 x 7.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>A single framing line extends around the image, excluding the
                    colophon.</framelines>
                <binding>full calf binding <note>This page is bound as the first leaf in the volume
                        before the title-pages.</note>
                </binding>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1972</date>
                <dealer>Zeitlin and Ver Brugge Books</dealer>
                <price>$623.74</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired in 1972 by Robert N. Essick from the Los
                    Angeles dealer Zeitlin and Ver Brugge Books as part of 102 volumes of *Bell's
                    Edition [of] The Poets of Great Britain*, $623.74 for the set.</note>
                <note>The set acquired by Essick is incomplete, as it contains only 102 volumes of
                    the 109 volume set.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena, California</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="bb442.1.comeng.01" dbi="BB442.1.1.COM">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">Frontispiece to Volume XIII</title> , <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>6.7 x 10.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>none</objnote>
                <windowsize width="500" height="615"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Pictured in an oval frame in the center of the plate, a resting
                        figure — almost certainly Samson — lies unconscious and limp on the ground.
                        He is muscular and bare-chested, and wears a cloth or loincloth around his
                        waist. His body faces left, and his face faces forward and tilts slightly to
                        the right. His head, with curly hair, rests against his bare left shoulder.
                        His eyes are closed. His left arm bends ninety degrees at elbow so that his
                        clenched fist rests on his lap, while his right forearm extends over his
                        right thigh. One finger of his right hand is pointed, as the hand drapes
                        over his inner thigh. Samson's upper body is propped upright against the
                        legs of a woman standing behind him. This woman is most likely Delilah. She
                        wears a gown with a bodice or vest over her torso and has dark hair that is
                        pulled into a bun. She bends forward and reaches her left arm downward to
                        support or hold up the unconscious Samson. Her left hand is held behind his
                        back. Her head, turned to look behind her, is encircled with a strip of
                        cloth. She may be blindfolded. A group of three men stand behind her. These
                        figures may be the “fooman” in “The Monk's Tale,” to whom Delilah sells
                        Samson. The central figure in the group wears the uniform of a Roman
                        solider, including a helmet and tunic. His body faces forward and his legs
                        are spread apart, with the left leg extended to the left and the right leg
                        bent at the knee (although it is mostly obscured by Delilah's dress). He
                        twists his upper body to the right, and bends his right arm upward at the
                        elbow to cross over his chest. His face is turned downward and to the left
                        to look at the ground or, perhaps, at Samson. A cloak or cape billows from
                        his back to his left, and it may be worn by him or by the figure to his
                        right. To the right of the central figure, a man with long white hair looks
                        downward and to the right. His body faces right, and his left arm extends
                        outward to grab a curtain, visible at the edge of the frame. Only his upper
                        body is visible, but he appears to wear a tunic similar to that of the
                        central figure. To the left of the central figure, a third figure, likely a
                        male with long dark hair, faces the right. His upper body and face are
                        obscured by the central figure, so that only his legs are visible. His legs
                        are spread, with one leg extended backward and the other bent at the knee,
                        as if he is lunging. He appears to wear a tunic similar to that of the
                        central figure. A column is visible behind and to the left of the figures,
                        and they appear to stand or lay on a hard floor. A curtain or drapery
                        extends from the top of the oval frame to the lower third of both sides. The
                        oval frame sits within a backdrop that appears to be of bricks. Above the
                        oval frame, there is a stone or marble plaque. Below the plaque, there is
                        the statue or sculpture of the head of a figure, perhaps a female. Her long
                        curly hair extends to either side, and from both sides of hair two pieces of
                        cloth or drapery extend, draped to the sides and upward, where it hangs over
                        two hooks on either side of the plaque. The ends of the cloth twist over
                        itself to form two loops on either side. A second plaque sits below the oval
                        frame.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Samson</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>limp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap </characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm reaching between legs</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Pictured in an oval frame in the center of the plate, a
                            resting figure — almost certainly Samson — lies unconscious and limp on
                            the ground. He is muscular and bare-chested, and wears a cloth or
                            loincloth around his waist. His body faces left, and his face faces
                            forward and tilts slightly to the right. His head, with curly hair,
                            rests against his bare left shoulder. His eyes are closed. His left arm
                            bends ninety degrees at elbow so that his clenched fist rests on his
                            lap, while his right forearm extends over his right thigh. One finger of
                            his right hand is pointed, as the hand drapes over his inner thigh.
                            Samson's upper body is propped upright against the legs of a woman
                            standing behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>woman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Delilah</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding </characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth </characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blindfolded</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> A woman, most likely Delilah, stands behind Samson. She wears
                            a gown with a bodice or vest over her torso and has dark hair that is
                            pulled into a bun. She bends forward and reaches her left arm downward
                            to support or hold up the unconscious Samson. Her left hand is held
                            behind his back. Her head, turned to look behind her and away from the
                            viewer, is encircled with a strip of cloth. She may be blindfolded.
                        </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Roman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at the knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> A group of three men stand behind Delilah. These figures may
                            be the “fooman” in “The Monk's Tale,” to whom Delilah sells Samson. The
                            central figure in the group wears the uniform of a Roman solider,
                            including a helmet and tunic. His body faces forward and his legs are
                            spread apart, with the left leg extended to the left and the right leg
                            bent at the knee (although it is mostly obscured by Delilah's dress). He
                            twists his upper body to the right, and bends his right arm upward at
                            the elbow to cross over his chest. His face is turned downward and to
                            the left to look at the ground or, perhaps, at Samson. A cloak or cape
                            billows from his back to his left, and it may be worn by him or by the
                            figure to his right. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic </characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> A group of three men stand behind Delilah. These figures may
                            be the “fooman” in “The Monk's Tale,” to whom Delilah sells Samson. To
                            the right of the central figure, a man with long white hair looks
                            downward and to the right. His body faces right, and his left arm
                            extends outward to grab a curtain, visible at the edge of the frame.
                            Only his upper body is visible, but he appears to wear a tunic similar
                            to that of the central figure. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of three men stand behind Delilah. These figures may
                            be the “fooman” in “The Monk's Tale,” to whom Delilah sells Samson. To
                            the left of the central figure, a third figure, likely a male with long
                            dark hair, faces the right. His upper body and face are obscured by the
                            central figure, so that only his legs are visible. His legs are spread,
                            with one leg extended backward and the other bent at the knee, as if he
                            is lunging. He appears to wear a tunic similar to that of the central
                            figure. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>column</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background is scarcely detailed, but there is a visible
                            column behind and to the left of the figures. They appear to stand or
                            lay on a hard floor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>curtain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A curtain or drapery extends from the top of the oval frame to
                            the lower third of both sides.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>

                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facade</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> The oval frame over backdrop or façade that appears to be
                            made of bricks. The oval frame casts a slight shadow over the bricks.
                        </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>

                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hook</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> Above the oval frame, there is the statue or sculpture of the
                            head of a figure, perhaps a female. Her long curly hair extends to
                            either side, and from both sides of hair two pieces of cloth or drapery
                            extend, draped to the sides and upward, where it hangs over two hooks or
                            posts on either side of a plaque. The ends of the cloth twist over
                            itself to form two loops on either side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>marble</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frame</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two plaques, which may be made of marble or stone, are
                            positioned above and below the oval frame. Each plaque contains a frame,
                            within which text is engraved.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.01" justify="left" indent="19">
                        <hi rend="i"> BELL'S EDITION </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.02" justify="left" indent="14"> The POETS of GREAT
                        BRITAIN</l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.03" justify="left" indent="19">
                        <hi rend="i"> COMPLETE FROM </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.04" justify="left" indent="16">
                        <hi> CHAUCER to CHURCHILL. </hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="18"/>
                <lg>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.05" justify="left" indent="17"> CHAUCER VOL
                        <choice><orig>XIII</orig><reg>8</reg></choice>.</l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.06" justify="left" indent="14"> Sampson
                        <choice><orig>yhad</orig><reg>had</reg></choice> experience</l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.07" justify="left" indent="14">
                        <choice>
                            <orig> That Womenwereful trew </orig>
                            <reg> That Women were full true </reg>
                        </choice>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>ifound</orig>
                            <reg>I found</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.08" justify="left" indent="27">
                        <hi rend="i">In praise of Women L 81,82.</hi>
                    </l>
                    <vspace extent="0.5"/>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="2"/>
                <lg>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.09" justify="left">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>
                                <hi rend="i">Stodhard</hi>
                            </orig>
                            <reg type="alt_name">Stothard</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <hi rend="i">del</hi>
                        <space extent="37"/>
                        <hi rend="i">Blake sculp.</hi>
                        <hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="bb442.1.comeng.01.10" justify="left"> London Printed for John Bell British
                        Library Strand May 24,<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1783.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
