<bad id="bb469.1" type="comeng" work="Hayley, The Life of George Romney" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="bentley" catid="469"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Life of George Romney"><main><author>William Hayley</author>, The Life of George Romney</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>

            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 30KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 202KB to 1200KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>. We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>&#160;illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.<lb/><lb/>
                In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>. Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.<lb/><lb/>                                                
                The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809). Only one of these plates, <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>, was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>

         This work copyright © 2013 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation and image color correction</change><date>June 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, and</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change><date>Fall 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>William Hayley, *The Life of George Romney*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>etcher,</role><role>engraver</role></origination><origination>George Romney<role>inventor</role></origination><imprint><publisher>T. Payne
                    </publisher><pubplace>London</pubplace><date>1809</date></imprint><compdate value="1809.A">1809</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1809.A">1809</printdate><numberobj>1</numberobj><objorder>1</objorder><objsize>18.2 x 17.7 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>22.3 x 29.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>etching and engraving</medium><printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>contemporary calf rebacked<note>This is a large-paper copy.</note></binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1992</date><dealer>Apollo Book Shop</dealer><price>$215</price><note>The history of this copy prior to its sale by Apollo Book Shop is not known.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena</addressline><addressline>California</addressline></repository></source><desc id="bb469.1.comeng.01" dbi="BB469.1.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney.</title>,

<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 469.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objnote><p>Blake based his etching/engraving on his own wash drawing, now in the British Museum, in turn based on George Romney's painting, now lost.</p></objnote><objsize>18.2 x 17.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design depicts a ship floundering amongst a storm and heavy waves of the sea. In the center of the design is the ship's mast. Extending down and to the right of the mast are a large sail and three ropes. Extending down and to the left of the mast are four ropes. At the top left of the mast are two cross spars, onto which are attached parts of the sail. Three ropes extend down from the left end of the uppermost cross spar. Extending from the base of the mast to the left is the aft or rear of the ship. There are three figures standing on the aft deck. The leftmost figure stands next to the stern and is a young female wearing a long gown. She faces forward and to the right. Both her arms are raised and bent, and she grasps her long, curly hair with both hands. Her mouth is open indicating shock or surprise. The second figure from the right is an adult male. Between these two figures is a large rectangular object that may be a wooden chest or hatch. The male figure is probably the father of this family group. His body faces forward, legs apart, and his head face to the left in profile. He has short hair and appears to be wearing tights. His mouth is open and he may be shouting at the figure to the left. His right arm is raised horizontally and the palm of his right hand faces outward. His fingers are spread and he may be touching the female to his left. To the right of the father is an older female, presumably the mother, facing forward and to the right. Her mouth is open and her long hair is wild. She is wearing a long dress and is carrying an infant with short hair across her shoulders and around her neck, with its feet dangling. The infant faces forward with both arms raised. The infant's right arm is raised above its head. Billowing out behind the mother and child is a large piece of cloth. This may be part of the mother's dress, or a cloak worn by the father, or a piece of detached sail. To the right of the mast is a group of partially submerged figures and part of a second mast, which has been broken. The figure to the left of the mast is almost entirely submerged apart from both forearms and hands, which reach upward, palms facing right and figures spread. The figure second from the right in this group is a partially nude male, facing away and to the left, his bald head in profile. He is wearing a belt around his waist. His right arm is bent and his left arm is raised. The third figure from the right is a nude male facing to the left. He is bent at the waist and his left leg is bent. His left arm is raised above his head and with his left hand grasps the tattered end of the main sail. The third figure from the left in this group is another nude male, facing away and to the left, in profile. His left arm is raised above his head and he too grasps the sail with his left hand. He has short hair and appears to be looking at the central mast. His mouth is open slightly. The second figure from the left is a face in left profile, just to the left of the left shoulder of the man holding the sail. The leftmost figure in this group is the head and neck of a male figure, facing forward. He has short hair and his mouth is open. He may be looking at the figures to the right. Directly below the central mast is a partly submerged nude male, facing left in profile. He has short, wild hair blown by the wind and his mouth is open. He may be shouting to, and looking at, the figures to the left. Both arms are bent and raised above his head. The left hand is palm up with fingers spread and the right hand holds onto the bridle of a horse. To the right of this figure is the bald head of a submerged male. He faces forward and his head tilts to the left. His mouth is open. To the left of the mast and in the mid-ground are a group of three figures: a horse, its rider and a female. The horse faces away and to the right, its head in profile. In its mouth is a bit attached to a bridle. The horse's head is tilted upward. A male, nude from the waist up, sits on the horse. He faces away, with his head turned left in profile. He has short curly hair and is looking downward at the female he is holding. She is supine, has long hair and her left arm is extended to the left and is bent slightly. She is wearing a gown, visible right of the man holding her. In the lower right-hand corner of the design is another unconscious or possibly dead female with long hair. She is nude and is supine on rocks with her left arm by her side. Her left leg is bent and her long hair drapes over the rocks. The sky on the upper right of the design is dark and stormy. The billowing form right and left of the central mast may be a cloud or possibly a shoreline cliff. An illuminated area with beams of light, just above and to the left of the male on the ship with his arm extended to the left, may be the sun.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shouting</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>shock</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There are four figures stood on the aft deck. The leftmost figure stands next to the stern and is a young female, possibly daughter, wearing a long gown. She faces forward and to the right. Both her arms are raised and bent, and she grasps her long, curly hair with both hands. Her mouth is open indicating shock or surprise. The second figure from the right is an adult male. The male figure is probably the father of this family group. His body faces forward, legs apart, and his head face to the left in profile. He has short hair and appears to be wearing tights. His mouth is open and he may be shouting at the figure to the left. His right arm is raised at 90 degrees and the palm of his right hand faces outward. His fingers are spread and he may be touching the female to his left. To the right of the father is an older female, presumably the mother, facing forward and to the right. Her mouth is open and her long hair is wild. She is wearing a long dress and is carrying an infant with short hair across her shoulders and around her neck, with its feet dangling. The infant faces forward with both arms raised. The infant's right arm is raised above its head. Billowing out behind the mother and child is a large piece of cloth. This may be part of the mother's dress, or a cloak worn by the father, or a piece of detached sail.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>box</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between the daughter and father is a large rectangular object that may be a wooden or wicker box or a hatch on the ship.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>ship</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>sail</characteristic><characteristic>mast</characteristic><characteristic>rope</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The design depicts a ship floundering amongst a storm and heavy waves. In the center of the design is the ship's mast. Extending down and to the right of the mast are a large sail and three lines of rope. Extending down and to the left of the mast are four lines of rope. At the top left of the mast are two cross spars, onto which are attached parts of the sail. Three lines of rope extend down from the left end of the upper most cross spar. Extending from the base of the mast to the left is the aft or rear of the ship. Part of a second mast, which has been broken, is visible above the waves on the right of the design</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>swimming</characteristic><characteristic>drowning</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the mast are a group of partially submerged figures. The figure to the left of the second, broken mast is almost entirely submerged apart from both forearms and hands, which reach upward, palms facing right and figures spread. This figure is almost certainly drowning. The figure second from the right in this group is a partially nude male, facing away and to the left, his bald head in profile. He is wearing a belt around his waist. His right arm is bent and his left arm is raised. The third figure from the right is a nude male facing to the left. He is bent at the waist and his left leg is bent. His left arm is raised above his head and with his left hand grasps the tattered end of the main sail. The third figure from the left in this group is another nude male, facing away and to the left, in profile. His left arm is raised above his head and he too grasps the sail with his left hand. He has short hair and appears to be looking at the central mast. His mouth is open slightly. The second figure from the left is a face in left profile, just to the left of the left shoulder of the man holding the sail. The leftmost figure in this group is the head and neck of a male figure, facing forward. He has short hair and his mouth is open. He may be looking at the figures to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>drowning</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Directly below the central mast is a partly submerged nude male, facing left in profile. He has short, wild hair blown by the wind and his mouth is open. He may be shouting to, and looking at, the figures to the left. Both arms are bent and raised above his head. The left hand is palm up with fingers spread and the right hand holds onto the bridle of a horse. To the right of this figure, is the bald head of a submerged male. He faces forward and his head titles to the left. His mouth is open. He may be drowning.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>bit</characteristic><characteristic>harness</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>dying</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the mast and in the mid-ground are a group of three figures: a horse, its rider and an unconscious female. The horse faces away and to the right, its head in profile. In its mouth is a bit attached to a bridle. A male, nude from the waist up, is sitting on the horse. He faces away, with his head turned left in profile. He has short curly hair and is looking downward at the female he is holding. She is supine, has long hair, her eyes are closed and her left arm is extended to the left and is bent slightly. She is wearing a gown, visible to the right of man holding her.  She may be dead, dying, or unconscious.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>dying</characteristic><characteristic>drowning</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the lower right-hand corner of the design is another unconscious or possibly dead female with long hair. She is nude and is supine on rocks with her left arm by her side. Her left leg is bent and her long hair drapes over the rocks. Her eye is closed.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky on the upper right of the design is dark and stormy. On the left it appears clear with some clouds. The billowing form right and left of the central mast may be a cloud or possibly a shoreline cliff. An illuminated area with beams of light, just above and to the left of the male on the ship with his arm extended to the left, may be the sun.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>rock</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the lower right-hand corner of the design are rocks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The foreground is dominated by the waves of a storm-tossed sea.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb469.1.comeng.01.01" justify="left" indent="20">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb469.1.comeng.01.02" justify="left" indent="30">Engraved by Blake</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb469.1.comeng.01.03" justify="left" indent="29">Published, April 14th 1809 by Thomas Payne, Pall Mall.</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>