<bad id="bb468.1" type="comeng" work="Hayley, The Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William Cowper" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="bentley" catid="468"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper"><main><author>William Hayley</author>, The Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William Cowper</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>

            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 43KB; 12 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 131KB to 1000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>. We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>&#160;illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.<lb/><lb/>
                In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>. Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.<lb/><lb/>                                                
                The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809). Only one of these plates, <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>, was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>

         This image copyright © 2013 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation and image color correction</change><date>June 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, and</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change><date>Fall 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>William Hayley, *The Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William Cowper*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>etcher,</role><role>engraver,</role></origination><origination>George Romney (Object 1), D. Heins (Object 2), Thomas Lawrence (Object 3), William Blake (Object 4), Francis Stone (Object 5), and John Flaxman (Object 6)<role>inventor</role></origination><imprint><publisher>Joseph Johnson <note>The title page specifies that the book was "Printed by J. Seagrave, / for J. Johnson, St. Paul's Church-Yard, London."</note></publisher><pubplace>London</pubplace><date>1803 and 1804</date><note>vols. 1-2 were published in 1803; vol. 3 was published in 1804.</note></imprint><compdate value="1803.A">1803-04</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1803.A">1803-04</printdate><numberobj>6</numberobj><objorder>1-6</objorder><objsize>ranging between 15.7 x 11.7 and 25.1 x 16.4 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>6</numberleaves><leafsize>28.2 x 22.6 cm.<note/></leafsize><medium>etching and engraving</medium><printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>
                </watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>1<note>Single frame lines surround the designs in Objects 3 and 5.</note></framelines><binding>publisher's blue-paper boards</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1991</date><dealer>William Reese Co. through John Windle</dealer><price>$750</price><note>The history of this copy before its sale by William Reese Co. is not known.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena</addressline><addressline>California</addressline></repository></source><desc id="bb468.1.comeng.01" dbi="BB468.1.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">WILLIAM , COWPER . Carmine Nobilem</title>,

<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 468.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>23.1 x 14.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design is the frontispiece for William Hayley's biography and is a portrait of William Cowper after George Romney. Cowper dominates the design, his upper body facing forward and his head facing to the left slightly. Cowper is wearing a coat with broad collars and lapels, and a necktie or scarf. On his head, Cowper wears a morning cap. Cowper's arms appear to be at his side. He is looking to the left. 
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>William Cowper</characteristic><characteristic>portrait</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>William Cowper dominates the design, his upper body facing forward and his head facing to the left slightly. Cowper is wearing a coat with broad collars and lapels, a shirt and a necktie or scarf. On his head, Cowper wears a morning cap. Cowper's arms appear to be at his side. He is looking to the left. </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.01" justify="left">From a Portrait in Crayons Drawn from the Life by Romney in 1792 Engravd by W Blake 1802</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.02" justify="left" indent="15">WILLIAM, COWPER.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.03" justify="left" indent="25">Carmine Nobilem</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.04" justify="left" indent="45">Hor:</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.01.05" justify="left" indent="3">Publish'd Novemb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 5. 1802. by J. Johnson S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Pauls Church Yard</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb468.1.comeng.02" dbi="BB468.1.2.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Mrs COWPER Mother of the Poet</title>,

<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 468.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>21.3 x 12.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="650"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is a portrait of Mrs Cowper, William Cowper's mother. Only her upper body is visible. She faces forward with her head facing left slightly. She has long hair in ringlets, which runs down her neck and shoulders. She is wearing a gown decorated with lace trimmings and a jewelled device in the center of her chest. She looks forward and appears to be smiling. Her arms are at her side. 
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mrs Cowper</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>jewelry</characteristic><characteristic>chest</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Only Mrs Cowper's upper body is visible. She faces forward with her head facing left slightly. She has long hair in ringlets, which runs down her neck and shoulders. She is wearing a gown decorated with lace trimmings and a jewelled device in the center of her chest. She looks forward and appears to be smiling. Her arms are at her side.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.02.01" justify="left" indent="10">D. Heins Pinx<space extent="20"/>W Blake sculp</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.02.02" justify="left" indent="28">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> COWPER</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.02.03" justify="left" indent="26">Mother of the Poet</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.02.03" justify="left" indent="5">Publish'd Novemb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 5. 1802 by J. Johnson S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Pauls Church Yard</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb468.1.comeng.03" dbi="BB468.1.3.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">William Cowper— Author of "The Task"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 468.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objnote><p>
                        The imprint has been trimmed off this impression. The imprint reads "Publish'd Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 5. 1802 by J Johnson S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Pauls Church Yard".
                    </p></objnote><objsize>25.1 x 16.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design is a portrait of William Cowper after Thomas Lawrence. Cowper dominates the design facing forward and to the left. He is wearing a coat with broad collars, and lapels, a shirt and a necktie or scarf. On his head he wears a cap with an elaborate bow-like decoration on top. He is looking to the left and his arms are by his side. 
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>William Cowper</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>portrait</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><illusobjdesc>William Cowper dominates the design facing forward and to the left. He is wearing a coat with broad collars and lapels, a shirt and a necktie or scarf. On his head he wears a cap with an elaborate bow-like decoration on top. He is looking to the left and his arms are by his side.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.03.01" justify="left" indent="25">William Cowper —</l><l n="bb471.1.comeng.03.02" justify="left" indent="27">Author of "The Task"</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.03.03" justify="left">T Lawrence RA: ad vivum del: 1793<space extent="18"/>W. Blake sculp 1802<note>
                        The small dot after "sculp," very close to the "p," is a stain in this impression, not a period.
                    </note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb468.1.comeng.04" dbi="BB468.1.4.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">THE PEASANTS NEST</title>,          

<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 468.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>15.7 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design depicts a weather house containing two outdoor vignettes. Below the weather house is a roundel containing three hares. At the top of the design is a structure with a thatched roof and three trees that form the vertical supports. Leafy vines wrap around the center and right tree. The vine on the right tree extends to the right side and top of the thatched roof. The vignette on the right side of the weather house depicts a female in a long gown, facing forward. She stands on tip toe on the upper edge of a see-saw and her hair is in a bun. With her right hand, she is holding her gown to form a basket, which contains fruit or vegetables. In her left hand she is holding a round fruit. Behind her and to the right is a cottage with two windows, a central door and a thatched roof. A pathway leads up to the cottage door. To the left of the cottage are trees. Behind the female and to the left are at least three sheep, two of which are grazing. Behind the sheep are tree tops and a large hill. The sun is emerging from behind the hill. The vignette on the left side of the weather house depicts a male standing on the lower edge of the see-saw. The male faces left, in profile and is wearing a long coat and a broad-rimmed hat. The male holds a walking stick in his right hand. His left arm is bent across his chest. His left foot is on tip toe indicating that he is walking. Behind and to the right of the man, is a large mountain above which are dark clouds. Directly behind the man is a large body of water, possibly the sea, with a shore to the right. Diagonal lines indicate that it is raining. The weather house stands on a two-tiered plinth. Below the plinth are leaf and flower bearing garlands that drape onto a roundel containing a rural scene. Within the roundel are three hares. The rightmost hare (Bess) is lying on the ground, facing left, with its ears pointed upward. The leftmost hare (Puss) is also lying on the ground, but in a more contracted position and its ears are flat against its body. The third hare (Tiney) is running above them. To the right of the hares is the twisting trunk of a leafy tree. Below the hares is grass. Above the hares is a hill surrounded by vegetation, including trees and bushes. On top of the hill is a cottage with a visible window and a chimney issuing smoke. The cottage is surrounded by trees and bushes. </illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="AB"><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>weather house</characteristic><characteristic>thatch</characteristic><characteristic>vines</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>vegetation</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the design is a structure with a thatched roof and three trees that form the vertical supports. Leafy vines wrap around the center and right tree. The vine on the right tree extends to the right side and top of the thatched roof.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>tip toe</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>carrying</characteristic><characteristic>fruit</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The vignette on the right side of the weather house depicts a female in a long gown, facing forward. She may be wearing a hat. She stands on tip toe on the upper edge of a see-saw and her hair is in a bun. With her right hand, she is holding her gown to form a basket, which contains fruit or vegetables. In her left hand she is holding a round fruit.
                       </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>see-saw</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Both the female and male appear to be standing on a see-saw.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="B"><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>pathway</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the woman and to the right is a cottage with two windows, a central door and a thatched roof. A pathway leads up to the cottage door.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>eating</characteristic><characteristic>grazing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the female and to the left are at least three sheep, two of which are grazing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>walking stick</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The vignette on the left side of the weather house depicts a male standing on the lower edge of the see-saw. The male faces left, in profile and is wearing a long coat with a collar turned up and a broad-rimmed hat. The male holds a walking stick in his right hand. His left arm is bent across his chest. His left foot is on tip toe indicating that he is walking.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>lake</characteristic><characteristic>rain</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Directly behind the man is a large body of water, possibly the sea or a lake, with a shore to the right. Diagonal lines indicate that it is raining.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>garland</characteristic><characteristic>ribbon</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc> The weather house stands on a two-tiered plinth. Below the plinth are leaf and flower bearing garlands and ribbons that loop and drape onto a roundel.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>rabbit</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Within the roundel are three hares. The rightmost hare (Bess) is lying on the ground, facing left, with its ears pointed upward. The leftmost hare (Puss) is also lying on the ground, but in a more contracted position and its ears are flat against its body. It may be asleep. The third hare (Tiney) is running above them. To the right of the hares is the twisting trunk of a leafy tree, possibly ivy. Below the hares is grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="CD"><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>chimney</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the hares is a hill surrounded by vegetation, including trees and bushes. On top of the hill is a cottage with a visible window and a chimney issuing smoke. The cottage is surrounded by trees and bushes. There are also hills behind and to the left of the cottage. There are clouds above the cottage and hills.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="5"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.01" justify="left" indent="10">Peace to the Artist whose ingenious thought</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.02" justify="left" indent="9">Devised the Weather-house, that useful toy!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.03" justify="left" indent="9">Fearless of humid air and gathering rains.</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.04" justify="left" indent="9">Forth steps the Man, an emblem of myself,</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.05" justify="left" indent="9">More delicate his tim'rous mate retires.</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.06" justify="left" indent="48">Task. B 1. line 200</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.07" justify="left" indent="8">Blake d &amp;sc</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.08" justify="left" indent="20">THE PEASANTS NEST</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.09" justify="left" indent="20">PUSS TINEY &amp; BESS</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.10" justify="left" indent="5">Cowper's <space extent="29"/> tame Hare's</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.01.11" justify="left" indent="9">Publish'd Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 5 1802 by J Johnson S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Pauls Church Yard</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb468.1.comeng.05" dbi="BB468.1.5.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">A View of St Edmund's Chapel, in the Church of East Dereham, Containing the Grave of William Cowper Esq.</title>,           
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 468.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>14.25 x 18.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="725"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design depicts the interior of a church, containing a tomb. A large Norman arch frames the scene. On the left of the arch is a column or pillar that runs from the stone floor to the ceiling. Within the arch are decorative pilasters that begin at the mid-point of the arch. Beyond the arch is a rectangular tomb behind a low metal fence or railing. To the left of the tomb is another arch with a pilaster. This arch forms a doorway to another part of the church. On top of the tomb, occupying a central position is a raised plinth. On top of the plinth are two books standing with their spines outward. The slimmer volume leans against the thicker volume. The books are covered by a large drooping laurel leaf. On the side of the tomb, beneath the books is a large white (marble) plaque with an indecipherable inscription. Above the tomb is a large Norman-style, stained-glass window that sits in a shallow casement. Above the window, there are parts of an ornamental ceiling.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>church</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large Norman arch in a church frames the scene. On the left of the arch is a pilaster that runs from the stone floor to the roof. Within the arch are more decorative pilasters that begin at the mid-point of the arch.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="AC"><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the tomb is another Norman arch with a pilaster. This arch forms a doorway to another part of the church. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>grave</characteristic><characteristic>fence</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>laurel</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>marble</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A rectangular tomb sits behind a low metal fence or railing. On top of the tomb, occupying a central position is a raised plinth. On top of the plinth are two books standing with their spines outward. The slimmer volume leans against the thicker volume. The books are covered by a large drooping laurel branch. On the side of the tomb, beneath the books is a large white (marble) plaque with an indecipherable inscription.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the tomb is a large Norman-style, stained-glass window that sits in a shallow casement. Above the window, there are parts of an ornamental roof or ceiling.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb4681.1.comeng.05.01" justify="left">Francis Stone del:<space extent="40"/>W Blake. sculp</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb4681.1.comeng.05.02" justify="left" indent="15">A View of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Edmund's Chapel,</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.05.03" justify="left" indent="16">in the Church of East Dereham,</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.05.04" justify="left" indent="14">Containing the Grave of William Cowper Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi>,</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.05.05" justify="left" indent="20">Publish'd by J Johnson S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Pauls 25 March 1804</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb468.1.comeng.06" dbi="BB468.1.6.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">A Sketch of the Monument Erected in the Church of East Dereham in Norfolk In Memory of William Cowper Esqre</title>,         
            <objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 468.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>15.s x 17.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design depicts the marble monument that adorns William Cowper's tomb. The monument consists of marble plaque containing an inscribed epitaph by William Hayley. Above the inscription is a plinth. There are two books located centrally on the plinth. The books face spine outward. The slimmer of the two volumes is Cowper's most popular work, "The Task," and leans against the thicker of the books. This is the "Holy Bible." A large laurel branch drapes over the books forming a arch.     
               </illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>marble</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>grave</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The design depicts the marble monument that adorns William Cowper's tomb. The monument consists of marble plaque containing an inscribed epitaph by William Hayley.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>laurel</characteristic><characteristic>marble</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>bible</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the inscription is a plinth. There are two books located centrally on the plinth. The books face spine outward. The slimmer of the two volumes is Cowper's most popular work, The Task, and leans against the thicker of the books. This is the Holy Bible. A large laurel leaf drapes over the books forming a arch.  </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.01" justify="left" indent="20">HOLY</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.02" justify="left" indent="19">BIBLE</l><l n="bb648.1.comeng.06.03" justify="left" indent="17">THE</l><l n="bb648.1.comeng.06.04" justify="left" indent="16">TASK</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.05" justify="left" indent="17">IN MEMORY</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.06" justify="left" indent="12">OF WILLIAM COWPER ESQ<hi rend="superscript">R</hi>.</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.07" justify="left" indent="11">BORN IN HERTFORDSHIRE 1731</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.08" justify="left" indent="13">BURIED IN THIS CHURCH 1800.</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.09" justify="left" indent="10">YE,WHO WITH WARMTH THE PUBLIC TRIUMPH FEEL</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.10" justify="left" indent="10">OF TALENTS, DIGNIFIED BY SACRED ZEAL,</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.11" justify="left" indent="10">HERE, TO DEVOTION'S BARD DEVOUTLY JUST,</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.12" justify="left" indent="10">PAY YOUR FOND TRIBUTE DUE TO COWPER'S DUST!</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.13" justify="left" indent="10">ENGLAND, EXULTING IN HIS SPOTLESS FAME,</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.14" justify="left" indent="10">RANKS WITH HER DEAREST SONS HIS FAV'RITE NAME:</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.15" justify="left" indent="10">SENSE, FANCY, WIT SUFFICE NOT ALL TO RAISE</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.16" justify="left" indent="10">SO CLEAR A TITLE TO AFFECTION'S PRAISE;</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.17" justify="left" indent="10">HIS HIGHEST HONOURS TO THE HEART BELONG;</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.18" justify="left" indent="10">HIS VIRTUES FORM'D THE MAGIC OF HIS SONG.</l></lg><vspace extent="3"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.19" justify="left" indent="12">A Sketch of the Monument</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.20" justify="left" indent="5">Erected in the Church of East Dereham in Norfolk</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.21" justify="left" indent="6">In Memory of William Cowper Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.22" justify="left" indent="12">Etch'd by W Blake from the original Model</l><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.23" justify="left" indent="12">by John Flaxman Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sculptor to his Majesty</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb468.1.comeng.06.24" justify="left" indent="13">Publish'd by J Johnson S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Pauls 25 March 1804</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>