<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2006-12-09T21:31:02-06:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="bb466.2" type="comb" work="William Hayley, Designs to Ballads" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="bentley" catid="466" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Designs to Ballads"><main><author>William Hayley</author>, Designs to a Series of Ballads</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
           and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 21KB; 28 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 49KB to 1000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; CDLA<date>May 2009</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt><lb/><b>November 2013</b><lb/><lb/>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>. We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>&#160;illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.<lb/><lb/>
                In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>. Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.<lb/><lb/>                                                
                The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809). Only one of these plates, <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>, was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                <lb/><lb/><b>May 2009</b><lb/><lb/>                
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of Blake's etchings and engravings of his illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and to the 1805 edition of Hayley's <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>. These nineteen plates, all but two of which are based on Blake's own designs, are presented in our Preview mode, which provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (our image annotation program). <lb/><lb/>
            While Blake was resident in Felpham on the Sussex coast, beginning in 1801, his new patron William Hayley began to write a series of ballads to be illustrated by the artist-engraver. These were published in 1802 as quarto numbers, each with a frontispiece, headpiece, and tailpiece by Blake. As the general title page indicates, the poems all deal with "Anecdotes Relating to Animals." In his preface, Hayley states that his plan was to issue one ballad a month "and to complete the whole series in fifteen Numbers." The letterpress text was printed by the Chichester printer Joseph Seagrave; the plates were printed by Blake and his wife Catherine on their own rolling press. Although two book dealers, P. Humphry and R. H. Evans, were selected to sell the ballads, most copies seem to have been sold by Hayley to his friends. Sales were less than brisk and the project ceased after only four ballads were issued. Blake designed and executed twelve plates, including a frontispiece for the general title page and a tailpiece to the preface, both issued with the first ballad. Two further plates were engraved by Blake after designs on antique gems (Plates 5 and 11, the tailpieces to "The Elephant" and "The Lion").<lb/><lb/>
            We are also publishing a closely related work, Blake's five illustrations for the 1805 edition of Hayley's <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>. In January 1805, Hayley contacted the London bookseller Richard Phillips about publishing a new, octavo edition of the ballads. Blake began to execute engravings for this edition no later than March and completed five plates by June. For this 1805 volume, Hayley added twelve ballads to the four published in 1802. Blake engraved new, smaller plates of his designs for three of the 1802 ballads (Plates 1-3) and both designed and engraved new illustrations for two of the additional ballads (Plates 4-5). Blake and Phillips were to "go equal shares ... in the expense and the profits" (Blake's letter to Hayley of 22 January 1805, Erdman page 763), but it is unlikely that Blake made any profit. Robert Southey's mocking review of Hayley's poems and Blake's illustration to "The Dog" (Plate 1) appeared in the <hi rend="i">Annual Review</hi> for 1805.<lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2009</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This work copyright © 2009 Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
         <lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants:</resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Natalie Moix,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Lily Todorinova,</name><name>and Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation and image color correction</change><date>June 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, and</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change><date>Fall 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                  <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>William Hayley, *Designs to a Series of Ballads*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher,</role><role>engraver,</role><role>printer.  Objects 5 and 11 are based on antique gems and thus were not designed by Blake.  Blake and his wife Catherine printed the plates on their own rolling press.</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination><origination>Thomas Hayley <role>delineator.  Object 11, a copy of an antique gem, is signed "T. H. del:".  This indicates that "T. H." (very probably William Hayley's son, Thomas, who died in 1800) made a drawing of the gem; this drawing was the basis for Blake's engraving.</role></origination><imprint><publisher>William Blake<note>The title page specifies that the ballads were "Published, by William Blake."  They were "Printed by J. Seagrave, and sold by him and P. Humphry; and by R. H. Evans, Pall-Mall, London, for W. Blake, Felpham" (title page).</note></publisher><pubplace>Chichester</pubplace><date>1802</date></imprint><compdate value="1802.A">1802</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1802.A">1802</printdate><numberobj>14</numberobj><objorder>Bentley Plates 1-14</objorder><objsize>ranging between 4.6 x 8.3 cm. and 24.0 x 15.6 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>14</numberleaves><leafsize>27.0 x 23.4 cm.</leafsize><medium>etching and engraving</medium><printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>1802<note>In this copy, the watermark appears on the leaves bearing text pages [i]/ii, 3/4, 17/18, 21/22, 27 (Object 10)/28, 29/30, 33/34, 39 (Object 11)/[40], 43/44, and 49/50.  All the objects appear to have been printed on this same paper.</note></watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>Etched or engraved framing lines are present in Objects 12 and 14.</framelines><binding>blue levant morocco by Riviere and Son, elaborately gilt, with the original blue paper wrappers for ballads 2-4 bound at the end.<note>A coded dealer's note in pencil on the recto of the back free endpaper suggests that the book was placed in its present binding c. 1903.</note></binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name><date>1915</date><dealer>not recorded</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>The dealer Frank T. Sabin, who probably acquired each ballad separately and had them bound together in 1903; sold to Frederick R. Halsey by May 1903; acquired by Henry E. Huntington as part of the Halsey collection in December 1915.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution><addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline><addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline><addressline>USA</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2191</addressline><addressline>Fax: 626-405-0225</addressline><addressline>URL, general: http://www.huntington.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Library Division: http://www.huntington.org/LibraryDiv/LibraryHome.html</addressline><department>Rare Books</department><collection>Halsey Collection</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">57448</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="bb466.2.comb.01" dbi="BB466.2.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">General Frontispiece</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 466.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>16.9 x 13.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="825"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The central image appears in an arched frame above a text panel. A nude male with short, curly hair sits below a tree in the center of the design. The trunk of the tree divides into several branches with sparse leaves visible, particularly above and to the right of the figure. The ground below is likely covered with grass, particularly in the lower right corner of the image. The male figure rests on a stone or mound of earth. This is probably Adam in Eden, shown in the act of naming the animals. A second stone or mound appears to the left of the tree. The figure's eyes are raised and he may look at the eagle above. He faces forward with both legs bent; his left foot may be raised on tiptoe. The figure's left arm is bent with the elbow resting on his left knee; his left palm is turned up with the fingers spread slightly. His right arm is down and he touches the mane of the lion below. The lion lies on the ground and faces right in profile with its head down and possibly resting on its front paws. Its right eye is raised and the lion may look at the figure above. Its mouth is open with the tongue extended; the lion may lick the right foot of the male figure. The lion has a distinct mane of curly fur and its tail extends below. A snake or serpent with a spiky crest on its head appears on the ground below the central male figure. The snake's body faces right with its head turned to the left in profile. Its mouth is open with the tongue extended. Shading along the length of its body suggests scales. The snake's body forms four loops. Two birdsprobably dovessit or lie on the ground below the snake. The bird to the left faces right while the bird to the right faces left. Their beaks are touching. The bird to the left spreads its wings slightly. A horse with a visible mane and tail stands to the right of the central male figure. The horse faces forward and slightly right with its head turned down and to the left. The horse's front left leg is bent and raised off the ground. Both front hooves are visible. A sheep with curved horns stands in the lower right corner of the image. The sheep faces left and grazes with its head down. The sheep's eyes are closed or perhaps cast downward. The sheep's left foreleg is visible with the hoof clearly distinguishable. A peacock stands on a rock or mound of earth to the left of the central figure. The peacock is seen from behind with its head turned to the right; it may look at the male figure. The peacock's tail feathers extend downward. A rooster stands on a rock or mound of earth to the left of the central figure. The rooster faces right in profile with its head turned up. Its beak is open with the tongue extended; it is likely crowing. The rooster's tail feathers form a plume and a spiky comb appears on its head. A winged insect, possibly a moth, flies in the upper left corner of the image, facing left. A bird sits on a slender branch at the left border of the image, below the rooster. The bird faces left with its head turned to the right. The shape of its beak suggests that this may be a parrot. A horned ox or cow appears to the left of the central figure. Lines on the cow's body (to the left and right of the rooster) suggest long hair or fur. The animal is likely standing and faces to the right. Its head is down and its mouth is open slightly; it may be grazing. An eagle with outstretched wings sits or rests in the tree directly above the central male figure. The eagle's feathers are clearly visible. The eagle faces forward with its head turned up and to the right. Horizontal lines in the upper portion of the design indicate sky.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Adam</characteristic><characteristic>Eden</characteristic><characteristic>naming</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short, curly hair sits below a tree in the center of the design. This is probably Adam in Eden, shown in the act of naming the animals. His eyes are raised and he may look at the eagle above. The figure faces forward with both legs bent; his left foot may be raised on tiptoe. The figure's left arm is bent with the elbow resting on his left knee; his left palm is turned up with the fingers spread slightly. His right arm is down and he touches the mane of the lion below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a stone or mound of earth. A second stone or mound appears to the left of the tree.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>Tree of Knowledge</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tree appears in the central portion of the design above a nude male. The trunk of the tree divides into several branches with sparse leaves visible, particularly above and to the right of the figure. If the figure is Adam naming the beasts, this might be the Tree of Knowledge. The ground below is likely covered with grass, particularly in the lower right corner of the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>lion</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mane</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>paw</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A lion lies on the ground below and to the left of the nude male. The lion faces right in profile with its head down and possibly resting on its front paws. Its right eye is raised and the lion may look at the figure above. Its mouth is open with the tongue extended; the lion may lick the right foot of the male figure. The lion has a distinct mane of curly fur and its tail extends below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A snake or serpent with a spiky crest on its head appears on the ground below the central male figure. The snake's body faces right with its head turned to the left in profile. Its mouth is open with the tongue extended. Shading along the length of its body suggests scales. The snake's body forms four loops.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>dove</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two birdsprobably dovessit or lie on the ground below the snake. The bird to the left faces right while the bird to the right faces left. Their beaks are touching. The bird to the left spreads its wings slightly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="BD"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>mane</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hoof</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A horse with a visible mane and tail stands to the right of the central male figure. The horse faces forward and slightly right with its head turned down and to the left. The horse's front left leg is bent and raised off the ground. Both front hooves are visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>grazing</characteristic><characteristic>hoof</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A sheep with curved horns stands in the lower right corner of the image. The sheep faces left and grazes with its head down. The sheep's eyes are closed or perhaps cast downward. The sheep's left foreleg is visible with the hoof clearly distinguishable.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AC"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>peacock</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A peacock stands on a rock or mound of earth to the left of the central figure. The peacock is seen from behind with its head turned to the right; it may look at the male figure. The peacock's tail feathers extend downward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>rooster</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>plume</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A rooster stands on a rock or mound of earth to the left of the central figure. The rooster faces right in profile with its head turned up. Its beak is open with the tongue extended; it is likely crowing. The rooster's tail feathers form a plume and a spiky comb appears on its head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>parrot</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bird sits on a slender branch at the left border of the image, below the rooster. The bird faces left with its head turned to the right. The shape of its beak suggests that this may be a parrot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bird sits on a slender and bare branch at the left border of the image, below the rooster.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged insect, possibly a moth, flies in the upper left corner of the image, facing left. Its wings are bat-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>ox</characteristic><characteristic>cow</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>grazing</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A horned ox or cow appears to the left of the central figure. Lines on the cow's body (to the left and right of the rooster) suggest long hair or fur. The animal is likely standing and faces to the right. Its head is down and its mouth is open slightly; it may be grazing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>eagle</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An eagle with outstretched wings sits or rests in the tree directly above the central male figure. The eagle's feathers are clearly visible. The eagle faces forward with its head turned up and to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines in the upper portion of the design indicate sky.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="borderdesign" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The frame around the central design suggests a structure, possibly made of brick or stone and arched at the top. The foundation of this structure suggests a plinth. The wall above bears the inscribed text as though it were a plaque.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>brick</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The frame around the central design suggests a structure, possibly made of brick or stone and arched at the top. The foundation of this structure suggests a plinth. The wall above bears the inscribed text as though it were a plaque.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.01" justify="left" indent="8">Their strength, or speed, or vigilance, were giv'n  </l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.02" justify="left" indent="7">In aid of our defects. In some are found</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.03" justify="left" indent="7">Such teachable and apprehensive parts,</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.04" justify="left" indent="7">That man's attainments in his own concerns</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.05" justify="left" indent="7">Match'd with th' expertness of the brutes in theirs</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.06" justify="left" indent="7">Are oft times vanquish'd and thrown far behind.</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.07" justify="left" indent="37">Cowpers Task</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.08" justify="left" indent="45">Book VI.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.09" justify="left" indent="60">Blake d &amp; s</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.01.10" justify="left" indent="10">Publishd June 1. 1802 by W Blake Felpham
               </l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.02" dbi="BB466.2.2.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Tailpiece to the Preface</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 466.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>4.6 x 12.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="625" height="400"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Several buildings representing a city, probably an imaginative vision of Chichester and its cathedral, appear near the left border of the design. The building furthest right has a tall spire and is likely a church. The church and at least three buildings below have distinct roofs. Two windows are visible on the central building, and three windows appear on the building furthest right. A forest of leafy trees with visible trunks appears to the right of the church and extends to the right border of the design. The ground below the forest may be covered with grass. Indeterminate leafy vegetation appears in the foreground along the lower left border. A body of water, probably the sea, appears above the forest in the lower right portion of the design. The more distant shore of the sea rises into a hill at the right border. Etched lines in the upper portion of the image indicate sky, possibly marked with clouds. Beams of light from a rising or setting slant upwards from the lower right portion of the design.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="AC"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>Chichester</characteristic><characteristic>church</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several buildings representing a city, probably an imaginative vision of Chichester and its cathedral, appear near the left border of the design.  The letterpress text immediately above this design states that the ballads are presented to the "Inhabitants of Chichester." The building furthest right has a tall spire and is likely a church. The church and at least three buildings below have distinct roofs. Two windows are visible on the central building, and three windows appear on the building furthest right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A forest of leafy trees with visible trunks appears to the right of the church and extends to the right border of the design. The ground below the forest may be covered with grass. Indeterminate leafy vegetation appears in the foreground along the lower left border.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A body of water, probably the sea, appears above the forest in the lower right portion of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>shore</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The more distant shore of the sea rises into a hill at the right border of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate sky, possibly marked with clouds. Beams of light from a rising or setting sun slant upward from the lower right portion of the design.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb466.2.comb.02.01" justify="left" indent="65">W'B d &amp; s<note>The ampersand and final letter are poorly printed and smudged in this impression.</note></l><l n="bb466.2.comb.02.02" justify="left" indent="10">Publishd June 11 1802 by W Blake Felpham<note>The day, June 11, may be an error for June 1.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.03" dbi="BB466.2.3.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Frontispiece to The Elephant, Ballad the First</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 466.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>15.0 x 9.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="840"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An elephant stands in the center of the design with its right foreleg bent and raised off the ground. The elephant faces right with its head turned up. Its mouth is open with the tusks extend upward. Its right eye is raised and it likely looks at the figure above. The elephant holds and lifts a dark-skinned male with its trunk wrapped around the figure's waist. The figure is partly nude and wears short pants and a cloth turban. His legs extend down and to the left; the left leg crossed in front of the right, and only the figure's left foot is visible. The figure's right arm is down at his side with the palm turned down. His left arm is bent and he touches the elephant's trunk with his left hand. The figure faces forward with his head turned left in profile; his expression suggests fear or surprise. The setting is likely a city street in India; the ground may be bare earth or is perhaps covered with grass. A tent-like structure, described in the poem as a gardener's shed, appears to the right of the elephant.  In this context, the shed would appear to serve as a market stall. The shed's sloped roof is supported by at least two visible posts. A plate or shallow basket rests on the shed's counter; the plate is piled with fruit or other food, including two pineapples. Two wicker baskets with distinct handles stand on the ground below the shed; both are filled with round, possibly leafy fruits. A wall or building appears in the background to the right of the elephant. An arch appears in the middle of the structure, likely representing a door or open entryway. At least three posts or pillars support a small domed roof above the structure; a spire rises above the roof. A building with three domes on the roof appears above and to the left of the elephant. Each dome is topped with a spire. Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="E"><characteristic>elephant</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>tusk</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lifting</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>ear</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An elephant stands in the center of the design with its right foreleg bent and raised off the ground. The elephant faces right with its head turned up. Its mouth is open with the tusks extend upward. Its right eye is raised and it likely looks at the figure above. The elephant holds and lifts a dark-skinned male with its trunk wrapped around the figure's waist. The elephant's right ear is prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>turban</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An elephant holds a dark-skinned male aloft in the center of the design; the elephant's trunk wraps around the figure's waist. The figure is partly nude and wears short pants and a cloth turban. His legs extend down and to the left; the left leg crossed in front of the right, and only the figure's left foot is visible. The figure's right arm is down at his side with the palm turned down. His left arm is bent and he touches the elephant's trunk with his left hand. The figure faces forward with his head turned left in profile; his expression suggests fear or surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>hut</characteristic><characteristic>stall</characteristic><characteristic>tent</characteristic><characteristic>post</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><characteristic>fruit</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>pineapple</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tent-like structure, described in the poem as a gardener's shed, appears to the right of the elephant.  In this context the shed would appear to also serve as a market stall. The shed's sloped roof is supported by at least two visible posts. A plate or shallow wicker basket rests on the shed's counter; the plate is piled with fruit or other food, including two pineapples. Two wicker baskets with distinct handles stand on the ground below the shed; both are filled with round, possibly leafy fruits.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>dome</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>post</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A wall or building appears in the background to the right of the elephant. An arch appears in the middle of the structure, likely representing a door or open entryway. At least three posts or pillars support a small domed roof above the structure; a spire rises above the roof.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="A"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>dome</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A building with three domes on the roof appears above and to the left of the elephant. Each dome is topped with a spire.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>street</characteristic><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>India</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting is likely a city street in India; the ground may be bare earth or is perhaps covered with grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="20"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.03.01" justify="left" indent="58">Blake d &amp; s</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.03.02" justify="left" indent="9">Publish'd June 1. 1802 by W Blake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.04" dbi="BB466.2.4.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Headpiece to The Elephant, Ballad the First</title>,          
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 466.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>7.6 x 11.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="475"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is an oval. A house apparently made of stone or brick stands in the right portion of the design. The building is at least two stories tall with a ledge or balcony supported above the first floor by two pillars.  This ledge or balcony also serves as a roof for the porch below. An arched entryway is visible between the pillars; the door stands open. A leafy potted plant is visible through the open doorway. Two pilasters appear to the left and right of the arch. A single open window is visible on the second story of the house. A second window is visible through the open doorway. The building is raised on a step or other plinth-like platform. A dark-skinned male stands on a ledge or balcony above the first floor of the house. The figure is partly nude and wears short pants and a cloth turban. His left leg is bent and enters the open window; his right leg is extended backward and to the left. His right arm is bent upward; his right hand and left arm are not pictured. The figure faces right with his head turned forward, towards the viewer. He may look down and to the left towards the tiger below.  The man's lunging posture suggests that he is fleeing the beast. The tiger, which may be pursuing the man, stands facing right in a crouched position with its head down. Its mouth is open and its two canine teeth are visible. The tiger's eyes are raised and it looks at the figure on the ledge above. The ground below may be bare earth or is perhaps covered with grass. The trunk of a tree appears in the foreground along the right border of the image. Two leafy branches split off from the main trunk. A snake-like vine wraps around the trunk of the tree and the upper branch. Seven leaves appear along the vine. A tendril forms two loops suggestive of a spiral to the left of the tree trunk. Four large leaves appear below the tree along the lower border of the design. Indeterminate leafy vegetation appears to the left of the house; it may represent a jungle or forest. Two palm trees with distinct trunks and arching leaves appear above the tiger; a third palm tree appears at the left border of the image. A group of four buildings with domed roofs appear above the tiger. Each roof is topped with a spire. A triangular structure below the rightmost dome may represent a tent. A column or tower rises above the trees to the left of the domes; the structure is topped with a palmette or other decorative design. Etched lines in the upper left portion of the design indicates a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>brick</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A house apparently made of stone or brick stands in the right portion of the design. The building is at least two stories tall with a ledge or balcony supported above the first floor by two pillars.  This ledge or balcony also serves a roof for the porch below. An arched entryway is visible between the pillars; the door stands open. Two pilasters appear to the left and right of the arch. A single open window is visible on the second story of the house. A second window is visible through the open doorway. The building is raised on a step or other plinth-like platform.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>pot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A leafy potted plant is visible through the open doorway of the house.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>turban</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned male stands on a ledge or balcony above the first floor of the house. The figure is partly nude and wears short pants and a cloth turban. The figure's legs are spread apart. His left leg is bent and enters the open window; his right leg is extended backward and to the left. His right arm is bent upward; his right hand and left arm are not pictured. The figure faces right with his head turned forward, towards the viewer. He may look down and to the left towards the tiger below.  His lunging posture suggests that he is fleeing from the tiger.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>tiger</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>pursuing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tiger appears in the lower left portion of the design, possibly pursuing the man on the ledge or balcony. The tiger stands facing right in a crouched position with its head down. Its mouth is open and its two canine teeth are visible. The tiger's eyes are raised and it looks at the figure on the roof above. The tiger's tail extends upwards.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The trunk of a tree appears in the foreground along the right border of the image. Two leafy branches split off from the main trunk. A snake-like vine wraps around the trunk of the tree and the upper branch. Seven leaves appear along the vine. A tendril forms two loops suggestive of a spiral to the left of the tree trunk. Four large leaves appear below the tree along the lower border of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground may be bare earth or is perhaps covered with grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>palm</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Indeterminate leafy vegetation appears to the left of the house; it may represent a jungle or forest. Two palm trees with distinct trunks and arching leaves appear above the tiger; a third palm tree appears at the left border of the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="AC"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>dome</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>tent</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><characteristic>palmette</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of four buildings with domed roofs appear above the tiger. Each roof is topped with a spire. A triangular structure below the rightmost dome may represent a tent. A column or tower rises above the trees to the left of the domes; the structure is topped with a palmette or other decorative design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper left portion of the design indicates a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.04.01" justify="left" indent="52">Blake d &amp; s<note>Blake's signature is slightly curved to follow the outline of the oval image above.</note></l><l n="bb466.2.comb.04.02" justify="left" indent="9">Publish'd June 1. 1802 by W Blake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.05" dbi="BB466.2.5.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Tailpiece to The Elephant, Ballad the First</title>,           
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 466.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>6.9 x 8.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="475"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The image of an elephant appears within an oval representing the "Antique Gem" referenced in the inscription. The elephant stands facing left on a plinth or floor. Its tail and a single tusk are visible. The elephant's trunk is curved and raised off the ground. The gem is shadowed above, below, and to the right of the elephant.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>gem</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The image of an elephant appears within an oval representing the "Antique Gem" referenced in the inscription. The elephant is carved into the gem and thus is a bas-relief statue.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="E"><characteristic>elephant</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>tusk</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>ear</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An elephant stands facing left in the center of the design. The elephant's tail and a single tusk are visible. Its trunk is curved and raised off the ground. The animal's curving left ear is prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The elephant stands on a plinth or floor.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The gem is shadowed above, below, and to the right of the elephant.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.05.01" justify="left">Size of the Gem<note>The text is slightly curved to follow the outline of the oval below.</note></l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.05.02" justify="left" indent="58">Blake. sc<note>Blake's signature is slightly curved to follow the outline of the oval image above.</note></l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.05.03" justify="left" indent="25">From an Antique Gem</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.05.04" justify="left" indent="20">Publish'd June 1 1802, by W Blake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.06" dbi="BB466.2.6.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Frontispiece to The Eagle, Ballad the Second</title>,           
            <objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 466.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>15.2 x 9.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="825"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A gowned female kneels on a cliff in the upper portion of the design. She is identified as Jessy in Hayley's poem, "The Eagle." Jessy is the mother of the child below. The figure's legs are bent and her right foot is visible below her gown. She bends slightly right and her arms are raised nearly horizontally with the palms turned out towards the viewer. The figure's head is down and her long hair trails to the right. Her eyes are cast down and she looks at the eagle and child below. An eagle stands above a nest in the center of the design. Both talons are clearly visible. The eagle's wings are outstretched and have distinct feathers. The eagle faces forward with its head turned down and to the right. A male child or infant sits or reclines in an eagle's nest in the center of the design. The child is gowned and has short, curly hair. Both feet are visible below his gown. His left arm is bent and his left hand rests on the ground with the palm turned down; he is likely supporting his weight. The child's right arm is bent upward with the palm turned up; he touches the underside of the eagle's head with his right hand. The eagle's nest is made of straw laid on top of wooden sticks. An animal skull and perhaps part of a rib cage appear in the nest to the right of the child. A section of the cliff to the right of the eagle's nest is covered with vegetation, perhaps moss or lichens. Horizontal lines in the upper and left portions of the design indicate sky. Cross-hatching suggest clouds. Beams of light appear to emanate from a cloud above the female figure.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Jessy</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>bending right</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female kneels on a cliff in the upper portion of the design. She is identified as Jessy in Hayley's poem, "The Eagle." Jessy is the mother of the child below. The figure's legs are bent and her right foot is visible below her gown. She bends slightly right and her arms are raised nearly horizontally with the palms turned out towards the viewer. The figure's head is down and her long hair trails to the right. Her eyes are cast down and she looks at the eagle and child below. The figure's mouth is open; her expression suggests surprise or fear.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>eagle</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>talon</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>An eagle stands above a nest in the center of the design. Both talons are clearly visible. The eagle's wings are outstretched and have distinct feathers. The eagle faces forward with its head turned down and to the right.</characteristic></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child or infant sits or reclines in an eagle's nest in the center of the design. The child is gowned and has short, curly hair. Both feet are visible below his gown. His left arm is bent and his left hand rests on the ground with the palm turned down; he is likely supporting his weight. The child's right arm is bent upward with the palm turned up; he touches the underside of the eagle's head with his right hand. The child faces forward and slightly left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>nest</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>stick</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>skull</characteristic><characteristic>ribs</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An eagle's nest rests on a cliff in the center of the design. The nest is made of straw laid on top of wooden sticks. An animal skull and perhaps part of a rib cage appear in the nest to the right of the infant.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place on a cliffside that rises along the right border of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>moss</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A section of the cliff to the right of the eagle's nest is covered with vegetation, perhaps moss or lichens.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines in the upper and left portions of the design indicate sky. Cross-hatching may suggest clouds. Beams of light appear to emanate from a cloud above the female figure.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="20"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.06.01" justify="left" indent="55">Blake d &amp; s</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.06.02" justify="left" indent="12">Publishd July 1. 1802 by W Blake</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.06.03" justify="left" indent="21">Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.07" dbi="BB466.2.7.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Headpiece to The Eagle, Ballad the Second</title>,           
            <objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 466.7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>7.3 x 9.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="475"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An eagle flies in the upper portion of the design. The eagle faces left with its head turned down and to the right; it may look at the infant below. The eagle's beak is open and the tongue slightly extended. Its wings extend up and to the right, and its left talon is visible. The eagle's body is covered with feathers. A nude(?), male child or infant lies in a wicker basket or cradle in the lower portion of the design. A blanket or sheet is draped over the left and right edges of the basket. The child lies on his side with his body horizontal. His legs point to the left; only his right leg is fully visible. The child's right arm is down and crosses in front of his chest. His left arm is bent and his head may rest on his left hand. The child's eyes are closed and he is likely sleeping. He may be smiling. A chair stands to the right of the cradle. A spinning wheel appears in the lower right corner of the design. A distaff is propped upright to the right of the spinning wheel; thread hangs from the distaff. A house or cottage appears in the right portion of the design. The roof of the building is probably made of straw. The doorway of the cottage stands open with the interior cast in dark shadow. A latticed window appears to the left of the door. The ground below is covered with grass. A series of mountains rise in the distance to the left of the cottage. Shadows on the mountain above and to the left of the child may suggest distant trees. A building or other square structure stands below the peak of the second mountain from the left. A house, hut, or cottage stands below the mountain furthest right. A single door or window is visible. Etched lines above the mountains indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>eagle</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>talon</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An eagle flies in the upper portion of the design. The eagle faces left with its head turned down and to the right; it may look at the infant below. The eagle's beak is open and the tongue slightly extended. Its wings extend up and to the right, and its left talon is visible. The eagle's body is covered with feathers.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude(?), male child or infant lies in a woven basket or cradle in the lower portion of the design.  His hair is short and curly. A blanket or sheet is draped over the left and right of the basket. The child lies on his side with his body horizontal. His legs point to the left; only his right leg is fully visible. The child's right arm is down and crosses in front of his chest. His left arm is bent and his head may rest on his left hand. The child's eyes are closed and he is likely sleeping. He may be smiling.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>cradle</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A child lies in a wicker basket or cradle in the lower portion of the design. A blanket or sheet is draped over the left and right edges of the basket.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A chair stands to the right of the cradle.  Its seat may be made of wicker.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>spinning wheel</characteristic><characteristic>distaff</characteristic><characteristic>thread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A spinning wheel stands in the lower right corner of the design. A distaff is propped upright to the right of the spinning wheel; thread hangs from the distaff.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A house or cottage appears in the right portion of the design. The roof of the building is probably made of straw. The doorway of the cottage stands open with the interior cast in dark shadow. A latticed window appears to the left of the door.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the child and the cottage is covered with grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A series of mountains rise in the distance to the left of the cottage.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Shadows on the mountain above and to the left of the child may suggest distant trees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="A"><characteristic>building</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A building or other square structure stands below the peak of the second mountain from the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="D"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>hut</characteristic><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A house, hut, or cottage stands below the mountain furthest right. A single door or window is visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines above the mountains indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.07.01" justify="left" indent="15">Publish'd July 1 1802 by W Blake Felpham <space extent="13"/>Bl<note>Only the first two letters of Blake's signature are printed in this copy.  Other copies show that the full signature is "Blake in &amp; s".</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.08" dbi="BB466.2.8.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Tailpiece to The Eagle, Ballad the Second</title>,          
            <objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 466.8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>7.2 x 10.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="475"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An eagle lies supine in the lower portion of the design. The eagle is upside down with its wings spread. Both talons are visible. The eagle's head is turned to the right with its beak open and tongue extended. Its left eye is closed and the eagle may be dead or dying. The eagle's body is covered in feathers. A male child with short, curly hair stands triumphant in the center of the design. He wears short pants and an open shirt. He stands with his legs spread apart; both feet cast shadows to the right. The child's arms are raised horizontally with the palms turned down. He faces forward with his head turned slightly down and to the right; he may look at the eagle below. The child's mouth is open and he appears to be smiling. Large stones or perhaps distant mountains appear to the left and right of the child. The child may stand at the edge of a cliff. The ground below the eagle may be covered with grass. One or more large leaves, perhaps palm fronds, appear in the lower left corner of the design. Patches of indeterminate vegetation, perhaps moss or lichens, appear on the stone at the right border of the image. Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>eagle</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>talon</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>dying</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An eagle lies supine in the lower portion of the design. The eagle is upside down with its wings spread. Both talons are visible. The eagle's head is turned to the right with its beak open and tongue extended. Its left eye is closed and the eagle may be dead or dying. The eagle's body is covered in feathers.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms down</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child with short, curly hair stands triumphant in the center of the design. He wears short pants and an open shirt. He stands with his legs spread apart; both feet cast shadows to the right. The child's arms are raised horizontally with the palms turned down. He faces forward with his head turned slightly down and to the right; he may look at the eagle below. The child's mouth is open and he appears to be smiling.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Large stones or perhaps distant mountains appear to the left and right of the child. The child may stand at the edge of a cliff.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>moss</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>palm</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the eagle may be covered with grass. One or more large leaves, perhaps palm fronds, appear in the lower left corner of the design. Patches of indeterminate vegetation, perhaps moss or lichens, appear on the stone at the right border of the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.08.01" justify="left" indent="10">Publish'd July 1 1802 by W Blake Felpham <space extent="13"/>Blake in<note>Blake's name in the signature lower right is very lightly printed in this copy.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.09" dbi="BB466.2.9.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Frontispiece to The Lion, Ballad the Third</title>,           
            <objid><objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber><objcode code="B9">(Bentley 466.9)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>16.0 x 12.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="870"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned female stands in the lower right portion of the design. She is identified as an African woman, Boulla, in Hayley's poem "The Lion." She is the mother of the boy to the right and the wife of the male in the tree, above and to the left. She is partly nude and wears a skirt and a cloth cap or turban over her curly hair. Boulla is seen from behind; she faces away with her head turned to the left and her mouth open slightly. The figure stands with her legs spread apart and her right foot raised on tiptoe. Her right arm is bent upward with the palm of her right hand turned up. Her left arm is bent and she holds a stringed bow in her left hand. Two arrows appear on the ground below the female figure. The arrowheads point to the left. Both arrows have visible fletchings, possibly made of feather. A dark-skinned African male child stands in the lower right portion of the design; his left foot may be raised on tiptoe. He is not identified in Hayley's poem by name, but likely represents Boulla's son. The child wears a skirt and has short, curly hair. He faces forward with his head turned up and to the left in profile. His mouth is open slightly and his left eye is raised; he may look at Boulla or towards the figure in the tree above and to the left. The child's arms are bent upward with the right palm facing down and the left palm facing slightly up. A lion stands in the lower left portion of the design, facing left. The lion's mouth is open with teeth visible and the tongue extended. Its neck or lower jaw is pierced by an arrow, and it wears an expression of pain. A dark-skinned African male appears in the upper left corner of the design, among the leaves of a palm tree. His hair is short and curly. The figure is identified as Demba in Hayley's poem, "The Lion." He is the husband of the female archer and the father of the male child. Only his upper body is visible. His arms are bent upward at approximately 135 degrees; he holds onto palm leaves with both hands. He faces forward with his head turned slightly right; he may look down toward the figures below. Two bunches of round fruit appear in the tree, to the left and below Demba. A second palm tree grows along the right border of the design; a bunch of fruit is visible at the top of the palm's trunk. The ground below both trees is covered with grass. The lion stands on a cliff or ledge in the left portion of the design while Boulla and her son stand on a cliff below and to the right. A third cliff is visible in the middle distance above and to the left of Boulla. A body of water, perhaps a river or the sea, appears between the cliffs near the lower border of the design. A distant mountain rises above the water. Indeterminate, leafy vegetation extends to the left and right of Boulla and her son; this may represent a forest or jungle located on the cliff in the middle distance. A single tree trunk is distinguishable to the left of Boulla's left leg. Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Boulla</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>African</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>turban</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned female stands in the lower right portion of the design. She is identified as an African woman, Boulla, in Hayley's poem "The Lion." She is the mother of the boy to the right and the wife of the male in the tree, above and to the left. She is partly nude and wears a skirt and a cloth cap or turban over her curly hair. Boulla is seen from behind; she faces away with her head turned to the left and her mouth open slightly. The figure stands with her legs spread apart and her right foot raised on tiptoe. Her right arm is bent upward with the palm of her right hand turned up. Her left arm is bent and she holds a stringed bow in her left hand. She appears to have just shot the arrow piercing the lion to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two arrows appear on the ground below the female figure. The arrowheads point to the left. Both arrows have visible fletchings, possibly made of feather.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>African</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned African male child stands in the lower right portion of the design; his left foot may be raised on tiptoe. He is not identified in Hayley's poem by name, but likely represents Boulla's son. The child wears a skirt and has short, curly hair. He faces forward with his head turned up and to the left in profile. His mouth is open slightly and his left eye is raised; he may look at Boulla or towards the figure in the tree above and to the left. The child's arms are bent upward with the right palm facing down and the left palm facing slightly up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>lion</characteristic><characteristic>mane</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>pain</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A lion stands on a cliff or ledge in the lower left portion of the design. It faces left. The lion's mouth is open with teeth visible and the tongue extended. Its neck or lower jaw is pierced by an arrow, and it wears an expression of pain. The lion's tail is raised.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>African</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>Demba</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned African male appears in the upper left corner of the design, among the leaves of a palm tree. His hair is short and curly. The figure is identified as Demba in Hayley's poem, "The Lion." He is the husband of the female archer and the father of the male child. Only his upper body is visible. His arms are bent upward at approximately 135 degrees; he holds onto palm leaves with both hands.  He faces forward with his head turned slightly right; he may look down toward the figures below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>palm</characteristic><characteristic>fruit</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Demba appears in a tree with a distinct trunk and arching palm leaves at the left border of the design. Two bunches of round fruit appear in the tree, to the left and below the figure. A second palm tree grows along the right border of the design; a bunch of fruit is visible at the top of the palm's trunk. The ground below both trees is covered with grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>Africa</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Hayley's poem, "The Lion," indicates that the setting is Africa. The lion stands on a cliff or ledge in the left portion of the design while Boulla and her son stand on a cliff below and to the right. A third cliff is visible in the middle distance above and to the left of Boulla. A body of water, perhaps a river or the sea, appears between the cliffs near the lower border of the design. A distant mountain rises above the water.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Indeterminate, leafy vegetation extends to the left and right of Boulla and her son; this may represent a forest or jungle located on the cliff in the middle distance. A single tree trunk is distinguishable to the left of Boulla's left leg.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="20"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.09.01" justify="left" indent="10">Publish'd Aug<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>: 5: 1802 by WBlake Felpham <space extent="13"/>Blake<note>Only Blake's name in the signature, lower right, is printed in this copy.  Other copies show that the full signature is "Blake in &amp; s".</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.10" dbi="BB466.2.10.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Headpiece to The Lion, Ballad the Third</title>,           
            <objid><objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber><objcode code="B10">(Bentley 466.10)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>7.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is an oval. A dark-skinned African female stands in the center of the design. She is identified as Boulla in Hayley's poem, "The Lion," and is likely the mother of the boy to the left. Boulla is gowned and wears a cloth cap or turban over her curly hair. She stands facing left with her left leg bent and her right leg extended backward. Her right foot is raised on tiptoe and she may walk or stride to the left. Both arms are bent and she holds two arrows in her left hand and a third arrow in her right hand. All three arrows point downward and each has a feathered fletching. A dark-skinned male child stands to the left. Though not identified by name in Hayley's poem, he likely represents Boulla's son. The child wears a skirt and has short, curly hair. He faces forward with his head turned slightly right; he may look at Boulla or the arrows she holds in her hands. The child stands with his legs spread and slightly bent. His left foot may be raised on tiptoe; he may be striding or walking to the left. The figure's left arm is bent and he holds a bow and bowstring in his left hand. His right arm is raised horizontally and he points to the left with his forefinger extended. Three huts with straw roofs appear in the right portion of the design. A fence of wooden posts stands below the right corner of the leftmost hut and extends to the right border of the image. The huts may represent a village.  A road or path, or perhaps even a river or stream, appears in the lower left portion of the design, visible between and to the left of the child's legs. The ground below the figures is covered with grass. Indeterminate, leafy vegetation appears left and right of the child and above the central hut. A tree with a slender trunk and arching palm leaves rises above the central hut. A distant mountain rises above the vegetation at the left border of the image. Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>African</characteristic><characteristic>Boulla</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>turban</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned African female stands in the center of the design. She is identified as Boulla in Hayley's poem, "The Lion," and is likely the mother of the boy to the left. Boulla is gowned and wears a cloth cap or turban over her curly hair. She stands facing left with her left leg bent and her right leg extended backward. Her right foot is raised on tiptoe and she may walk or stride to the left. Both arms are bent and she holds two arrows in her left hand and a third arrow in her right hand. All three arrows point downward and each has a feathered fletching.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dark-skinned male child stands to the left of the female. Though not identified by name in Hayley's poem, he likely represents Boulla's son. The child wears a skirt and has short, curly hair. He faces forward with his head turned slightly right; he may look at Boulla or the arrows she holds in her hands. The child stands with his legs spread and slightly bent. His left foot may be raised on tiptoe; he may be walking or striding to the left. The figure's left arm is bent and he holds a bow and bowstring in his left hand. His right arm is raised horizontally and he points to the left with his forefinger extended.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>hut</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>fence</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>post</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three huts with straw roofs appear in the right portion of the design. A fence of wooden posts stands below the right corner of the leftmost hut and extends to the right border of the image. The huts may represent a village.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>stream</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A road or path, or perhaps even a river or stream, appears in the lower left portion of the design, visible between and to the left of the child's legs.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>palm</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the figures is covered with grass. Indeterminate, leafy vegetation appears left and right of the child and above the central hut. A tree with a slender trunk and arching palm leaves rises above the central hut.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A distant mountain rises above the vegetation at the left border of the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.10.01" justify="left" indent="47">Blake inv &amp; sc<note>Blake's signature is curved slightly to follow the outline of the oval image above.</note></l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.10.02" justify="left" indent="8">Publish'd Aug<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 5: 1802. by W Blake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.11" dbi="BB466.2.11.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Tailpiece to The Lion, Ballad the Third</title>,           
            <objid><objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber><objcode code="B11">(Bentley 466.11)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>6.2 x 8.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="400"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The image of a lion appears within an oval frame represting the "Antique" gem referenced in the inscription. The lion stands facing left with its left foreleg extended. The lion's head is down slightly and its mouth is open. The lion's mane is full and its tail visible; the tip of its tail is obscured by the rear left leg. The lion stands on a floor or the ground.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>gem</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>The image of a lion appears within an oval frame represting the "Antique" gem referenced in the inscription. The lion is carved into the gem and is thus a bas-relief statue.</characteristic></component><component type="animal" location="E"><characteristic>lion</characteristic><characteristic>mane</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The image of a lion appears within an oval frame represting the "Antique" gem referenced in the inscription. The lion stands facing left with its left foreleg extended. The lion's head is down slightly and its mouth is open. The lion's mane is full and its tail visible; the tip of its tail is obscured by the rear left leg.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>floor</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The lion stands on a floor or the ground.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.11.01" justify="left" indent="5">T.H. del: <space extent="29"/>Blake. sc
               <note>The text is curved to follow the outline of the oval image above.</note></l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.11.02" justify="left" indent="22">From an Antique
               </l><l n="bb466.2.comb.11.03" justify="left" indent="10">Publishd Aug<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 5 1802 by WBlake Felpham
               </l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.12" dbi="BB466.2.12.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Frontispiece to The Dog, Ballad the Fourth</title>,           
            <objid><objnumber code="A12">Object 12 </objnumber><objcode code="B12">(Bentley 466.12)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>24.0 x 15.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="850"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The central image depicts a scene from Hayley's poem, "The Dog." A nude male identified in the poem as Edward stands at the edge of a cliff in the upper right portion of the design. Edward faces left with his head turned down slightly; he looks at the dog and crocodile below. His mouth is open and his expression suggests fear or surprise. The figure leans backward and to the right. Both legs are bent and spread apart with his right foot raised on tiptoe. His arms are bent upward with the left palm turned slightly up and the right palm held vertically. Indeterminate leafy vegetation appears on the cliff to the right of Edward; it may represent moss or lichens. A dog with curly fur falls upside down in the lower left portion of the design. The dog is identified as Fido in Hayley's poem. The dog's legs are spread with the rear legs extended upward and the forelegs extended down. The open jaws of a crocodile appear above the water in the lower left corner of the image; its teeth are clearly visible. The crocodile faces up and to the right. Its right eye is visible below the surface of the water. A body of water, likely the sea, appears in the lower portion of the design. Small waves are visible on the water's surface, particularly at the base of the cliff. A distant shore rises above the sea; the area of land furthest left may represent an island. Indeterminate, leafy vegetation appears on the upper shores of the sea. Two trees with arching palm leaves rise above the indeterminate vegetation near the left border of the image. Three domed roofs appear on the distant shore of the sea, just right of the falling dog. Each dome is topped with a spire. A structure immediately to the right may represent a spire or tower. A wall or part of a building is visible below the edge of the cliff. Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Edward</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short, curly hair stands at the edge of a cliff in the upper right portion of the design. The figure is identified as Edward in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." The figure faces left with his head turned down slightly; he looks at the dog and crocodile below. His mouth is open and his expression suggests fear or surprise. The figure leans backward and to the right. Both legs are bent and spread apart with his right foot raised on tiptoe. His arms are bent upward with the left palm turned slightly up and the right palm held vertically.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male figure stands at the edge of a rocky cliff.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>moss</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Indeterminate leafy vegetation appears on the cliff to the right of the male figure. It may represent moss or lichens.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>Fido</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dog with curly fur falls upside down in the lower left portion of the design. The dog is identified as Fido in Hayley's poem, "The Dog.". The dog's legs are spread with the rear legs extended upward and the forelegs extended down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>crocodile</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The open jaws of a crocodile appear above the water in the lower left corner of the image. The crocodile's teeth are clearly visible. The crocodile faces up and to the right. Its right eye is visible below the surface of the water.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><characteristic>island</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A body of water, likely the sea, appears in the lower portion of the design. Small waves are visible on the water's surface, particularly at the base of the cliff. A distant shore rises above the sea; the area of land furthest left may represent an island.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>palm</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Indeterminate, leafy vegetation appears on the upper shores of the sea. Two trees with arching palm leaves rise above the indeterminate vegetation near the left border of the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="C"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>dome</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>fence</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three domed roofs appear on the distant shore of the sea, just right of the falling dog. Each dome is topped with a spire. A structure immediately to the right may represent a spire or tower. A wall or part of a building is visible below the edge of the cliff.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="borderdesign" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several vignettes. A female stands in the lower left portion of the frame, facing forward. The figure's left arm is down at her side and she holds a book or tablet in her left hand. Her right arm is raised vertically and she holds a pair of balances above her head. The figure may represent Justice. Her eyes are closed and she may be blind. Two twisting, intertwining branches form an elaborate, intertwined pattern, suggestive of the Tree of Jesse motif, above the female figure. A nude male child with short, curly hair appears in the lower left corner of the frame. The child's legs are spread apart with his right leg bent back; he may stride, run, or leap to the right. His right arm is bent upward with the palm turned up. The child's left arm is raised horizontally and he holds a bow in his left hand. This figure may be Cupid. A body of water, perhaps the sea, appears in the lower portion of the frame. A rectangular object or structure appears in the center of the water. Waves are visible, particularly to the right of the object. The heads of the two fish swim in the water at the bottom of the frame, left of the rectangular object; they face up and to the right with their mouths open. A third fish appears to the right, facing left. All three fish have spiky dorsal fins. A fishing pole appears directly left of the rectangular object; a fishing line hangs from the pole. A female(?) figure kneels in the lower right corner of the frame. The figure's legs are bent with the right leg drawn up slightly. Both arms are bent upward with at least the left palm turned up. The figure faces left in profile with her head down; the figure's face is covered by her hands. A quiver of arrows appears on the figure's back with a strap visible over her left arm.  She may be mourning. A gowned male with curly hair and a beard stands in the lower right portion of the frame. He faces forward and wears a blindfold. His right arm is bent in front of his chest and a shackle appears on his right wrist; the shackle is connected to a chain of at least nine links. A gowned child of indeterminate gender stands to the right; the child holds the end of the chain in his or her right hand. Two twisting, intertwining branches form an elaborate pattern, suggestive of the Tree of Jesse motif, above the two figures.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Justice</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>blind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>tablet</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>pair of balances</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. A female stands in the lower left portion of the frame. She faces forward and wears a gown or skirt. The figure's left arm is down at her side and she holds a book or tablet in her left hand. Her right arm is raised vertically and she holds a pair of balances above her head. The figure may represent Justice. Her eyes are closed and she may be blind.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>Tree of Jesse</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. Two twisting, intertwining branches form an elaborate intertwined pattern, suggestive of the Tree of Jesse motif, above the female figure in the left portion of the frame.  The pattern also suggests a spiral.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>leaping</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>Cupid</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. A nude male child with short, curly hair appears in the lower left corner of the frame. The child's legs are spread apart with his right leg bent back; he may stride, run, or leap to the right. His right arm is bent upward with the palm turned up. The child's left arm is raised horizontally and he holds a bow in his left hand. This figure may be Cupid.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. A body of water, perhaps the sea, appears in the lower portion of the frame. A rectangular object or structure appears in the center of the water. Waves are visible, particularly to the right of the rectangular object.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>fish</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>fin</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>swimming</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. The heads of the two fish appear in the water at the bottom of the frame, left of the rectangular object; they face up and to the right with their mouths open. A third fish swims to the right of the rectangular object, facing left. All three fish have spiky dorsal fins.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>fishing pole</characteristic><characteristic>pole</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. A fishing pole appears in the lower portion of the frame, directly left of the rectangular object. A fishing line hangs from the pole.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent up</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>quiver</characteristic><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. A female(?) figure appears in the lower right corner of the frame. The figure kneels on a small mound with both legs bent and the right leg drawn up slightly. Both arms are bent upward with at least the left palm turned up. The figure faces left in profile with her head down; the figure's face is covered by her hands. A quiver of arrows appears on the figure's back with a strap visible over her left arm.  She may wear a gown with a belt at the waist. She may be mourning.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>mound</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. The figure in the lower right corner of the frame kneels on a small mound or hillock.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mustache</characteristic><characteristic>blindfolded</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. An old gowned male with curly hair and a beard and mustache stands in the lower right portion of the frame. He faces forward and wears a blindfold. His right arm is bent in front of his chest and a shackle appears on his right wrist; the shackle is connected to a chain of at least nine links. The figure's left arm is not clearly pictured, but may be down at his side.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. A gowned child of indeterminate gender stands in the lower right portion of the frame. The child faces forward with the head turned up and to the left; he or she may look at the figure to the left. The child's right arm is bent and he or she holds the end of a chain; the chain attaches to a shackle bound to the figure to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>Tree of Jesse</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is surrounded by a frame containing several figures and vignettes. Two twisting, intertwining branches form an elaborate pattern, suggestive of the Tree of Jesse motif, above the two figures in the right portion of the frame. The pattern also suggests a spiral.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="20"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb466.2.comb.12.01" justify="left" indent="58">Blake inv &amp; sc</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.12.02" justify="left" indent="7">Publish'd Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: 9: 1802 by W Blake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.13" dbi="BB466.2.13.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Headpiece to The Dog, Ballad the Fourth</title>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A13">Object 13 </objnumber><objcode code="B13">(Bentley 466.13)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>7.1 x 9.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A male figure with curly hair stands in the center of this oval design. He is identified as Edward in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." Edward is dressed as a soldier; he wears boots, pants or tights, a coat with distinct buttons, a bow tie, and a helmet with a large plume. The figure faces forward with his head turned down and to the right; he looks toward the female figure to the right. Both arms are down at his sides. The palm of his right hand is turned down and he touches the right paw of the dog below with his left hand. A female identified in the poem as Lucy stands in the center of the design. She wears heeled shoes a gown with a ruffled collar. She stands with both legs bent slightly and her left foot raised on tiptoe. Lucy faces left and bends forward at the waist with her head down; she looks at the dog below. Both arms are bent. Her right hand points to the left toward the male figure; her left arm is down and she touches the chin and neck of the dog below. A dog identified in the poem as Fido sits in the center of the design, between Edward and Lucy. Fido sits facing left with his head turned up and to the right; he looks at Lucy. The dog's right foreleg extends upward and he touches Edward's right leg. Three steps or stairs appear to the right of the female figure. A pillar stands atop a pedestal at the top of the stairs; further right, the corner of a building or other structure is visible. The ground below the figures may be covered with grass. Two leafless trees stand to the left of the figures; their trunks divide into several branches. A leafy tree stands to the right of the figures, behind and above the stairs. Shapes to the left of the figures suggest mountains. Horizontal lines below the mountain furthest left indicates a body of water, perhaps the sea or a lake. At the base of the mountain furthest left, a triangular structure suggests a building with a spire. Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Edward</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>boots</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>button</characteristic><characteristic>tie</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>plume</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure with curly hair stands in the center of the design. He is identified as Edward in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." Edward is dressed as a soldier; he wears boots, pants or tights, a coat with distinct buttons, a bow tie, and a helmet with a large plume. The figure faces forward with his head turned down and to the right; he looks toward the female figure to the right. Both arms are down at his sides. The palm of his right hand is turned down and he touches the right paw of the dog below with his left hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Lucy</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female with curly hair, perhaps partly pulled back into a bun, stands in the center of the design. She is identified as Lucy in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." She wears a gown with a ruffled collar and heeled shoes. She stands with both legs bent slightly and her left foot raised on tiptoe. The figure faces left and bends forward at the waist with her head down; she looks at the dog below. Both arms are bent. Her right hand points to the left toward the male figure; her left arm is down and she touches the chin of the dog below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>Fido</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dog with curly fur sits in the center of the design, between Edward and Lucy. He is identified as Fido in Hayley's poem, "the Dog." Fido sits facing left with his head turned up and to the right; he looks at Lucy. The dog's right foreleg extends upward and he touches Edward's right leg.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>pedestal</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three steps or stairs appear to the right of the female figure. A pillar stands atop a pedestal at the top of the stairs; further right, the corner of a building or other structure is visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the figures may be covered with grass. Two leafless trees stand to the left of the figures; their trunks divide into several branches. A leafy tree stands to the right of the figures, behind and above the stairs.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>lake</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Shapes to the left of the figures suggest mountains. Horizontal lines below the mountain furthest left indicates a body of water, perhaps the sea or a lake.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="C"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>triangle</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the base of the mountain furthest left, a triangular structure suggests a building with a spire.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Etched lines in the upper portion of the design indicate a sky filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="borderdesign" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The central image is in an oval frame. Two leafy vines or branches grow along the outer border of the frame. As many as twenty-five flowers or buds grow along the vines, and both vines are covered with small thorns. The flowers may be roses.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>bud</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>thorn</characteristic><characteristic>rose</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central image is in an oval frame. Two leafy vines or branches grow along the outer border of the frame. As many as twenty-five flowers or buds grow along the vines, and both vines are covered with small thorns. The flowers may be roses.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="10"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.13.01" justify="left" indent="44">Blake inv s<note>Blake's signature is slightly curved to follow the outline of the image above.</note></l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.13.02" justify="left" indent="10">Publish'd Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 9: 1802 by WBlake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb466.2.comb.14" dbi="BB466.2.14.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Tailpiece to The Dog, Ballad the Fourth</title>,            
            <objid><objnumber code="A14">Object 14 </objnumber><objcode code="B14">(Bentley 466.14)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>13.7 x 9.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="760"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A female with long hair stands in the left portion of the design. She is identified as Lucy in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." Lucy wears a gown with a ruffled hem and collar. She stands facing right with her head down; her head may rest on the statue of the dog to the right. The figure's left arm is bent upward and her left hand rests on her chest. Her right arm is bent and she touches the statue of the dog with her fingers spread slightly. Lucy's expression and posture suggest a gentle form of grief. A statue of a dog rests on a pedestal above a dresser, table, or bookcase.  If a bookcase, the vertical rectangles on the three shelves may be the spines of books. The dog is identified as Fido in Hayley's poem. Fido lays facing right with its head held up and turned to the left. The dog's front legs are crossed with the right paw resting on top of the left paw. The scene takes place in a room. The floor of the room is covered with an elaborate carpet, perhaps decorated with a vine or other vegetative motif. A bed with a canopy is visible at the left border of the design; the bed may be covered with a sheet or blanket with a pillow. A window with a valance curtain appears in the upper right corner of the wall. Through the window, a crescent moon is visible in a dark sky, indicating that the scene takes place at night. Two mountain peaks are visible below the moon. Horizontal lines at the base of the mountains may indicate a body of water, perhaps the sea or a lake. Leafy, indeterminate vegetation, or distant trees, are visible through the window and below the mountains.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Lucy</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breast</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female with long hair stands in the left portion of the design. She is identified as Lucy in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." Lucy wears a gown with a ruffled hem and collar. She stands facing right with her head down; her head may rest on the statue of the dog to the right. The figure's left arm is bent upward and her left hand rests on her chest. Her right arm is bent and she touches the statue of the dog with her fingers spread slightly. Lucy's expression and posture suggest a gentle form of grief.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>pedestal</characteristic><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>Fido</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>paw</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A statue of a dog rests on a pedestal above a dresser or table. The dog is identified as Fido in Hayley's poem, "The Dog." Fido lays facing right with its head held up and turned to the left. The dog's front legs are crossed with the right paw resting on top of the left paw.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>curtain</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>carpet</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>canopy</characteristic><characteristic>table</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room. A window with a valance curtain appears in the upper right corner of the wall. The floor is covered with an elaborate carpet, perhaps decorated with a vine or other vegetative motif. A bed with a canopy is visible at the left border of the design; the bed may be covered with a sheet and a blanket with a pillow. A low dresser, table, or bookcase stands to the right of the bed.  If a bookcase, the vertical rectangles on the three shelves may be the spines of books.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>crescent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Through the window, a crescent moon is visible in a dark sky, indicating that the scene takes place at night.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>lake</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two mountain peaks are visible through the window. Horizontal lines at the base of the mountains may indicate a body of water, perhaps the sea or a lake.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Leafy, indeterminate vegetation, or distant trees, are visible through the window, below the mountains and the sea.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="borderdesign" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The central design is surrounded by a single framing line on all four sides. Two vines appear in the lower border. Two leaves grow on each vine at the lower left and right corners of the design. A tendril rises from each vine, each with several loops suggestive of spirals.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>line</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A single framing lines surrounds the central design on all four sides.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two vines appear at the lower border of the image. Two leaves grow on each vine at the lower left and right corners of the design. A tendril rises from each vine, each with several loops suggestive of spirals.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="20"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb466.2.comb.14.01" justify="left" indent="58">Blake. in: s</l><l n="bb466.2.comb.14.02" justify="left" indent="7">Publish'd Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>: 9: 1802 by W Blake Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>