<bad catalog="bentley" catid="467" copy="1" copyid="1" id="bb467.1" institution="essick" type="comeng" work="Hayley, An Essay on Sculpture">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="An Essay on Sculpture">
          <main>
            <author>William Hayley</author>, An Essay on Sculpture</main>
          <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;


          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and


          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>1 XML file approx. 28KB; 10 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 54KB to 1100KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
        <date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his 
        <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>
        , the broadside ballad 
        <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>
        , 
        <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>
        , 
        <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>
        , and 
        <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>
        . We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to 
        <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi>
        (1802) and Hayley’s 
        <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>
        (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of 
        <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>
         illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem 
        <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>
        . Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s 
        <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>
        (1809). Only one of these plates, 
        <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>
        , was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. 
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2013</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This image copyright © 2013 William Blake Archive.

         
      <lb/>
      <lb/></userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>November 2013</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
          <name>Laura Bell</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
          <name>Adam Engel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Michael Fox,</name>
          <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
          <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
          <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
          <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
          <name>Eric Loy,</name>
          <name>Kate Massie,</name>
          <name>Adam McCune,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
          <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
          <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
          <name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
        <date>July 2012</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               
          <name>Robert Essick,</name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
          <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
          <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
          <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
        <date>Fall 2005</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               
          <name>Robert Essick,</name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue </name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
          <name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>
            William Hayley, *An Essay on Sculpture*
          </title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake
          <role>etcher,</role>
          <role>engraver</role></origination>
        <origination><role>inventor.  Anonymous classical sculptor (Object 1), Thomas Hayley (Object 2), and John Flaxman (Object 3).  Flaxman may have also assisted in the composition of Object 2.</role></origination>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>T. Cadell and W. Davies
                    </publisher>
          <pubplace>London</pubplace>
          <date>1800</date>
        </imprint>
        <compdate value="1800.A">1800</compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <printdate value="1800.A">1800</printdate>
        <numberobj>3</numberobj>
        <objorder>Bentley Plates 1-3</objorder>
        <objsize>11.8 x 9.7 cm. (Object 1), 15.7 x 18.0 cm. (Object 2), 10.8 x 7 cm. (Object 3)</objsize>
        <numberleaves>3</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>29.6 x 22.2 cm.</leafsize>
        <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
        <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
        <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
        <support>wove paper</support>
        <watermark>J WHATMAN / 1794
          <note>The watermark appears only in Object 3 in this copy.</note></watermark>
        <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
        <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
        <framelines>1
          <note>The design in Object 2 is surrounded with a single framing line.</note></framelines>
        <binding>publisher's boards</binding>
        <stabholes>none</stabholes>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
        <date>2005</date>
        <dealer>Alex Fotheringham Books</dealer>
        <price>$660</price>
        <note>Early history not known; acquired Aug. 2005 by Essick from Alex Fotheringham Books ($660).</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
        <addressline>Altadena, California</addressline>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="BB467.1.1.COM" id="bb467.1.comeng.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">PERICLES.</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B1">(Bentley 467.1)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objsize>11.8 x 9.7 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
          <p>The platemark measures 22.8 x 16.4 cm. For the inscription top right, select &quot;Supplemental Views&quot; on the &quot;Show Me...&quot; menu.</p>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize height="700" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a roundel containing the head of Pericles, in profile facing left. Pericles is wearing a classical helmet with an eye hole, and lower face guard. The helmet is pushed upward and the face guard rests on Pericles's forehead. He sports a closed cropped bearded and short hair. His eye is open and his lips are slightly parted. His left shoulder is visible and he is wearing a garment of some sort over that shoulder. Bordering the roundel are two leafy branches, possibly laurel, with berries. Beneath the roundel, the branches are connected with a double loop device, possibly a rope, string, or ribbon, that appears to be a continuation of the branches.       
                    </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Pericles</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a roundel containing the head of Pericles, in profile facing left. Pericles is wearing a classical helmet with an eye hole, and lower face guard. The helmet is pushed upward and the face guard rests on Pericles's forehead. He sports a closed cropped bearded and short hair. His eye is open and his lips are slightly parted. His left shoulder is visible and he is wearing a garment of some sort, possibly a robe.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>laurel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
            <characteristic>string</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Bordering the roundel are two leafy branches, possibly laurel, with prominent berries. Beneath the roundel, the branches are connected with a double loop device, possibly a rope, string, or ribbon, that appears to be a continuation of the branches.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="13" justify="center" n="bb467.1.comeng.01.01">to face the Title
            <note>This line can be seen by selecting &quot;Supplemental Views&quot; on the &quot;Show Me...&quot; menu.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="6"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="16" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.01.02">PERICLES.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.01.03">from a Bust in the Possession of Charles Townley Esq.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="2" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.01.04">Publishd June 14. 1800 by Cadell &amp; Davis Strand</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="bb467.1.1-full.com" id="suppbb467.1.rm.01">
      <objtitle>,                

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">full view with inscriptions</objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>This view shows the inscription top right.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>18.2 x 12.3 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
          <p>The platemark measures 22.8 x 16.4 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize height="700" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
    </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB467.1.2.COM" id="bb467.1.comeng.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The DEATH of DEMOSTHENES.</title>,


        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B2">(Bentley 467.2)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objsize>15.7 x 18.0 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
          <p>The platemark measures 16.2 x 20.6 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize height="650" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The scene depicts a dying Demosthenes being supported by a young male and watched by three soldiers. Demosthenes occupies the center of the design, facing right in profile with the lower half of his body supine. His legs are slightly bent. His upper body is raised, propped up in his right arm, which is bent at the elbow. His left hand is raised, with his palm upward. He has short, thinning hair and a beard and is wearing a robe. His eye and mouth are open and he is looking in the direction of the soldiers. He may be speaking to them. In his right hand he holds a scroll. Demosthemes is supported by a young male who is kneeling and looking downward, in profile, at the philosopher. The youth is wearing a robe, and his right hand supports Demosthenes's torso. The youth is kneeling on his right knee and his left leg is also bent. He has short curly hair. These two figures are located on a plinth or platform.  The inscribed verse below the design indicates that this is the base of a large statue. There are Greek letters inscribed on this base. To the right of the base are three male figures wearing military garb. The rightmost figure is in profile, wears a helmet with a crest and holds a spear and an oval shield in his left hand. The central figure of this group faces forward, wears a helmet with a crest and wears a long cloak over his left shoulder. With his right hand, he grasps a spear. The leftmost figure in this group also faces forward and is wearing a helmet with a crest.  He may also be wearing armor. He holds a shield in his left hand. His right arm extends horizontally behind the base. 
               </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Demosthenes</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>An old man, Demosthenes occupies the center of the design, facing right in profile with the lower half of his body is supine. His legs are slightly bent. His upper body is raised, propped up in his right arm, which is bent at the elbow. He appears to be reclining. His left is raised, with his palm upward. He has short, thinning hair and a beard and is wearing a robe. He is balding.  His eye and mouth are open and he is looking in the direction of the soldiers. He may be speaking to them. In his right hand he holds a scroll.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Demosthemes is supported by a young male who is kneeling and looking downward, in profile, at the philosopher. The youth is wearing a robe, and his right hand supports Demosthenes's torso. The youth is kneeling on his right knee and his left leg is also bent. He has short curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Demosthenes and the youth are on a plinth or platform. The verse inscribed below the design indicates that this is the base of a large statue, although no statue is pictured. An inscription in Greek, &quot;To Poseidon,&quot; appears on the base above the figures.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crest</characteristic>
            <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the base are three male figures wearing military garb. The rightmost figure is in profile, wears a helmet with a crest and holds a spear and an oval shield in his left hand. The central figure of this group faces forward, wears a helmet with a crest and is wearing a long cloak or robe. With his right hand, he grasps a spear. The leftmost figure in this group also faces forward and is wearing a helmet with a crest. He holds a shield in his left hand. A strap from his armor is visible over his right shoulder. His right arm extends horizontally behind the base of a statue. They may be looking toward Demosthenes.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="70" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.01">To face Page 126.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.02">ΜΟΣΕΙΔΩΝΙ
            <note>This inscription in Attic Greek, &quot;To Poseidon,&quot; appears on the wall above Demosthenes.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.03">T. H. invenit.
            <space extent="60"/>
            W. Blake Sc.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.04">The DEATH of DEMOSTHENES.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.05">He views this Outrage with indignant Eyes,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.06">And at the Base of Neptunes Statue dies.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="55" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.02.07">Epistle 5. Verse 61.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="13" justify="left" n="bb471.1.comeng.02.08">Publishd June 14. 1800 by Cadell &amp; Davis Strand</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB467.1.3.COM" id="bb467.1.comeng.03">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">THOMAS HAYLEY, the Disciple of John Flaxman. from a Medallion.</title>,
        
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 3 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B1">(Bentley 467.3)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objsize>10.8 x 7 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
          <p>The platemark measures 22.6 x 16.2 cm. For the inscription top right, select &quot;Supplemental Views&quot; on the &quot;Show Me...&quot; menu.</p>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize height="700" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a roundel containing the head of Thomas Hayley, William Hayley's son. Thomas Hayley is facing left in profile. He has long hair that rests on his shoulder. His eye is open and he is wearing a shirt with a ruffle collar or scarf. He might also wear a coat.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Hayley, Thomas</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a roundel containing the head of Thomas Hayley, William Hayley's son. Thomas Hayley is facing left in profile. He has long hair that rests on his shoulder. His eye is open and he is wearing a shirt with a ruffle collar or scarf. He might also wear a coat.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="13" justify="center" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.01">to face Page 163
            <note>This line can be seen by selecting &quot;Supplemental Views&quot; on the &quot;Show Me...&quot; menu.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="6"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.02">Blake. sc</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.03">THOMAS HAYLEY,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="17" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.04">the Disciple of</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="16" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.05">John Flaxman.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="17" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.06">from a Medallion.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb467.1.comeng.03.07">Publishd June 14. 1800 by Cadell &amp; Davis Strand</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
            <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="bb467.1.3-full.com" id="suppbb467.1.rm.02">
      <objtitle>,
        
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">full view with transcriptions</objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>This view shows the inscription top right.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>18 x 10.7 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
          <p>The platemark measures 22.6 x 16.2 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize height="700" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
    </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>
