<bad id="bb470.3" type="comb" work="William Hayley, Little Tom the Sailor" copy="3" copyid="3" institution="fitzwilliam" value="proof" catalog="bentley" catid="470"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Little Tom the Sailor"><main><author>William Hayley</author>, Little Tom the Sailor</main><copy> Copy 3</copy>: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
               
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester
           </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 28KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 189KB to 1200KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>. We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>&#160;illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.<lb/><lb/>
                In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>. Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.<lb/><lb/>                                                
                The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809). Only one of these plates, <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>, was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This image copyright © 2013 Fitzwilliam Museum.<lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>November 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing, metadata collection and color correction</change><date>February 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>William Hayley, <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>colorist, </role><role>engraver, </role><role>printer</role></origination><origination>William Hayley<role>author</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake  
               <role>printer. According to Blake's letter of 26 Nov. 1800, his wife Catherine (perhaps with his assistance) printed this work.</role></origination><imprint><publisher>Widow Spicer<note>The colophon at the foot of the complete work indicates that it was "Printed for &amp; Sold by the Widow Spicer."  Her full name is not known.</note></publisher><pubplace>Folkestone<note>Blake and his wife Catherine printed this work in Felpham.</note></pubplace><date>October 5, 1800</date></imprint><compdate value="1800.A">1800</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1800.C">1800</printdate><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>11.1 x 16.0 cm.<note>This print is of the tailpiece only. Although sometimes described as a "proof," it is in the same state as the tailpiece in complete copies of <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>. The light printing suggests that this impression may have been pulled by Blake or his wife Catherine as a trial effort to adjust the press or make other alterations in preparation for printing complete copies of the work. The size of the margins, however, indicates that this tailpiece could have been cut from a complete copy of the work rather than separately printed.</note></objsize><leafsize>11.6 x 16.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>white-line etching
                </medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper
                </support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>none<note>Glue residue in all four corners suggests that the print was probably pasted at one time to a backing leaf or mat.</note></binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name><date>1982</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>bequest</price><note>Acquired at an unknown time by Geoffrey Keynes; given by Keynes by bequest upon his death in 1982 to the Fitzwilliam Museum. The earlier history of this copy is unknown.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution><addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline><addressline>Cambridge CB2 IRB</addressline><addressline>UK</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 44-1223-332900</addressline><addressline>Fax: 44-1223-332923</addressline><addressline>URL, general: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Call number">P.470-1985</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="bb470.3.comb.01" dbi="BB470.fitzproof.3.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Little Tom the Sailor</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 470)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>16.8 x 11.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="800" height="600"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc> The tailpiece design is a cottage door scene populated by four figures. The central figure is a tall female, facing the viewer. Her body faces slightly to the right while her head is turned to the left and downward slightly. According to Hayley's poem, this is Little Tom's mother, the Widow Spicer of Folkestone. She wears a long dress and bonnet. Below the hem of her dress, feet are visible. Her right foot is on tip toe and she appears to be walking. Her right arm is by her side and in her right hand she holds a basket or container covered with cloth. Her left arm is bent at 90 degrees across her chest. She is pointing with her right hand to the figures on the left of the plate. She is also looking in that direction. The figures that the Widow Spicer is pointing and looking at are located on the left of the plate and in a stone cottage. The figure standing in the doorway is a young male with long hair, wearing breeches and a coat with three buttons. Beneath the coat is a shirt with a collar. This is Little Tom. He faces toward the viewer with his head facing right in the direction of his mother. His eyes and mouth are open. He is both looking at his mother and may be speaking to her. His right arm is raised 90 degrees and the palm on his right hand faces outward. He is gesturing to the interior of the cottage and the two figures behind him. His left arm is by his side. The fingers on his left hand appear to be spread. Little Tom's legs are together, with his right leg extending behind his left leg. His right foot is on tip toe. Behind Little Tom are two figures. The leftmost figure is a (female?) child, identified in Hayley's poem as an "Ideot." The child is in profile, facing right with head slightly downward, has long hair and is wearing a gown. The child's right arm is by its side. This is an infant in a wicker crib, identified in Hayley's poem as a sick little infant. The crib has a hood, is on a rocker and has a handle. The gender of the infant is indeterminate and only the head, which rests on a pillow, is visible. The body is obscured by a blanket and by the lower body of Little Tom. On the left of the plate is a stone cottage with an open, wood-framed door. Above the crib is a wood-framed window. Next to, and slightly behind the right wall of the cottage is a large, heavily-leaved tree. The shape of the leaves suggest that this is might be an oak. The trunk divides into two main branches and some roots are visible. The foliage on the right branch extends over the Widow Spicer, along the top of the plate. A path or road curves in the lower right portion of the tailpiece. Either side of the path is grass and/or indeterminate vegetation. There is also grass just above the lower edge of the design. The path winds through a densely wooded area in the middle distance with visible tree trunks. There is a hill in the middle distance, behind Widow Spicer and the oak tree. In the background, to the right of Widow Spicer's shoulder, are the spires and towers of a building or series of buildings. This is probably a city, identified in Hayley's poem as Folkestone. Behind the city is a peaked mountain. The sky is cloudy, possibly with a sunrise or sunset above the mountain peak. </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>widow</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>Widow Spicer</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breast</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The tailpiece design is a cottage door scene populated by four figures. The central figure is a tall female, facing the viewer. Her body faces slightly to the right while her head is turned to the left and downward slightly. According to Hayley's poem, this is Little Tom's mother, the Widow Spicer of Folkestone. She wears a long dress and bonnet. Below the hem of her dress, feet are visible. Her right foot is on tip toe and she appears to be walking. Her right arm is by her side and in her right hand she holds a (wicker?) basket or container covered with cloth. Her left arm is bent at 90 degrees across her chest. She is pointing with her left hand to the figures on the left of the plate. She is also looking in that direction.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>son</characteristic><characteristic>Little Tom</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>button</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure standing in the doorway is a young male with long hair, wearing breeches and a coat with three buttons. Beneath the coat is a shirt with a collar. This is Little Tom. He faces toward the viewer with his head facing right in the direction of his mother. His eyes and mouth are open. He is both looking at his mother and may be speaking to her. His right arm is raised 90 degrees and the palm on his right hand faces outward. He is gesturing to the interior of the cottage and the two figures behind him. His left arm is by his side. The fingers on his left hand appear to be spread. Little Tom's legs are together, with his right leg extending behind his left leg. His right foot is on tip toe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>idiot</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind Little Tom are two figures. The leftmost figure is a (female?) child, identified in Hayley's poem an "Ideot." The child is in profile, facing right with head slightly downward, has long hair and is wearing a gown. The child's right arm is by its side with the right palm vertical.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>sick</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An infant, described as ill in the poem, lies in a wicker crib.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="C"><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the plate is a stone cottage with an open, wood-framed door. Inside the cottage is a wood-framed window above the crib.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>crib</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Inside the cottage there is a wicker crib holding an infant, a pillow, and blanket</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>oak</characteristic><characteristic>root</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Next to, and slightly behind the right wall of the cottage is a large, heavily-leaved tree. The shape of the leaves suggest that this is an oak. The trunk divides into two main branches and roots are visible. The foliage on the right branch extends over the Widow Spicer, along the top of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A path or road curves in the lower right portion of the tailpiece. Either side of the path is grass and/or indeterminate vegetation. There is also grass just above the lower edge of the design. The path winds through a densely wooded area in the middle distance with visible tree trunks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="D"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>church</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>Folkestone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the distance, to the right of Widow Spicer's shoulder, are the spires and towers of a building or series of buildings, perhaps including a church. This is probably a city, identified in Hayley's poem as Folkestone.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the city is a peaked mountain. A hill rises between the standing woman and the large tree.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky is cloudy, possibly with a sunrise or sunset above the mountain peak.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb470.3.comb.01.01" justify="left" indent="40">W. Blake Inv<note>Only fragments of these letters are printed in white line; "Inv" is particularly difficult to see.  Other impressions of the tailpiece show the letters more clearly.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>