<bad id="bb470.1" type="comb" work="William Hayley, Little Tom the Sailor" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="bentley" catid="470" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Little Tom the Sailor"><main><author>William Hayley</author>, Little Tom the Sailor</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
               
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester
           </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 40KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 101KB to 1100KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>. We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>&#160;illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.<lb/><lb/>
                In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>. Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.<lb/><lb/>                                                
                The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809). Only one of these plates, <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>, was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This work copyright © 2013 William Blake Archive.<lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation and image color correction</change><date>October 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change><date>October 2002</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Dickens</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Gerald Miller,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee,</name><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>William Hayley, Little Tom the Sailor</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>engraver, </role><role>printer</role></origination><origination>William Hayley<role>author</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake 
               <role>printer. According to Blake's letter of 26 Nov. 1800, his wife Catherine (perhaps with his assistance) printed this work (Erdman page 714).</role></origination><imprint><publisher>Widow Spicer<note>The colophon at the foot of the work indicates that it was "Printed for &amp; Sold by the Widow Spicer."  Her full name is not known.</note></publisher><pubplace>Folkestone<note>Blake and his wife Catherine printed this work in Felpham.</note></pubplace><date>October 5, 1800</date></imprint><compdate value="1800.A">1800</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1800.A">1800</printdate><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>Overall image 47.9 x 16.1 cm.<note>The image and platemark of the headpiece measure 11.0 x 16.1 cm.  The poem measures 22.1 x 10.1 cm. with a platemark of 22.5 x 10.7 cm. The image and platemark of the tailpiece measure 11.1 x 16.0.  The colophon measures 2.1 x 11.0 with a platemark of 3.7 x 12.0 cm.</note></objsize><leafsize>51.3 x 18.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>relief etching and white-line etching (possibly white-line engraving)<note>Four plates were printed on one sheet to form this broadside. The headpiece and tailpiece were executed as white-line etchings, possibly with some white-line engraving. The poem and the colophon are relief etchings.</note></medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>none</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>August 1995</date><dealer>John Windle</dealer><price>$15,000</price><note>Acquired at an unknown time by W.E. Moss and offered at Sotheby's, 2 March 1937, lot 191 ("withdrawn," apparently because mislaid); sold from the Moss Collection, Sotheby's, 20 December 1938, lot 458 (£48 to the dealer W. H. Robinson); offered by Robinson in December 1939 for £84; sold anonymously, Parke-Bernet auction, New York, 9 December 1952, lot 87 ($130 to Joseph Holland); offered in John Windle's 1995 catalogue 26, *The Blake Collection of Joseph Holland &amp; Vincent Newton*, item 3 (price on request); acquired August 1995 by Robert N. Essick.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline></repository></source><desc id="bb470.1.comb.01" dbi="bb470.1.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Little TOM the Sailor.</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 470)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>47.9 x 16.1 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="475" height="725"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location=""><illusobjdesc>This broadside comprises head and tailpiece designs separated by twelve quatrains of relief-etched text. Beneath the tailpiece is a colophon. The headpiece depicts an ocean scene during a storm. In the upper center of the design is a partly nude male, identified as the spirit of Little Tom's father in Hayley's poem, facing forward and floating or hovering between storm clouds. Only his upper body is visible. There is a belt or rope around his upper waist. Both arms are raised horizontally in a cruciform pose, with palms facing outward parting the clouds. The figure has long flame-like hair; his head faces forward, to the right and slightly downward. His mouth may be slightly open and he may be speaking. The figure below is a clothed child with long, curly hair, identified as Little Tom in Hayley's poem. Facing forward, with his head titled slightly to the left and upward, Little Tom is looking at the figure above. Little Tom is standing on the bow of a boat. His legs are apart, with the right leg bent at 90 degrees and the left slightly bent. Both feet are visible. His left arm is at his side while his right arm is bent upward above his head. With his left hand, Little Tom grasps a rope and with his right hand holds a vertical mast. Little Tom is wearing breeches and a coat, which is open to the waist. Beneath the coat is a shirt with a collar.  
  Much of the boat that Little Tom is standing on is submerged by a white-crested wave. Its vertical mast extends diagonally to the right. At the tip of the mast is a flag. A boom extends diagonally to the left with a sail beneath. Alternatively, this could be a bowsprit, the spar that extends from a boat's prow. A rope extends from a pulley on the upper side of the boom or bowsprit. An extension of this rope or another rope extends from Little Tom's left hand to the bottom right edge of the design. Also to the right of the mast, and extending downward from the left palm of Little Tom's father, is a bolt of lightening. The background is dark, suggesting a night scene. Vertical lines extending beneath the clouds may indicate rain.   
  The tailpiece design is a cottage door scene populated by four figures. The central figure is a tall female, facing the viewer. Her body faces slightly to the right while her head is turned to the left and downward slightly. According to Hayley's poem, this is Little Tom's mother, the Widow Spicer of Folkestone. She wears a long dress and bonnet. Below the hem of her dress, feet are visible. Her right foot is on tip toe and she appears to be walking. Her right arm is by her side and in her right hand she holds a basket or container covered with cloth. Her left arm is bent at 90 degrees across her chest. She is also looking in that direction.  
  The figures that the Widow Spicer is looking at are located on the left of the plate, in a stone cottage. The figure standing in the doorway is a young male with long hair, wearing breeches and a coat with three buttons. Beneath the coat is a shirt with a collar. This is Little Tom. He faces toward the viewer with his head facing right in the direction of his mother. His eyes and mouth are open. He is both looking at his mother and may be speaking to her. His right arm is raised 90 degrees and the palm on his right hand faces outward. He is gesturing to the interior of the cottage and the two figures behind him. His left arm is by his side. The fingers on his left hand appear to be spread. Little Tom's legs are together, with his right leg extending behind his left leg. His right foot is on tip toe. Behind Little Tom are two figures. The leftmost figure is a (female?) child, identified in Hayley's poem as an "Ideot." The child is in profile, facing right with head slightly downward, has long hair and is wearing a gown. The child's right arm is by its side. There is an infant in a wicker crib, identified in Hayley's poem as a sick little infant. The crib has a hood, is on a rocker and has a handle. The gender of the infant is indeterminate and only the head, which rests on a pillow, is visible. The infant's face is turned toward the viewer; his or her eyes appear to be closed and the mouth may be open. The infant is wearing a tight-fitting hat or hood. The body is obscured by a blanket and by the lower body of Little Tom.
   On the left of the plate is a stone cottage with an open, wood-framed door. Above the crib is a wood-framed window with lattice panes. The ceiling of the cottage is visible above the window. Next to, and slightly behind the right wall of the cottage is a large, heavily-leaved tree. The shape of the leaves suggest that this is might be an oak. The trunk divides into two main branches and some roots are visible. The foliage on the right branch extends over the Widow Spicer, along the top of the plate. 
      A path or road curves in the lower right portion of the tailpiece. Either side of the path is grass and/or indeterminate vegetation. There is also grass just above the lower edge of the design. The path winds through a densely wooded area in the middle distance with visible tree trunks. There is a hill in the middle distance, behind Widow Spicer and the oak tree. In the background, to the right of Widow Spicer's shoulder, are the spires and towers of a building or series of buildings. This is probably a city, identified in Hayley's poem as Folkestone. Behind the city is a peaked mountain. The sky is cloudy, possibly with a sunrise or sunset above the mountain peak.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head toward viewer</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>rope</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>dividing</characteristic><characteristic>pushing</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the upper center of the plate is a partly nude male, identified as the spirit of Little Tom's father in Hayley's poem, facing forward and hovering between storm clouds. Only his upper body is visible. There is a belt or rope around his upper waist. Both arms are raised horizontally in a cruciform pose, with palms facing out to part the storm clouds. The figure has long flame-like hair; his head faces forward, to the right and slightly downward. His mouth may be open and he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Little Tom</characteristic><characteristic>son</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>sailor</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A clothed child with long, curly hair, identified as Little Tom in Hayley's poem, stands facing forward with his head titled slightly to the left and upward. Little Tom is looking at the figure above. Little Tom is standing on the curved rim of a boat. His legs are apart, with the right leg bent at 90 degrees and the left slightly bent. Both feet are visible. His left arm is by his side while his right arm is bent upward above his head. With his left hand, Little Tom grasps a rope and with his right hand holds a mast. Little Tom is wearing breeches and a coat open to the waist. Beneath the coat is a shirt with a collar.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>boat</characteristic><characteristic>ship</characteristic><characteristic>pole</characteristic><characteristic>flag</characteristic><characteristic>rope</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Little Tom stands on a sinking boat. Its vertical mast extends diagonally to the right. At the tip of the mast is a flag. A boom extends diagonally to the left. Alternatively, this pole is a bowsprit extending from the prow of the ship. A sail is attached to the underside of the boom or bowsprit. A rope extends from a pulley on the upper side of the boom or bowsprit. An extension of this rope or another rope extends from Little Tom's left hand to the bottom right edge of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>wave</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A white-crested wave is depicted at the bottom center of the headpiece, partially submerging the boat.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>lightening</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>rain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Storm clouds dominate the upper half of the headpiece. Vertical lines extending beneath the clouds may indicate rain. A bolt of lightening appears to extend downward from the palm of the left hand of Little Tom's father.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>widow</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>Widow Spicer</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breast</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The tailpiece design is a cottage door scene populated by four figures. The central figure is a tall female, facing the viewer. Her body faces slightly to the right while her head is turned to the left and downward slightly. According to Hayley's poem, this is Little Tom's mother, the Widow Spicer of Folkestone. She wears a long dress and bonnet. Below the hem of her dress, feet are visible. Her right foot is may be on tip toe and she appears to be walking. Her right arm is by her side and in her right hand she holds a (wicker?) basket or container covered with cloth. Her left arm is bent at 90 degrees across her chest. She is looking to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>son</characteristic><characteristic>Little Tom</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>button</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure standing in the doorway is a young male with long hair, wearing breeches and a coat with three buttons. Beneath the coat is a shirt with a collar. This is Little Tom. He faces toward the viewer with his head facing right in the direction of his mother. His eyes and mouth are open. He is both looking at his mother and may be speaking to her. His right arm is raised 90 degrees and the palm on his right hand faces outward. He is gesturing to the interior of the cottage and the two figures behind him. His left arm is by his side. The fingers on his left hand appear to be spread. Little Tom's legs are together, with his right leg extending behind his left leg. His right foot is on tip toe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>idiot</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind Little Tom are two figures. The leftmost figure is a (female?) child, identified in Hayley's poem an "Ideot." The child is in profile, facing right with head slightly downward, has long hair and is wearing a gown. The child's right arm is by its side with the right palm vertical.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>sick</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There is an infant in a wicker crib, identified in Hayley's poem as a sick little infant. The crib has a hood, is on a rocker and has a handle. The gender of the infant is indeterminate and only the head, which rests on a pillow, is visible. The infant's face is turned toward the viewer; his or her eyes appear to be closed and the mouth may be open. The infant is wearing a tight-fitting hat or hood. The body is obscured by a blanket and by the lower body of Little Tom.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="C"><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>lattice</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>room</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the plate is a stone cottage with an open, wood-framed door, revealing a room. In the room is a wood-framed window with lattice panes, above the crib. The ceiling is visible above the window</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>crib</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>rocker</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Inside the cottage there is a wicker crib holding an infant, a pillow, and blanket. The crib is on a rocker and has a handle.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>oak</characteristic><characteristic>root</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Next to, and slightly behind the right wall of the cottage is a large, heavily-leaved tree. The shape of the leaves suggest that this is an oak. The trunk divides into two main branches and roots are visible. The foliage on the right branch extends over the Widow Spicer, along the top of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A path or road curves in the lower right portion of the tailpiece. Either side of the path is grass and/or indeterminate vegetation. There is also grass just above the lower edge of the design. The path winds through a densely wooded area in the middle distance with visible tree trunks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="D"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>church</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>Folkestone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the distance, to the right of Widow Spicer's shoulder, are the spires and towers of a building or series of buildings, perhaps including a church. This is probably a city, identified in Hayley's poem as Folkestone.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the city is a peaked mountain. A hill rises between the standing woman and the large tree.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky is cloudy, possibly with a sunrise or sunset above the mountain peak.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.01" justify="left">Little TOM the Sailor</l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.02" justify="left">And does then the Ocean possess</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.03" justify="left">The promising, brave, little youth,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.04" justify="left">Who display'd, in a scene of distress,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.05" justify="left">Such Tenderness, Courage, and Truth?</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.06" justify="left">Little Tom is a Cottagers Son;</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.07" justify="left" indent="1">His years not amounting to ten!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.08" justify="left">But the Dawn of his Manhood begun</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.09" justify="left" indent="1">With a Soul like the noblest of Men.</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.10" justify="left">In an Hospital, distant from Home,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.11" justify="left" indent="1">He lost his unfortunate Sire;</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.12" justify="left">And his Mother was tempted to roam,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.13" justify="left" indent="1">But to see that kind Father expire.</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.14" justify="left">To depart from her Cottage was hard;</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.15" justify="left" indent="1">To desert the dear dying was worse,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.16" justify="left">Tho'! She had an Ideot to guard,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.17" justify="left">And a sick little Infant to nurse.</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.18" justify="left">The brave little Tom tried to chear</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.19" justify="left" indent="1">The Grief that He shudder'd to see:</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.20" justify="left">"Go! Mother (He said) without Fear!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.21" justify="left" indent="1">Go! and leave these poor creatures to me!</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.22" justify="left">Go you my sick Father restore!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.23" justify="left" indent="1">And I will take Care of these two:</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.24" justify="left">I will not stir out of the Door,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.25" justify="left" indent="1">For what without me could they do?</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.26" justify="left">I will carefully dress them, and feed.</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.27" justify="left" indent="1">Go you our dear Father to save!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.28" justify="left">I will not desert them indeed:"<note>Two short vertical lines that look like misplaced double-quotation marks appear about 1.0 cm. right of the end of this line.  They were printed from the plate.</note></l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.29" justify="left" indent="1">And Tom kept the promise he gave,</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.30" justify="left">But his Mother a Widow came back;</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.31" justify="left" indent="1">Want and Sorrow her Portion must be;</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.32" justify="left">And her Heart, on Necessity's Rack,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.33" justify="left" indent="1">Has sent little Thomas to Sea.</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.34" justify="left">O Sea! Thou grand Servant of God!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.35" justify="left" indent="1">The Children of Britain defend!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.36" justify="left">As a braver the Deck never trod,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.37" justify="left" indent="1">Little Thomas will find Thee a Friend:</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.38" justify="left">And when He's aloft in the Shrouds,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.39" justify="left" indent="2">If a Storm threats aloud to destroy,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.40" justify="left">His Fathers free Soul, in the Clouds,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.41" justify="left" indent="1">Will watch o'er the venturous Boy:</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.42" justify="left">I hear, when the Tempests appall,</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.43" justify="left" indent="1">That Spirit paternal exclaim<note>A short, slightly curved but horizontal line appears about 5.0 mm. right of the end of this line.  This short horizontal was printed from the plate.</note></l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.44" justify="left">"O God! Thou Protector of All!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.45" justify="left" indent="1">Let me shelter this dear little Frame!</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.46" justify="left">A Defender, with Honour, his Due!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.47" justify="left" indent="2">In the Man may his Country admire!</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.48" justify="left">Since the Child was a Guardian so true</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.49" justify="left">To the desolate Cot of his Sire."</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.50" justify="left" indent="42">W. Blake Inv</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.51" justify="left">Printed for &amp; Sold by the Widow Spicer of Folkstone</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.52" justify="left" indent="9">For the Benefit of her Orphans</l><l n="bb470.1.comb.01.53" justify="left" indent="14"> October 5, 1800</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>