<bad id="bb471.1" type="comeng" work="William Hayley, The Triumphs of Temper" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="bentley" catid="471" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Triumphs of Temper"><main><author>William Hayley</author>, The Triumphs of Temper</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>

            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 77KB; 12 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 119KB to 1200KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to works by William Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>. We are also republishing Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). The designs and engraved texts of both sets of <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>&#160;illustrations, as well as the new material now being published, are fully searchable.<lb/><lb/>
                In late 1799, William Hayley was seeking an engraver to illustrate his poem <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>. Possibly on the advice of the sculptor John Flaxman, Hayley commissioned Blake to produce three plates. In July 1800, Blake spent much of July working on the final plate, an engraving of Hayley’s deceased son, Thomas, in Hayley’s library in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex. During these weeks, Hayley persuaded Blake to relocate from London to Felpham to work on a number of graphic projects.  Disenchanted with his failure to secure commercial engraving work in London, Blake enthusiastically took up Hayley’s offer.<lb/><lb/>                                                
                The works now published and republished include all of Blake’s commercial engravings executed for Hayley during the three-year period Blake and his wife Catherine spent in Felpham. In addition, the Blake Archive is publishing two more engravings Blake worked on for Hayley after the Blakes had returned to London in September 1803. These plates were commissioned to illustrate Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi> (1809). Only one of these plates, <hi rend="i">Sketch of a Shipwreck after Romney</hi>, was included in the published biography. The other, a portrait engraving of Romney, was rejected and, until very recently, has not been seen since the 1939 Blake exhibition in Philadelphia. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>

         This work courtesy William Blake Archive.

         <lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation and image color correction</change><date>January 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, and</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change><date>Fall 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>William Hayley, *The Triumphs of Temper*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>etcher,</role><role>engraver,</role></origination><origination>Maria Flaxman<role>inventor</role></origination><imprint><publisher>T. Cadell and W. Davies<note>The title page specifies that the  were "Printed by J. Seagrave, and sold by T. Cadell and W. Davies, Strand, London (title page).  This is the twelfth edition of the poem.</note></publisher><pubplace>London</pubplace><date>1803</date></imprint><compdate value="1803.A">1803</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1803.A">1803</printdate><numberobj>6</numberobj><objorder>1-6</objorder><objsize>ranging between 13.2 x 7.8 cm and 14.2 x 8.4 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>6</numberleaves><leafsize>23.1 x 14.0 cm.<note>This is a large-paper copy, uncut.  The leaves in a small-paper copy measure 17.6 x 10.2 cm., uncut.</note></leafsize><medium>etching and engraving</medium><printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>1803<note>The watermark appears in Object 2.</note></watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>1 or 2 or 3<note>A single, double, or triple frame line extends around the design and the canto and verse reference inscribed below it.  Another frame line, double or single, appears around the canto and verse reference.</note></framelines><binding>publisher's original boards, inscribed in pen and ink on the spine, "Hayley."</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1971</date><dealer>Reginald Hennessey Books</dealer><price>$175</price><note>The provenance of this copy is not known prior to its acquisition by the dealer Reginald Hennessey in 1971 and its sale to Essick in the same year.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena</addressline><addressline>California</addressline></repository></source><desc id="bb471.1.comeng.01" dbi="BB471.1.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Canto I. Verse 29</title>,

<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 471.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>13.7 x 8.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design provides a general illustration of canto one, verses 29-36 of Hayley's poem. In the center of the design are two figures beneath a leafy tree. The rightmost figure is a clothed and seated male, seen from behind and facing left. This is Sir Gilbert, the father of the main protagonist in Hayley's poem, Serena. Sir Gilbert is wearing a long coat with a collar, his face is in profile, facing left, and he has long, swept back hair. His left arm is bent at the elbow and his left hand is holding his collar. Sir Gilbert's left eye is open and he may be reading the open book in front of him (the book is presumably held in Sir Gilbert's right hand although this is not visible). Sir Gilbert's legs and feet are visible. He is wearing shoes and stockings; his left shoe is on tiptoe and the visible part of his right shoe is on the ground. He is sitting in a wooden chair, described as an "elbow chair" in Hayley's poem. The leftmost figure is a female with long hair. This is Serena; she faces right, her head in profile. Her right eye is open and she is looking at the book her father is holding. Serena is wearing a long white gown and is holding a wicker basket with a handle that contains leaves and either flowers, vegetables, or fruit. Her right arm is bent at 90 degrees and her right hand holds the bottom of the basket. Her left hand is placed on top of the basket's handle. Below the hem of Serena's gown her shoes are visible. The shoes are on tiptoe, indicating that Serena is walking toward her father. The scene takes place in Sir Gilbert's garden. On the right of the design is a tree trunk, with leafy vegetation at its base. Creeping vines are visible on the lower portion of the tree trunk. In the top right corner of the design, the tree separates into several leafy branches that extend to the left. In the left foreground is a flowering lily-like plant, with two blooming flowers and two buds. In the center foreground is a pathway that Serena is walking on as she approaches her father. In the background there is more vegetation, including bushes and trees. The scene takes places during the daytime and the sky appears to be partially cloudy.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Sir Gilbert</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design are two figures beneath a leafy tree. The rightmost figure is a clothed and seated male, seen from behind and facing left. This is Sir Gilbert, who is wearing a long coat with a prominent collar. Sir Gilbert's face is in profile, facing left, and he has long, swept back hair. His left arm is bent at the elbow and his left hand is holding is collar. Sir Gilbert's left eye is open and he may be reading the open book in front of him (the book is presumably held in Sir Gilbert's right hand although this is not visible). Sir Gilbert's legs are bent and his lower legs and feet are visible. He is wearing shoes and stockings; his left shoe is on tiptoe and the visible part of his right shoe is on the ground.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There is an open book in front of Sir Gilbert. Parallel lines indicate text on the pages.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Sir Gilbert is sitting on a wooden chair, described in the text as an "elbow chair."</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design is a tree trunk, with leafy vegetation at its base. Creeping vines are visible on the lower portion of the tree trunk At the top right corner of the design, the tree separates into several leafy branches that extend to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Serena</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design are two figures beneath a leafy tree. The leftmost figure is a female with long hair. This is Serena; she faces right, her head in profile. Her right eye is open and she appears to be looking at the book her father is holding. Serena is wearing a long gown and is holding a wicker basket with a handle that contains various flowers, vegetables, or fruit. Her right arm is bent at 90 degrees and her right hand holds the bottom of the vegetable basket. Her left hand is placed on top of the basket's handle. Below the hem of Serena's gown her shoes are visible. The left shoe is to be on tiptoe, indicating that Serena is walking toward her father.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>fruit</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Serena is holding a wicker basket with a handle that contains various flowers, vegetables, or fruit.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>lily</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the left foreground is a lily-like flowering plant, with two blooming flowers and two buds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>path</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center foreground is a pathway that Serena is walking on as she approaches her father.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>bush</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the background there is more vegetation, including bushes and trees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes places during the daytime and the sky appears partially cloudy.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.01.01" justify="left" indent="13">Canto. I.<space extent="7"/>Verse 29</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.01.02" justify="left">Maria Flaxman. inv &amp;. del.<space extent="15"/>W Blake. sculp</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.01.03" justify="left" indent="2">Publish'd, May 1. 1803. by Cadell &amp; Davies. Strand</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb471.1.comeng.02" dbi="BB471.1.2.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Canto IId. Verse 471</title>,

<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 471.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objnote><p>
                        The imprint is not included here. It reads "Publishd May 1. 1803. by Cadell &amp; Davies. Strand".
                    </p></objnote><objsize>13.2 x 8.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="650"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place at night in a bedchamber and illustrates canto two, verse 471 of Hayley's poem. A female figure kneeling on a carpeted floor occupies the center of the design. This is Serena, the main protagonist of Hayley's poem. Serena is facing right, in profile. Her right arm is bent at 90 degrees; the upper part of her arm rests on a pillow atop a table and her right hand is clasping the fingers of her left hand, held in front of her face in prayer. According to Hayley's text, Serena is praying to "her guardian Sprite." Serena is wearing a semi-transparent gown and her hair is drawn up and tied back with a band or headscarf. She is looking upward and her mouth is open. On the left of the design is the side of a bed with the curtains drawn back. To the right of the bed is a chair with a wicker(?) back and seat. On the right of the design is a lampstand with a burning oil lamp issuing flames and possibly smoke. Behind the oil lamp and its stand is a table covered with a table cloth that extends to the patterned carpet. The hem of the table cloth is also patterned. On top of the table is an oval mirror set within a decorative stand that incorporates an oval decoration below the mirror. The mirror is reflecting the oil lamp, the shadow of which falls across the table. Behind the table and mirror are half-drawn curtains. To the left of these curtains and above the chair is an area of wall.      

               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Serena</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>band</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure kneeling on a carpeted floor occupies the center of the design. This is Serena, the main protagonist of Hayley's poem. Serena is facing right, in profile. Her right arm is bent at 90 degrees, the upper part of her arm rests on a pillow atop a table and her right hand is clasped with the fingers of her left hand, held in front of her face in prayer. According to Hayley's text, Serena is praying to "her guardian Sprite." Serena is wearing a semi-transparent gown, her hair is drawn up in a bun and tied back with a band or headscarf. She is looking upward and her mouth is open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>curtains</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design is the side of a bed with a pillow visible. The curtains surrounding the bed have been drawn back.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the bed is a wooden chair with a wicker(?) back and seat.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>carpet</characteristic><characteristic>pattern</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design is a lampstand with a wide, round base, holding a burning oil lamp issuing fires and possibly smoke. The lamp sits on a patterned carpet.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>table</characteristic><characteristic>mirror</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>pattern</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the oil lamp is a table covered with a table cloth that extends to the patterned carpet. The hem of the table cloth is also patterned. On top of the table is an oval mirror set within a decorative stand that incorporates an oval jeweled device below the mirror. The mirror is reflecting the oil lamp; the shadow of which falls across the table.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>curtain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the table are half-drawn curtains. To the left of these curtains is an area of wall.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.02.01" justify="left" indent="10">Canto. II d<space extent="8"/>Verse 471.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.02.02" justify="left">Maria Flaxman inv &amp; del.<space extent="12"/>W Blake. sculp</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb471.1.comeng.03" dbi="BB471.1.3.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Canto III. Verse 201</title>,

            

<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 471.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>13.5 x 8.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates canto three, verse 201 of Hayley's poem: Serena entering the dome of spleen. A female figure occupies the center of the design. This is Serena, her body facing away and to the left with her head turned to the right. Serena has long hair pulled into a bun and secured with a band or scarf. She is wearing a semi-transparent gown. Her left arm is bent and her hands are placed together in front of her, in prayer or supplication. Serena's left leg is bent at the knee and her left shoe is visible beneath the hem of her gown. The shoe is on tiptoe indicating that she is walking toward the entrance of the cave-like dome of spleen. A stone arch, described in Hayley's poem as a "wide fantastic arch," forms the entrance to the dome of spleen. At the apex of the arch and aligned centrally above Serena's head is a sign or plaque containing undecipherable letters. Beyond the arch, there are five figures and a creature with bat-like wings. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the arch and are vertically aligned. The lower figure is male, nude from the waist upward, with a prominent forehead and short hair. His body faces away, with his left arm raised horizontally while his head is turned back and faces right. His eyes are open and he is looking in the direction of Serena. His mouth is open and issues forth a stream of vapour or smoke. His lower body is covered in scales and his legs are serpent coils. The figure above is male with hair centrally parted. He may be nude. His head faces forward and he is looking in the direction of Serena. His body faces right and his left leg extends backward, indicating that he is walking to the right. The figure above and to the left is male and nude. He has short hair and his head faces right, in the direction of Serena. His body faces left and his genitals are visible. His right leg is bent and his right foot is on tiptoe. His left leg is straight, suggesting that his is walking to the left. His left arm is raised horizontally and bent at 90 degrees, and rests on the shoulder of the male figure below and to the right. Behind these figures is another male(?) figure. Only the head and shoulders are visible. He faces forward and to the right; he has curly hair and is looking in the direction of Serena. Above this group is a bird with bat-like wings, a long, open beak and a long serpentine tail. The bird's head faces right in profile and its wings are spread. Above this creature is a soaring male(?) figure with long hair. He faces forward and to the right, in the direction of Serena. His left arm is raised at 135 degrees and his right arm is by his side. The lower part of the design comprises a stone floor. Light from the flames inside the dome of spleen illuminates the section of floor that Serena is walking on.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Serena</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>band</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoe</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure occupies the center of the design. This is Serena, her body facing away and to the left with her head facing right. Serena has long hair pulled into a bun and secured with a band or scarf. She is wearing a semi-transparent gown. Her left arm is bent and her hands are placed together in front of her in prayer or supplication. Serena's left leg is bent and her left shoe is visible beneath the hem of her dress. The shoe is on tiptoe indicating that she is walking toward the entrance to the dome of spleen.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>coil</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>vapor</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beyond the arch there are five figures and a flying creature with bat-like wings. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the rock arch and are vertically aligned. The lower figure is male, nude from the waist upward, with a prominent forehead and short hair. His body faces away, with his left arm raised horizontally while his head is turned back and faces right. His eyes are open and he is looking in the direction of Serena. His mouth is open and issues forth a stream of vapor or smoke. His lower body is covered in scales with his legs are serpent coils. He appears to be hovering in the air.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beyond the arch there are five figures and a flying creature with bat-like wings. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the rock arch and are vertically aligned. The second figure in this group is male with hair centrally parted. He may be nude. His head faces forward, his eyes are open and he appears to be looking in the direction of Serena. His body faces right and his left leg extends backward, suggesting that he is walking to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>tip toe</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beyond the arch there are five figures and a flying creature with bat-like wings. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the arch and are vertically aligned. The figure above and to the left is male and is nude. He has short hair and his head faces right, in the direction of Serena.  His body faces left and his genitals are visible. His right leg is bent and his right foot is on tiptoe. His left leg is straight, suggesting that his is walking to the left. His left arm is raised horizontally and bent at 90 degrees, and rests on the shoulder of the male figure below and to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beyond the arch there are five figures and a flying creature with bat-like wings. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the arch and are vertically aligned. Behind these figures is another male(?) figure. Only the head and shoulders are visible. He may be nude. He faces forward and to the right, has curly hair and his eyes are open. He is looking in the direction of Serena.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beyond the arch, there are five figures and a flying creature with bat-like wings. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the arch and are vertically aligned. The upper-most human figure is a flying or hovering male(?) figure with long hair. He faces forward and to the right, his eyes are open and he is looking in the direction of Serena. His left arm is raised at 135 degrees and his right arm is by his side.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wings</characteristic><characteristic>bat winged</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beyond the arch, there are five figures and a flying creature. These figures represent the "unnumber'd phantoms" from Hayley's poem and are surrounded by flames or smoke. They are grouped on the left side of the interior of the arch and are vertically aligned. The bird creature has bat-like wings, a long, open beak and a long serpentine tail. The bird's head faces right in profile and its wings are spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>dome</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A stone arch, described in Hayley's poem as a "wide fantastic arch," forms the entrance to the cave-like dome of spleen. At the apex of the arch and aligned centrally above Serena's head, is a sign or plaque inscribed with undecipherable letters. The lower part of the design comprises the stone floor. Light from the fire inside the dome of spleen illuminates the section of floor that Serena is walking on. Either side of the entrance is in shadow.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.03.01" justify="left" indent="15">Canto. III.<space extent="7"/>Verse. 201.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.03.02" justify="left">Maria Flaxman inv &amp; del:<space extent="21"/>W Blake. sc</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.03.03" justify="left" indent="3">Publish'd, May 1. 1803. by Cadell &amp; Davies. Strand</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb471.1.comeng.04" dbi="BB471.1.4.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Canto IV. Verse 328</title>,          

<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 471.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>13.3 x 7.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design illustrates canto four, verse 328 of Hayley's poem: Serena's discovery of, and reading from, a book "toss'd upon a vacant chair." Three figures occupy the center of the design. The figure on the right is Serena, with long hair. She is sitting and wearing a gown. Her upper body faces forward while her legs, which are bent, face left. Serena's eyes are open and she is looking down at, and reading from, the open pages of a book. Her left arm is bent and rests on the back of a chair. Her right arm is slightly bent and in her right hand she holds the open book. The central figure is a seated female, facing forward with her head facing left in the direction of Serena. This is Serena's aunt, Penelope. Her eyes are open and she is looking at Serena. Her downturned mouth suggests displeasure or anger. Her hair is drawn up under a scarf or tight-fitting hat and tied with a bow. She is wearing a gown with a large collar. The seated figure on the left is male. This is Serena's father, Sir Gilbert. He faces right, in profile, and has long hair tied in a pony tail. His legs and arms are bent and he is holding a newspaper in both hands. His eyes are open and he appears to be looking at either the newspaper or Serena. His expression suggests anger. He is wearing a long coat, stockings and shoes. Sir Gilbert sits in a large chair. Between these figures is a round table covered with a table cloth. On top of the table are two tea cups and their saucers and a teapot. On the right of the design is a wooden chair with a wicker(?) seat. Hanging over the back of the chair is a robe, large piece of cloth, or a lap rug. On the left of the design in a large window set in a casement and adorned with sash curtains. In the background of the room, behind the seated figures and right of the window, are two walls with a decorative panel (perhaps a shutter) and moulding just below the ceiling. The floor may be carpeted.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Serena</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three figures occupy the center of the design. The figure on the right is Serena, with long hair, seated on a chair. She is wearing a gown and her upper body faces forward while her legs, which are bent, face left. Serena's eyes are open and she is looking down at, and reading, the open pages of a book. Her left arm is bent and rests on the back of a chair. Her right arm is slightly bent and in her right hand she holds the open book. Parallel lines indicate text on the book.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Penelope</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>anger</characteristic><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three figures occupy the center of the design. The central figure is a female, sitting on a wooden chair, facing forward with her head facing left in the direction of Serena. This is Serena's aunt, Penelope. Her eyes are open and she is looking at Serena. Her downturned mouth and slightly raised eyedbrows suggest displeasure or anger. Her hair is drawn up under a scarf or tight-fitting hat and tied with a bow. She is wearing a gown with a large collar.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Sir Gilbert</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>anger</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>paper</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>anger</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The seated figure on the left is male. This is Serena's father, Sir Gilbert. He faces right, in profile, and has long hair the runs down his upper back. His legs and arms are bent and he is holding a newspaper in both hands.  Parallel lines on the newspaper indicate text. His eyes are open and he appears to be either reading the newspaper or looking at Serena. His expression suggests anger. He is wearing a long coat, stockings and shoes. Sir Gilbert is sat in a large chair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>table</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>bowl</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><characteristic>pot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between the figures is a round table covered with a table cloth. On top of the table are two tea cups, their saucers and a teapot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>curtains</characteristic><illusobjdesc> On the left of the design in a large, glass panelled window set in a casement and adorned with sash curtains.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>clothing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design is a wooden chair with a wicker(?) seat. Hanging over the back of the chair is a long robe, large piece of cloth, or a lap rug.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>shutter</characteristic><characteristic>ceiling</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>carpet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the background of the room, behind the seated figures and right of the window, are two walls with a decorative panel (possibly a shutter) and moulding just below the ceiling. The floor may be carpeted.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.04.01" justify="left" indent="15">Canto. IV.<space extent="10"/>Verse 328</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.04.02" justify="left">Maria Flaxman inv: &amp; .del<space extent="19"/>W Blake. sculp.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.04.03" justify="left" indent="4">Publish'd, May 1. 1803. by Cadell &amp; Davies Strand</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb471.1.comeng.05" dbi="BB471.1.5.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Canto V. Verse 43</title>,           

<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 471.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>14.2 x 8.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="725"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates canto five, verses 43-44 of Hayley's poem. In the center of the design is a reclining female figure with her left eye closed. This is a slumbering Serena. She is wearing a gown and her hair is covered with a turban-like scarf. She faces left, in profile and her right arm is bent at 90 degrees and rests across her mid-drift. Her left arm is at her side. Her head is bent downward and she is partially covered with a sheet or blanket which extends to the floor. Serena's upper body is propped up on pillows and she is lying on a bed. The bed curtains are drawn back. Above Serena and to the left of the design is a flying or hovering figure with four wings shaped like those of a dragonfly.  She is shrouded in a semi-transparent cloak that extends to the floor. This is the nymph Sophrosyne, Serena's guide throughout Hayley's poem, descending "with guardian love." Sophrosyne's body faces away and her head faces to the right, in profile. She has long hair and her eye is open and she may be looking at the sleeping Serena. Sophrosyne's right arm is raised horizontally and she may be holding the semi-transparent cloak. Her left leg extends back and is bent slightly. The area behind these figures and the bed and curtains is dark and may represent the bedchamber wall. The floor may be carpeted.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Serena</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>turban</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the lower center of the design is a recling female figure with her left eye closed. This is the sleeping Serena. She is wearing a gown and her hair is covered with a cloth or turban-like scarf. She faces left, in profile and her right arm is bent at 90 degrees and rests across her mid-drift. Her left arm is at her side. Her head is bent downward and she is partially covered with a sheet or blanket which extends to the floor. Serena's upper body is propped up on pillows and she is lying on a bed with her legs crossed and slightly bent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nymph</characteristic><characteristic>Sophrosyne</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>dragonfly</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>eyes open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>love</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above Serena and to the left of the design is a flying or hovering figure with four wings like those of a dragonfly.  She is shrouded in a semi-transparent cloak that extends to the floor. This is the nymph Sophrosyne, Serena's guide throughout Hayley's poem, descending "with guardian love." Sophrosyne's body faces away and her head faces to the right, in profile. She has long hair and her eye is open and she may be looking at the sleeping Serena. Sophrosyne's right arm is raised horizontally and she may be holding the semi-transparent sheet. Her left leg extends back and is bent slightly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>sheet</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>curtain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a bed with curtains drawn back. On the bed are pillows, and a sheet that extends to the floor.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>carpet</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>chamber</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The area behind the two central figures, the bed and curtains is dark and may represent the bedchamber wall. The floor may be carpeted.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.05.01" justify="left" indent="16">Canto V.<space extent="9"/>Verse 43</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.05.02" justify="left">Maria Flaxman inv &amp; .del<space extent="19"/>W Blake sculp</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.05.03" justify="left" indent="3">Publish'd, May 1. 1803. by Cadell &amp; Davies Strand</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb471.1.comeng.06" dbi="BB471.1.6.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Canto VI. Verse 294</title>,           

            <objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 471.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc><objsize>13.2 x 8.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates canto six, verse 294 of Hayley's poem: Serena removing her "hot oppressive mask" during the masquerade ball. In the center foreground are two standing figures. The figure on the right is female, with long hair and is facing left in profile. This is Serena. She is wearing a long gown with a cape or cloak. A set of butterfly-like wings are attached to the top of the cape. Serena is dressed as the nymph, Ariel, from Shakespeare's "The Tempest." Serena's left shoe protrudes from the hem of her gown. Her left arm is bent and in her left hand she holds a mask. Serena's right hand rests on the hand of the male figure to the left. This is Sir Gilbert dressed as a Caliban. Sir Gilbert faces forward with his head facing slightly left. His costume is covered in fur and he sports a long moustache and dark eyebrows. His hair is short and there are two protrusions either side of his head that may be horns. His right arm is bent at 90 degrees and in his hand he holds the narrow end of a wooden club. The thicker end of the club rests on the floor. His left hand is by his side and supports his daughter's right hand. Sir Gilbert's legs are apart and his left foot is visible. Behind Serena and Sir Gilbert are ten standing figures attired in a variety of costumes. The figure on the left of the design is a male(?) facing right, in profile. He is wearing a long coat and his right shoe is visible. He wears an elaborate hat that appears to be made of feathers or straw. The second figure from the left is female(?), facing forward. She is wearing a mask and a bicorn hat with a large feather. She is wearing a long gown and her left hand is visible, held palm outward. The third figure faces away and may be female(?). She is wearing a small round hat that has feathers attached, possibly on top of a powdered wig. She is wearing a coat or gown. The fourth figure from the left is a female. She has short hair, faces right, in profile, and is wearing a gown and a mask. Her right arm is extended and bent slightly. Her right hand is holding another hand. Her left shoe is visible, on tip toe, suggesting that she is walking or possibly dancing. The fifth figure from the left is male. Only his face and headgear are visible. He faces left in profile and may be wearing a helmet with the visor up. The sixth figure from the left is male, faces forward and appears to be smiling. He is dressed in a shirt and toga and is wearing a cap with a band. Part of his left leg is visible. The seventh figure from the left is male. Only the head and shoulders of this figure are visible. He faces forward and is wearing a helmet topped with an elaborate plume of feathers. The eighth figure from the left is male(?). Only part of the face and right hand are visible. He faces right, in profile and appears to be smiling. In his right hand he holds the left hand of the masked female. The figure on the right of the design faces away. He or she appears to be wearing a turban and a cloak or gown. The second figure from the right is female. She faces left, has long hair and is wearing a wide brimmed hat that narrows to a point. She is wearing a dark dress with a cloak or cape: the costume of a witch. The scene takes place indoors, in a large room with Gothic arches and pillars. Behind Serena and Sir Gilbert is a central pillar. Part of a pillar is visible on the left of the design and there are two, possibly three pillars behind the figures. On the right of the design is a curtain that has been drawn back. The floor may be carpeted.    

               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Serena</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Ariel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>mask</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center foreground are two standing figures. The figure on the right is female, with long hair and is facing left in profile. This is Serena. She is wearing a long gown with a cape or cloak. A set of butterfly-like wings are attached to the top of the cape. Serena is dressed as the nymph, Ariel, from Shakespeare's "The Tempest." Serena's left shoe protrudes from the hem of her gown. Her left arm is bent and in her left hand she holds a mask. Serena's right hand rests on the hand of the male figure to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Sir Gilbert</characteristic><characteristic>Caliban</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>club</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs apart</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center forground are two standing figures. The figure on the left is male. This is Sir Gilbert dressed as a Caliban. Sir Gilbert faces forward with his head facing slightly left. His costume is covered in fur and he sports a long moustache, and dark eyebrows. His hair is short and there are two protrusions either side of his head that may be horns. His right arm is bent at 90 degrees and in his hand he holds the narrow end of a wooden club.The thicker end of the club rests on the floor. His left hand is by his side and supports his daughter's right hand. Sir Gilbert's legs are apart and his left foot is visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>shoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind Serena and Sir Gilbert are ten standing figures attired in a variety of costumes. The figure on the left of the design is a male(?) facing right, in profile. He is wearing a long coat and his right shoe is visible. He wears an elaborate hat that appears to be made of feathers or straw.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>mask</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>wig</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>shoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>tip toe</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The second figure from the left is female(?), facing forward. She is wearing a mask and a bicorn hat with a large feather. She is wearing a long gown and her left hand is visible, held palm outward. The third figure faces away and may be female (?). She is wearing a small round hat that has feathers attached possibly on top of a powdered wig. She is wearing a coat or gown. The fourth figure from the left is a female. She has short hair, faces right, in profile, and is wearing a gown and a mask. Her right arm is extended and bent slightly. Her right hand is holding another hand. Her left shoe is visible, on tip toe, suggesting that she is walking or possibly dancing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>tunic</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>plume</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The fifth figure from the left is male. Only his face and headgear are visible. He faces left in profile and may be wearing a helmet with the visor up. The sixth figure from the left is male, faces forward and appears to be smiling. He is dressed in a shirt and toga or tunic and is wearing a hat with a band. Part of his left leg is visible. The seventh figure from the left is male. Only the head and shoulders of this figure are visible. He faces forward and is wearing a helmet topped with an elaborate plume of feathers. The eighth figure from the left is male (?). Only part of the face and right hand are visible. He faces right, in profile and appears to be smiling. In his right hand he hold the left hand of the masked female.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>turban</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>witch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure on the right of the design faces away. He/she appears to be wearing a turban and a cloak or gown. The second figure from the right is female. She faces left, has long hair and is wearing a wide brimmed hat that narrows to a point. She is wearing a dark gown with a cape: the costume of a witch.

                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>curtain</characteristic><characteristic>carpet</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>ceiling</characteristic><illusobjdesc> The scene takes place indoors, in a large room with Gothic arches and pillars. Behind Serena and Sir Gilbert is a central pillar. Part of a pillar is visible on the left of the design and there are two, possibly three pillars forming the far wall behind the figures. On the right of the design is a curtain that has been drawn back. The floor may be carpeted.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="12"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.06.01" justify="left" indent="16">Canto. VI.<space extent="5"/>Verse 294.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.06.02" justify="left">Maria Flaxman. inv. &amp; del.<space extent="16"/>W Blake. sculp.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb471.1.comeng.06.03" justify="left" indent="2">Publish'd, May 1. 1803. by Cadell &amp; Davies. Strand</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>