<bad catalog="bentley" catid="504" copy="1" copyid="1" id="bb504.2" institution="huntington" type="comb" work="Pastorals of Virgil">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="Pastorals of Virgil">
          <main>The Pastorals of Virgil</main>
          <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
              and the University of Rochester </sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>1 XML file approx. 190KB; 26 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 70KB to 520KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
        <date>January 2011</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to Robert John Thornton's edition of 
        <hi rend="i">The Pastorals of Virgil</hi>
        (1821) and a selection of his preliminary drawings for his Virgil wood engravings.  The texts and images in both groups are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        When planning a third edition of his successful school text of Virgil's 
        <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi>
        , Robert John Thornton employed Blake to contribute some of the new designs for the two-volume work.  His assignment was to illustrate Ambrose Philips' English &quot;imitation&quot; of Virgil's first eclogue.  Blake produced four small designs as relief etchings on a single copperplate, but these were rejected by Thornton.  There may have been several reasons, including the unconventional style of etching, the semi-nudity of some of the figures, and the difficulties letterpress printers would have encountered with such an unusual matrix.  Apparently Blake was asked to prepare wood engravings, a medium in which he had never before worked, instead of relief etchings.  He executed a series of at least twenty-one pen, pencil, and wash preliminary drawings; these were probably approved by Thornton.  The wood engravings that Blake produced from them, however, were far less conventional.  Thornton was again taken aback by Blake's bold transgression of contemporary styles and sensibilities.  Several influential artists, including John Linnell and Sir Thomas Lawrence, commended Blake's work; their opinions convinced Thornton to print them in his 1821 edition.  Three designs were engraved by a journeyman for the sake of comparison with Blake's own productions in wood, and Thornton added a statement below Blake's first design implying his hesitations about Blake's artistry.  Pre-publication proofs of Blake's wood engravings show that each group of four were cut on a single block; these were cut apart, slightly reduced in size on all four sides, and printed with brief letterpress captions.  This format, as published in Thornton's Virgil, is preserved in our reproductions.
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        In addition to his original wood engravings, Blake contributed six copperplate intaglio engravings picturing famous classical figures.  He also executed a reduced drawing, perhaps directly on the woodblock, based on a painting by Nicolas Poussin.  This was cut in the block by John Byfield.  All these materials are included in our reproductions of Thornton's Virgil.  In addition, the relief etching of four designs, the woodblock of Blake's first wood engraving, and the pre-publication proofs of two groups of designs before they were separated are available under Related Works in the Archive on the Show Me menu for Objects 5-7.
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Twenty of Blake's preliminary drawings for his wood engravings, all executed in monochrome wash, were sold at auction from the Linnell collection in 1918.  These are now widely dispersed; seven are untraced and one drawing in the group was not engraved.  We are now publishing a selection of seven of these drawings and plan to add more as they become available.  
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Although small in size and almost rejected by the man who commissioned them, Blake's Virgil wood engravings have been among his most influential works.  The young artists who gathered around Blake in his final years, including Samuel Palmer, George Richmond, and Edward Calvert, were deeply inspired by the Virgil engravings.  Palmer called them &quot;visions of little dells, and nooks, and corners of Paradise&quot;—an encomium that ignores the darker implications of some designs.  Several twentieth-century British artists, including Graham Sutherland, were also influenced by Blake's wood engravings.                     
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2011</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This image copyright © 2011 Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
         
      <lb/>
      <lb/></userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Publication prep</change>
        <date>November-December 2010</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Joseph Vogel,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Illustration description created</change>
        <date>Spring 2010</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Lamperez,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>BAD created</change>
        <date>October 2008</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
          <name>April Brown, </name>
          <name>Kit Curtin, </name>
          <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
          <name>Eric Forster, </name>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
          <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
          <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Images acquired and catalogued, metadata collected</change>
        <date>September 2005</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
          <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
          <name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>
            *The Pastorals of Virgil*
          </title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>delineator, </role>
          <role>etcher, </role>
          <role>engraver.  Blake invented, delineated, and engraved seventeen wood engravings (Objects 5-8, 10 as presented here).  He designed and delineated as drawings, but did not engrave, three wood engravings (Object 9).  He delineated as drawings, and etched and engraved, six plates based on sculpture and coins (Objects 1-4, 12, 13).  He delineated as a drawing (possibly on a woodblock) one design, invented (and executed as a painting) by Nicolas Poussin and engraved in wood by John Byfield (Object 11).</role></origination>
        <origination>Nicolas Poussin
          <role>inventor.  Object 11 is based on a painting by Poussin.</role></origination>
        <origination>John Byfield
          <role>engraver.  Object 11 was engraved in wood by Byfield.</role></origination>
        <origination>anonymous
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>engraver.  Three wood engravings (Object 9) were engraved by one or more anonymous journeymen based on Blake's designs.  The busts and coins pictured in Objects 1-4, 12, and 13 were invented by anonymous artists and craftsmen.</role></origination>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>F. C. and J. Rivingtons, Longman and Co., Sherwood and Co., Whittaker and Co., Cadell and Co., Arch and Co., Black and Co., J. Richardson, Asperne, Souter, Sir Richard Phillips and Co., Rodwell and Co., Gosling, Cox, Highly, Bumpus, and Sharp.</publisher>
          <pubplace>London</pubplace>
          <date>1821</date>
        </imprint>
        <compdate value="1821.A">1821</compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <printdate value="1821.A">1821</printdate>
        <numberobj>13
          <note>Objects 5-8 and 10 each include four separate wood engravings.  Object 9 includes three separate wood engravings.</note></numberobj>
        <objorder>1-6</objorder>
        <objsize>ranging between 9.5 x 7.1 cm. and 16.4 x 11.7 cm.
          <note>This is the range of sizes of the objects as presented here, including associated texts.  See the Editors' Notes for the sizes of individual engraved images.</note></objsize>
        <numberleaves>13</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>17.4 x 10.1 cm.</leafsize>
        <medium>etching, engraving, and letterpress
          <note>Objects 1-4, 12, and 13 are copperplate etchings/engravings.  Objects 5-11 are wood engravings.  The texts in Objects 5-11 were printed in letterpress.</note></medium>
        <printingstyle>intaglio and relief
          <note>Objects 1-4, 12, and 13 were printed in intaglio.  Objects 5-11 were printed in relief.</note></printingstyle>
        <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
        <support>wove paper</support>
        <watermark>none</watermark>
        <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
        <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
        <framelines>Two frame lines surround the pictorial images (but not the associated texts) in Objects 1-5, 12, and 13.  A single frame line surrounds the pictorial image in Object 11.</framelines>
        <binding>late nineteenth- or early twentieth-century brown morocco over brown cloth boards by Riviere and Son</binding>
        <stabholes>none</stabholes>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</name>
        <date>1919</date>
        <dealer>not recorded</dealer>
        <price>not recorded</price>
        <note>Acquired by Henry E. Huntington in April 1919 from the library of Frederic Rowland Marvin.  The earlier history of this copy is not known.</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</institution>
        <addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline>
        <addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline>
        <addressline>USA</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2100</addressline>
        <addressline>Fax: 626-405-3477</addressline>
        <addressline>URL, general: http://www.huntington.org</addressline>
        <addressline>URL, Library Division: http://www.huntington.org/LibraryDiv/LibraryHome.html</addressline>
        <department>Library Division, Rare Books</department>
        <repositoryid label="Call number">137046</repositoryid>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.1.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Theocritus,</title>,
            

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B1">(Bentley 504.1)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 9.8 x 7.2 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>13.1 x 7.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="725" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>A bust, identified in the inscription below the image as that of Theocritus, sits in the center of the design, facing right with eyes open. Theocritus is depicted with curly hair and a beard. He is crowned with squared leaves, resembling a vine or possibly a crown of laurel.
               </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Theocritus</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bust</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bust, identified in the inscription below the image as that of Theocritus, sits in the center of the design, facing right with eyes open. Theocritus is depicted with curly hair and a beard. He is crowned with squared leaves, resembling a vine or possibly a crown of laurel.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="8"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="33" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.01">Blake, del. et Sculp.</l>
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.02">Theocritus,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.03">A Grecian Poet, of Sicily Flourished 273 years</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.04">before the Birth of Christ, and quitting his</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.05">native country, governed by Hiero, King of</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.06">Syracuse, went over to King Ptolemy in Egypt,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.07">by whom he was greatly patronized.</l>
          <l indent="35" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.08">Vide Idyllium, 17.</l>
          <l indent="3" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.01.09">London, Published by D
            <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
            . Thornton, 1821.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.2.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Publius Virgilius Maro.</title>,
            

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B2">(Bentley 504.2)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 10.2 x 6.8 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>13.9 x 9.2 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="750" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>A bust, identified in the inscription below the image as Publius Virgilius Maro (Virgil), faces forward and to the left. He is portrayed with long, curly hair with a band that crowns his head. The bust may be resting on a plinth or table.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bust</characteristic>
            <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>band</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bust, identified in the inscription below the image as Publius Virgilius Maro (Virgil), faces forward and to the left. He is portrayed with long, curly hair with a band that crowns his head.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>table</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The bust appears to be resting on a table or plinth.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="10"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="41" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.01">Blake, del. et Sculp.</l>
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.02">Publius Virgilius Maro.</l>
          <l indent="17" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.03">Poetarum Latinorum Princeps.</l>
          <l indent="3" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.04">Born 69 years before the Birth of Christ; was 7 years older</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.05">than Augustus; lost his Estate, at 30; recovering it was nearly killed</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.06">by Arius, the Centurion; some think he began his Eclogues, at 31;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.07">which took him 3 years. Commenced his Georgies, at 34, which</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.08">occupied him 7 years; and at 41 began his Æneid, which employed</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.09">him 11 years; at 52, Virgil died, 19 years before the Christian Æra.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="12" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.02.10">London, Published by D
            <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
            . Thornton, 1821.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.3.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.03">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Octavius Augustus Cæsar.</title>,
            

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B3">(Bentley 504.3)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 12.4 x 8.5 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>15.2 x 9.0 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="820" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of a male, identified in the inscription below the image as Octavius Augustus Cæsar, looks left in profile. Unlike preceding plates, this figure appears life-like rather than a sculpture. His hair is short, and his shoulders are covered by fabric that is clasped by a brooch or cloth band on his left shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
            <characteristic>brooch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>band</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of a male, identified in the inscription below the image as Octavius Augustus Cæsar, looks left in profile in the center of the plate. Unlike preceding plates, this figure appears life-like rather than a sculpture. His hair is short, and his shoulders are covered by fabric that is clasped by a brooch or cloth band on his left shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="10"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="41" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.01">Blake, del. et Sculp.</l>
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.02">Octavius Augustus Cæsar.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.03">Was Nephew to Julius Cæsar, and 18 years old when Cæsar was aƒsaƒsinated;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.04">joins Antony, and Lepidus, and defeats Brutus and Caƒsius, at the</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.05">Battle of Phillippi, 41 years B.C. __ Antony marries Octavia, Sister</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.06">to Augustus, whom he deserts for Cleopatria, Queen of Egypt, whom</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.07">Cæsar defeats in a naval battle at Actium, 31 years before Christ,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.08">__ Shuts the Temple of Janus, the world having been created 3948</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.09">years, when a new Æra commences, the Birth of Christ; __ dies,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.10">14 years after that period, at 76, having reigned 44 years.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="12" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.03.11">London, Published by D
            <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
            . Thornton, 1821.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.4.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.04">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">From Antique Coins.</title>,
            

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B4">(Bentley 504.4)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 13.3 x 8.4 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>15.6 x 8.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="835" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>In each corner of the plate is a coin with the engraving of a male's head and neck on it, each facing outward from the center of the design, identified as representations of Pollio, Gallus, Varus, and Mecænas. In the center of the design, a bust of a man with short hair, identified below as Agrippa, faces forward and slightly left, surrounded by a ring of laurels, which in turn is surrounded by a halo or aura of light.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Agrippa</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bust</characteristic>
            <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <characteristic>brooch</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a bust of a man with short hair, identified below as Agrippa.  The bust of Agrippa faces forward and slightly left.  His shoulders are covered by fabric that is clasped by a brooch on his right shoulder.  A separate piece of cloth appears just below his neck.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>berry</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>string</characteristic>
            <characteristic>band</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The bust of Agrippa is surrounded by two arching laurel branches that form a complete circle.  The branches are tied together below the bust with a string or ribbon and take the form of a crown.  The laurel branches also contain at least eighteen small buds or berries.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
            <characteristic>aura</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Lines indicating radiant light form a halo or aura around the bust of Agrippa.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Pollio</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the upper left corner of the design is a coin with the engraving of a male's head and neck on it, identified above as Pollio. The figure is facing left and has shoulder-length hair and wears a spiky crown.
            
         </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Gallus</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the upper right corner of the design is a coin with the engraving of a male's head and neck on it, identified above as Gallus. The figure faces right and has short, possibly curly, hair.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Varus</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the design is a coin with the engraving of a male's head and neck on it, identified below as Varus. The figure faces left and has short hair.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Mecaenas</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the design is a coin with the engraving of a male's head and neck on it, identified below as Mecænas. The figure faces right, and has short hair and a prominent forehead.  Lines on his face suggest he is old.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="28" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.01">From Antique Coins.</l>
          <l indent="21" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.02">POLLIO
            <space extent="16"/>
            GALLUS</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="10"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="32" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.03">AGRIPPA</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="3"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.04">VARUS
            <space extent="15"/>
            MECÆNAS</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="60" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.05">Blake del et Sculp.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.06">POLLIO was a Poet, a General, &amp; a great favourite to Augustus, &amp; was twice Consul.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.07">GALLUS was made Præfect of Egypt, a Poet, who slew himself having ruled Tyrannically.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.08">AGRIPPA a famous General to Augustus, commanded in all his battles, &amp; was married to Julia daughter to Augustus.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.09">VARUS was of noble extraction, Father to Maia, Virgil's wife, was also a Poet, &amp; Governor of Cisalpine Gaul.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.10">MECÆNAS was prime Minister to Augustus, &amp; died 7 Years after the birth of Christ.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.04.11">London, Published by D
            <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
            . Thornton, 1822.
            <note>The year, &quot;1822,&quot; is probably an error for 1821.</note></l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.5.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.05">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.  FRONTISPIECE.</title>,
           

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B5">(Bentley 504.5)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 6.0 x 8.4 cm.  Blake's preliminary drawing is unrecorded.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>12.4 x 8.5 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="700" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="relbb504.1.rm.01" ovp="noindex">The face of the engraved woodblock from which Object 5 was printed.
         </related>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Two shepherds, identified as Thenot (left) and Colinet (right) in the letterpress caption below the design, stand with a flock of sheep between them. The leftmost figure, Thenot, is an older male with long hair and a beard. He stands, with his left foot peeking out from under the hem of his gown, with his left arm by his side and his right arm bent at the elbow, palm raised vertically. Colinet, the rightmost male, leans against a tree on which is hung a horn and a set of shepherd's pipes. He holds a crook in his right arm, which is by his side, and rests his left elbow on the tree, with his left hand in his hair. Colinet has long hair and is wearing what may be a transparent gown. Between the two shepherds are a flock of seven grazing sheep.  The sheep fourth from the left may be a horned ram. Behind the figures is a landscape of hillsides, with the sun rising or setting over the hilltops. The roof and the upper portion of a window or door of a small building, possibly a house or cottage, are set into the hills behind the flock of sheep.
      </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two shepherds, identified as Thenot (left) and Colinet (right) in the letterpress caption below the design, stand with a flock of sheep between them. The leftmost figure, Thenot, is an older male with long hair and a beard. His left foot is visible below the hem of his gown.  His left arm is down at his side with the palm turned downward; his right arm is bent at the elbow with the palm raised vertically and turned out toward the viewer.  His head is bent to the right.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two shepherds, identified as Thenot (left) and Colinet (right) in the letterpress caption below the design, stand with a flock of sheep between them. Colinet, the rightmost male, leans in an almost contrapposto position against a tree to the right. His right arm is by his side; in his right hand he holds a shepherd's crook. His left arm is bent with the elbow resting on the tree; his left hand rests against his face or head. Colinet has long hair and is wearing what may be a transparent gown that ends just below the knees. He faces forward and his expression may indicate despair or melancholy.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between the two shepherds are a flock of seven grazing sheep.  The sheep fourth from the left may be a horned ram.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Colinet leans against a tree at the right edge of the design.  The leafy branches of the tree extend to the left above Colinet to the center of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="object">
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A musical horn and a set of shepherd's pipes are hung on the tree rising along the right margin.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The roof and upper portion of a door or window of a small building, possibly a house or cottage, appear within the folds of the hills above the flock of sheep.  The sun rises or sets above the hills in the background, just above the building.  Four beams of light radiate from it.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The foreground may be covered with grass.  The background hills appear to be covered with vegetation of some sort.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.01">To face page 13,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.02">ILLUSTRATIONS</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="25" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.03">OF</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="13" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.04">IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="3"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.05">FRONTISPIECE.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="5"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="14" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.06">THENOT AND COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="1" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.07">The Illustrations of this English Pastoral are by the famous</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.08">BLAKE, the illustrator of 
            <hi rend="italic">Young's</hi>
            Night Thoughts, and 
            <hi rend="italic">Blair's</hi></l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.09">Grave; who designed and engraved them himself.  This is men-</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.10">tioned, as they display less of art than genius, and are much</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.05.11">admired by some eminent painters.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="bb504.bm-woodengraving.5" id="relbb504.1.rm.01">
         <objtitle>
            <title type="transcribed">Illustrations of Imitation of Eclogue I: woodblock</title>,
           

            <objid>
               <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
               <objcode code="B5">(Bentley 504.5)</objcode></objid>
         </objtitle>
         <physdesc>
            <objnote>
               <p>This is the engraved woodblock from which impressions of Object 5 were printed.  The image on the woodblock, including the framing lines, measures 6.0 x 8.4 cm.</p>
            </objnote>
            <objsize>6.0 x 8.4 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="400" width="400"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration location="E" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>Two shepherds, Thenot (right) and Colinet (left), stand with a flock of sheep between them. The rightmost figure, Thenot, is an older male with long hair and a beard. He stands, with his right foot peeking out from under the hem of his gown, with his right arm by his side and his left arm bent at the elbow, palm raised vertically. Colinet, the leftmost male, leans against a tree on which is hung a horn and a set of shepherd's pipes. He holds a crook in his left arm, which is by his side, and rests his right elbow on the tree, with his right hand on his head. Colinet has long hair and is wearing what may be a transparent gown. Between the two shepherds are a flock of seven grazing sheep.  The sheep fourth from the right may be a horned ram. Behind the figures is a landscape of hillsides, with the sun rising or setting over the hilltops. The roof and the upper portion of a window or door of a small building, possibly a house or cottage, are set into the hills behind the flock of sheep.
               </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="BD" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two shepherds, Thenot (right) and Colinet (left), stand with a flock of sheep between them. The rightmost figure, Thenot, is an older male with long hair and a beard. His right foot is visible below the hem of his gown.  His right arm is down at his side with the palm turned downward; his left arm is bent at the elbow with the palm raised vertically and turned out toward the viewer.  His head is bent to the left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AC" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two shepherds, Thenot (right) and Colinet (left), stand with a flock of sheep between them. Colinet, the leftmost male, leans in an almost contrapposto position against a tree to the left. His left arm is by his side; in his left hand he holds a shepherd's crook. His right arm is bent with the elbow resting on the tree; his right hand rests against his head or face. Colinet has long hair and is wearing what may be a transparent gown that ends just below the knees. He faces forward and his expression may indicate despair or melancholy.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Between the two shepherds are a flock of seven grazing sheep.  The sheep fourth from the right may be a horned ram.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AC" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Colinet leans against a tree at the left edge of the design.  The leafy branches of the tree extend to the right above Colinet to the center of the design.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AC" type="object">
                  <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A musical horn and a set of shepherd's pipes are hung on the tree rising along the left margin.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="E" type="object">
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The roof and upper portion of a door or window of a small building, possibly a house or cottage, appear within the folds of the hills above the flock of sheep.  The sun rises or sets above the hills in the background, just above the building.  Four beams of light radiate from it.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="E" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The foreground may be covered with grass.  The background hills appear to be covered with vegetation of some sort.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
      </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.6-9.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.06">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</title>,
           

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B6-9">(Bentley 504.6-9)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The individual wood engravings, from top to bottom, measure 3.6 x 7.4 cm., 3.2 x 7.5 cm., 3.2 x 7.3 cm., and 3.5 x 7.5 cm.  Blake's preliminary drawings, from top to bottom, are in the following collections: Keynes Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge; Robert N. Essick, Altadena, California; collection of Arthur Vershbow, Boston, Massachusetts; untraced since 1924 (Butlin 769.1-3, 5).</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>16.3 x 7.5 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="830" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="relbb504.1.rm.02" ovp="noindex">Blake’s relief etching of versions of the designs in Object 6 among the wood engravings.
         </related>
      <related objectid="relbb504.1.rm.03" ovp="noindex">Proof impression of Object 6 before the individual designs were separated and reduced in size.
         </related>
      <related objectid="but769.1.wd.01" ovp="noindex">Preliminary drawing for the top design.
         </related>
      <related objectid="but769.1.wd.02" ovp="noindex">Preliminary drawing for the design second from the top.
         </related>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom in letterpress (top to bottom) &quot;COLINET.&quot;; &quot;THENOT.&quot;; &quot;COLINET and THENOT.&quot;; and &quot;COLINET.&quot; In the top image, Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm raised, palm vertical and facing out. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. Thenot, the older shepherd on the left, faces Colinet with his arms raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture. A dog lays his head on Thenot's right foot. At least three sheep graze to the left and right of Colinet. The sun sets or rises over the hills in the background and a tree trunk frames the right side of the scene.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the top image, Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm bent upward with his left hand raised above his head and the palm turned out toward the viewer. His right arm is bent and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. His hair is long. He faces forward and to the left, perhaps looking toward Thenot. He wears a knee-length gown, possibly with a high-waisted belt.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>An older shepherd, Thenot, stands to the left with his back to the viewer.  His head is turned to the right and he may be looking toward Colinet.  His arms are raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture; his hands are held out with the palms held vertically.  He has long hair and a beard, and wears a full-length gown.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A dog stands to the right of Thenot with its head down at Thenot's right foot. The dog may be greeting Thenot, perhaps by sniffing his foot.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>At least three sheep graze with their heads down to the left and right of Colinet.  The body of a fourth sheep may be visible just to the right of Colinet.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The trunk of a tree rises along the right border of the design. The leafy branches of the tree extend to the left and dangle above the sun on the horizon.  There may be grass in the foreground and some sort of vegetation on the hills, particularly left of Thenot's left knee.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures is a landscape of hills or distant mountains, with the sun rising or setting in the center of the design.  Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;COLINET.&quot;; &quot;THENOT.&quot;; &quot;COLINET and THENOT.&quot;; and &quot;COLINET.&quot; In the second image from the top, Thenot sits on the left under the branches of a fruit tree, possibly with his eyes closed, and with his arms bent and raised. Another figure, Colinet, sits or reclines to the right under another tree with his body twisted and head bowed.  He leans on his right elbow; his left hand may be raised to his face. Two sheep, perhaps part of a larger flock, lie between the two figures. A sun shines in the sky over a scene of grassy hills, leafy trees, and a small building, perhaps a house or cottage.         
      </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Thenot sits on the left side of the image, his eyes possibly closed and his arms bent upward with the palms raised and turned up. His legs and head face to the right and his torso is twisted to face forward towards the viewer. He is old, with long hair and a beard, and wears a gown.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Another figure, Colinet, sits or reclines to the right under a tree. His head is bowed and may rest on his raised left hand. His right leg is extended to the left while his left leg is bent back; his upper body is twisted and faces away from the viewer. Both arms are bent, and his right elbow leans against a rock or mound of earth.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two sheep lie on the ground between the human figures.  The one on the left turns its head to the left; the one on the right, apparently a horned ram, faces forward.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two trees flank the scene. The branches of the tree on the left arch to the right over Thenot; the branches are leafy and bear at least seven round fruits. The tree to the right of Colinet extends its branches over him, with its leafy branches arching to the left.  There may be grass in the foreground; the background hills and valleys also contain vegetation, perhaps including trees.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Thenot, on the left, appears to be sitting on bank or mound of earth.  Colinet, on the right, leans against a similar bank or mound.  The background is a landscape of grassy hills or more distant mountains, with the sun in the sky over the hilltops.  Beams of light radiate from the sun. The roof and top window of what appears to be a small building, probably a house or cottage, are visible below and to the right of the sun.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;COLINET.&quot;; &quot;THENOT.&quot;; &quot;COLINET and THENOT.&quot;; and &quot;COLINET.&quot; In the third image from the top, Colinet stands on the left, leaning against the trunk of a tree. He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and looks down, perhaps at the two sheep in front of him. He may be holding musical pipes in his lowered right hand, as in the relief etching of this design (see Related Works in the Archive). To the right, Thenot, with long hair and a beard, also leans against the trunk of a tree. He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and raises his right hand to gesture towards the left. In the center foreground of the design, two sheep stand with their heads turned to the left.  Directly above, a nude(?) figure runs on a hill, with a dog behind him and possibly chasing him.  The running man holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. At least five sheep stand or run below and to the right of the running figure.
      </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Colinet stands on the left of the image and leans against a tree trunk to the left. He has long hair and wears a knee-length gown, perhaps with a belt around the waist. His arms are at his sides; he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand.  He may be holding musical pipes in his lowered right hand, as in the relief etching of this design (see Related Works in the Archive). His left leg is bent back with his left foot raised on tiptoe or resting against the tree trunk. He looks down, possibly at the two sheep in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Thenot stands on the right side of the image, leaning against the trunk of a tree.  His body is slightly twisted as he faces both forward and to the left with his left foot slightly extended and visible below the hem of his garment. He has long hair and a beard and wears a gown. He raises his right hand horizontally as though gesturing, palm out and up, to the left. His left arm is slightly bent and down at his side; he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His mouth may be open and he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Both Colinet, on the left, and Thenot, on the right, stand beneath and lean against trees. Very little is visible of the tree on the left, with the exception of some of the trunk and a few leafless(?) branches top left. The tree on the right is larger; a few leaves are visible on the branch over Thenot's head and possibly near the upper right margin.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>running</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center foreground of the image, two sheep stand facing Colinet with their mouths open. At least three additional sheep appear above and to the right. These sheep may run or leap to the right with their heads turned back to the left; they may look toward the running figure above and to the left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>running</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Directly above the pair of sheep, a nude(?) male figure with short hair on a hill runs or leaps to the right. Both arms are raised horizontally, with the palm of his right hand facing down, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His left leg is bent at the knee and his left foot is raised on tiptoe; his right leg is extended backward, nearly horizontally. He looks down and to the left, perhaps at the dog behind him.  He may be fleeing from the dog.
         </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
            <characteristic>running</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>barking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A dog on a hill leaps to the right; it may be running after and pursuing the figure to the right. The dog's legs are extended, with its hind legs on the ground and its fore legs in the air. Its visible ear and tail are blown back horizontally to indicate its speed. The dog's mouth appears to be open and it may be barking.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The background landscape includes at least two hills, one below the running man and dog and one far right.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The foreground may be grassy. There are indications of vegetation in the middle distance, particularly left of the running sheep.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;COLINET.&quot;; &quot;THENOT.&quot;; &quot;COLINET and THENOT.&quot;; and &quot;COLINET.&quot; In the bottom image, Thenot stands to the left of Colinet.  Thenot may be walking towards Colinet, right foot on tiptoe and with arms lowered and palms facing down. Colinet's arms are raised and he appears to be walking forward toward the viewer, prominent left foot forward and the right foot perhaps on tiptoe. On the right of the image is a large tree with riven trunk and one arching limb bare of leaves. A horned ram and three sheep stand to the right of Colinet.  One sheep, facing right, kneels to nurse. The ground may be covered in grass; two hills appear in the background.
      </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned male, Thenot, stands on the left side of the image. He is seen from behind and may be walking towards Colinet. Thenot's right leg is bent and his right foot raised on tiptoe. His arms are down but raised toward 45 degrees with both palms facing down. His head faces right in profile; the figure has long hair and a beard.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A male, Colinet, stands to the right of Thenot.  Colinet wears a gown that reaches to his knees; his hair is long.  He faces forward and may walk toward the viewer; his right leg is bent and his right foot raised on tiptoe.  Colinet's right arm is bent upward with the palm turned out and up, fingers slightly spread. His left arm is bent and raised nearly horizontally, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand.  Colinet's mouth may be open; he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large, riven, and probably dead tree rises on the right.  One leafless branch arches to the left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A group of four sheep stand to the right of Colinet.  Furthest left, a horned ram grazes with its head down.  To the right, a sheep stands facing left with its head turned to the right.  Its mouth is open.  Further to the right, a ewe stands facing right with its head turned down; it may look at the lamb below.  The lamb faces left with its front legs kneeling on the ground; its head is bent up as it suckles on the ewe.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two hills or more distant mountains rise in the background.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>There may be grass in the foreground.  There may be trees in the middle distance, rising just below the hills.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="38" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.06.01">To face page 14.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.06.02">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.06.03">COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.06.04">THENOT.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="12" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.06.05">COLINET and THENOT.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.06.06">COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="bb504.essick-reliefetching.6-9" id="relbb504.1.rm.02">
         <objtitle>
            <title type="transcribed">Illustrations of Imitation of Eclogue I: relief etching</title>,
           

            <objid>
               <objnumber code="A6">Object 6</objnumber>
               <objcode code="B6-9">(Bentley 504.6-9)</objcode></objid>
         </objtitle>
         <physdesc>
            <objnote>
               <p>This relief etching of Object 6 was probably executed before the wood engravings and even before the preliminary drawings for the wood engravings.  See Robert N. Essick, &quot;A Relief Etching of Blake's Virgil Illustrations,&quot; 
                  *Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly*
                  , 25 (1991-92): 117-27.</p>
            </objnote>
            <objsize>14.3 x 8.5 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="830" width="600"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the top image, Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm raised, palm vertical and facing out. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. Thenot, the older shepherd on the left, faces Colinet with his arms raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture. A dog lays his head on Thenot's right foot. At least three sheep graze to the left and right of Colinet. The sun sets or rises over the hills in the background and a tree trunk frames the right side of the scene.</illusobjdesc>
               <component location="B" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the top image, Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands in a semi-contrapposto posture, with his left arm bent upward with his left hand raised above his head and the palm turned out. His right arm is bent and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. He faces forward and to the left, perhaps looking toward Thenot. His mouth may be open and he may be speaking He appears to be wearing semi-transparent tights (note the lines at his calves, indicating the lower reaches of the garment).</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>An older shepherd, Thenot, stands to the left with his back to the viewer.  His head is turned to the right and he may be looking toward Colinet.  His arms are raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture; his hands are with the right palm held out and vertically and the left palm facing up.  He has long hair and a beard, and wears a full-length, possibly semi-transparent, gown.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A dog stands to the right of Thenot with its head down at Thenot's right foot. The dog may be greeting Thenot, perhaps by sniffing his foot.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>At least two sheep graze with their heads down to the left of Colinet.  The body of a fourth sheep may be visible just to the right of Colinet. The left-most sheep may be a horned ram.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The trunk of a tree rises along the right border of the design. The leafy branches of the tree extend to the left and dangle above the sun on the horizon. There may be grass in the foreground and some sort of vegetation on the hills, particularly left of Thenot's left knee.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures is a landscape of hills, with the sun rising or setting in the center of the design.  Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the second image from the top, Thenot sits or kneels on the left under the branches of a fruit tree, with his arms bent and raised. Another figure, Colinet, sits or reclines to the right under another a tree with his body twisted and head bowed.  He leans on his right elbow; his left hand may be raised to his face. A dog lies, facing forward, to the right of his left foot. Three sheep, perhaps part of a larger flock, lie between the two figures. A sun shines in the sky over a scene of grassy hills or trees.         
      </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="A" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Thenot sits or kneels on the left side of the image, his arms bent upward.  His right palm faces up, his left palm out toward the viewer. His legs and head face to the right and his torso is twisted to face forward towards the viewer. He is old, with long hair and a beard, and wears a gown.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Another figure, Colinet, sits or reclines to the right under a tree. His head is bowed and may rest on his raised left hand. His right leg is extended to the left while his left leg is bent back; his upper body is twisted and faces away from the viewer. Both arms are bent, and his right elbow leans against a rock or mound of earth. He may wear semi-transparent tights (note the line at his neck and the line at his left calf, the latter indicating the end of the garment).</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two sheep lie on the ground between the human figures, with a third one standing.  The one on the left turns its head to the left; the one in the center faces forward; the one on the right faces right and grazes.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A dog lies on the ground to the right of Colinet's left foot. Its eyes are closed, and it may be sleeping.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two trees flank the scene. The branches of the tree on the left arch to the right over Thenot; the branches are leafy and bear at least seven round fruits. The tree to the right of Colinet extends its branches over him, with its branches arching to the left.  There may be grass in the foreground; the background hills and valleys may also contain vegetation, perhaps including trees.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="object">
                  <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Colinet, on the right, sits on what may be a low bank or mound (or possibly a large root of the tree to the right).  The background is a landscape of hills and possibly distant mountains, with the sun in the sky over the hilltops. Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the third image from the top, Colinet stands on the left, leaning against the trunk of a tree. He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and musical pipes in his right hand.  He looks down, perhaps at the two sheep in front of him. To the right, Thenot, with long hair and a beard, also leans against the trunk of a tree. He raises his right hand to gesture towards the left. In the center foreground of the design, two sheep stand with their heads turned to the left.  Directly above, a nude(?) figure runs on a hill, with a dog behind him and possibly chasing him.  The running man holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. At least three sheep stand or run below and to the right of the running figure.
      </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Colinet stands on the left of the image and leans against a tree trunk to the left. He has long hair and wears semi-transparent breeches or tights. His arms are at his sides; he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and musical pipes in his right. His left leg is bent back with his left foot raised on tiptoe or resting against the tree trunk. He looks down, possibly at the two sheep in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Thenot stands on the right side of the image, leaning against the trunk of a tree.  His body is slightly twisted as he faces both forward and to the left. He has long hair and a beard and wears a semi-transparent gown. He raises his right hand horizontally as though gesturing, palm out and up, to the left. His left arm is slightly bent and down at his side.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Both Colinet, on the left, and Thenot, on the right, stand beneath and lean against leafy trees, their branches extending along the top of the design toward its center.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the center foreground of the image, two sheep stand facing Colinet with their mouths open. At least three additional sheep appear above and to the right. These sheep may run or leap to the right with their heads turned back to the left; they may look toward the running figure above and to the left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Directly above the pair of sheep, a nude(?) male figure with short hair on a hill runs or leaps to the right. Both arms are raised horizontally, with the palm of his right hand facing down, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His left leg is bent at the knee and his left foot is raised on tiptoe; his right leg is extended backward, nearly horizontally. He looks down and to the left, perhaps at the dog behind him.  He may be fleeing from the dog.
         </illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="C" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>barking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A dog on a hill leaps or to the right; it may be running after and pursuing the figure to the right. The dog's legs are extended, with its hind legs on the ground and its fore legs in the air. Its visible ear and tail are blown back horizontally to indicate its speed. The dog's mouth appears to be open and it may be barking.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The background landscape includes at least two hills, one below the running man and dog and one far right.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The foreground may be grassy. There are indications of vegetation in the middle distance, particularly left of the running sheep.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the bottom image, Thenot stands to the left of Colinet. His arms are lowered, palms facing down. Colinet's arms are raised and he appears to be walking forward toward the viewer, prominent left foot forward and the right foot perhaps on tiptoe. On the right of the image is a large tree with riven trunk and arching limbs bare of leaves. A horned ram and three sheep lie to the right of Colinet. The ground may be covered in grass; two hills or distant mountans appear in the background. The scene appears to be backed by a cloudy sky, perhaps with rain falling.
      </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A gowned male, Thenot, stands on the left side of the image. He is seen from behind and his arms are down with both palms facing down. His head faces right in profile; the figure has long hair and a beard.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A male, Colinet, stands to the right of Thenot.  Colinet wears a transparent shirt and tights or breeches; his hair is long.  He faces forward and may walk toward the viewer; his right leg is bent and his right foot raised on tiptoe.  Colinet's right arm is bent upward with the palm turned out and up. His left arm is bent and raised nearly horizontally.  He points to the right with his left index finger.  Colinet's mouth may be open; he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A large, riven, and probably dead tree rises on the right.  Leafless branches arch to each side of the trunk.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A group of four sheep lie to the right of Colinet, facing forward with their heads turned slightly left. The sheep on the far right may be a horned ram.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two hills or distant mountains rise in the background. Lines in the sky indicate clouds and perhaps rain falling diagonally from right to left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>There may be grass in the foreground.  There may be trees in the middle distance, rising just below the hills.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
      </desc>
      <desc dbi="bb504.NGA-imp.6-9.COM" id="relbb504.1.rm.03">
         <objtitle>
            <title type="transcribed">Illustrations of Imitation of Eclogue I: proof impression</title>,
            
            
            <objid>
               <objnumber code="A6">Object 6</objnumber>
               <objcode code="B6-9">(Bentley 504.6-9)</objcode></objid>
         </objtitle>
         <physdesc>
            <objnote>
               <p>This proof of Object 6 was printed before the individual designs were separated and reduced in size, particularly on their left and right margins.</p>
            </objnote>
            <objsize>14.6 x 8.5 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="750" width="500"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the top image, Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm raised, palm vertical and facing out. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. Thenot, the older shepherd on the left, faces Colinet with his arms raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture. A dog lays his head on Thenot's right foot. At least three sheep graze to the left and right of Colinet. The sun sets or rises over the hills in the background and a tree trunk frames the right side of the scene.</illusobjdesc>
               <component location="B" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the top image, Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm bent upward with his left hand raised above his head and the palm turned out toward the viewer. His right arm is bent and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. His hair is long. He faces forward and to the left, perhaps looking toward Thenot. He wears a knee-length gown, possibly with a high-waisted belt.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>An older shepherd, Thenot, stands to the left with his back to the viewer.  His head is turned to the right and he may be looking toward Colinet.  His arms are raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture; his hands are held out with the palms held vertically.  He has long hair and a beard, and wears a full-length gown.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A dog stands to the right of Thenot with its head down at Thenot's right foot. The dog may be greeting Thenot, perhaps by sniffing his foot.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>At least three sheep graze with their heads down to the left and right of Colinet.  The body of a fourth sheep may be visible just to the right of Colinet.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The trunk of a tree rises along the right border of the design. The leafy branches of the tree extend to the left and dangle above the sun on the horizon.  There may be grass in the foreground and some sort of vegetation on the hills, particularly left of Thenot's left knee.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures is a landscape of hills or distant mountains, with the sun rising or setting in the center of the design.  Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the second image from the top, Thenot sits on the left under the branches of a fruit tree, possibly with his eyes closed, and with his arms bent and raised. Another figure, Colinet, sits or reclines to the right under another tree with his body twisted and head bowed.  He leans on his right elbow; his left hand may be raised to his face. Two sheep, perhaps part of a larger flock, lie between the two figures. A sun shines in the sky over a scene of grassy hills, leafy trees, and a small building, perhaps a house or cottage.         
      </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="A" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Thenot sits on the left side of the image, his eyes possibly closed and his arms bent upward with the palms raised and turned up. His legs and head face to the right and his torso is twisted to face forward towards the viewer. He is old, with long hair and a beard, and wears a gown.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Another figure, Colinet, sits or reclines to the right under a tree. His head is bowed and may rest on his raised left hand. His right leg is extended to the left while his left leg is bent back; his upper body is twisted and faces away from the viewer. Both arms are bent, and his right elbow leans against a rock or mound of earth.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two sheep lie on the ground between the human figures.  The one on the left may turn its head to the left; the one on the right, apparently a horned ram, faces forward.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two trees flank the scene. The branches of the tree on the left arch to the right over Thenot; the branches are leafy and bear at least eleven round fruits. The tree to the right of Colinet extends its branches over him, with its leafy branches arching to the left.  There may be grass in the foreground; the background hills and valleys also contain vegetation, perhaps including trees.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="object">
                  <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Thenot, on the left, appears to be sitting on bank or mound of earth.  Colinet, on the right, leans against a similar bank or mound.  The background is a landscape of grassy(?) hillsides, perhaps with distant mountains and with the sun in the sky over the hilltops.  Beams of light radiate from the sun. The roof of what appears to be a small building, probably a house or cottage, are visible below and to the right of the sun.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the third image from the top, Colinet stands on the left, leaning against the trunk of a tree. He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and looks down, perhaps at the two sheep in front of him.  He may hold musical pipes in his right hand, as in the relief etching of this design (see Related Works in the Archive). To the right, Thenot, with long hair and a beard, also leans against the trunk of a tree. He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and raises his right hand to gesture towards the left. In the center foreground of the design, two sheep stand with their heads turned to the left.  Directly above, a nude(?) figure runs on a hill, with a dog behind him and possibly chasing him.  The running man holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. At least five sheep stand or run below and to the right of the running figure.
      </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Colinet stands on the left of the image and leans against a tree trunk to the left. He has long hair and wears a knee-length gown, perhaps with a belt around the waist. His arms are at his sides; he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand.  He may hold musical pipes in his right hand, as in the relief etching of this designs (see Related Works in the Archive). His left leg is bent back with his left foot raised on tiptoe or resting against the tree trunk. He looks down, possibly at the two sheep in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Thenot stands on the right side of the image, leaning against the trunk of a tree.  His body is slightly twisted as he faces both forward and to the left with his left foot slightly extended and visible below the hem of his garment. He has long hair and a beard and wears a gown. He raises his right hand horizontally as though gesturing, palm out and up, to the left. His left arm is slightly bent and down at his side; he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His mouth may be open and he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Both Colinet, on the left, and Thenot, on the right, stand beneath and lean against trees. The leafless branches of the tree on the left extend along the top edge of the design to its center. A few leaves are visible on the branches of the tree on the right where it arches over Thenot and possibly near the upper right margin.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the center foreground of the image, two sheep stand facing Colinet with their mouths open. At least three additional sheep appear above and to the right. These sheep may run or leap to the right with their heads turned back to the left; they may look toward the running figure above and to the left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Directly above the pair of sheep, a nude(?) male figure with short hair on a hill runs or leaps to the right. Both arms are raised horizontally, with the palm of his right hand facing down, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His left leg is bent at the knee and his left foot is raised on tiptoe; his right leg is extended backward, nearly horizontally. He looks down and to the left, perhaps at the dog behind him.  He may be fleeing from the dog.
         </illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="C" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A dog on a hill leaps to the right; it may be running after and pursuing the figure to the right. The dog's legs are extended, with its hind legs on the ground and its fore legs in the air. Its visible ear and tail are blown back horizontally to indicate its speed.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The background landscape includes at least two hills, one below the running man and dog and one far right.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The foreground may be grassy. There are indications of vegetation in the middle distance, particularly left of the running sheep.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. In the bottom image, Thenot stands to the left of Colinet.  Thenot may be walking towards Colinet, right foot on tiptoe and with arms lowered and palms facing down. Colinet's arms are raised and he appears to be walking forward toward the viewer, prominent left foot forward and the right foot perhaps on tiptoe. On the right of the image is a large tree with riven trunk and two arching limbs bare of leaves. A horned ram and three sheep stand to the right of Colinet.  One sheep, facing right, kneels to nurse. The ground may be covered in grass; two hills or distant mountains appear in the background.
      </illusobjdesc>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A gowned male, Thenot, stands on the left side of the image. He is seen from behind and may be walking towards Colinet. Thenot's right leg is bent and his right foot raised on tiptoe. His arms are down but raised toward 45 degrees with both palms facing down. His head faces right in profile; the figure has long hair and a beard.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A male, Colinet, stands to the right of Thenot.  Colinet wears a gown that reaches to his knees; his hair is long.  He faces forward and may walk toward the viewer; his right leg is bent and his right foot raised on tiptoe.  Colinet's right arm is bent upward with the palm turned out and up, fingers slightly spread. His left arm is bent and raised nearly horizontally, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand.  Colinet's mouth may be open; he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A large, riven, and probably dead tree rises on the right.  Two leafless branches arch to the right and left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A group of four sheep stand to the right of Colinet.  Furthest left, a horned ram grazes with its head down.  To the right, a sheep stands facing left with its head turned to the right.  Its mouth is open.  Further to the right, a ewe stands facing right with its head turned down; it may look at the lamb below.  The lamb faces left with its front legs kneeling on the ground; its head is bent up as it suckles on the ewe.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two hills or distant mountains rise in the background.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>There may be grass in the foreground.  There may be trees in the middle distance, rising just below the hills.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
      </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.10-13.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.07">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B10-13">(Bentley 504.10-13)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The individual wood engravings, from top to bottom, measure 3.4 x 7.3 cm., 3.4 x 7.4 cm., 3.2 x 7.3 cm., and 3.6 x 7.4 cm.  The letterpress text top left (&quot;To face page 15.&quot;) has been trimmed off in this copy.  Blake's preliminary drawings, from top to bottom, are in the following collections: Keynes Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge; Beinecke Library, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut; Houghton Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts; Houghton Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts (Butlin 769.6-9).</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>16.2 x 7.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="830" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="relbb504.1.rm.04" ovp="noindex">Proof impression of Object 7 before the individual designs were separated and reduced in size.
         </related>
      <related objectid="but769.1.wd.04" ovp="noindex">Preliminary drawing for the top design.
         </related>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Colinet.&quot; The top image is dominated by a large, gnarled tree with branches reaching to the right towards the crescent moon in the night sky. Shafts of grain, blown down by a stormy wind, dominate the middle distance, with vegetation (possibly trees) in the background.  A small hill or distant mountain rises in the right background.  Diagonal lines in the dark sky indicate rain or hail.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The top image is dominated by a large, gnarled tree with branches arching to the right towards the crescent moon. There may be a few leaves on the ends of its branches, but on the whole it appears leafless.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A crescent moon inscribed within a dark circle appears in the night sky to the right of the tree.  Diagonal lines in the sky of this storm-tossed scene indicate rain or hail and a wind blowing from left to right.  A hill or distant mountain rises on the horizon far right.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trees</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Shafts of grain with prominent tassels dominate the middle distance.  They are bent to the ground by a wind blowing from left to right. Behind the grain is some vegetation, possibly trees.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Colinet.&quot; The second image from the top depicts a shepherd who resembles Colinet in previous images, although the text does not support an identification with him. This shepherd is seen from behind and strides or runs to the left with his arms raised. He is pursuing, or at least attempting to scare away, a fox or wolf (the text names both animals) which flees to the left. The body of a sheep (dead?) lies at the figure's feet.  A fox(?) stands to the left of the sheep. To the right of Colinet is a fold with sheep and a small building shaded by a tree. Another tree rises between the shepherd and the left margin, arching over the fox. The background is hilly with indeterminate leafy vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>running</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The second image from the top shows a gowned shepherd who resembles Colinet in previous images, although the text does not support an identification with him. This shepherd is seen from behind and strides or runs to the left with his left foot raised on tiptoe.  He is pursuing, or at least attempting to scare away, the fox or wolf (the text names both animals) which flees to the left.  The figure's left arm is raised vertically with the palm turned away from the viewer and fingers spread; his right arm is bent upward and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand.  His gown descends, like Colinet's, to his knees.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying on side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A sheep lies on its side to the left of the shepherd.  Its head is down towards the viewer.  It is probably dead.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>fox</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A fox(?) appears in the lower left corner of the image.  It stands or strides with its body facing left and head turned back to the right; it may look towards the dead sheep.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>fox</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wolf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>running</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A fox or wolf (the text names both animals) appears in the middle distance above and to the left of the dead sheep.  It runs to the left with its legs extended and its front legs raised off the ground.  Its head is turned back to the right, and it may look towards the shepherd.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A tree rises left of the shepherd.  It leans to the left, and a few leafy branches hang above the fox.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="structure">
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fence</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the shepherd is a fenced pen or fold.  Its posts and rails are probably made of wood.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A flock of sheep are held within the fold.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>straw</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small structure is pictured at the right border of the image.  Only a thatched roof and two tree-like pillars that terminate in V-shaped extensions are clearly pictured, but this may be a hut or cottage of some sort.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A tree grows just to the left of the small building on the right.  Its leaves dominate the top right portion of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines at the top of the design indicate sky.  The unlined portion in the top left of the image hint at a sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Hills or more distant mountains rise in the distance.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The suggestions of vegetation in the middle distance right and left of the shepherd may include trees.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Colinet.&quot; The third image from the top includes a small house or cottage with a thatched roof set before trees. To the left of the building is a stream or river that flow from, or into, a lake in the middle distance. The hills in the distance may be covered with leafy vegetation, possibly trees. On the grassy left bank of the stream are a tree and a flock of sheep, with at least five sheep discernable.  The front-most sheep, a lamb, may be suckling.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="D" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>straw</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The third image from the top includes a small building, probably a house or cottage, with a thatched roof set before trees. We see the structure from the front, with a roof, two windows, and a door clearly visible. The prominent door-frame, and possibly the walls, are probably made of wood.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A tree with leafy branches stands beside and overhangs the house.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>stream</characteristic>
            <characteristic>river</characteristic>
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>winding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the building is a winding, serpentine stream or river that may be flowing out of, or into, a lake in the middle distance.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A hill or distant mountain rises above the river.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A tree stands to the left of the river.  Its trunk divides into several branches with clearly visible leaves.  The land left and right of the river may be grassy.  There may also be vegetation on the hill or distant mountain on the horizon.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component>
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A flock of sheep stand grazing on the left bank of the river, with at least five sheep discernable. The sheep face right with their heads down. A sheep stands facing left below the front-most sheep; it appears to be suckling.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Colinet.&quot; In the bottom image, Colinet walks leftward on a road. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand and wears a hat and gown. The road is marked by a milestone and a cross. The landscape is hilly, grassy, and has patches of indeterminate vegetation, perhaps bushes. The buildings of a town or city, including a spire, rise just below the most distant hill or mountain.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Blake, William</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the fourth image, Colinet walks leftward on a road. He is gowned and wears a brimmed hat over his long hair.  His left arm is down at his side; though not pictured, his right arm is likely bent, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his visible right hand.  His left foot is raised on tiptoe. The figure has sometimes been identified with William Blake as an imaginative self-portrait.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="structure">
            <characteristic>post</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>road</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A road extends across the image and curves leftward at the right border.  It is marked by a milestone and a cross, both to the right of Colinet.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Although the inscription on the milestone is unclear in this darkly printed impression, other impressions reveal the following text: &quot;LXII / Miles / London.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>city</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>church</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Chichester</characteristic>
            <characteristic/>
            <illusobjdesc>The buildings of a city, town, or village appear in the distance, above the milestone and just below the most distant hill or mountain. The buildings include a spire, possibly of a church. The identification of the traveler with Blake and the distance to London inscribed on the milestone suggest that this city may be Chichester.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The ground around the milestone is covered by vegetation, perhaps grass. Leafy vegetation appears above the road to the left and right of Colinet.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two large hills rise above the scene in the distance.  The most distant may be a mountain.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.07.01">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.07.02">THENOT.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.07.03">THENOT.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.07.04">COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.07.05">COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="bb504.NGA-imp.10-13.COM" id="relbb504.1.rm.04">
         <objtitle>
            <title type="transcribed">Illustrations of Imitation of Eclogue I: proof impression</title>,
            
            
            <objid>
               <objnumber code="A7">Object 7</objnumber>
               <objcode code="B10-13">(Bentley 504.10-13)</objcode></objid>
         </objtitle>
         <physdesc>
            <objnote>
               <p>This proof of Object 7 was printed before the individual designs were separated and reduced in size, particularly on their left and right margins.</p>
            </objnote>
            <objsize>14.8 x 8.6 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="750" width="500"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. The top image is dominated by a large, gnarled tree with branches reaching to the right towards the crescent moon in the night sky. Shafts of grain, blown down by a stormy wind, dominate the middle distance, with vegetation (possibly trees) in the background.  A small hill or distant mountain rises in the right background.  Diagonal lines in the dark sky indicate rain or hail.</illusobjdesc>
               <component location="A" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The top image is dominated by a large, gnarled tree with branches reaching to the right towards the crescent moon. There may be a few leaves on the ends of its branches, but on the whole it appears leafless.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="object">
                  <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hail</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A crescent moon inscribed within a dark circle appears in the night sky to the right of the tree.  Diagonal lines in the sky of this storm-tossed scene indicate rain or hail and a wind blowing from left to right.  A hill or distant mountain rises on the horizon far right.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trees</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Shafts of grain with prominent tassels dominate the middle distance.  They are bent to the ground by a wind blowing from left to right. Behind the grain is some vegetation, possibly trees.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. The second image from the top depicts a shepherd who resembles Colinet in previous images, although the text does not support an identification with him. This shepherd is seen from behind and strides or runs to the left with his arms raised. He is pursuing, or at least attempting to scare away, a fox or wolf (the text names both animals) which flees to the left. The body of a sheep (dead?) lies at the figure's feet.  A fox(?) stands to the left of the sheep. To the right of Colinet is a fold with sheep and a small building built between two trees. Another tree rises between the shepherd and the left margin, arching over the fox. The background is hilly with indeterminate leafy vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
               <component location="AB" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The second image from the top shows a gowned shepherd who resembles Colinet in previous images, although the text does not support an identification with him. This shepherd is seen from behind and strides or runs to the left with his left foot raised on tiptoe.  He is pursuing, or at least attempting to scare away, the fox or wolf (the text names both animals) which flees to the left.  The figure's left arm is raised vertically with the palm turned away from the viewer and fingers spread; his right arm is bent upward and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand.  His gown descends, like Colinet's, to his knees.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying on side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A sheep lies on its side to the left of the shepherd.  Its head is down towards the viewer.  It is probably dead.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>fox</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A fox(?) appears in the lower left corner of the image.  It stands or strides with its body facing left and head turned back to the right; it may look towards the dead sheep.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>fox</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wolf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A fox or wolf (the text names both animals) appears in the middle distance above and to the left of the dead sheep.  It runs to the left with its legs extended and its front legs raised off the ground.  Its head is turned back to the right, and it may look towards the shepherd.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="A" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A tree rises left of the shepherd.  It leans to the left, and a few leafy branches hang above the fox.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="structure">
                  <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fence</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>To the right of the shepherd is a fenced pen or fold.  Its posts and rails are probably made of wood.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="animal">
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A flock of sheep are held within the fold.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="structure">
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>straw</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A small structure consisting of only vertical (wooden?) poles and a thatched roof, but possibly a cottage or house, is pictured between the two trees on the right. The poles may consist only of sapplings that divide into branches near their tops.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="B" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two trees grow just to the left and right of the small building on the right.  Their leaves dominate the top right portion of the design.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="object">
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines at the top of the design indicate sky.  The unlined portion in the top left of the image hint at a sunrise or sunset.  Hills or distant mountains rise on the horizon.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The suggestions of vegetation in the middle distance right and left of the shepherd may include trees.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images. The third image from the top includes a small house or cottage with a thatched roof set before trees. To the left of the building is a stream or river that flow from, or into, a lake in the middle distance. The hills in the distance may be covered with leafy vegetation, possibly trees. On the grassy left bank of the stream are a tree and a flock of sheep, with at least five sheep discernable.  The front-most sheep, a lamb, may be suckling.</illusobjdesc>
               <component location="D" type="structure">
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>straw</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The third image from the top includes a small building, probably a house or cottage, with a thatched roof set before trees. We see the structure from the front, with a roof, two windows, and a door clearly visible. The prominent door-frame, and possibly the walls, are probably made of wood.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Trees with leafy branches overhang both sides of the house.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>stream</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>winding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>To the left of the building is a winding, serpentine stream or river that may be flowing out of, or into, a lake in the middle distance.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A hill or distant mountain rises above the river.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A tree stands to the left of the river.  Its trunk divides into several branches with clearly visible leaves.  The land left and right of the river may be grassy.  There may also be vegetation on the hill or distant mountain on the horizon.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component>
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A flock of sheep stand grazing on the left bank of the river, with at least five sheep discernable. The sheep face right with their heads down. A sheep stands facing left below the front-most sheep; it appears to be suckling.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
            <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
               <illusobjdesc>In the bottom image on this page, Colinet walks leftward on a road. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand and wears a hat and gown. The road is marked by a milestone and a cross. The landscape is hilly, grassy, and has patches of indeterminate vegetation, perhaps bushes. The buildings of a town or city, including a spire, rise just below the most distant hill or mountain.</illusobjdesc>
               <component location="C" type="figure">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Blake, William</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the bottom image, Colinet walks leftward on a road. He is gowned and wears a brimmed hat over his long hair.  His left arm is down at his side; though not pictured, his right arm is likely bent, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his visible right hand. He may be holding some object in his lowered left hand.  His right(?) foot is raised on tiptoe. The figure has sometimes been identified with William Blake as an imaginative self-portrait.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="structure">
                  <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>road</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A road extends across the image and curves leftward at the right border.  It is marked by a milestone and a cross, both to the right of Colinet.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>the milestone is inscribed with the following text: &quot;LXII / Miles / London.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="D" type="object">
                  <characteristic>city</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>church</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Chichester</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The buildings of a city, town, or village appear in the distance, above the milestone and just below the most distant hill or mountain. The buildings include a spire, possibly of a church. The identification of the traveler with Blake and the distance to London inscribed on the milestone suggest that this city may be Chichester.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The ground around the milestone is covered by vegetation, perhaps grass. Leafy vegetation appears above the road to the left and right of Colinet.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component location="CD" type="object">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Two large hills rise above the scene in the distance.  The most distant may be a mountain.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
      </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.14-17.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.08">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B14-17">(Bentley 504.14-17)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <related objectid="but769.1.wd.05" ovp="noindex">Preliminary drawing for the top design.
         </related>
      <related objectid="but769.1.wd.06" ovp="noindex">Preliminary drawing for the bottom design.
         </related>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The individual wood engravings, from top to bottom, measure 3.2 x 7.7 cm., 3.2 x 7.6 cm., 3.5 x 7.7 cm., and 3.5 x 7.7 cm.  Blake's preliminary drawings, from top to bottom, are in the following collections: Morgan Library and Museum, New York; untraced since 1927; untraced since 1924; Robert N. Essick, Altadena, California (Butlin 769.10-13).</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>16.2 x 7.8 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="830" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Thenot.&quot; In the top image, a man with short, curly hair faces and strides left. With both arms extended back, he holds a (wood?) handle attached to a large (stone?) lawn roller. In the right foreground of the image is a large tree trunk. To the left of the tree is a neoclassical building, very probably a house, with a grassy lawn below and trees to its left. The house is two stories and has a door and five small and four large windows visible. Its front door is centered over a stoop; the façade is decorated with classical pilasters.  A path extends below the figure and towards the door of the house.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the top image, a male figure with short, curly hair strides left with both legs bent; his left leg is extended backward (to the right) with his left foot raised on tiptoe. The figure is seen in part from behind and wears breeches and shoes; he may be shirtless.  With both arms extended back, he holds the handle of a lawn roller.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>road</characteristic>
            <characteristic>path</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roller</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure walks on a road or private drive that extends horizontally across the image; a small path leads from the road to the front door of a large house.  The man pulls a lawn roller, probably made of wood (the handle) and stone (the roll).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>façade</characteristic>
            <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pilaster</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the figure is a large, two-story neoclassical building, very probably a house, with nine paned windows. Its front door is centered over a stoop; its façade is decorated with classical pilasters. The house may be made of brick or stone.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A tree trunk rises along the right border of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leafy</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The ground below the house is covered with grass.  Leafy vegetationperhaps a tree or large bushappears just left of the house.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines in the top left of the image indicates sky.  A small band of diagonal lines may suggest a single cloud.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Thenot.&quot; In the second image from the top, Colinet sits and partly reclines on the ground just left of a large tree.  His upper body is twisted to the right, arms bent slightly upward and hands raised up to the right.  He wears a hat and gown. To his left are three sheep; a shepherd's crook rests on the ground below.  A dog lies to the right of Colinet and below the tree trunk. The scene takes place at night, as a crescent moon illuminates the river and hills. The landscape is marked by indeterminate, leafy vegetation, especially on the river's left bank.  A building with spires appears upper left.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the second image from the top, Colinet sits and partly reclines just to the left of a large tree. He is gowned and wears a hat over his long hair.  The illuminated brim of the hat creates a halo-like effect. The figure's legs are extended to the left; his right leg may be bent and is partially obscured by his left leg.  His torso is twisted to face forward or slightly to the right; his arms are bent upward with his palms held vertically and facing away from his body to the right. Colinet's head faces left and his mouth may be open.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="object">
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A shepherd's crook lies horizontally on the ground below the seated figure.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three sheep stand to the left of the seated figure.  The sheep furthest left faces left and grazes with its head down.  The central sheep faces left with its head turned back to the right and its mouth open.  The sheep furthest right stands(?) facing left and is partially obscured by the shepherd.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A dog lies on the ground below and to the right of the seated figure.  It faces left with its head up; it may look at the shepherd.  The dog may wear a collar.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large tree with leafy branches stands at the right border of the image.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="object">
            <characteristic>river</characteristic>
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>winding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A serpentine river winds upward from the lower left corner of the image.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The ground below the shepherd is covered with grass.  Leafy, indeterminate vegetation grows on hills left and right of the river.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The landscape is hilly, perhaps with a distant mountain on the left. A crescent moon hangs in a dark sky, indicating that the scene takes place at night.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>church</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A building with spires, possibly a church, appears in the upper left section of the image.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Thenot.&quot; In the third image from the top, Colinet stands in a grove of trees and holds a musical horn in his left hand. His right arm is close to his side and he looks left towards two figures. He may be smiling. Two male figures stand or dance to the left of the trees. The leftmost figure faces away, with his arms bent and his palms turned out away from his body. The figure to the right looks towards him, with his arms raised horizontally and extended right. A small building, possibly a cottage or house, is visible in the distance between the second figure and the leftmost tree trunk.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the third image from the top, Colinet stands in a grove of trees.  He faces forward with his head turned left; he may look toward two figures to the left.  His mouth may be open, or he may be smiling.  His right arm is down near his side with the palm turned down; his left arm is bent and he holds a musical horn in his right hand.  He is gowned; his hair may be long.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Colinet, the figure holding a musical horn, stands in a grove of trees. At least three tree trunks with leafy tops are visible, though the areas above, left, and right of the figure suggest additional trees. The ground below and to the left of the trees may be covered with grass.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two gowned males stand or dance in the left portion of the design.  Both have short, curly hair.  The leftmost figure is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer; he walks or strides to the left with his left foot raised on tiptoe.  His arms are bent upward at his sides with the palms turned out (facing away).  His head is bent back and turned towards his companion to the right, possibly looking at his companion.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>singing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two gowned males stand or dance in the left portion of the design.  Both have short, curly hair.  The figure to the right strides or walks forward with his left leg crossed in front of his right and his right foot raised on tiptoe.  His arms are raised horizontally and are slightly bent; both arms are extended to the right.  His left palm appears to be turned upward, and he may point towards the figure to the right with his left hand.  The figure's head is turned towards his companion to the left. His mouth may be open; he may be speaking or singing.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="structure">
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small building, possibly a house or cottage, appears in the distance just left of the leftmost tree trunk.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The landscape is hilly, possibly with a distant mountain rising above the small building.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; &quot;Colinet.&quot;; and &quot;Thenot.&quot; In the bottom image, a group of seven figures appears on the lawn of a large house with multiple pillars and windows visible. Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image. The leftmost figure holds a tambourine above her head. The second figure from the left faces away from the viewer. The third figure from the left faces forward with her arms bent upward. Two musicians sit in chairs in the right half of the design. The figure furthest to the right plays a violin and may be singing.  To the left, a female musician plays a lyre.  A gowned femalepossibly a childstands to the left of the female musician.  She bends slightly over and may hold onto a male child to the left.  He stands facing forward with one foot raised and both arms bent upward.  Indeterminate, leafy vegetation is visible to the right of the male musician and between the two leftmost female dancers.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tambourine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image.  The two on the left have their hair pulled back in buns. The leftmost figure faces forward with her lower body twisted to the left and at least her right foot raised on tiptoe. Her head is turned to the right in profile. Her arms are bent upward and she holds a tambourine above her head.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image.  The two on the left have their hair in buns. The second figure from the left faces away from the viewer, but with her head twisted to left profile. Her left foot is on the ground and may be raised on tiptoe; her right leg is bent and extended backwards. Her arms are near her side; she may be holding her gown in both hands.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image. The third figure from the left faces forward with her left leg crossed in front of her right and her right foot raised on tiptoe. Her hair is either short or pulled back in a bun. Her arms are raised and bent upward with the palms held vertically.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
            <characteristic>buckle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
            <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>violin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bow</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>singing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two musicians sit in chairs in the right half of the design.  The figure furthest right is a male wearing a hat, coat, breeches, and buckled shoes.  He sits facing left with his legs crossed at the ankles.  He holds a violin with his left hand and plays it with a bow held in his right hand; both forearms rest on the arms of the chair. His mouth is open and he may be singing.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left hand</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two musicians sit in chairs in the right half of the design. To the left of the violinist is a female wearing a gown and a wide-brimmed hat topped with feathers. Her left arm is bent and she plays a lyre with her left hand.  She faces left and may look towards the dancers.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The musician on the right, playing a violin, sits in a chair.  His companion to the left probably also sits on a chair, although none is pictured.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned femalepossibly a childstands to the left of the female musician.  She bends slightly to the left (forward with respect to her body) and may hold onto a male child to the left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A male child, apparently with short hair, stands to the left of a gowned female.  He faces forward and slightly to the left with his arms bent and raised at 135 degrees.  His right leg is bent and may be slightly raised off the ground; he may be dancing.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pilaster</characteristic>
            <characteristic>façade</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A building, probably a large neoclassical house, appears in the background of the image, covering the space between the right border and the second figure from the left. There are at least five windows visible and the façade of the structure is decorated with pilasters. Four large pillars support the classical entry porch before the front door. The tiangular pediment may contain a sculpted image. The house may be made of brick or stone.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Indeterminate, leafy vegetation is visible to the right of the male musician and between the leftmost female dancers.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="38" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.08.01">To face page 16.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.08.02">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.08.03">THENOT.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.08.04">COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.08.05">COLINET.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.08.06">THENOT.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.18-20.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.09">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B18-20">(Bentley 504.18-20)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <related objectid="but769.1.wd.07" ovp="noindex">Preliminary drawing for the middle design.
         </related>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The individual wood engravings, from top to bottom, measure 3.2 x 7.4 cm., 3.2 x 7.4 cm., and 3.0 x 7.4 cm.  These three wood blocks, based on Blake's designs, were engraved by one or more anonymous journeymen.  Blake's preliminary drawings, from top to bottom, are in the following collections: untraced since 1939; Morgan Library and Museum, New York; untraced since 1927 (Butlin 769.14-16).</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>14.7 x 7.5 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="780" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains three distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;First Comparison.&quot;; &quot;Second Comparison.&quot;; and &quot;Third Comparison.&quot; In the top image, fourteen birds fly above a field of grain.  A hill rises above the field.  Several buildings, including a spire, appear to the right, possibly a town or village.  Indeterminate, leafy vegetation appears in the lower left and right corners of the design.  A rock or mound of earth appears just left of the rightmost clump of vegetation.  Horizontal lines in the sky suggests two clouds.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beak</characteristic>
            <characteristic/>
            <illusobjdesc>Fourteen birds fly on outstretched wings at the top of the image.  At least one bird (fourth from the left) appears to descend towards the field below.  Other birds, including two of the three on the right, are rising.  Two birds, among those flying the highest, appear to touch beaks as though kissing.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bundle</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A field of grain appears near the bottom of the image in the middle distance. Three sheaves of grain stand in front of the field.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
            <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Indeterminate, leafy vegetation appears in the lower left and right corners of the design.  A large stone or mound of earth appears just left of the rightmost clump of vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A hill or distant mountain rises above the field in the center of the design. The buildings to the right are on a lower hill. The grain grows in a field or plain.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>church</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>city</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Distant buildings, possibly a town or village, appear right of the background hill.  The building third from the right may be a church with a tall spire.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines above and to the left of the hill suggest two low clouds in the sky.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains three distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;First Comparison.&quot;; &quot;Second Comparison.&quot;; and &quot;Third Comparison.&quot; In the second image from the top, seven sailing vessels face rightward on a calm ocean's surface.  The first, second, and fifth ships from the left are small sailboats, while the rest are larger wooden ships with multiple sails.  A series of waves and the shore are visible in the lower portion of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>ship</characteristic>
            <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sailing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flag</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Seven sailing vessels face rightward on a calm ocean's surface.  The first, second, and fifth ships from the left are small sailboats, while the rest are larger wooden ships with multiple sails.  The third ship from the left has two masts and at least three sails.  The fourth ship from the left also has two masts and five sails; the rightmost mast is topped with a flag and the leftmost mast may support a crow's nest.  The sixth ship from the left has three masts and ten sails; each mast is topped with a flag.  The ship furthest right also has three masts topped with flags and perhaps nine sails in total.  A row of portholes or gun ports is visible on the side of the fourth and sixth ships from the left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
            <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The ships sail on a calm ocean or sea.  A series of waves and the shore are visible in the lower portion of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains three distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;First Comparison.&quot;; &quot;Second Comparison.&quot;; and &quot;Third Comparison.&quot;  In the lowest image, a river winds through a landscape of hills and cliffs.  A group of three sailboats appears on the lower left portion of the river.  A fourth sailboat appears above and to the right of this group, directly above a barge.  Two figures sit or crouch on the right edge of the barge; the figure to the right may hold a pole.  A wall, turret, and a door on the right bank of the river may suggest a city wall.  In the lower left of the image, at least three pillars support a domed roof, possibly made of stone.  Three buildingspossibly all part of the same structurestand above and to the left of the domed structure.  The central tower is topped by four spires, and suggests a church.  To the right is some vegetation, possibly a tree.  A building or group of buildings appears to be in ruins above and to the right of the church.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>river</characteristic>
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>winding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large river in the center of the image winds through a hilly landscape and town or city.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Large cliffs and hills (or more distant mountains) rise above the river to the left and right.  The river banks are a prominent feature.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Small triangular shapes in the middle distance on both shores may represent trees.  A clump of vegetation, possibly a tree, rises above one of the roofs on the left, just right of the tower.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sailing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flag</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A group of three sailboats appears on the lower left portion of the river.  At least one has a flag atop its mast.  A fourth sailboat appears above and to the right of this grouping, directly above a barge.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand, sit, or crouch on the right edge of the barge.  They appear to face away from the viewer.  The figure to the right may wear a hat and holds a pole.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="structure">
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ruin</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A wall, turret, and a door on the right bank of the river may suggest a city wall.  Several small windows are visible along the wall.  The wall, perhaps broken in some areas, includes three towers and perhaps a building at its left end.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="structure">
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dome</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the lower left of the image, at least three pillars support a domed roof, possibly made of stone.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="structure">
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>church</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three buildingspossibly all part of the same structurestand above and to the right of the domed structure.  The central tower is topped by four spires that suggest a church.  The buildings below and right of the tower have several visible windows and clearly defined roofs; an arched doorway also appears on the rightmost building.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="structure">
            <characteristic>ruin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>building</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A building or group of buildings appears to be in ruins in the middle distance on the left bank of the river.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.09.01">To face page 17.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="8" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.09.02">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF</l>
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.09.03">ECLOGUE I.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="5"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.09.04">First Comparison.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.09.05">Second Comparison.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="19" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.09.06">Third Comparison.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.21-24.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.10">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B21-24">(Bentley 504.21-4)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The individual wood engravings, from top to bottom, measure 3.5 x 7.6 cm., 3.4 x 7.7 cm., 3.5 x 7.7 cm., and 3.2 x 7.8 cm.  Blake's preliminary drawings, from top to bottom, are in the following collections: untraced since 1927; untraced since 1924; Maurice Sendak, Connecticut; Art Museum, Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey (Butlin 769.17-20).</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>16.4 x 7.8 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="865" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot. To illustrate lines 1, 2.&quot;; &quot;3, 4, 5, 6.&quot;; &quot;7, 8, 9.&quot;; and &quot;10.&quot; In the top image, Colinet (left) and Thenot (right) stand to the left of a sheepfold.  Colinet is seen from behind and faces right.   He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand and may stride or walk towards Thenot.  Thenot faces forward but bends to the left, perhaps to touch or pet the sheep or dog that stands at his right knee; he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand.  Leafy, indeterminate vegetation, possibly small trees, backs the scene extending to the left and right borders.  The trunk and at least two branches of a tree anchors the right margin.  The sun rises or sets in the upper right portion of the design.  The thatched roof and latticed windows of a cottage are visible above the sheepfold.
               </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Colinet stands on the left in the group of two gowned shepherds.  He is seen from behind and faces right with his right leg bent back and his right foot raised on tiptoe.  He may be walking or striding towards the figure to the right.  Colinet has long hair.  His left arm is at his side and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand; his right arm is raised at 45 degrees with his palm vertical and facing out toward Thenot.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two gowned shepherds stand to the left of a sheepfold.  Thenot, on the right, faces forward but bends to the left, perhaps to touch the animal that stands at his right knee.  His left arm is raised at 45 degrees and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand.  He has long hair and a beard.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grazing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two sheep appear to the right of Colinet and possibly another behind him; only their heads are visible.  The lowest sheep's head is down, and it may be grazing.  To the right, a sheep (or possibly a dog) stands facing right with its head turned forward; its head leans or rests against Thenot's right knee.  A flock of sheep fill the pen on he right.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="structure">
            <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fence</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A fenced pen or sheepfold stands to the right of two shepherds.  The fence is probably made of wood.  A diagonal line in the middle of the fold indicates that it may be divided into separate pens; there is an opening in the fence along its leftmost edge.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The ground below the figures may be covered with grass.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The trunk of a tree stands at the right border of the design.  The top of the trunk divides into at least two branches.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Leafy, indeterminate vegetation, possibly trees, extends from the left to right border of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="structure">
            <characteristic>house</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>window</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The thatched roof and latticed windows of a wooden cottage are visible above the sheepfold.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines in the upper left of the image indicate sky.  A rising or (more probably) setting sun appears above background hill or mountain; diagonal lines emanating from the right half of the sun indicate beams of light.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot. To illustrate lines 1, 2.&quot;; &quot;3, 4, 5, 6.&quot;; &quot;7, 8, 9.&quot;; and &quot;10.&quot; In the second image from the top, Thenot (left) and Colinet (right) sit on chairs to the left and right of a table with a wicker basket laden with food (round fruit?) and two large cups.  Above the table is a large, arched fireplace.  The rectanglar object below the table might be a grate.  The scene takes place in a small hut or cottage with a sloping thatched roof.  Perhpas this building is open on its front side; alternatively, we see the dwelling in a cutaway view. A crecent moon is visible to the left of the hut; two stars appear above the moon and perhaps four additional stars are seen to the right of the hut.
               </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Thenot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
            <characteristic>giving</characteristic>
            <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the second image from the top, Thenot sits facing right with his back partly turned to the viewer.  He is old with long hair and a beard.  His right arm is extended to the right; he holds a large bowl in his right hand.  He may be extending it, and attempting to give it, to Colinet, even thought the latter already holds a large bowl.  His right foot extends beyond the hem of his gown.  Both men are presumably eating or about to eat.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Colinet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the second image from the top, Colinet sits on the right right sits facing forward.  His left leg is extended to the left, and crosses in front of his right leg.  He is gowned and has long hair; his left foot is prominent.  Colinet's arms are bent over his chest with his left elbow resting on the back of the chair and his right resting on the table; with both hands he holds a bowl in front of his chest.  Both men are presumably eating or about to eat.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fireplace</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
            <characteristic>apple</characteristic>
            <characteristic>goblet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cup</characteristic>
            <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wicker</characteristic>
            <characteristic>table</characteristic>
            <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Thenot and Colinet sit on chairs to the left and right of a table. A wicker basket and two large cups or goblets rest on the table. In the center of the image, above the table, are round objects.  These are probably fruit (apples?) of some sort in the woven basket--or just possibly coals in the background fireplace with an arched top.  The rectangular object below the table may be a grate in, or in front of, the fireplace.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
            <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a small hut or cottage with a sloping thatched roof.  This structure may be open on its front side, or we see it in a cutaway view. The roof is supported by two tree trunks, used as pillars, left and right of the seated figures.  The floor of the hut may be bare earth.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
            <characteristic>star</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The dark sky left and right of the hut indicates a night scene.  A crecent moon is visible to the left of the hut; two stars appear above the moon and perhaps four additional stars are seen to the right of the hut.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>This page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot. To illustrate lines 1, 2.&quot;; &quot;3, 4, 5, 6.&quot;; &quot;7, 8, 9.&quot;; and &quot;10.&quot; In the third image from the top, two male figures stand near the right border. Their mouths are open and they appear to be singing or talking. The figure to the left holds a musical horn in his hands while the figure to the right holds a set of musical pipes. To the left stand two horned oxen facing right. A third figure stands in front of the oxen with his right leg extended backward and his arms raised; he holds a yoke above his head. A large curved plow is visible in the lower left corner of the image. In the background, a sun sets above a hill.  There are indications of a hill, perhaps with vegetation, left and right of the two figures on the right.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
            <characteristic>boots</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>talking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>singing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tambourine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>purse</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the third image from the top, two male figures stand near the right border. They both face forward and may walk towards the viewer.  They are clothed alike and both wear hats, scarves, knee-length gowns, and shoes or boots. The figure to the left bends both arms and holds a musical horn in front of his chest with both hands.  The figure to the right holds a set of pipes in front of his chest in his right hand; his left arm may be down at his side.  The round object below and to the left of his lowered left hand may be a tambourine (to continue the musical theme), flask, or purse.  Both figures' mouths are open and they may to be singing or talking.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>ox</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two horned oxen stand in the center of the image, facing right.  The ox furthest right is partially obscured by its companion.  The tail of the front-most ox is clearly pictured.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>yoke</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A third male figure stands in front of of the oxen with his right leg extended backward and his right foot raised on tiptoe.  He is seen from behind and faces slightly to the right.  His head is bent back. Both arms are bent upward and he holds a yoke above his head with both hands.  He appears to have short hair and possibly a short, dark beard. He wears a shirt and breeches, a belt, and shoes.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>plow</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large curved plow is visible in the lower left corner of the image.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A hill or distant mountain rises to the left of the pair of oxen.  A second hill may be visible left and right of the musicians.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The background hills, particularly the one left and right of the two figures standing on the right, may be covered with leafy vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A sun with beams of light appears above the hill in the left half of the image.  The text illustrated makes it clear that the sun is setting.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The page contains four distinct images, labeled top to bottom &quot;Thenot. To illustrate lines 1, 2.&quot;; &quot;3, 4, 5, 6.&quot;; &quot;7, 8, 9.&quot;; and &quot;10.&quot; In the bottom image, a gowned figure walks on a path or road to the left with his head turned back to the right. He holds a large shepherd's crook or agricultural hook in his left hand. To the right of the figure stand two horned cows (the text illustrated specifies &quot;heifers&quot;).  A large curved plow is visible in the lower right corner of the image. Above the plow, a sun sets above a hill.  Curved lines in the sky may suggest a cloud.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
            <characteristic>boots</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A male figure walks (right foot on tiptoe) left with his head turned back to the right; he may look at the two cows to the right. He wears a hat, gown, and boots, and may have long hair.  The figure's left arm is bent upward and he holds a large shepherd's crook or agricultural hook in his left hand. His right arm may also be bent, but is partially obscured by his body.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>cow</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two horned cows (the text illustrated specifies &quot;heifers&quot;) stand or walk facing left. The leftmost cow rasies its head with its mouth open; it may be mooing. The rightmost cow looks forward, with its tail curved up and to the right.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>plow</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large curved plow is visible in the lower left corner of the image.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>path</characteristic>
            <characteristic>road</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure and cows may stand or walk on a path or road extending horizontally across the design.  Low hills or more distant mountains rise in the distance.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines in the top half of the design indicate sky.  Curved lines along the top edge may suggest a large cloud.  Directly above the plow on the right, the sun is visible with beams of light radiating outward.  The text indicates that the sun is setting.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="45" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.10.01">To face page 18.</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.10.02">ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.10.03">THENOT. To illustrate lines 1, 2.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="24" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.10.04">3, 4, 5, 6.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="25" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.10.05">7, 8, 9.
            <note>In this copy, the letterpress numbers are very lightly printed.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="27" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.10.06">10.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.25.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.11">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">ILLUSTRATION OF ECLOGUE I.  INTRODUCTORY.</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B25">(Bentley 504.25)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 7.9 x 11.6 cm.  The wood engraving, cut by John Byfield, is based on a drawing by Blake, in turn copied from a painting by Nicolas Poussin.  His oil painting, 
            *Landscape with Polyphemus*
            , is now in the Hermitage, St. Petersburg.  Blake may have executed his drawing directly on the face of the woodblock.  In this copy, the letterpress text below the design is partly bound into the book's gutter and thus is difficult to reproduce.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>9.5 x 11.7 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="550" width="750"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>In the upper center of the design, the giant Polypheme (or Polyphemus) sits atop a mountain.  He is seen from behind and faces left.  He plays a pipe and a shepherd's crook extends below him to the right. To the right of Polypheme's mountain rises a taller and more jagged mountain.  A cluster of leafy trees grows on a small hill below Polypheme.  To the left, a large tree with a bifurcating trunk and several visible branches extends nearly to the upper border of the image.  A small sailboat(?) is visible just to the left of the leftmost tree; it may sail on the sea or a large lake.  Three additional trees stand in the middle-distance below and to the right of Polypheme.  Below the central cluster of trees, a male figure guides a plow pulled by two horned oxen through a field.  The foreground of the image is dominated by several varieties of leafy vegetation and perhaps grass.  Horizontal lines at the bottom of the image may represent water, suggesting that this is the shore of a pond, lake, or stream.  A group of three figures rest on the ground in the lower left portion of the image.  The leftmost figure leans to the right with his left hand resting on the back of the figure to the right.  His head is turned in profile to the left.  The figure to the right kneels or lies with her(?) back to the viewer; she may rest her head on the back of the figure above.  The upper figure sits with his upper body twisted away from the viewer and his legs extended to the right.  Below this group of three figures is a large urn, resting on its side.  In the lower right corner of the image, a male figure reclines on a small hill or mound.  He faces left with his head turned away from the viewer.  He may rest against a cushion or a cloak.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Polyphemus</characteristic>
            <characteristic>giant</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the upper center of the design, the giant Polypheme (or Polyphemus) sits atop a mountain.  His hair is short and he appears to be nude.  He is seen from behind and faces left; his left leg is bent rests against the left side of the mountain.  His left arm is bent upward; he holds a set of musical pipes in his left hand and appears to be playing it.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="object">
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A shepherd's crook appears below and to the right of Polypheme, extending diagonally from the edge of the mountain.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The giant Polypheme sits atop a mountain in the center of the design. To the right of Polypheme's mountain rises a taller and more jagged mountain with rocky cliffs.  A small hill rises below and the the left of Polypheme's mountain.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A cluster of leafy trees grows on a small hill below Polypheme.  To the left, a large tree with a bifurcating trunk and several visible branches extends nearly to the upper border of the image.  The ground right of the large tree is marked by clumps of indeterminate vegetation, some spiky.  Three additional trees stand in the middle-distance below and to the right of Polypheme.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="object">
            <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The sea or a lake is pictured far left in the middle distance.  The object reflected in it may be a small sailboat just to the left of the leftmost tree.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plowing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plow</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below the central cluster of trees, a male figure walks to the right and guides a plow pulled by two horned oxen.  He wears a hat and coat.  His right leg is bent.  His right arm is extended at 45 degrees and he holds onto the plow with his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>ox</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below the central cluster of trees, a male figure guides a plow pulled by two horned oxen through a field.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The foreground of the image is dominated by several varieties of leafy vegetation and perhaps grass.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>stream</characteristic>
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
            <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A body of water, perhaps a pond or stream, appears in the lower center of the design.  The foreground figures sit on low mounds of earth or rock.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A group of three figures rest on the ground in the lower left portion of the image.  The leftmost figure leans to the right with his left arm bent and left hand resting on the back of the figure to the right.  His head is turned in profile to the left.  He may wear a toga or other drapery which trails off to the left; only the figure's upper body is clearly visible.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A group of three figures rest on the ground in the lower left portion of the image.  The front-most figure in the group reclines, apparently prone and with legs extended to the left, with her(?) back to the viewer.  Her hair may be long.  Her head is turned to face right, and she may rest her head on the back of the figure above.  Her right arm is bent upward and she may touch the figure above with her right hand.  The figure wears a toga or cloak.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A group of three figures rest on the ground in the lower left portion of the image.  The upper figure sits with his upper body twisted away from the viewer.  He reclines with his right leg is extended to the right and his left bent underneath him.  He may lean his weight on his left arm, which appears to be bent.  His right arm is at his side with his right hand resting on his left knee.  His hair is short and bushy.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="object">
            <characteristic>vase</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large urn or vase rests on its side below the group of three figures.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg drawn back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner of the image, a male figure reclines on a mound.  He appears to be gowned and may also wear a cloak.  He faces left with his head turned away from the viewer.  He may wear a crown of leaves in his short hair.  His right leg is bent and extends to the left; his left leg possibly dangles below him. His left arm is bent and he may rest against a cushion or a part of a cloak.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Large clouds fill the sky in the upper portion of the design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.11.01">To face page 21.</l>
          <l indent="25" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.11.02">ILLUSTRATION OF ECLOGUE I.</l>
          <l indent="30" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.11.03">INTRODUCTORY.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="15"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.11.04">
            *Blake, del.*
            <space extent="65"/>
            *Byfield, sculps.*
          </l>
          <l indent="8" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.11.05">THE GIANT POLYPHEME, FROM A FAMOUS PICTURE BY N. POUSSIN.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.26.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.12">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Caius Julius Cæsar,</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A12">Object 12 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B26">(Bentley 504.26)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 12.5 x 8.4 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>14.6 x 8.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="800" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of a male, identified below the image as Caius Julius Cæsar, face forward and to the right. His hair is short and crowned wih what is most likely laurel leaves. He wears what appears to be a breastplate of armor with ornate straps over a shirt.  The front of the breastplate is decorated with a head with wings, flame hair, and two serpents.  This is probably Medusa.  Her mouth is open.  Decorative ribbons extend from Medusa; another descends from the strap over Caesar's right shoulder.
               </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Caesar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bust</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of a male, identified below as Caius Julius Cæsar, face forward and to the right in the center of the design. His hair is short and crowned wih what is most likely laurel leaves. He wears what appears to be a breastplate of armor with ornate straps over a shirt. The collar of the shirt is ruffled, and the sleeves are ornamental and might end in tassels.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Medusa</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>anger</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>serpent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The front of Caesar's armor is decorated with a (female?) head, facing forward and to the right, with flame-like hair, wings, and two serpents.  This is probably Medusa, looking angry with mouth open.  Ribbons descend right and left of her head.  Another ribbon or tassel descends from the strap over Caesar's right shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="12"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="35" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.12.01">Blake, del. et Sculp.</l>
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.12.02">Caius Julius Cæsar,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.12.03">Aƒsaƒsinated 44 years before the Christian Æra.</l>
          <l indent="17" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.12.04">Virgil: æt. 26.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.12.05">London, Published by D
            <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
            . Thornton, 1821.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BB504.2.27.COM" id="bb504.2.comb.13">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Epicurus.</title>,
            
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A13">Object 13 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B27">(Bentley 504.27)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc>
        <objnote>
          <p>The pictorial image, including the framing lines, measures 10.3 x 6.9 cm.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>14.3 x 7.1 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="800" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>A sculpted bust of a man with curly hair and a beard, identified below the image as Epicurus, faces forward and slightly left.
               </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Epicurus</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bust</characteristic>
            <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A sculpted bust of a man with curly hair, m and a beard, identified below the image as Epicurus, faces forward in the center of the design. His head is raised slightly to the left, and his brow is furrowed.  His name in Greek letters is inscribed at the base of the bust; see the textual transcription.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure's name, Epicurus, is inscribed in Greek letters on the base of the bust; see the textual transcription.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="9"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.01">ΕΠΙΚΟϒRΟΣ</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="30" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.02">Blake, del. et Sculp.</l>
          <l indent="17" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.03">Epicurus.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.04">A Grecian Philosopher, Flourished 264 years before</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.05">Christ, His philosophy was transfused into Latin,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.06">by the great Roman Poet Lucretius, who</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.07">flourished 105 years before Christ, and wrote</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.08">his &quot;De Rerum Naturâ&quot; on the Nature of</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.09">Things.  He placed the summum bonum on</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.10">Tranquillity of Mind, arising from Virtue, and</l>
          <l justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.11">The Contemplation of Nature.</l>
          <l indent="2" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.12">He is said to have been born 342 B.C. Died 270 B.C. æ: 72.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="bb504.2.comb.13.13">London, Published by D
            <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
            . Thornton, 1821.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>