<bad id="bb514.3" type="comb" work="Mary Wollstonecraft, Original Stories" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="bentley" catid="514A"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Original Stories from Real Life"><main>Mary Wollstonecraft, Original Stories from Real Life</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
           and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 240KB; 12 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 150KB to 2500KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>August 2009</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
   The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an 
   electronic edition of Blake's ten monochrome wash drawings illustrating 
   Mary Wollstonecraft's <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi> and the first and 
   second editions of the book containing Blake's six engravings of his 
   designs. &#160;The designs and inscribed texts in all three series are fully 
   searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.
  <lb/><lb/>
   In 1788, Joseph Johnson published the first edition of Mary 
   Wollstonecraft's morally instructive narrative for children, <hi rend="i">Original 
      Stories from Real Life; with Conversations, Calculated to Regulate the 
      Affections, and Form the Mind to Truth and Goodness</hi>. &#160;A few years later, 
   Johnson decided to issue a new edition, for which he commissioned Blake to 
   prepare a series of illustrations. &#160;Blake's extant drawings, now in the 
   Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress, are datable to c. 1791. &#160;In 
   addition to these ten designs, Blake must have executed at least one 
   further drawing as a preliminary for his fifth plate; this drawing is 
   untraced. &#160;Six designs were selected for publication in the 1791 edition 
   of Wollstonecraft's book; Blake engraved the designs himself. &#160;The first 
   and second states of Blake's plates appear variously in copies of the 1791 
   edition.  The second edition to contain Blake's plates was published by 
   Johnson in 1796; it contains the third (final) states of Blake's plates. 
   The copy of the 1791 edition now in the Archive is from the Huntington 
   Library; it contains the second states of the plates.  The copy of the 
   1796 edition in the Archive is from the Essick collection and contains the 
   third (final) states of the plates.
   <lb/><lb/>
   Modern interpreters of the illustrations have detected a pictorial 
   critique of Wollstonecraft's stories. &#160;Blake appears to have found her 
   morality too calculating, rationalistic, and rigid. &#160;He represents 
   Wollstonecraft's spokesperson, Mrs. Mason, as a domineering presence. 
   &#160;From Blake's perspective, Mason's acts of charity are excessively 
   condescending and tend to reinforce the underlying social conditions that 
   create disparities between wealth and poverty. &#160;As Blake wrote in "The 
   Human Abstract," "Pity would be no more, / If we did not make somebody 
   Poor."
   <lb/><lb/>
   With this publication, the Archive adds a new set of scholarly tools. 
   These tools, known collectively as our Related Works system, are designed 
   to show relationships among works and individual objects in the Archive. 
   They function at two levels.  First, work index pages now include active 
   links to related materials in the Archive (for example, a set of 
   preliminary sketches for a group of engravings).  Second, the Show Me menu 
   on object view pages now includes Related Works in the Archive.  Like the work-level menu, this list includes active 
   links to the related objects and is meant to allow study of the related 
   materials side-by-side.  The Wollstonecraft illustrations are the first 
   publication in the Archive to use this feature.
   <lb/><lb/>
   As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access 
   restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible 
   by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the cooperation of 
   the international array of libraries and museums that have generously 
   given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the 
   Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2009</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This work courtesy Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
         <lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Publication prep</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD modified to include new Related Works protocols</change><date>April 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Natalie Moix,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Lily Todorinova,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction, illustration markup and BAD creation</change><date>June-August 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition and metadata collection</change><date>October 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Mary Wollstonecraft, *Original Stories from Real Life*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher,</role><role>engraver</role></origination><imprint><publisher>Joseph Johnson</publisher><pubplace>London</pubplace><date>1791</date></imprint><compdate value="1791.A">1791</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1791.A">1791</printdate><numberobj>6</numberobj><objorder>1-6</objorder><objsize>ranging between 13.7 x 6.8 cm. and 14.0 x 7.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>6</numberleaves><leafsize>16.6 x 9.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>etching and engraving<note>The plates in this copy are in the second state.  The first and second states appear variously in copies of the 1791 edition, the first to contain Blake's plates.  The third state, with Blake's signature added to Objects 2-6, appear in the 1796 edition of the book.  For a description of the states, see the Editors' Notes to both copies published in the Archive.</note></medium><printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>heavy laid paper</support><watermark>Object 4 shows the fragment of a watermark (two parallel curved lines) near its outer margin.</watermark><etchednumbers>Facing page numbers are engraved top right on Plates 2-6; see the transcriptions.</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>late nineteenth-century tan calf, with the bookplate of E. Dwight Church</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name><date>1911</date><dealer>none recorded</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Acquired at an unknown time by E. Dwight Church; acquired as part of the Church collection by Henry E. Huntington in April 1911.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution><addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline><addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline><addressline>USA</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2191</addressline><addressline>Fax: 626-405-0225</addressline><addressline>URL, general: http://www.huntington.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Library Division: http://www.huntington.org/LibraryDiv/LibraryHome.html</addressline><department>Library Division, Rare Books</department><collection>Church Collection</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">108272</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="bb514.3.comb.01" dbi="bb514.3.1.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Look what a fine morning it is.</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 514.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>In the second state of the plate, presented here, the background has been darkened with the addition of fine diagonal lines within the doorway, dots to the right doorjamb, and dark lines to the surrounding wall.  Crosshatching has been added to the central woman's dress where it falls over her lower right leg.</p></objnote><objsize>13.8 x 6.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><related objectid="but244.1.wd.04"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A gowned female, Mrs. Mason, stands between two female children, Mary and Caroline.  
                  The adult wears a large hat with a bow, and buckle shoes.  Her long hair rests upon her shoulders.  
                  Her arms are raised horizontally over the heads of the other figures, slightly bent at the 
                  elbows, palms facing out and fingers spread.  Her eyes are cast down as if looking at the ground.  
                  The two female children to her left and right are both gowned and wear hats 
                  over their long hair.  The child on the left has her arms crossed in front of her chest while 
                  the child on the right has her arms bent upwards, palms vertical, with the fingers on at least 
                  her left hand spread.  The figures stand in front of a building with a door, possibly made of 
                  brick, stone, or wood.  Two large, branching vines grow to the left and right of the figures.  The 
                  vine to the right is covered in large leaves, while the vine on the left has many smaller 
                  leaves.  The ground below the figures may be covered with grass.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>buckle</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised palms out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female, Mrs. Mason, stands facing forward between two female children.  She wears a 
                     large hat with a bow, and buckle shoes.  Her long hair rests upon her shoulders.  Her 
                     arms are raised horizontally over the heads of the other figures, slightly bent at the elbows, palms 
                     facing out and fingers spread.  Her eyes are cast down as if looking at the ground.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms folded</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female child stands to the left of the central figure.  She is one of Mrs. Mason's charges, 
                     either Mary or Caroline.  She has long hair and wears a hat and probably shoes.  The hem of her gown is ruffled.  
                     She faces forward with her arms crossed over her breasts.  Her eyes are raised as if looking at the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female child stands to the right of the central figure.  She is one of Mrs. Mason's charges, either 
                     Mary or Caroline.  She has long hair and wears a hat and probably shoes.  The hem of her gown is ruffled.  She faces 
                     forward with her arms bent and raised in front of her.  Her palms are held vertically, with the fingers on at least her 
                     left hand spread.  Her eyes are raised as if looking at the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>brick</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the group of figures is a building with a clearly defined door frame.  
                     The structure may be made of wood, stone, bricks, or a combination of these.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two branching vines rise to the left and right of the group of figures.  The vine on 
                     the right is covered in large leaves—perhaps 19 in all.  The vine on the left has many smaller leaves.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground beneath the figures is covered with vegetation, perhaps grass.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.01.01" justify="left" indent="33">Frontispiece.
               </l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.01.02" justify="left" indent="32">Blake. d. &amp; sc:
               </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.01.03" justify="left">Look what a fine morning it is. __ Insects,
               </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.01.04" justify="left">Birds, &amp; Animals, are all enjoying existence.
               </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.01.05" justify="left" indent="1">Published by J.Johnson, Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1.<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1791.
               </l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb514.3.comb.02" dbi="bb514.3.2.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Dog strove to attract his attention.</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 514.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>In the second state of the plate, presented here, the floor, window, and upper left corner of the room have been darkened with dots and crosshatching.  A few lines have been added to the legs of the bed and to the dog's left rear leg.</p></objnote><objsize>13.9 x 7.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><related objectid="but244.1.wd.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A male figure stands in a room with the dead bodies of two children.  The man, Robin, is the father of the 
                  children, the boy Jacky (closest to the viewer) and the girl Nancy.  The adult has short, curly hair and wears breeches 
                  and a sleeveless shirt or vest.  His body faces forward with his head turned to the left and slightly down; he wears an 
                  expression of despair or grief and may be looking at the two children.  His muscular arms are down at his sides with both 
                  hands forming fists; his bare feet are prominent.  Two corpses—a male and female child—lay supine on a bed.  
                  Their eyes are closed and their heads are back; their heads seem to be resting on a bundle or pillow.  The male child has 
                  short curly hair and wears breeches and a shirt.  His right arm is pictured at his side with the palm down.  The female 
                  child is gowned and has long hair.  Her right arm is bent and rests on her chest.  A slight indication of her left hand 
                  suggests that her hands are clasped over her chest.  A dog with curly fur stands to the right of the male figure.  It stretches 
                  upward with its mouth open and tongue extended to lick the man's left fist.  The scene is set in a stone cell of a prison. 
                  There is a narrow window, top left, with three horizontal bars.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>Robin</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>fist</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure stands in a room with the bodies of two dead children; he is Robin, their father.  
                     He has short, curly hair and wears breeches and a sleeveless shirt or vest.  His body faces forward 
                     with his head turned to the left and slightly down; he wears an expression of despair or grief and he may be looking 
                     at the two children.  His muscular arms are down at his side with both hands forming fists.  His bare feet are prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Jacky</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a male child (Jacky, closest to the viewer) lies supine on a bed with his head bent back and his eyes 
                     closed.  He wears breeches and a shirt.  His right arm is pictured at his side with the palm down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Nancy</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a gowned female child (Nancy, second from the viewer) lies supine on a bed with her head bent back 
                     and her eyes closed.  Her right arm is bent and rests on her chest.  Slight indications of her left hand suggest that her 
                     hands are clasped and resting on her chest.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="BD"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>stretched</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dog with curly fur stands to the right of the male figure.  It stretches 
                     upward with its mouth open and tongue extended to lick the man's left fist.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>bier</characteristic><characteristic>bundle</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The two dead children lie on a bed, used here as a bier.  Their heads are supported by a bundle or pillow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>chamber</characteristic><characteristic>cell</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>prison</characteristic><characteristic>rod</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in a stone cell of a prison.  There is a 
                     narrow window, top left, with three horizontal bars.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.02.01" justify="left" indent="35">P. 24</l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.02.02" justify="left">The Dog strove to attract his attention.__</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.02.03" justify="left">He said, Thou wilt not leave me!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.02.04" justify="left" indent="1">Published by J. Johnson, Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1, 1791.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb514.3.comb.03" dbi="bb514.3.3.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Indeed we are very happy!</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 514.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>In the second state of the plate, presented here, crossing lines have been added to the floor (lower left and center), the wall (left, center, and within the fireplace), the molding surrounding the fireplace, and the legs of the boy standing near the right margin.</p></objnote><objsize>13.7 x 7.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><related objectid="but244.1.wd.07"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A gowned female (Mrs. Mason) sits in a chair on the left and faces right.  She wears a hat and her long hair falls 
                  onto her shoulders.  Her arms rest in her lap, with her hands on her knees.  Her eyes are down and 
                  she appears to be smiling; she looks at the two  female children (Mary and Caroline) sitting to either side of her.  Both children 
                  have long hair; the figure on the left has hers drawn back into a braid.  The figure on the left is seen from the side, with her 
                  upper body turned away from the viewer.  Her right hand rests in the woman's lap.  Her head is down and rests in the 
                  woman's lap in an apparent expression of sorrow.  The figure on the right mirrors this position; she holds the woman's left arm 
                  with her left hand.  To the right of this group, a male figure sits in a chair facing left.  He is Jack, a sailor, with two of his 
                  children near him.  He wears a coat, breeches, shoes, and a scarf.  His left arm is bent and rests in his lap.  His crutch lies on 
                  the wooden floor below his left foot.  A child (possibly female and wearing a hat) stands behind and to the left of the seated man.  
                  She has her head down, and holds a scarf or cloth to her face.  The figure appears to stand, but her legs are not pictured.  A male 
                  child stands to the right of the seated male figure.  He may be leaning against the back of the chair.  He has short curly hair 
                  and his eyes are cast down.  His arms are crossed in front of his chest, with his left hand holding or 
                  resting on his right shoulder.  His legs are crossed at the ankles.  He may be wearing tights or a shirt and breeches.  The six 
                  figures appear in a room with a large fireplace.  A fire burns on a stack of wood kindling and smoke 
                  rises up the chimney.  Two model ships sit on a mantel above the fireplace; the ship on the 
                  right has sails.  Three objects, probably candlesticks, sit between the two ships.  Two framed pictures 
                  hang on the wall to either side of the mantel.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms on lap</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female (Mrs. Mason) sits in a chair facing right.  She wears a hat and her long hair 
                     falls onto her shoulders.  Her arms rest in her lap, with her hands on her knees.  Her eyes are 
                     down and she appears to be smiling; she is probably looking at the two female children sitting to either side of her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned female children, Mary and Caroline, sit to either side of the adult female, Mrs. Mason.  Both figures 
                     have long hair; the figure on the left has hers drawn back into a braid.  The figure on the left is seen from the side, but 
                     her upper body is twisted away from the viewer as she bends forward towards the woman.  The girl's right arm and hand rest in 
                     the woman's lap; her head is down and also rests in the woman's lap in an apparent expression of 
                     sorrow. The figure on the right mirrors this position.  Her left hand rests on or holds the woman's left arm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>Jack</characteristic><characteristic>sailor</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure sits on the right in a chair and faces left.  He is Jack, a sailor, and the father of the two children 
                     near him.  He wears a coat, pants, shoes, and a scarf.  His hair is short and perhaps a bit curly.  His left arm is bent and 
                     rests in his lap.  His crutch rests on the floor beneath his left foot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A child, probably female, stands behind and to the left of the seated 
                     adult male.  She is wearing a hat, has her head down, 
                     and holds a scarf or cloth to her face.  Her posture suggests sorrow.  The figure appears to be standing, but her legs are not 
                     pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child stands to the right of the seated male figure.  He may be leaning against the 
                     back of the chair.  He has short curly hair and his eyes are cast down.  His arms are crossed in front 
                     of his chest, with his left hand holding or resting on his right shoulder.  His legs are crossed at the 
                     ankles.  He may be wearing tights or a shirt and breeches.  His posture suggests melancholy or sorrow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>stool</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The two adult figures in the scene are seated on chairs.  The leftmost child in the design 
                     sits on a stool.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>fireplace</characteristic><characteristic>chimney</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There is a fireplace in the center of the design.  A fire burns on a stack of wood 
                     kindling and smoke rises up the chimney.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>mantel</characteristic><characteristic>ship</characteristic><characteristic>sail</characteristic><characteristic>candlestick</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two model ships sit on a mantel above the fireplace.  The ship on the right has sails.  
                     Three objects, probably candlesticks, sit between the two ships.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>picture</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><characteristic>boat</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two framed pictures hang to the left and right of the shelf.  The picture on the left shows a boat sinking in a storm.  
                     The picture on the right is probably also a seascape, including a boat.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>crutch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The man's crutch rests on the floor below his left foot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in a room with beams supporting the roof.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514b.comb.03.01" justify="left" indent="33">P. 74.</l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.03.02" justify="left">Indeed we are very happy! ________</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.03.03" justify="left" indent="1">Published by J. Johnson, Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1, 1791.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb514.3.comb.04" dbi="bb514.3.4.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Be calm, my child,</title>,
            
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 514.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>In the second state of the plate, presented here, crossing lines have been added to the areas on the intertwined trees (left margin) shaded only with hatching in the first state.</p></objnote><objsize>14.0 x 7.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><related objectid="but244.1.wd.08"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An adult female figure (Mrs. Mason) walks with two female children (Mary and Caroline).   The 
                  woman is seen from behind and walks away from the viewer, with her head turned in profile to the right and slightly down.  
                  She is gowned and wears a cloak or shawl around her shoulders; she also wears a large hat with a bow, 
                  and her long hair cascades out from under a bonnet.  Her arms are at her side and are slightly bent at 
                  the elbows.  With her right arm, she embraces or holds the child to the right; though not pictured, 
                  she may hold hands with the child to the left.  A female child stands to the left of the central figure.  
                  She is gowned and wears a hat.  Her head is turned to the left, away from the other figures.  She may 
                  be looking at something not pictured.  Part of her body is hidden by the central figure; her right arm 
                  is bent and she may hold the left hand of the central figure.  A second female child stands or walks to 
                  the right of the central figure.  She is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer.  She is gowned 
                  and wears a hat with a ribbon or bow.  Her left arm is extended at 45 degrees and touches the 
                  right leg of the central figure.  On the right of the design stands a ruined house.  
                  The structure has two distinct windows and what might be a pilaster at its left corner.  The structure appears broken, particularly 
                  above the highest window.  Extending to the left is a wall or fence that is partially hidden by the 
                  figures and tree trunks.  A lake or river is pictured to the left and right of the group of figures, below the 
                  ruined building.  Clumps of indeterminate vegetation are pictured in the lake.  The plants in the water may be lily pads.  
                  Several trees with leaves and crossing trunks surround the group of 
                  figures.  More distant trees appear above and to the left of the 
                  ruined structure.  The ground beneath the group of figures is covered with grass.  
                  There are indications of sky above the figures and ruined structure.  Heavier etched lines may suggest 
                  clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A central adult female (Mrs. Mason) walks with two children, Mary and Caroline.  The 
                     woman is seen from behind and walks away from the viewer, with her head turned in profile to the right and slightly down.  
                     She is gowned and wears a cloak or shawl around her shoulders; she also wears a large hat with a bow, 
                     and her long hair cascades out from under a bonnet.  Her arms are at her side and are slightly bent at 
                     the elbows.  With her right arm, she embraces or holds the child to the right; though not 
                     pictured, she may hold hands with the child to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary or Caroline) stands to the left of the central figure.  She is gowned 
                     and wears a hat.  Her body faces forward with her head turned to the left, away from the other figures.  She may 
                     be looking at something not pictured.  Part of her body is hidden by the central figure; 
                     her right arm is bent and she may hold the left hand of the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>touches</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary or Caroline) stands or walks to the right of the central figure.  She is 
                     seen from behind and faces away from the viewer; her hair is long.  She is gowned and wears a hat with a bow or ribbon.  
                     Her left arm is extended at 45 degrees and touches the right leg of the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>ruin</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>fence</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><characteristic>broken</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design stands a ruined house.  
                     The structure has two distinct windows and what may be a pilaster at its left corner.  The structure appears 
                     broken, particularly above the highest window.  Extending to the left is a wall or fence 
                     that is partially hidden by the figures and tree trunks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>lake</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>stream</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A lake or river is pictured in the middle distance to the left and right of the group of figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>lily</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Clumps of vegetation are pictured in the lake or river.  They may be the pads of water lilies.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>willow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several trees with leaves and crossing trunks surround 
                     the group of figures.  They may represent willows.  Other, less distinct trees appear above and 
                     to the left of the ruined house.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground beneath the group of figures is covered with 
                     grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There are indications of sky above the figures and ruined house.  Heavier 
                     etched lines may suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.04.01" justify="left" indent="36">P.94.</l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.04.02" justify="left">Be calm, my child, remember that you</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.04.03" justify="left">must do all the good you can the present day.</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.04.04" justify="left" indent="2">Published by J. Johnson, Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1. 1791.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb514.3.comb.05" dbi="bb514.3.5.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Trying to trace the sound,</title>,
           
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 514.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>In the second state of the plate, presented here, crossing lines have been added to the harper's left thigh, his coat below his left arm, the shaded area left and right of his left ankle, and the back and right leg of the chair.  More fine diagonal lines have been added to the sky.  The preliminary drawing for this plate is untraced.</p></objnote><objsize>14.0 x 6.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design, a male figure sits in a small building playing the harp.  
                  He wears shoes, breeches, a shirt, and a coat.  His head is turned up and to the right; his short hair seems to stand on end.  His mouth is open and he may be singing.  His 
                  right leg is drawn up towards his body.  His right arm is bent upward with his palm out.  
                  His left arm is bent and the fingers on his left hand are spread in the act of playing the 
                  harp.  The building in which he sits (called a "hut" in the text) is constructed out of the larger ruined structure around him, described in the text as a castle.  The building has at least one 
                  distinct pillar and plinth on the right.  This pillar shows an arched recess containing an indistinct 
                  shape—it may be a small statue.  The roof is made of straw thatching.  The male figure sits 
                  on a series of platforms or steps.  Two or three stairs lead from the building to the female figure (Mrs. Mason) 
                  standing to the right of the building.  She faces forward and left, towards the male figure, and is likely 
                  listening to his music.  She wears either a gown or a skirt and shirt as well as a hat.  Her arms 
                  are at her sides with her palms facing down.  Above and to the right are more fragments of the ruined Gothic castle.  
                  On the far upper left and right stand large Gothic arches, possibly windows.  
                  The arch upper left is adjacent to a broken wall or pillar.  Near the center of the design, just left 
                  of the female figure, is a tall broken pillar and plinth.  Indeterminate vegetation fills much of 
                  the background, perhaps representing trees, and possibly a mountain on the right.  There are indications of grass on 
                  the ground beneath the female figure.  At the top of the design, 16 stars appear in the night sky.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>singing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design, a male figure (a Welsh harper) sits on a chair in a portion 
                     of a ruined castle and plays a harp.  
                     He wears shoes, breeches, a shirt, and coat.  His head is turned up and to the right, 
                     and his short hair seems to stand on end.  His mouth is open and he may be singing.  His 
                     right leg is drawn up towards his body.  His right arm is bent upward with his palm out.  
                     His left arm is bent and the fingers on his left hand are spread in the act of playing the 
                     harp.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>harp</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male figure plays a harp.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The harper sits on a chair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>listening</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure (Mrs. Mason) stands to the right of the building.  She faces forward and to the left, towards the 
                     male harper, and is likely listening to his music.  She wears either a gown or a skirt and shirt 
                     as well as a hat.  Her arms are at her sides with her palms facing down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>cottage</characteristic><characteristic>hut</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design, a male harpist sits in a small building, a cottage-like structure (called a "hut" in 
                     the text) built into the surrounding ruins.  The building has at least one distinct pillar and plinth.  This pillar 
                     shows an arched recess containing an indistinct shape within—it may be a small statue.  The roof is made of straw thatching.  
                     The male figure sits on a series of platforms or steps.  Two or three stairs 
                     lead from the building to the female figure on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A diagonal shadow is cast on the step below the small building.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>ruin</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>tracery</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>broken</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of the small building are the ruins of a Gothic castle.  
                     On the far upper left and right stand large Gothic arches, possibly windows.  The arch on the left is 
                     adjacent to a broken wall or pillar.  Near the center of the design, just left of the female figure, 
                     is a tall broken pillar and plinth.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Indeterminate vegetation fills much of the background, perhaps representing trees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The shape upper right may be a distant mountain.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There are indications of grass on the ground beneath the female figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the design, 16 stars appear in the night sky.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.05.01" justify="left" indent="35">P.114.</l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.05.02" justify="left">Trying to trace the sound, I discovered</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.05.03" justify="left">a little hut, rudely built.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.05.04" justify="left" indent="1">Published by J. Johnson, Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1, 1791.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="bb514.3.comb.06" dbi="bb514.3.6.COM"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Œconomy and self-denial are necessary,</title>,
           
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 514.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>In the second state of the plate, presented here, the floor lower left has been darkened with heavy hatching lines.  Crossing lines have been added to the upper half of the wall within the fireplace, a small area to the left of the upper left arm of the man seated in the chair, the area seen through the background door, the lintel above the door, and the ceiling beams upper right.</p></objnote><objsize>14.0 x 6.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="750"/></physdesc><related objectid="but244.1.wd.09"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Mrs. Mason and her two charges, Mary and Caroline, visit a poor family.  Eight figures are pictured in 
                  a small room with a door, a fireplace with a grate (but no fire), and holes in the wall on the left.   
                  We can also see the inside of the roof with two supporting rafters.  On the right of the design, an adult 
                  female (Mrs. Mason) stands between two female children (Mary and Caroline).  
                  She is gowned and wears a hat.  She may be listening to the woman to her left.  She appears to 
                  be looking at the crouched figures in the lower half of the plate with an expression of pity.  
                  She holds the hands of the children to her left and right.  The children  
                  to her left and right are both gowned and wear hats.  The child on the right bends her right arm 
                  and holds the hand of the adult woman; the girl's left arm is down and the fingers of her left hand are 
                  slightly spread.  The child on the left is partially obscured.  She may hold hands (with her left hand?) with the adult 
                  woman; her right arm is bent across her body.  Both children look towards the other figures in the scene with 
                  expressions suggesting pity or surprise.  Another female figure stands to the left of the doorway; she is the mother of 
                  the poor family that Mrs. Mason and her charges are visiting.  She is gowned  
                  and wears a tattered hat.  She faces forward, but her head is turned in 
                  profile to the right.  Her mouth is open; she is speaking to the woman to the right.  Her arms are 
                  crossed in front of her chest.  She holds a (nude?) infant, one of her children.  We see only the infant's head and 
                  upper body from behind.  The child has short, curly hair, and his or her left arm is bent.  An adult male 
                  figure, the father, sits in a chair in the lower half of the design.  He wears shoes, striped stockings, breeches, and a shirt.  His 
                  hair is short and curly.  His left arm rests on his lap with his hand on his knee.  His right arm is bent 
                  and supports his head, which is bent down.  His eyes are closed, and he wears an expression of despair, melancholy, or 
                  grief.  To the left of the seated figure, a male child sits in an extremely contracted position and 
                  leans with his shoulder against the wall.  He is facing forward, with his head turned slightly to the 
                  left.  The figure wears breeches and appears to have long hair.  His legs are drawn up and crossed at 
                  the ankles.  His right arm is at his side.  The child's eyes are closed and his mouth is slightly open; he may be 
                  crying in despair or grief.  The leftmost figure in this design is a male child seated on the floor with 
                  his back against the wall.  He wears breeches and a shirt or coat.  He faces to the right, with his legs 
                  extended together.  His right arm is at his side with his palm down.  His head is bent down, and he 
                  wears a rather blank expression.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>pity</characteristic><characteristic>listening</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design, an adult female (Mrs. Mason) stands between two female children.  
                     She is gowned and wears a hat.  She faces forward with her head turned slightly to the left.  She may be 
                     listening to the woman to her left.  She appears to 
                     be looking at the crouched figures in the lower half of the plate with an expression of pity.  
                     She holds the hands of the children to her left and right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pity</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two female children, Mary and Caroline, flank the adult woman standing on the right.  Both are gowned and wear hats.  
                     The child on the right holds the adult's hand with her right hand; her left arm is down and her 
                     fingers spread.  The child on the left is partially obscured.  She may hold hands (with her left hand?) with the adult 
                     woman; her right arm is bent across her body.  Both children look towards 
                     the other figures in the scene with expressions suggesting pity.  The expression of the girl on the right also suggests surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, the mother of the family visited by Mrs. Mason and her charges, stands to the left of 
                     the doorway.  She is gowned and wears a tattered hat.  She faces forward, but her head 
                     is turned in profile to the right.  Her mouth is open; she is speaking to the woman to the right.  Her arms are crossed in front 
                     of her chest.  She holds a (nude?) infant, one of her children.  We see only the infant's head and 
                     upper body from behind.  The child has short, curly hair, and his left arm is bent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure, the father of the poor family, sits in a chair in the lower half of the design.  
                     He faces left and wears shoes, striped stockings, 
                     breeches, and a shirt.  His hair is short and curly.  His left arm rests on his lap with his 
                     hand on his knee.  His right arm is bent and supports his head, which is bent down.  His 
                     eyes are closed, and he wears an expression of despair, melancholy, or grief.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the seated figure, a male(?) child sits in an extremely 
                     contracted position and leans with his shoulder against the wall.  The figure wears breeches 
                     and appears to have long hair.  His legs are drawn up and crossed at the ankles; his feet are bare.  His right 
                     arm is at his side.  The child's eyes are closed and his mouth is open; he may be crying in 
                     despair or grief.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The adult male in the lower half of the design sits in a chair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure in this design is a male child seated on the floor with 
                     his back against a wall.  He wears breeches and a shirt.  He faces to the right, with his 
                     legs extended together.  His right arm is at his side with his palm down.  His prominent feet are bare.  His head is bent 
                     down, and he wears a blank expression.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>fireplace</characteristic><characteristic>grate</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>broken</characteristic><characteristic>rafter</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in a small room with a doorway in the right background, a fireplace in the wall on the left, 
                     and a grate (but not fire) in the fireplace.  The wall on the left appears to be broken with holes in it.  We can also 
                     see the inside of the roof with supporting rafters.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.06.01" justify="left" indent="35">P. 173.</l></lg><vspace extent="15"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.06.02" justify="left">Œconomy &amp; Self-denial are necessary, in</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.06.03" justify="left">every station, to enable us to be generous.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="bb514.3.comb.06.04" justify="left" indent="2">Published by J. Johnson, Sept<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 1, 1791.</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>