<bad id="bbwba1.1" type="ms" work="The Phoenix to Mrs Butts" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="bl" catalog="Bentley, *Blake Books Supplement*" 
    catid="pages 105-106" hidden="false"> 
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Phoenix to Mrs Butts">
                    <main>The Phoenix to Mrs Butts</main>
                    : electronic edition
                </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                </principal>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 32KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 169KB to 1.4MB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>
                Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries
                <date>August 2023</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of four miscellaneous manuscript poems. Three of these four scraps of Blake’s legacy may have disappeared permanently were it not for the remarkable energy and devotion of the Gilchrists and Rossettis in tracing and publicizing what was left of “William Blake” by the second half of the nineteenth century. Not until a century later, in the 1980s, did the previously unknown “The Phoenix to Mrs Butts” resurface. Amazing things do happen. 
      <lb/>
                <lb/>Two prose poems, “then She bore Pale desire” and “Woe cried the muse,” in seven pages on four leaves, are likely Blake’s earliest surviving manuscript drafts (c. 1783). “then She bore Pale Desire” seems to begin in mid-course; whatever preceded the first line is missing.
      <lb/>
<lb/>In both style and content they resemble other early works such as “Fair Elenor” in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783), relying heavily on popular late eighteenth century conventions such as the personification of abstractions&#8212;“Hate brooding in her Dismal den grew Pregnant &amp; bore Scorn, &amp; Slander” (“Pale Desire,” Object 5, lines 1-3)&#8212;alongside a few unmistakable anticipations of Blake’s later poetry, as in “the Nightly Blast that Blights the Infant Bud.” Compare “London,” Songs of Experience: “How the youthful harlots curse / Blasts the new born infants tear” (lines 15-16, Erdman page 27).
      <lb/>
<lb/>Four-beat couplets structure “A fairy leapt.” On the verso is a pencil sketch, <hi rend="i">The Infant Hercules Throttling the Serpents</hi>, though there is no obvious connection between the two. Fairies are not rare in Blake’s work. “So sang a Fairy mocking as he sat on a streak’d Tulip / . . . My Fairy sat upon the table, and dictated EUROPE” (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> Plate iii, Erdman page 60). They seem to be associated with something like mischievous, potentially disruptive knowledge. Blake’s fairies fall taxonomically between angels and devils, emerging from a dimension somehow separate from the ghost world of history, mostly human, that he readily sketched on command for his young artist friends in his later life (collected as the Visionary Heads).
      <lb/>
<lb/>More carefully crafted, “The Phoenix to Mrs Butts”&#8212;the first Mrs. Butts&#8212;is designed in a manner reminiscent of Blake’s illuminated books, in this case close to the design of “A Little Girl Lost” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789) but composed as a kind of letter, and delivered by hand rather than by post. Beyond that, little is known of the circumstances that produced “The Phoenix.” It echoes the lexical imagery, meter (in this case, again, four-beat couplets), subject matter, and graphic design of, say, the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>&#8212;and, yet again, a fairy:
      <lb/>
<lb/>
The Fairy to my bosom flew<lb/>
Weeping tears of morning dew<lb/>
I said: Thou foolish whimpring thing<lb/>
Is not that thy Fairy Ring . . . <lb/>
Seem a Child &amp; be a Child<lb/>
And the Phoenix is beguild<lb/>
                <lb/>
                All works in the Archive are accessible via the Table of Contents, which is accessible via the "sandwich" button at the right end of the banner. This drops down a second banner that identifies the categories of works in the Archive: Illuminated books, Commercial Book Illustrations, Separate Prints and Prints in Series, Drawings and Paintings, Manuscripts and Typographic Works. To further improve accessibility to the works, we've added a Table of Contents item, "All Works," which twice lists all of the works in the Archive without categorizing them according to genre or medium. One list puts the works in alphabetical order and the other in order of composition date. The latter list would of course be of interest to any Blake scholars mindful of the historical progression of Blake's works.
      <lb/>
<lb/>As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt> 
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>
            Copyright ©
            <date>2023</date>
            by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. 
            Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. 
            Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the 
            editors and advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive 
            has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            This image copyright © 2023 British Library.
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing, revisions, and publication</change>
                <date>June-August 2023</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
                    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher Catanese, </name>
                    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>
                    <name>Mary Geisert, </name>
                    <name>HaiLee Hearburg, </name>
                    <name>Liam Kusmierek, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
                    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
                    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
                    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
                    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
                    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created and text transcribed</change>
                <date>June 2014</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin, </name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Adam Engel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham, </name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime, </name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kirilloff, </name>
                    <name>Eric Loy, </name>
                    <name>Kate Massie, </name>
                    <name>Adam McCune, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer, </name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai, </name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner, </name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Images acquired, scanned, and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2005</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>The Phoenix to Mrs Butts</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>
                    William Blake
                    <role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1794">
                    sometime between c. 1794 and c. 1803
                    <note>
                        Bentley notes that the date is "problematic," as "The Phoenix" is likely to have been 
                        written during Blake's closest association with his chief patron Thomas Butts, somewhere between 1794-1806 
                        (*Blake Books Supplement* page 105). 
                        Essick cites similarities between the poem and early illuminated pages, concluding that the work was 
                        created c. 1794 (Essick, “William Blake’s 
                        ‘The Phoenix’: A Problem in Attribution,” *Philological Quarterly* 67 [1988], page 377). 
                        Viscomi dates the poem as c. 1800–1803, the period when Blake moved from London to Felpham and 
                        started to write to the Butts’s regularly 
                        (Viscomi, “William Blakes’s ‘The Phoenix / to Mrs Butts’ Redux,” *Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly* 
                        29.1 [summer 1995], page 15). </note> 
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>22.7 x 15.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22.7 x 15.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and watercolor</medium>
                <inkcolor>blue
                    <note>Bentley notes that the primary ink in this document is an unusual pale blue with touching up in red, brown, and purple.
                        He further states that the colors have changed as the ink has aged 
                        (*Blake Books Supplement* page 105). Upon closer inspection, the blue ink appears to have been executed with a pen, 
                        while the various other hues appear to be watercolor applied with a brush.</note>
                </inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <framelines>straight lines at the right and bottom of the page; curling lines at the left.</framelines>
                <binding>none
                    <note>The manuscript was donated with an accompanying "brownish-Grey mid(?)-nineteenth-century envelope of crude, rough paper" 
                        (Bentley, *Blake Books Supplement* page 105).</note>
                </binding>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Library</name>
                <date>1985</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <note>Given by Blake sometime between c. 1794 and c. 1803 to the dedicatee Elizabeth Cooper Butts, first wife of Thomas Butts; 
                    passed by inheritance to Butts's daughter by her first marriage, Mary Anne Long; 
                    passed down to Long's grandson, Mr. Owen D. Long; 
                    deposited in the British Library by Long in 1981; 
                    sold by Long to the British Library in July 1985 
                    (Bentley, *Blake Books Supplement* page 106).</note> 
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Library</institution>
                <department>Western Manuscripts</department>
                <repositoryid label="Inventory number">Add. MS 63583</repositoryid>
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="bbwba1.1.ms.01" dbi="BBWBA1.1.1.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Phoenix to Mrs Butts</title>
                ,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code ="B1">(Bentley, Supplement pages 105-106)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>22.7 x 15.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="500" height="615"/>
                <objnote>
                    <p>
                        The poem is written within a frame consisting of mostly straight lines at the right and bottom, 
                        curling like a vine at the left. To the right of the 
                        title is a faint flying figure, comparable to one in *The Book of Thel* Plate 2, 
                        with a flying bird to the 
                        right of the figure. There seems to be no 
                        significance in the colors added to the letters, except that it is often where 
                        the blue is faint. The format of the manuscript is similar to pages in Blake's 
                        illuminated books (Bentley, *Blake Books Supplement* pages 105-6).
                    </p>
                </objnote>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The pictorial image for this plate frames the text. To the right of the title, a 
                        human form hovers or flies with arms lifted upwards, outstretched, and bent. The figure faces up 
                        and right and may be female, perhaps the fairy mentioned in the poem. Its legs are faintly outlined, 
                        covered by a robe or a gown which trails behind the figure. The figure's legs appear to be bent 
                        and extend to the left of the figure's upper body, with the right thigh and knee crossed over the
                        left leg, which appears to be streched out and down, though it is obscured by the figure's gown. 
                        The human figure appears to be reaching up and towards a golden-colored spot that hangs above it
                        and to the right. The spot may be a celestial body like the sun or a star. A bird, probably the 
                        phoenix of the poem, flies to the right of the figure and below the celestial orb. Its outstreached 
                        wings and tail are visible. It faces away or to the right, though its beak and head are indistinctly 
                        rendered. Directly below the bird, a plant grows vertically along the right side of the plate. The 
                        plant may be sapling or a reed with a slim trunk or stem, with a base that is thicker than the trunk, suggesting roots. 
                        Horizontal growths protrude outwards from the plant's stem or trunk towards the lines of the text. These 
                        are likely leaves or catkins. The plant branches into two main stems to the right of lines 8 and 9. 
                        One stem arches delicately towards the human figure and has at least three leaves. The other stem grows 
                        upwards and tapers off to the right of the celestial orb. There are several indistinct objects pictured 
                        to the left of the plant. These may be decorative flourishes, insects, or vegetation.
                        One object is pictured to the right of lines 5 and 6. The object consists of a small cluster of lines 
                        to the left of the stem with one long, wavy projection trailing towards the text of the poem. This 
                        object may be a flower with a long stamen or some other vegetative growth. It may also be an animal,
                        perhaps an insect like a caterpillar or worm. Another decorative object appears as an interlinnear design 
                        between lines 6 and 7. A dark spot pictured to the right of line 8 may be an insect, perhaps
                        a fly or beetle. Framing the left side of the poem, vegetation, probably a vine with multiple tendrils, 
                        grows towards the poem's title. At least two distinct vines are pictured, and intertwine. To the left of line 13,
                        two curving, arching stems branch from one of the vines. At least two leaves grow upwards from one of these stems. A 
                        third leaf may grow from the lower stem. The vine terminates above and to the left of line three. 
                        The layers of color and small spots, indistinctly rendered, along these vines may 
                        be insects or vegetation. To the left of line 4, four spots apear in a horizontal line. These may be insects.
                        Along the bottom of the plate, a horizontal line is faintly depicted. This may represent grass or uneven ground.  
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upwards</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>thigh</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the title, a human form hovers or flies with arms lifted upwards,
                            outstretched, and bent. The figure faces up and right and may be female, perhaps the fairy 
                            mentioned in the poem. Its legs are faintly outlined, covered by a robe or a gown which trails 
                            behind the figure. The figure's legs appear to be bent and extend to the left of the figure's upper body,
                            with the right thigh and knee crossed over the left leg, which appears to be streched out and down, 
                            though it is obscured by the figure's gown. The human figure appears to be reaching up and towards a 
                            golden-colored spot that hangs above it and to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>orb</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sun</characteristic> 
                        <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A a golden-colored spot is pictured above and to the right of the human figure.
                            The spot may be a celestial body like the sun or a star.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="B">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>phoenix</characteristic> 
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A bird, probably the 
                            phoenix of the poem, flies to the right of the figure and below the celestial orb. Its outstreached 
                            wings and tail are visible. It faces away or to the right, though its beak and head are indistinctly 
                            rendered.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic> 
                        <characteristic>reed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roots</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic> 
                        <characteristic>catkin</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stamen</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A plant grows vertically along the right side of the plate. The 
                            plant may be sapling or a reed with a slim trunk or stem. Its base is thicker than its stem, suggesting
                            roots. Horizontal growths protrude outwards from 
                            the plant's stem or trunk towards the lines of the text. These are likely leaves or catkins. The plant 
                            branches into two main stems to the right of lines 8 and 9. 
                            One stem arches delicately towards the human figure and has at least three leaves. The other stem grows 
                            upwards and tapers off to the right of the celestial orb. An object is pictured to the right of lines 5 and 6
                            and may be growing from the plant's trunk or stem. The object consists of a small cluster of lines 
                            to the left of the stem with one long, wavy projection trailing towards the text of the poem. This 
                            object may be a flower with a long stamen or some other vegetative growth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Framing the left side of the poem, vegetation, probably a vine with multiple tendrils, 
                            grows towards the poem's title. At least two distinct vines are pictured, and intertwine. To the left of line 13,
                            two curving, arching stems branch from one of the vines. At least two leaves grow upwards from one of these stems. A 
                            third leaf may grow from the lower stem. The vine terminates above and to the left of line three. 
                            The layers of color and small spots, indistinctly rendered, along these vines may 
                            indeterminate vegetative growth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> Along the bottom of the plate, a horizontal line is faintly depicted. This may represent grass 
                            or uneven ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>insect</characteristic> 
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fly</characteristic> 
                        <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several indistinct objects appear clustered in the vegetation to the right and left of the text which
                            may be insects. One object is pictured to the right of lines 5 and 6. The object consists of a small cluster of lines 
                            to the left of the stem with one long, wavy projection trailing towards the text of the poem. This 
                            object may be an insect like a caterpillar or worm. Another decorative object appears as an interlinnear design 
                            between lines 6 and 7, and may be a caterpillar or worm. A dark spot pictured to the right of line 8 may be an insect, perhaps
                            a fly or beetle. Along the vines to the left of the text, the layers of color and small spots, 
                            indistinctly rendered, may be insects. To the left of line 4, four spots apear in a horizontal line. These may be insects.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="B">
                    <illusobjdesc>An indeterminate object appears as an interlinnear design 
                        between lines 6 and 7. Above the word "gay", a wiggling line may represent an insect like a worm or caterpillar
                        or may be an extension of the plant pictured to the right of the text.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="indeterminate" location="B">
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>object</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>animal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An indeterminate object appears as an interlinnear design 
                            between lines 6 and 7. Above the word "gay", a wiggling line may represent an insect like a worm or caterpillar
                            or may be an extension of the plant pictured to the right of the text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.01" justify="left" indent="2">The Phoenix</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.02" justify="left" indent="3">
                        to <choice><orig>
                            M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></orig><reg>Mrs</reg>
                        </choice>
                        Butts
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.03" justify="left">I saw a Bird rise from the East</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.04" justify="left">As a Bird rises from its Nest</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.05" justify="left">With sweetest Songs I ever heard</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.06" justify="left">
                        It sang. I am <choice><orig>
                            M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></orig><reg>Mrs</reg>
                        </choice>
                        Butts's Bird
                        <note>Erdman reads "It sang." as "It sang" (517).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.07" justify="left">And then I saw a Fairy gay</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.08" justify="left">That with this beauteous Bird would play</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.09" justify="left">From a golden cloud she came</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.10" justify="left">
                        She
                        <choice>
                            <orig>calld</orig>
                            <reg>called</reg>
                        </choice>
                        the sweet Bird by its name
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.11" justify="left">
                        She
                        <choice>
                            <orig>call'd</orig>
                            <reg>called</reg>
                        </choice>
                        it Phoenix! Heavens Dove!
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.12" justify="left">
                        She
                        <choice>
                            <orig>call'd</orig>
                            <reg>called</reg>
                        </choice>
                        it all the names of Love
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.13" justify="left">But the Bird flew fast away</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.14" justify="left">Where little Children sport &#38; play</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.15" justify="left">
                        And they
                        <choice>
                            <orig>strok'd</orig>
                            <reg>stroked</reg>
                        </choice>
                        it with their hands
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.16" justify="left">
                        All their
                        <choice>
                            <orig>cooe's</orig>
                            <reg>coos</reg>
                        </choice>
                        it understands
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.17" justify="left">The Fairy to my bosom flew</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.18" justify="left">Weeping tears of morning dew</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.19" justify="left">
                        I said: Thou foolish
                        <choice>
                            <orig>whimpring</orig>
                            <reg>whimpering</reg>
                        </choice>
                        thing
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.20" justify="left">Is not that thy Fairy Ring</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.21" justify="left">Where those Children sport &#38; play</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.22" justify="left">In Fairy fancies light &#38; gay</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.23" justify="left">Seem a Child &#38; be a Child</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.24" justify="left">
                        And the Phoenix is
                        <choice>
                            <orig>beguild</orig>
                            <reg>beguiled</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.25" justify="left">But if thou 
                        <choice>
                            <orig>seem'st</orig>
                            <reg>seemest</reg>
                        </choice>a Fairy thing</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.26" justify="left">Then it flies on glancing wing</l>
                    <l n="bbwba1.1.ms.01.27" justify="left" indent="10">William Blake</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
