<bad id="but119Ar.1" type="penink" work="Goliath Cursing David" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="boston" catalog="butlin" catid="119Ar" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Goliath Cursing David">
                    <main>Goliath Cursing David</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Goliath Cursing David
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.  The pencil drawing on the verso, <hi rend="i">A Pulcinello Frightening a Child(?)</hi>, also dates from c. 1780-85.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>30.2 x 48.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>30.2 x 48.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink<note>A few lines in pencil indicate alternative positions for a few features.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>The leaf of paper shows evidence of a vertical center fold.</note>
                </support>
                <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>Inscribed on the verso, not by Blake, "A warrior haranging his soldiers.  Original drawing by William Blake From the collection of Henry Cunliffe of the South Kensington Museum" and "ow<hi rend="superscript">ner</hi>" (bottom right); "c" over "u" (bottom center).  A piece of paper stuck to the verso is inscribed by Cunliffe, "By William Blake. obit 12 Aug.<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1828.  Read Cunninghams Lives of British Painters-". </note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name>
                <date>1914</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; Frederick Tatham, sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 170 with five other works (14s. to the dealer H. Toovey, possibly acting for Henry Cunliffe); sold from Cunliffe's collection, Sotheby's, 11 May 1895, in lot 98 with three other works (£3.5s. to the dealer Frederick Keppel); David Keppel; given by David Keppel to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, in 1914.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution>
                <addressline>Avenue of the Arts</addressline>
                <addressline>465 Huntington Avenue</addressline>
                <addressline>Boston, Massachusetts 02115-5597</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-617-267-9300</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.mfa.org</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Digital Image Resources: 1-617-369-4338</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Digital Image Resources: 1-617-437-7471</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Digital Image Resources: mfaimages@mfa.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">14.955</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but119Ar.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT119A.1.1r.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Goliath Cursing David</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 119A recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>A pencil sketch, <hi rend="i">A Pulcinello Frightening a Child(?)</hi>, is on the verso of this drawing.  The verso sketch can also be dated to c. 1780-85.  The design in this recto drawing is basically the same as Blake's water color of c. 1803-05, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, Butlin 457.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>30.2 x 48.2 cm</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <related objectid="but457.1.wc.01"/>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design illustrates 1 Samuel 17:41-43.  On the left side of the composition, Goliath, accompanied by his shield-bearer, walks forward and extends his left arm.  With his right arm, he grasps a long pole, probaby the shaft of a spear.  His mouth is open, suggesting he is speaking; he may be cursing David, who stands on the left side of the scene and is identifiable by the shepherd's crook in his right hand.  Facing left, David looks up toward Goliath.  There are at least three figures behind David: a bearded shield-bearer immediately to the left of David raises a flag aloft; the rightmost figure in the composition, also bearded, walks right and raises his right hand; and two figures are positioned right of David, though only the heads of these figures and one shield are visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Goliath</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>giant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>giant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, Goliath walks forward with his left leg extended backward. Taller, larger and more muscular than the other figures, Goliath has short, curly hair and a beard.  He appears to be mostly nude, though drapery (or perhaps a cape?) billows behind his right shoulder and curves around his left thigh; additionally, he may wear some sort of loincloth.  He extends his left arm horizontally, palm facing the viewer, fingers spread, and, with his bent right arm, he grasps a long pole, probably the shaft of a spear.  His mouth is open, suggesting that he is speaking; he may be cursing David at whom he may look.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, Goliath walks forward and holds a long pole, probaby the shaft of a spear, close to his body with his bent right arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of Goliath on the left side of the composition, a male figure walks forward, his left leg extended backward.  He has short, curly hair, and dark shading on his right cheek may suggest a beard.  The parts of his body that are visible appear to be nude.  He turns his head sharply to the right and may look at the figures across from him.  He carries a sword in his right hand, which is by his side, and with his left, he holds a large shield.  These accoutrements may suggest he is a soldier, though he may merely hold them for Goliath.  A few light, pencil lines indicate an alternative position for his lower legs and feet.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of Goliath on the left side of the composition, a male figure walks forward.  He carries a sword in his right hand, which is by his side, and with his left, he holds a large shield.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>David</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Identifiable by the shepherd's crook in his right hand, David stands in contrapposto facing left on the right side of the composition.  He has long, curly hair and appears to wear some kind of gown or drapery around his lower body, though his upper torso is bare.  His left arm is by his side; in his bent right arm he holds the shepherd's crook.  With head tilted slightly up, David appears to look at Goliath and perhaps smile.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, David stands facing left and with his bent right arm holds a shepherd's crook.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are four figures behind David on the right side of the composition.  To the left of David stands or walks a bearded male figure with short, curly hair.  The parts of his body that are visible appears to be nude.  Facing forward, he appears to lean slightly right with his right foot elevated off the ground.  His right arm is raised vertically, and with it, he waves the flagpole of a flag or banner that billows to the left.  With his left arm he holds a shield in front of his torso.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>flagpole</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flag</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>banner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bearded male figure left of David waves with his right arm the flagpole of a flag or banner that billows to the left.  He holds a shield in front of his torso with his left arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are four figures behind David on the right side of the composition.  The rightmost figure stands or walks right but turns his head to look left, perhaps at the other figures.  He has short, curly hair and a beard.  He appears to wear a gown and perhaps also a cape, as billowing drapery is visible behind him.  His right arm is bent with his hand raised, palm out.  A few light pencil lines may indicate an alternative position for his legs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are four figures behind David on the right side of the composition.  Between the rightmost bearded figure and David, there are two figures, though only their heads are visible.  To the right of David, there is a head with long, curly hair turned to face left, though leaning right.  He may have a beard.  A shield is visible below this head and diagonal lines above its head may suggest additional flagpoles or perhaps spears.  To the immediate left of the rightmost figure is another head (only partially visible) with long hair, also partly turned to face left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flagpole</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of David, there is a partially visible figure who appears to hold a shield in front of his torso.  Diagonal lines above this figure's head may suggest additional flagpoles or perhaps spears.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>