<bad id="but184.1" type="wc" work="Pestilence" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="private" catalog="butlin" catid="184">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Pestilence">
                    <main>
                        Pestilence</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 49KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Pestilence*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1779.F">c. 1779</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>13.8 x 18.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.8 x 18.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none<note>Butlin 184 records a "JWHATMAN" watermark on the "mount."  This backing mount may no longer be with the work.</note></watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>private collection</name>
                <date>2014</date>
                <dealer>none recorded</dealer>
                <price>&#163;25,000</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Joseph Hogarth, sold from his collection, Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 21 June 1854, lot 4624, with seven other works by Blake (13s. to "Cowieson," possibly a dealer); Barron Grahame, sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 15 March 1878, probably in lot 22, with five other works by Blake, or lot 23, with one other work by Blake (both lots sold to "Chalmers," possibly a dealer, for &#163;2.11s. and &#163;5.7s.6d. respectively); Robert Carfrae; his son Robert Carfrae Jr., probably by inheritance in 1900; Donald Davidson of Steigal Fine Art, Edinburgh, c. 1980; offered Sotheby's, 8 July 1982, lot 102 (not sold); Robert Tear, London; presumably his estate or heirs in 2011; sold Sotheby's, 9 July 2014, lot 185 (&#163;25,000, apparently to a private collector); presently untraced.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>anonymous private collection</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but184.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT184.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Pestilence</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 184)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This work may be part of a series of water colors Blake executed c. 1779 illustrating major events in the history of England.  These designs may be related to "The History of England, a small book of Engravings" Blake listed in his advertisement "To the Public" of 10 Oct. 1793 (Erdman page 693).  No copy of that "book" has ever been recorded.  See also the list of subjects from the history of England Blake wrote in his Notebook c. 1793 (Erdman page 672).</p></objnote>
                <objsize>13.8 x 18.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design shows a scene of pestilence in a town square or other common area. The background is made up of a large building, possibly St. Paul's Cathedral in London, supported by heavy columns, three of which rest on a set of stairs leading to an entry way. Between the distant columns and the nearer one at left is a tall, arched doorway or monument with an inscription. The middle ground is a street, probably of dirt, and curved lines may suggest paving stones near the left side of the design. The design's upper right quadrant contains another building, much less ornate than the columned structure at left. The second building appears to be constructed partly of brick and partly of wood, and it is covered with a sloping tile roof. An open doorway or window appears in the center of the building's lower level. At left of the structure the back of a wheeled cart or wagon is visible. The scene is populated by at least sixteen figures, many of which are clustered into groups. In the lower lefthand corner, a couple sits propped up against the design's largest column. At left, immediately against the column's base, is a man with short, curly hair who wears a short-sleeved shirt. He faces right, hunches his shoulders forward, and leans his head downward to rest against the head of the woman in front of him, whom he appears to support. His eyes are down, perhaps to look at the woman; alternatively, they may be closed. His right arm dangles at his side. He may be caring for the sick woman in front of him or may be dying himself. Sitting in front of this man, or perhaps in his lap, is a woman with long, curling hair. She wears a gown, the long skirt of which drapes over her legs and onto the ground. The woman's right leg bends sharply, and her right foot is drawn up under her hip, her toes extended toward the ground. Her left leg bends slightly and extends out in front of her, her foot flat on the ground. The woman's shoulders hunch forward as she leans against the man behind her with her arms dangling loosely at her sides. She faces forward, but her eyes are closed and her head leans toward her left shoulder. Her mouth may be open. She appears to be sick and may be dying. Above and to the right of the couple, in the background of the design, a man in black robes and a bicorn hat walks leftward, ringing a bell at his waist. He strides forward with his right foot and holds the bell in his right hand. He appears to hold his left arm horizontally at his waist and may have his left hand thrust into his pocket or into the folds of the robe. He may be a town crier warning of the plague or calling for residents to bring out their dead. Above and to the right of the town crier, in the doorway of the columned building, are at least three nude (male?) figures who kneel at the door. The two rightmost figures face left and raise their arms above their heads. They may be begging for entrance to the building. The leftmost figure bends forward and left in a contracted position. Moving to the right and returning to the design's foreground, a group of three figures appears near the cart or wagon. A short-haired man in a sleeveless shirt and tights(?) faces right and kneels with his left knee on the ground and his left foot flexed to support his weight. The man's right leg is bent forward. On his right knee, and in his arms, is the body of a woman who faces up. His right arm bends slightly to support this woman, and his upper body leans backward. The man's shoulders are hunched forward, and his head tilts downward, his eyes downcast. His mouth may open slightly in an expression of pity, despair, or grief. The woman in his arms wears a long gown, and there is suggestion of some drapery or perhaps her right arm dangling behind the man's back. She is reclined on the man's knee with her knees bent under her slightly. Her breasts appear prominently near the man's right shoulder. She appears to be dead or dying. Above and to the right of this pair, a man wearing a shirt and a hat crouches in the bed of the cart or wagon. He appears to smoke a pipe. He faces left and holds his body in a contracted position with one leg bent forward. His back is nearly horizontal but curves such that his shoulders hunch forward toward the ground. His left arm extends downward and bends at a near-ninety-degree angle. He may reach behind the other man, toward the unseen head of the woman, perhaps to lift her into the cart or wagon. Below this group of figures, near the lower edge of the design, a horse and a man lie prone on the ground. Both appear to be dead. The horse faces leftward with closed eyes and an open mouth. The man lies below or in front of the horse, facing right. He has short hair, and wears a sleeveless shirt and pants. The man lies face down with his visible right arm extended backward along the ground. Another animal, perhaps a dog(?), may lie with legs extended forward and head at left above the figure and left of the horse on the ground. To the right of these figures stands another couple. The man has short hair and wears a short-sleeved gown or tunic that falls just above his knees. He stands, facing forward, with his right knee bent slightly as he supports a woman who appears to be fainting, perhaps from illness. The man's right arm bends around the woman's left shoulder and supports her back; his left arm bends slightly and extends downward beneath her right arm. His head faces left and turns downward as he looks at her. His brows are furrowed, and his mouth opens slightly, suggesting pity or grief. The woman in his arms has curly hair and wears a short-sleeved gown. She stands, facing right, with her left leg extended forward and her right bent back underneath her. Her left foot rests flat on the ground, and her right foot flexes such that the tips of her toes touch the ground directly beneath her hips. Her right arm dangles at her side with her fingers curled backward. Though her shoulders are upright, presumably supported by the man standing behind her, her neck bends backward, and her head faces directly upward. She may be fainting from illness. At right of this couple, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures: one man, three women, and a child. Leftmost is an old man with curly hair and a long beard. He faces right, perhaps bending foreward or kneeling, and may wear a gown. He bends his right arm upward to place the back of his right hand on or near the face of the woman in front of him. His palm is directed back toward his own face, which tilts downward slightly as he looks at the woman. She appears to be sitting, though it is unclear what supports her. She has long hair and wears a gown that is gathered at the waist by a cord or belt. The woman faces forward and to the left toward the old man with her eyes closed and mouth open. He may support her. The woman's legs bend to the right, and the toes of her left foot appear below the hem of her long gown. On her lap rests the body of a child that may be dead or dying. The child is nude and has short hair. He(?) lies supine with his head toward the left, dangling over the edge of the woman's right knee, and his feet toward the right. His right arm rests along his side. His mouth is open, and his eyes appear to be closed. To the right of the woman and child are two other women who face left and appear to be mourning. The woman at left tilts her head downward, perhaps looking at the woman with the child on her lap. The woman at right has her long hair pulled into a bun. She faces left, bends forward at the shoulders, and tilts her head to face the ground with mouth open. Her left arm bends upward, and she holds her left hand near her face. Her right hand may join it in a prayerful posture. She appears to be sitting and looking downward at the dead child. A cloud of smoke appears between the two buildings, perhaps suggesting a fire behind the smaller building. Shadows fill the smaller building's doorway or window and appear on the ground beneath several figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower lefthand corner, a couple sits propped up against the largest column of the building behind them. At left, immediately against the column's base, is a man with short, curly hair who wears a short-sleeved shirt. He faces right, hunches his shoulders forward, and leans his head downward to rest against the head of the woman in front of him, whom he appears to support. His eyes are cast downward toward her, or may be closed. His right arm dangles at his side and touches the arm of the women in front of him. He may be caring for the sick woman in front of him or may be dying himself.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower lefthand corner, a couple sits propped up against the largest column of the building behind them. Sitting at right, in front of the man, or perhaps in his lap, is a woman with long, curling hair. She wears a gown, the long skirt of which drapes over her legs and onto the ground. The woman's right leg bends sharply, and her right foot is drawn up under her hip, her toes extended toward the ground. Her left leg bends slightly and extends out in front of her, her foot flat on the ground. Her left foot may touch the figure lying prone at right. The woman's shoulders hunch forward as she leans against the man behind her with her arms dangling loosely at her sides. She faces forward, but her head leans toward her left shoulder with eyes closed. Her mouth opens slightly, and her face shows despair or resignation. She appears to be sick and may be dying.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bellman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of the couple, in the background of the design, a man in black robes and a bicorn hat walks leftward, ringing a bell at his waist. He strides forward with his right foot and holds the bell in his right hand. He appears to hold his left arm horizontally at his waist and may have his left hand thrust into his pocket or into the folds of the robe. He may be a town crier warning of the plague or calling for residents to bring out their dead.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                    	<characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of the town crier, in the doorway of the columned building, are at least three nude (male?) figures who kneel at the door. The two rightmost figures face left and raise at least one arm above their heads. The leftmost figure kneels facing left in a contracted position. They may be begging for entrance to the building.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures appear in or behind the cart or wagon visible at left of the brick wall of the smaller building. A short-haired man in a sleeveless shirt and tights(?) faces right and kneels with his left knee on the ground and his left foot flexed to support his weight. The man's right leg bends sharply in front of him. On his right knee, and in his arms, is the body of a woman who may be dead or dying. His right arm bends slightly to support her, and his upper body leans backward with her weight. The man's shoulders are hunched forward, and his head tilts downward, his eyes downcast. His mouth opens slightly in an expression of pity, despair, or grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures appear in or behind the cart or wagon visible at left of the brick wall of the smaller building. In the arms of the kneeling man is the body of a woman with her head toward the left. She wears a long gown, and there is suggestion of some drapery, or perhaps her right arm, dangling behind the man's back. She is reclined on the man's knee with her knees bent under her slightly. Her head is not visible, though her breasts appear prominently near the man's right shoulder. She appears to be dead or dying, and may be in the process of being placed in the cart or wagon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent at 90 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures appear in or behind the cart or wagon visible at left of the brick wall of the smaller building. Above and to the right of the man supporting the woman's body, a man who wears a shirt and hat appears to crouch in the bed of the cart or wagon. He also smokes a pipe. He faces left and holds his body in a contracted position with one leg bent beneath him. His back is nearly horizontal but curves such that his shoulders hunch forward as he leans toward the woman at left. His left arm extends downward and bends at a near-ninety-degree angle, perhaps touching the woman. He may be helping move the woman into the cart or wagon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the lower edge of the design a horse and a man lie prone on the ground. Both appear to be dead. The horse faces leftward with its head and neck extended along the ground. Its eyes are closed and its mouth is open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the lower edge of the design a horse and a man lie prone on the ground. Both appear to be dead. The man lies below or in front of the horse, facing right. He has short hair, and wears a sleeveless shirt and pants. The man lies face down with his visible right arm extended backward along the ground, perhaps touching the foot or leg of the woman at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another animal, perhaps a dog(?), may lie with legs extended forward and head at left above the prone figure and left of the horse lying in the central foreground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>man</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pity</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the dead horse and man stands another couple. The man has short hair and wears a short-sleeved gown or tunic that falls just above his knees. He stands, facing forward, with his right knee bent slightly as he supports a woman who appears to be fainting, perhaps from illness. The man's right arm bends around the woman's left shoulder and supports her back; his left arm bends slightly and extends downward beneath her right arm. His head faces left and turns downward as he looks at her. His brows are furrowed, and his mouth opens slightly, suggesting pity or grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fainting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the dead horse and man stands another couple. The woman has curly hair and wears a long, short-sleeved gown. The woman stands, facing right, with her left leg extended forward and her right bent back underneath her. Her left foot rests flat on the ground, and her right foot flexes such that the tips of her toes touch the ground directly beneath her hips. Her right arm dangles at her side with her fingers curled backward. Though her shoulders are upright, presumably supported by the man standing behind her, her neck bends backward, and her head faces directly upward. She may be fainting from illness.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the fainting woman, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures. Leftmost is an old man with curly hair and a long beard. He faces right and may stand or kneel. He bends his right arm upward to place the back of his right hand on or near the face of the woman in front of him. His palm is directed back toward his own face, which tilts downward slightly as he looks at the woman.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the fainting woman, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures. The leftmost woman of the group appears to be sitting, though it is unclear what supports her. She wears a gown that is gathered at the waist by a cord or belt. The woman faces forward and to the left, turning over her right shoulder with eyes closed toward the old man with her mouth slightly open. He may support her. Her left arm is visible dangling at her side. The woman's legs bend to the right, and the toes of her left foot appear below the hem of her long gown. On her lap rests the body of a child that may be dead or dying. Her facial expression shows grief or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the fainting woman, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures. On the lap of one of the women rests the body of a child that may be dead or dying. The (male?) child is nude and has short hair. He lies supine with his head toward the left, dangling over the edge of the woman's right knee, and his feet toward the right. His right arm rests along his side. His mouth is open, and his eyes appear to be closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the woman and child are two other gowned women who face left and appear to be mourning. The woman at left has curly hair. She tilts her head downward, perhaps looking at the woman with the child on her lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the woman and child are two other gowned women who face left and appear to be mourning. The woman at far right wears a gown and has her long hair pulled into a bun. She faces left, bends forward at the shoulders, and tilts her head to face the ground. Her left arm bends upward, and she holds her left hand near her face. Her right hand may join it in a prayerful posture. She appears to be sitting and looking downward at the dead child.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stairs</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>St. Paul's Cathedral</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>London</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background contains a large building, possibly St. Paul's Cathedral in London, supported by heavy columns, at least three of which rest on a set of stairs leading to an entry way. Between the distant columns and the nearer one at left is a tall, arched doorway or monument with an inscription, "Lord have / m &#8212;<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> on us" (see Diplomatic Transcription). Another door may appear faintly atop the stairs at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right, a second building appears to be constructed partly of brick and partly of wood, and it is covered with a sloping tile roof. An open doorway or window appears in the center of the building's lower level.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>cart</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wagon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wheel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the structure in the right foreground, the rear right wheel and the back of a cart or wagon are visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>street</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design's middle ground is a street, probably of dirt. Curved lines may suggest paving stones near the center at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plague</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows a scene of pestilence or plague in a town square or other common area. Many figures appear to be sick, dying, or dead from plague.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cloud of smoke appears between the two buildings, perhaps suggesting a fire behind the smaller building.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadows appear in the smaller building's doorway or window and beneath several figures in the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="3"/>
                <p n="but184.1.1.wc.01" justify="left" indent="3">Lord have<note>Lines 1 and 2 are written on the door of the building upper left.  All inscriptions are in pen and ink.</note></p>
                <p n="but184.1.1.wc.02" justify="left" indent="3">m &#8212;<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> on us</p>
                <vspace extent="6"/>
                <p n="but184.1.1.wc.03" justify="left" indent="22">WB</p>
                
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
