<bad id="but167.1" type="mono" work="Daniel" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="167">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Daniel">
                    <main>
                        Daniel</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
                </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 24KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries
                <date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
            </filedesc>
            <userestrict>Copyright © 
                <date>2024</date> 
                by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. 
                Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. 
                Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires 
                express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher.
                Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
                granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>April 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Daniel
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake 
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1785.I">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>14.2 x 10.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>JWHATMAN</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick 
                    Tatham, probably upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold by Tatham to the British Museum in Oct. 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Museum number">1867,1012.203</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but167.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT167.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Daniel</title>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 167)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>This is one of seven monochrome wash drawings (Objects 37-43) by Blake of figures painted by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel. They were very probably copied from the engravings of Adamo Ghisi, after drawings by Giorgio Ghisi, published in *Pitture dipinte nella Volta della Capella Sistina nel Vaticano* (1773).</p>
                    <p>Frederick Tatham added a pen and ink inscription in the lower right corner of the leaf bearing this wash drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing after Michelangelo shows the biblical figure Daniel with two smaller figures. In the drawing's center, Daniel sits on a low step or platform in the corner of a room with bare walls and a bare floor. Daniel has short, wavy hair and wears many layers of clothing: a long gown, a cape over his shoulders, and a fringed piece of draping cloth over his legs. Daniel sits with his knees bent and spread. His right leg is drawn up near to his body, and his right foot rests on the ground at the base of the step on which he sits. Daniel's left leg bends outward and extends forward, toward the viewer, and his prominent left foot rests on the ground at the lower edge of the drawing (which curves inward at the edges). Daniel's body faces the viewer but bends leftward at the waist, leaning to the side and dropping his right shoulder as he writes on a tablet next to him. The tablet is angled away from Daniel and rests on a stand. The upper portion of the stand is triangular in shape and is supported by a smaller rectangular piece, leaving an open area near Daniel's cape. In that empty space is a small scroll. On the left side of the stand, some other object is attached. It may provide storage for writing utensils. Daniel's right forearm extends outward along the tablet, and he grasps a quill or other implement as he writes near the top of the tablet. Daniel's head leans toward this tablet and tilts downward, but he does not appear to look at the tablet but instead at the ground. His eyes may even be closed. His mouth may be open. Daniel's left arm extends forward and to the right, bending sharply at the wrist. His left hand rests on the edge of another tablet; his index and middle fingers point downward. This second tablet is much larger than the first. It rests in Daniel's lap and leans out ward from him (toward the viewer). Beneath this tablet, perhaps hanging on it or supporting it, is a nude male child. This child, much smaller than Daniel, faces forward and to the left. His right leg nearly straightens as his foot rests on the ground near Daniel's right foot. The child's left leg bends inward, and his right foot is hidden behind the draping of Daniel's gown. The child's genitals appear between his slightly spread legs. He bends forward as if holding the tablet on his back. The child's right arm bends sharply as his elbow rises into the air beside his head and his right hand reaches toward his back. The child's left arm reaches upward, and he grasps the edge of the tablet with his left hand. His head lowers, and his eyes close. The child has short hair. A second child appears above Daniel's left shoulder. Now absent from Michelangelo's fresco, this child is almost entirely covered by a large cloak which extends from Daniel's neck at left to his elbow at right. The child faces the viewer and leans forward but looks to the left, perhaps toward Daniel's writing. The child's gender is uncertain. The left wall and rise of the step or platform are shaded; shadows appear at right of Daniel's neck and in the lower right-hand corner of the drawing beneath the larger tablet and Daniel's left leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Daniel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the drawing's center, Daniel sits on a low step or platform in the corner of a room with bare walls and a bare floor. Daniel has short, wavy hair and wears many layers of clothing: a long gown, a cape over his shoulders, and a fringed piece of draping cloth over his legs. Daniel sits with his knees bent and spread. His right leg is drawn up near to his body, and his right foot rests on the ground at the base of the step on which he sits. Daniel's left leg bends outward and extends forward, toward the viewer, and his prominent left foot rests on the ground at the lower edge of the drawing (which curves inward at the edges). Daniel's body faces the viewer but bends leftward at the waist, leaning to the side and dropping his right shoulder as he writes on a tablet next to him. Daniel's right forearm extends outward along the tablet, and he grasps a quill or other implement as he writes near the top of the tablet. Daniel's head leans toward this tablet and tilts downward, but he does not appear to look at the tablet but instead at the ground. His eyes may even be closed. His mouth may be open. Daniel's left arm extends forward and to the right, bending sharply at the wrist. His left hand rests on the edge of another tablet; his index and middle fingers point downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hanging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath the larger tablet, perhaps hanging on it or supporting it, is a nude male child. This child, much smaller than Daniel, faces forward and to the left. His right leg nearly straightens as his foot rests on the ground near Daniel's right foot. The child's left leg bends inward, and his right foot is hidden behind the draping of Daniel's gown. The child's genitals appear between his slightly spread legs. He bends forward as if holding the tablet on his back. The child's right arm bends sharply as his elbow rises into the air beside his head and his right hand reaches toward his back. The child's left arm reaches upward, and he grasps the edge of the tablet with his left hand. His head lowers, and his eyes close. The child has short hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>faces forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second child appears above Daniel's left shoulder. Now absent from Michelangelo's fresco, this child is almost entirely covered by a large cloak which extends from Daniel's neck at left to his elbow at right. The child faces the viewer and leans forward but looks to the left, perhaps toward Daniel's writing. The child's gender is uncertain.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>easel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The drawing contains two tablets. The first appears at left of Daniel and rests on a stand; it is angled away from him. The upper portion of the stand is triangular in shape and is supported by a smaller rectangular piece, leaving an open area near Daniel's cape. In that empty space is a small scroll. On the left side of the stand, some other object is attached. It may provide storage for writing utensils. The second tablet is much larger than the first. It rests in Daniel's lap and leans out ward from him (toward the viewer).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Daniel sits on a low step or platform in the corner of a room with bare walls and a bare floor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>The left wall and rise of the step or platform are shaded; shadows appear at right of Daniel's neck and in the lower right-hand corner of the drawing beneath the larger tablet and Daniel's left leg.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
        <phystext>
            <lg>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.01"><space extent="18" unit="character"/>DANIEL</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="10" unit="character"/>
            <lg><l n="but167.1.wd.01.02" justify="left"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen"><space extent="35" unit="character"/>William Blake</hi></l>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.03" justify="left"><space extent ="37.5" unit="character"/><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">After<choice>
                    <orig>Michael Angelo</orig>
                    <reg>Michelangelo</reg>
                </choice>
                </hi>
                </l>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.04" justify="left"><space extent="42" unit="character"/><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Frederick Tatham</hi></l>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.05" justify="left"><space extent="49.5" unit="character"/><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">&#8212;&#8212;</hi></l>
            </lg>
        </phystext>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
