<bad id="but122r.1" type="mono" work="The Good Farmer" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="122r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Good Farmer">
                    <main>
                        The Good Farmer</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>December 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>May 1999</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
               <name>David Cosca</name> and
               <name>Robert Bingler</name>
               <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Good Farmer
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.L">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>33.6 x 47.3 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>33.6 x 47.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>The work was seriously damaged in 1977; see the Note on Provenance.  The leaf was subsequently repaired.</note></support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Collection of Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1977</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>$159</price>
                <note>Early history not known; Alexander Macmillan by 1876; William Augustus White; acquired by the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach from White's estate in 1927; George C. Smith, Jr., sold from his collection, Parke-Bernet auction, New York, 2 Nov. 1938, lot 103 ($375 to the dealer R. Allan, possibly acting for the vendor's sister Mrs. Artemas Holmes); Dorothy S. Holmes by inheritance; offered from the estate of Dorothy S. Holmes, Sotheby's, 18 Nov. 1976, lot 163 (not sold on an estimate of &#163;3000-4000); agreement to purchase made between the estate of Dorothy S. Holmes and Robert N. Essick in summer 1977 but seriously damaged during transport from Sotheby's New York to Sotheby's Los Angeles; the drawing, now in several separate pieces, acquired by Sotheby's insurance company, late summer 1977; acquired by Essick from the insurance company for $159 in Oct. 1977 and subsequently repaired.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but122.1.1r.wd.01" dbi="BUT122.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Good Farmer</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 122 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>33.6 x 47.3 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Blake developed this subject and basic composition through a series of seven or eight further drawings, including Butlin 120 recto, 120A recto and verso, 121, 122 verso, 123 recto, 124, and possibly untraced 125, *Christ as the Good Shepherd*.  The pen and ink drawing on the verso of this wash drawing is one of these versions of the same subject and basic design.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The general theme and subject of this composition were probably influenced by several biblical passages, including Ruth 2:1-17, I Samuel 12:16-19, and Matthew 9:38.  This design depicts a field of grain and, near it, a Christ-like figure surrounded by other figures who seek his aid. This particular drawing differs from others in the set by omitting the buildings found in the left distance (which appear in all other versions), by showing traces of an erased figure at left of the Christ figure, and by replacing the gleaning woman (who appears in the lower righthand corner of some versions) with a small girl. This girl faces left, and she crouches low and strides forward with her right leg, on which a sheaf of grain appears to rest. Alternatively, she may kneel on the ground. Her left leg bends and extends backward; her left arm is raised horizontally, extending forward to grasp another piece of grain. Her right arm may join it. The girl leans forward as she gleans, and her head tilts downward slightly as her eyes close in a solemn or even despairing expression. She has long, curly hair and wears a long-sleeved gown that extends to her ankles. In front of the girl, at the left edge of the grain field, stands the "good farmer," who has been identified with Christ. The farmer has long hair and a beard; he wears a long-sleeved gown that reaches his ankles. The farmer's body faces forward and to the right; his right leg extends forward as if stepping toward the viewer. He extends both arms toward the young girl at right, his palms facing away from him and slightly upward. His mouth may be open. The farmer turns his head to the left and, though his eyes appear to be closed, could be looking back at the group of figures who kneel behind him. Three of these figures face rightward, and one faces away and to the left. They are, from left to right: a man with short, curly hair who is mostly hidden by the other figures, and who looks upward toward the farmer; a long-haired woman who faces right, leans forward, and reaches out with both arms toward the farmer as she gazes up toward him; a small male(?) child who kneels, facing left, and hides his face in the woman's skirt; and a bearded man who kneels, facing right, and lowers his left arm as he gazes upward toward the farmer. Above these figures is the shadow of another, apparently erased, who faces right and reaches toward the farmer's shoulder. Another shadowy figure who may be female appears over the field of grain, just above the gleaning girl. This figure may also have been erased. The figure faces left and bends over, extending both arms downward toward the same sheaf of grain that the young girl grasps. The woman appears to have long hair, and there is slight indication of eyes, a nose, and a mouth. To the right of the farmer, behind the edge of the grain field, stands another male figure who faces right and extends his bent arms across the top of the grain field. His palms face one another, hovering over the grain. He has long hair and a long beard, and his eyes are raised toward the sky. In the upper righthand corner, another field of grain appears in the distance. Curved lines above the field suggest smoke, indicating that the field may be on fire. To the right of the field stand five(?) figures. The two figures at left stand, facing left toward the field, and raising their arms above their heads. The three figures at right may also face the field, or they may turn away from it, facing the design's right border. Two prominent shadows appear in the design, in addition to the faded figures surrounding the main field of grain. One of these appears on the ground at left of the standing Christ figure, behind the young boy. The other appears behind the small girl who gleans in the lower righthand quadrant.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>harvesting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A small girl stands before a large area of waist-high grain (perhaps wheat or corn). She may be gathering the grain. This girl faces left, and she crouches low and strides forward with her right leg, on which a sheaf of grain appears to rest. Alternatively, she may kneel on the ground. Her left leg bends and extends backward; her left arm is raised horizontally, extending forward to grasp another piece of grain. Her right arm may join it. The girl leans forward as she gleans, and her head tilts downward slightly as her eyes close in a solemn or even despairing expression. She has long, curly hair and wears a long-sleeved gown that extends to her ankles.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>farmer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of the girl, at the left edge of the grain field, stands the "good farmer," who has been identified with Christ. The farmer has long hair and a beard; he wears a long-sleeved gown that reaches his ankles. The farmer's body faces forward and to the right; his right leg extends forward as if stepping toward the viewer. He extends both arms toward the young girl at right, his palms facing away from him and slightly upward. His mouth may be open. The farmer turns his head to the left and, though his eyes appear to be closed, could be looking back at the group of figures behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," four figures kneel and appear to be asking for aid. Leftmost is a man with short, curly hair who is mostly hidden by the other figures. He faces rightward and looks up at the farmer. He is at least partly nude.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," four figures kneel and appear to be asking for aid. Second from left--and the most prominent figure of the group--is a woman who reaches out with both arms toward the farmer. The woman has long, curly hair, and she wears a short-sleeved gown that gathers in folds around her ankles as she kneels on the ground, facing right. She bends forward at the waist, leaning toward the farmer as she gazes up toward him. Her arms extend outward and upward; her pams face one another, and her fingers are spread. The woman's mouth opens, suggesting an expression of despair, or perhaps that she speaks to the farmer. She may be the mother of the child who hides his face in her skirt.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," four figures kneel and appear to be asking for aid. A small male(?) child kneels, facing left, and hides his face in the woman's skirt. The back of his head is covered with short, dark hair. He is nude from the waist up, and is covered by a skirt or other garment from the waist down. His visible left foot is flexed, and he may sit on his heels. His left arm bends sharply upward, and his fingers are spread. He may clutch the garment of the woman in front of him, perhaps his mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," four figures kneel and appear to be asking for aid. Rightmost in the group is curly-haired, bearded man who kneels, facing right, and gazes upward toward the farmer. His body is mostly hidden by the woman at his right, but he appears to wear a gown secured with a belt, or perhaps a skirt and shirt. His bare left arm extends downward, and his open palm faces the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the four supplicating figures is the shadow of another. It may be an erased figure, or it may be a shadow of the kneeling female figure. This figure is larger than the others and appears to stand rather than kneel. She(?) faces right, bends forward, and reaches toward the farmer's shoulder with an extended right arm that bends upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gleaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another shadowy figure who may be female appears over the field of grain, just above the gleaning girl. This figure--much larger than the girl--may also have been erased. The figure faces left and bends over, extending both arms downward toward the same sheaf of grain that the young girl grasps. The woman appears to have long hair, and there is slight indication of eyes, a nose, and a mouth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the farmer, behind the edge of the grain field, stands another male figure who faces right and extends his bent arms across the top of the grain field. His palms face inward, hovering over the grain. The man has long hair and a long beard, and he wears a long-sleeved shirt or gown. His head tilts upward as he raises his eyes toward the sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The farmer figure and young girl in the foreground stand near a large area of waist-high grain (perhaps wheat or corn). A second grain field appears in the background, near the design's upper righthand corner. This second field may be on fire, as curved lines above it suggest smoke.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are five(?) figures. The leftmost figure stands, facing left toward the field, and raises at least one arm above his(?) head. His left leg bends and extends backward, perhaps indicating that he is walking.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
						<characteristic>male</characteristic>
						<characteristic>female</characteristic>
						<characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are five(?) figures. Next to the striding figure with raised arm(s) stands another, to the right and behind him. This figure also faces left, toward the field, and may raise one arm overhead. This figure also appears to wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are five(?) figures. At right of the two figures with raised arms, a group of three figures of indeterminate gender stands clustered together. It is unclear whether they also face the field or face away, toward the design's right border.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In addition to the faded figures surrounding the main field of grain, two prominent areas of shadow appear in the design. One appears on the ground at left of the standing Christ figure, behind the young boy. The other appears behind the small girl who gleans in the lower righthand quadrant.</illusobjdesc>
					</component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
