<bad id="but155.1" type="wc" work="Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="butlin" catid="155">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him">
                    <main>
                        Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him</main>  : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 41KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Fitzwilliam Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.A">c. 1785</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>40.3 x 56.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>40.3 x 56.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1900</date>
                <dealer>Robert Dunthorne</dealer>
                <price>&#163;55 for all three finished water colors based on the story of Joseph and his brethren.</price>
                <note>According to Alexander Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake* (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1:57, "the three *Joseph* drawings [this work and *Joseph Ordering Simeon to Be Bound* and *Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren*, Butlin 156 and 157] turned up within the last ten years in their original close rose-wood frames (a far from advantageous setting), at a broker's in Wardour Street [London], who had purchased them at a furniture-sale in the neighbourhood"; sold from the collection of "An Old-Established Printseller" (Walter E. Tiffin, according to Butlin 155), Sotheby's, 8 March 1860, lot 1826, with the two other *Joseph* designs noted above (&#163;10.5s. to the dealer H. Palser acting for James H. Chance); John Duke Coleridge, 1st Baron Coleridge, by 1862 (according to Butlin 155; listed in the collection of "Mr. J. D. Coleridge" by W. M. Rossetti in Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake*, 1863, 2:202); sold anonymously, Christie's, 12 Dec. 1898, lot 62, this drawing only (&#163;10.10s. to the dealer Robert Dunthorne); all three *Joseph* works sold by Dunthorne in 1900 for &#163;55 to the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, England.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">456A</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but155.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT155.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 155)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>40.3 x 56.2 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design illustrates Genesis 42:6. An indoor space with decorative tile flooring and shadowy walls hosts Joseph, ten of his brothers, and two other figures who appear to be servants. In the right half of the design, Joseph sits on a curved chair with legs that curve outward as they approach the ground. He has long, curly hair and wears a long-sleeved gown with a belt at the waist and a long piece of fabric secured with a ring at his left shoulder. This cloth covers his chest and right arm, and drapes over part of the chair beneath him. A sandal adorns his visible left foot. Joseph's body faces left as he sits in a reclined position with his knees bent and his left leg extended in front of him; his right foot is drawn back underneath him slightly. He twists at the waist so that his torso faces the viewer. Joseph's head turns toward the right, and his chin lifts as he tilts his head upward and gazes toward the ceiling. His mouth opens. Joseph's left arm bends sharply as he brings his hand in front of his chest, perhaps resting it there with his fingers curved. He raises his right arm, which is covered by the draping fabric, and bends it to rest his right hand on top of his head. The fingers of this hand curve as well, giving the impression that he scratches his head. The fabric wraps around this hand and falls away from it in graceful folds toward Joseph's waist. Across from Joseph, ten male figures (presumably Joseph's brothers) approach from the left side of the design. They appear in two rows: three bowing in front and seven standing in back. In the front row, farthest left, is a muscular man with long, curly hair and a beard. He is nude from the waist up, and a long draping garment covers him from the waist down. He wears sandals on his feet, both of which are visible beneath the hem of his robe. He stands with his weight on his left foot and his right leg bent such that his heel rises off the ground slightly. His back hunches over in a posture of genuflection, and both arms are lowered toward the ground. His palms face inward, toward each other, and the fingers of both hands are spread. The man's head is lowered as he gazes at the ground or toward Joseph's foot. To the right of this man (and partially hidden by him) is an older man with short, curly, white hair and a beard of similar color and texture. He also assumes a deferential posture, standing and bowing with his head and eyes lowered. This man's robe covers his shoulders and flows toward his ankles, but his bare right foot is visible as his leg extends forward slightly. His arms cross in front of his chest, and each hand grasps the crook of the other arm. The third man in this group, who appears to the right of the older man and is partially concealed by him, likewise stands and bows with his head and eyes lowered toward the ground. A long, draping robe covers all but his chest, his right hand, and his right foot. He has long hair and a short beard. He holds his hand at waist level with the fingers curved downward, perhaps grasping part of his garment. Seven figures stand behind these bowing brothers, and most in this second row are only visible from the shoulders up. They are, from left to right: a gowned man who stands, facing right, and looks at the figure in front of him; a gowned man with long hair or a head covering curled at the ends, facing away from the viewer but turning and facing left toward the man behind him; a man with short, curly hair who faces right and tilts his head downward slightly but appears to look straight ahead; a long-haired man who faces right, bowing his head and lowering his eyes; a man with short curly hair and a curly beard who wears a gown or robe and faces forward but turns his head to look directly right; the face of another man(?) who turns in the opposite direction, looking left toward the other figures; and a gowned man with long curly hair and a beard whose torso faces forward and to the right but who twists to look left at the men behind him. In the center of the design, between the brothers on the left and Joseph on the right, are two additional figures who may be servants. A partly nude woman stands, facing away and to the left, or she may walk toward the left side of the design. A skirt covers her from the waist down. Her hair is pulled into a bun that is covered with a cross-hatched object, perhaps netting of some sort. Her bare left foot strides forward. The woman's left breast is visible, though shadowed by her left arm. She holds both arms upward, bending them at ninety-degree angles to hold a wide bowl, basket, or other container atop her head. Her head turns to the left, and she looks straight in front of her as she carries the basket. Behind her, a male(?) figure bends forward and walks, carrying what appears to be a large sheath of grain. His left foot extends forward as he strides toward the left side of the design. His shoulders are hunched over, and one of his arms bends upward to hold the edge of the sheath at the top of his head. His head and eyes are lowered. To the right of these background figures, above and to the right of Joseph's head, are three much smaller figures that appear in shadows or have perhaps been painted onto the wall. The first, at left, is an angel of uncertain gender who stands, facing forward, with arms lowered at 45 degrees and palms facing the viewer. The angel has long hair and appears to wear a gown. Two large wings rise upward from the angel's shoulders. Next to the angel, in the upper righthand corner of the design, two figures of similar size kneel, facing right. Their bald heads suggest that they are male. The figure at right is slightly more defined. He kneels with his right leg forward and left leg bent and extended behind him. His upper body leans forward, and there is suggestions of his arms extending out in front of him. His head tilts upward. The other man kneels beside him in similar posture, though his arms and legs are not visible. This area and the walls of the room appear in shadows, but they are particularly dark behind and below Joseph, as well as in the area around his feet.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>Joseph</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ring</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on chest</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the right half of the design, Joseph sits on a curved chair with legs that curve outward as they approach the ground. He has long, curly hair and wears a long-sleeved gown with a belt at the waist and a long piece of fabric secured with a ring at his left shoulder. The cloth covers his chest and right arm, and drapes over part of the chair beneath him. A sandal adorns his visible left foot. Joseph's body faces left as he sits in a reclined position with his knees bent and his left leg extended in front of him; his right foot is drawn back underneath him slightly. He twists at the waist, such that his torso faces the viewer. Joseph's head turns toward the right, and his chin lifts as he tilts his head upward and gazes toward the ceiling. His mouth opens. Joseph's left arm bends sharply as he brings his hand in front of his chest, perhaps resting it there with his fingers curved. He raises his right arm, which is covered by the draping fabric, and bends it to rest his right hand on top of his head. The fingers of this hand curve as well, giving the impression that he scratches his head. The fabric wraps around this hand and falls away from it in graceful folds toward Joseph's waist.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Across from Joseph, ten figures (presumably Joseph's brothers) approach from the left side of the design. They appear in two rows: three bowing in front and seven standing in back. Most of the figures in the second row are only visible from the shoulders up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the front row, farthest left, is a muscular man with long, curly hair and a beard. He is nude from the waist up, and a long draping garment covers him from the waist down. He wears sandals on his feet, both of which are visible beneath the hem of his robe. He stands with his weight on his left foot and his right leg bent such that his heel rises off the ground slightly. His back hunches over in a posture of genuflection, and both arms are lowered toward the ground. His palms face inward, toward each other, and the fingers of both hands are spread. The man's head is lowered as he gazes at the ground or toward Joseph's foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms folded</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the front row of brothers (and partially hidden by the man farthest left) is an older man with short, curly, white hair and a beard of similar color and texture. He stands and bows with his head and eyes lowered. This man's robe covers his shoulders and flows toward his ankles, but his bare right foot is visible as his leg extends forward slightly. His arms cross in front of his chest, and each hand grasps the crook of the other arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third man in the front row of Joseph's brothers, who appears to the right of the older man and is partially concealed by him, stands and bows with his head and eyes lowered toward the ground. A long, draping robe covers all but his chest, his right hand, and his right foot. He has long hair and a short beard. He holds his hand at waist level with the fingers curved downward, perhaps grasping part of his garment.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Farthest left is a gowned man who stands, facing right, and looks at the figure in front of him at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Second from left is a gowned man with long hair or a head covering curled at the ends. His body faces away from the viewer but his head faces left to look toward the man behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Third from left is a man with short, curly hair. He faces right and tilts his head downward slightly but appears to look straight ahead to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Fourth from left is a long-haired man facing forward and right. He bows his head and lowers his eyes, perhaps to gaze toward the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Fifth from left is a man with short curly hair and a curly beard who wears a gown or robe. His torso faces forward but he turns his head to the right to look straight in front of him, perhaps at the figures in the center of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Sixth from left is the face of another man(?) who turns back to the left, looking toward the other figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand behind the bowing brothers. Farthest right is a gowned man with long curly hair and a beard. His torso faces forward and to the right, but he twists backward to look at the men behind him at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>net</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breast</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, between the brothers on the left and Joseph on the right, are two additional figures who may be servants. A partly nude woman stands, facing away and to the left, or she may walk toward the left side of the design. A skirt covers her from the waist down. Her hair is pulled into a bun that is covered with a cross-hatched object, perhaps netting of some sort. Her bare left foot strides forward. The woman's left breast is visible, though covered by the shadow of her left arm. She holds both arms upward, bending them at ninety-degree angles to hold a wide bowl, basket, or other container atop her head. Her head turns to the left, and she looks straight in front of her as she carries the basket.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, between the brothers on the left and Joseph on the right, are two additional figures who may be servants. Behind a woman carrying a large basket, a male(?) figure bends forward and left and walks, carrying what appears to be a large sheaf of grain. His left foot extends forward as he strides toward the left side of the design. His shoulders are hunched over, and one of his arms bends upward to hold the edge of the sheaf at the top of his head. His head tilts downward as he looks toward the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wings</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of Joseph's head are three much smaller figures that appear in shadows or have perhaps been painted onto the wall. At left, the first is an angel of uncertain gender who stands, facing forward, with arms lowered at 45 degrees and palms facing the viewer. The angel has long hair and appears to wear a gown. Two large wings rise upward and outward from the angel's shoulders.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of Joseph's head are three  much smaller figures that appear in shadows or have perhaps been painted onto the wall. In the upper righthand corner of the design, two figures of similar size kneel, facing right. Their bald heads suggest that they are male. The figure at right is slightly more defined. He kneels with his right leg forward and left leg bent and extended behind him. His upper body leans forward, and there is suggestions of his arms extending out in front of him. His head tilts upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of Joseph's head are three much smaller figures that appear in shadows or have perhaps been painted onto the wall. In the upper righthand corner of the design, two figures of similar size kneel, facing right. Their bald heads suggest that they are male. The figure at left is less defined than the one at right. He kneels with his upper body leans forward, and his head tilts upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Joseph sits on a curved chair with legs that curve outward as they approach the ground. It appears to be made of wood and may feature decorative carvings on the visible (back left) leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The setting is an indoor space with decorative tile flooring and shadowy walls.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The walls of the room appear in shadows, but they are particularly dark behind and below Joseph, as well as in the area around his feet.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
