<bad id="but158" type="wc" work="" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="158">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Sketch for 'Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound'">
                    <main>
                        Sketch for Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 37KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Sketch for "Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound"*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.B">c. 1785</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>33.6 x 47.8 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>33.6 x 47.8 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color<note>The water colors are faded.</note></medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>2013</date>
                <dealer>John Windle</dealer>
                <price>&#163;27,500</price>
                <note>Early history not known; Alexander Macmillan by 1876; his daughter, Mrs. Norman Maclehose, probably by inheritance in 1896; her daughter, Mrs. Arthur Moberley; her daughter, Mrs. B. Clarke; sold by Clarke, Sotheby's, 24 June 1971, lot 108 (&#163;2800 to "Mrs. Mazzolini" according to Butlin 158); private collection, Milan, Italy; sold Sotheby's, 3 July 2013, lot 160 (&#163;27,500 to the dealer John Windle acting for Robert N. Essick).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but158.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT158.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketch for Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="B1">(BUT158.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This is a full-size preliminary water color drawing for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum (Object 23, Butlin 156).</p></objnote>
                <objsize>33.6 x 47.8 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This sketch illustrates Genesis 42:19, 25, and anticipates Blake's more finished watercolor of the same design (Butlin 156). In the right third of the design, Joseph's brother Simeon is being bound at the wrists by another man, presumably one of Joseph's servants. Simeon kneels in a lunging position, facing the right edge of the design with his left leg forward and his right leg extended behind him with toes flexed. Both legs are bent; the right is bare from the knee down, while the left is mostly covered by a cloth that wraps around Simeon's back. He is nude from the waist up, and his torso faces forward and to the right. His arms extend downward and to the right; the left arm bends slightly. Simeon's palms face one another, and his fingers are spread as the servant clasps manacles around both wrists. Simeon twists at the shoulders and neck, turning his head to the left and looking at the brothers behind him. He has a short hair and a beard. His mouth opens slightly, and his expression suggests fear or despair. The man who binds Simeon stands to the right of him, facing forward and to the left. He has short, curly hair and a beard; he is nude from the waist up but may be covered by a skirt or other garment from waist to knees. He stands with his left foot forward, just to the right of Simeon's. He bends at the waist, lowering his left arm to secure the shackles around Simeon's wrists. His right arm bends at approximately ninety degrees, and he holds his forearm horizontally across his waist. In his right hand he holds a chain that extends down to the manacles in his left hand. The man's head turns downward and to the left; his eyes are downcast, likely to look toward Simeon. To the left of Simeon and his captor, on a raised platform, a male figure (very probably Joseph) sits sideways on a throne-like chair and leans against its back. He faces right and sits with his left knee forward, his left foot drawn back underneath him, and his right leg bent and extended back behind him in a position that mimics Simeon's. Joseph leans forward and extends his bent arms in front of him to rest his elbows on the chair back. His hands are raised and clasped together in a prayerful posture, and he may bring his forehead forward to rest on them. Joseph stares at the right edge of the design; his mouth opens slightly, and his facial expression may suggest grief. Joseph wears a long-sleeved gown. He has long, curly hair. Behind Joseph, in the left third of the design, the other nine brothers kneel or stand. Most of them look on as Simeon is bound. In the center of the kneeling group is an older-looking man with short,  curly hair and a beard. He is nude from the waist up and covered from the waist down with a skirt or other draping cloth. His lower body faces toward the right as his knees rest on the ground and his flexed feet support him. He leans backward slightly as his torso twists away from the viewer, who sees him from behind. His arms are lowered on either side and embrace the brothers on his left and right; his right arm bends at ninety degrees. The man's head turns to the right to watch Simeon. On his left is a younger-looking man with short, curly hair who faces right and kneels in a similar posture. He may wear a skirt or a long, sleeveless gown. His muscular right arm extends down and forward so that his hand rests on the right hip of the older man. His fingers extend forward. The man's shoulders hunch forward as he leans against the older man with his head and eyes down. At the older man's right hand is another man(?) with long hair. He faces forward and appears to kneel with his legs spread, though only his left leg is visible from behind the older man's embrace. His arms bend upward to cross in front of his chest, and the fingers of his right hand curve downward as if touching his left shoulder. The man's head turns to face right as he gazes at Simeon with an open mouth. Behind these three embracing figures are two more who also appear to kneel. One emerges at right of the group, just behind the figure with crossed arms. Only his head and raised left arm are visible. He faces forward and to the right. The palm of his raised left hand faces the viewer, and his fingers are spread. At left and above the embracing trio is the curly hair of another figure. Standing above these figures are four more brothers. They are, from left to right: a gowned man with long hair who faces right and leans his head on the shoulder of the man in front of him; a man in nearly identical posture whose eyes close as he lowers his head and raises his hands in a prayerful posture; a man with short, curly hair and a beard who faces right and raises his head to look forward with an open mouth; and a gowned man who faces to the right, and raises his hands on the sides of his head in a gesture of grief. The scene takes place in an indoor space with the floor divided into two levels. The single step up creates a platform, which holds the chair on which one of the brothers (probably Joseph) leans. Two sets of seven vertical lines may represent pilasters or folds in floor-length curtains. The back wall of the design is shaded, but more defined shadows appear at back of the group of brothers, behind the feet and below the knees of the older kneeling man at left, underneath Simeon's left leg and foot, underneath his captor's left foot, and underneath Joseph's chair.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackles</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Simeon</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> In the right third of the design, Joseph's brother Simeon is being bound at the wrists by another man, presumably one of Joseph's servants. Simeon kneels in a lunging position, facing the right edge of the design with his left leg forward and his right leg extended behind him with toes flexed. Both legs are bent; the right is bare from the knee down, while the left is mostly covered by a cloth that wraps around Simeon's back and gathers on the floor between his legs. He is nude from the waist up, and his torso faces forward and to the right. His arms extend downward and to the right; the left arm bends slightly. Simeon's palms face one another, and his fingers are spread as the servant clasps manacles around both wrists. Simeon twists at the shoulders and neck, turning his head to the left and looking at the brothers behind him. He has a short hair and a closely-trimmed beard. His mouth opens slightly, and his expression suggests fear or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm lowered</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackles</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man who binds Simeon stands to the right of him, facing forward and to the left. He has short, curly hair and a beard; he is nude from the waist up but may be covered by a skirt or other garment from waist to knees. He stands with his left foot forward, just to the right of Simeon's. He bends at the waist, lowering his left arm to secure the shackles around Simeon's wrists. His right arm bends at approximately ninety degrees, and he holds his forearm horizontally across his waist. In his right hand he holds a chain that extends down to the manacles in his left hand. The man's head turns downward and to the left; his eyes are downcast, likely to look toward Simeon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Joseph</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the left of Simeon and his captor, on a raised platform, a male figure (very probably Joseph) sits sideways on a throne-like chair and leans against its back. He faces right and sits with his left knee forward, his left foot drawn back underneath him, and his right leg bent and extended back behind him in a position that mimics Simeon's. Joseph leans forward and extends his bent arms in front of him to rest his elbows on the chair's back. His hands are raised and clasped together in a prayerful posture, and he may bring his forehead forward to rest on them. Joseph stares upward and toward the right edge of the design. His mouth opens slightly, and his facial expression may suggest grief. Joseph wears a long-sleeved gown. He has long, curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brothers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind Joseph, in the left half of the design, the other nine brothers kneel or stand. Most of them watch Simeon being bound.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knees bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the kneeling group is an older-looking man with short,  curly hair and a beard. He is nude from the waist up and covered from the waist down with a skirt or other draping cloth. His lower body faces toward the right as his knees rest on the ground and his flexed feet support him. He leans backward slightly as his torso twists away from the viewer, who sees him from behind. His arms are lowered on either side and  embrace the brothers on his left and right; his right arm bends at ninety degrees. The man's head turns to the right to watch Simeon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the older man's left is a younger-looking man with short, curly hair who faces right and kneels in a similar posture. He may wear a skirt or a long, sleeveless gown. His muscular right arm extends down and forward so that his hand rests on the right hip of the older man. His fingers extend forward. The man's shoulders hunch forward as he leans against the older man with his head and eyes down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the older man's right hand is another man(?) with long hair. He faces forward and appears to kneel with his legs spread, though only his left leg is visible from behind the older man's embrace. His arms bend upward to cross in front of his chest, and the fingers of his right hand curve downward as if touching his left shoulder. The man's head turns to face right as he gazes at Simeon with an open mouth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind these three embracing figures are two more who also appear to kneel. One emerges at right of the group, just behind the figure with crossed arms. Only his head and raised left arm are visible. He faces forward and to the right. The palm of his raised left hand faces the viewer, and his fingers are spread.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind these three embracing figures are two more who also appear to kneel. At left and above the embracing trio is the curly hair of another figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Leftmost is a man with long hair who wears a long-sleeved gown. He faces right and leans his head downward on the shoulder of the man in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clasped</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Second from left a man in nearly identical posture whose eyes close as he lowers his head and raises his hands in a prayerful posture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Third from left is a man with short, curly hair and a beard who faces right and raises his head to look forward with an open mouth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Rightmost is a gowned man who faces to the right, and raises his hands on the sides of his head, perhaps clutching it in a gesture of grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pilaster</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curtain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in an indoor space with the floor divided into two levels. The single step up creates a platform, which holds the chair on which one of the brothers (probably Joseph) leans. Two sets of seven vertical lines may represent pilasters or folds in floor-length curtains.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>back</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The center figure (probably Joseph) sits sideways on a chair, sofa, or throne and leans against its back. Only the right half and upper left corner of the chair are visible. The leg, side, and back of the chair appear to be made of wood, and some decorative carving appears on the leg, underneath Joseph's left knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in indoor space with the floor divided into two levels. The single step up creates a platform, which holds the chair on which one of the brothers (probably Joseph) leans. Two sets of seven vertical lines may represent columns or folds in floor-length curtains. The back wall of the design is shaded, but more defined shadows appear at back of the group of brothers, behind the feet and below the knees of the older kneeling man at left, underneath Simeon's left leg and foot, underneath his captor's left foot, and underneath Joseph's chair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>