<bad id="but162r.1" type="mono" work="Job, His Wife and Friends: The Complaint of Job" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="162r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Job, His Wife and Friends: The Complaint of Job">
                    <main>
                        Job, His Wife and Friends: The Complaint of Job</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Tate Collection.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Job, His Wife and Friends: The Complaint of Job
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.H">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>31.1 x 45.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>31.1 x 45.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1940</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; possibly sold Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, lot 164 with three other works by Blake (&#163;1.9s. to Francis Turner Palgrave); sold Sotheby's, 19 April 1904, lot 403 (&#163;11.15s. to W. Daniell, probably a dealer); Alice G. E. Carthew by 1914; bequeathed by Carthew to the Tate Gallery, now Tate Collection, in 1940.</note>
            </provenance>
                        <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                            <repositoryid label="Accession number">N05200</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but162.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT162.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Job, His Wife and Friends: The Complaint of Job</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 162 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>31.1 x 45.1 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Pencil sketches, *Job's Wife and Other Sketches*, are on the verso of this monochrome wash drawing.  The sketch of Job's wife, sideways in the middle of this leaf of pencil drawings, is preliminary to Blake's two subsequent versions of the full composition on the recto, *The Complaint of Job: "What Is Man that Thou Shouldest Try Him Every Moment?"* (Butlin 164) and the large separate engraving of "Job" of 1793.  Job's wife is in a different posture in this monochrome wash drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In the drawing's center, an old man representing Job sits on the ground with his knees drawn up toward his chest and his arms bent upward just outside his knees. Job's bare feet are planted on the ground in front of him. His right leg is covered by his long gown, but his left leg--which leans outward slightly--is uncovered at least to the knee, and perhaps to the hip, which is pictured on the ground below. Job's elbows point outward and may rest on his knees or legs. Job raises his hands to his face, turning both hands inward to support his head under the jaws; his fingers curl, perhaps covering his ears or grasping his hair. The cuffs of Job's long-sleeved gown appear below his hands. Job's long, curly beard occupies the space between his wrists and extends down between his knees. Long, wavy hair covers Job's head, which turns slightly to the left as he gazes toward something beyond the drawing's frame. Job's mouth is open, and his brows are knitted in an expression of grief or even despair. Three marks appear on Job's left cheek, suggesting tears. At left of Job sits his wife. She faces forward and to the right, bending toward Job as she pulls her knees into her chest in a contracted posture. Her bare right foot appears on the ground next to Job's right foot, and her legs are drawn up in front of her. Job's wife wraps her arms around her legs and clasps her hands in front of her knees by interlacing her fingers. Her shoulders hunch forward, and her neck extends forward so that her head hovers over her knees. Job's wife wears a long-sleeved gown with cuffs and a long, voluminous skirt that covers her legs. Another cloth may drape around her waist and right hip. She has long hair that parts in the center and drapes over both shoulders. Her head turns downward, and she appears to gaze at the ground in front of Job. Her mouth is open in an expression of despair. On Job's other side, occupying the right third of the drawing, sit three of his friends. Nearest the viewer kneels an old man with long hair and a long beard. His legs bend sharply, and he sits on his heels facing forward and to the left. His legs are entirely covered by the skirt of a long-sleeved gown with folded cuffs. The man bends forward, toward Job, and raises his hands in front of his chest. Each arm bends upward so that the forearms are nearly horizontal; the man's left hand hovers over his right, and the fingers of each hand points toward the opposite arm. The man's head tilts downward, and his downcast eyes suggest an expression of grief. Above and to the left of the old man's head is the face of another man, which bears a similarly grievous expression. This central man has short, curly hair and a beard of similar texture. He wears a long-sleeved gown like that of his counterparts. His head and eyes are lowered; he may look at the ground near where Job sits. The man kneels on the ground. His right arm bends at 90 degrees so that his forearm crosses his body (though his right hand is hidden by the beard of the man in front of him). His left arm extends downward in front of him, and he points toward the ground with his index finger. At left of this man appears the head and right arm of the third friend, furthest from the viewer. This man also has curly hair and a beard. His head and eyes lower in an expression of grief. His right arm bends upward so that his cupped hand supports his face. The cuffed sleeve below his wrist suggests that the man wears a gown or shirt, but the rest of his body is hidden by those of the other friends. The five figures stand out against a darker background. The setting is unclear, apart from the floor or ground on which the figures sit. Prominent shadows appear below the chin and hands of Job's wife, between Job and his friends, and behind the rightmost friend in the group.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Job</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands beside head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tears</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the drawing's center, an old man representing Job sits on the ground with his knees drawn up toward his chest and his arms bent upward just outside his knees. Job's bare feet are planted on the ground in front of him. His right leg is covered by his long gown, but his left leg--which leans outward slightly--is uncovered at least to the knee, and perhaps to the hip, which is pictured on the ground below. Job's elbows point outward and may rest on his knees or legs. Job raises his hands to his face, turning both hands inward to support his head under the jaws; his fingers curl, perhaps covering his ears or grasping his hair. The cuffs of Job's long-sleeved gown appear below his hands. Job's long, curly beard occupies the space between his wrists and extends down between his knees. Long, wavy hair covers Job's head, which turns slightly to the left as he gazes toward something beyond the drawing's frame. Job's mouth is open, and his brows are knitted in an expression of grief or even despair. Three marks appear on Job's left cheek, suggesting tears.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Job's wife</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of Job sits his wife. She faces forward and to the right, bending toward Job as she pulls her knees into her chest in a contracted posture. Her bare right foot appears on the ground next to Job's right foot, and her legs are drawn up in front of her. Job's wife wraps her arms around her legs and clasps her hands in front of her knees by interlacing her fingers. Her shoulders hunch forward, and her neck extends forward so that her head hovers over her knees. Job's wife wears a long-sleeved gown with cuffs and a long, voluminous skirt that covers her legs. Another cloth may drape around her waist and right hip. She has long hair that parts in the center and drapes over both shoulders. Her head turns downward, and she appears to gaze at the ground in front of Job. Her mouth is open in an expression of despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On Job's other side, occupying the right third of the drawing, sit three of his friends. Nearest the viewer kneels an old man with long hair and a long beard. His legs bend sharply, and he sits on his heels facing forward and to the left. His legs are entirely covered by the skirt of a long-sleeved gown with folded cuffs. The man bends forward, toward Job, and raises his hands in front of his chest. Each arm bends upward so that the forearms are nearly horizontal; the man's left hand hovers over his right, and the fingers of each hand points toward the opposite arm. The man's head tilts downward, and his downcast eyes suggest an expression of grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On Job's other side, occupying the right third of the drawing, sit three of his friends. The central man bears a grievous expression similar to that of the old man in front of him. This younger man has short, curly hair and a curly beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown like that of his counterparts. His head and eyes are lowered; he may look at the ground near where Job sits. The man kneels on the ground. His right arm bends at 90 degrees so that his forearm crosses his body (though his right hand is hidden by the beard of the man in front of him). His left arm extends downward in front of him, and he points toward the ground with his index finger.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On Job's other side, occupying the right third of the drawing, sit three of his friends. Leftmost in the group, furthest from the viewer, appears the head and right arm of the third friend. This man also has curly hair and a beard. His head and eyes lower in an expression of grief. His right arm bends upward so that his cupped hand supports his face. The cuffed sleeve below his wrist suggests that the man wears a gown or shirt, but the rest of his body is hidden by those of the other friends.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The five figures stand out against a darker background. The setting is unclear, apart from the floor or ground on which the figures sit.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Prominent shadows appear below the chin and hands of Job's wife, between Job and his friends, and behind the rightmost friend in the group.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>