<bad id="but159r.1" type="mono" work="Sketch for 'Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="royal" catalog="butlin" catid="159r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Sketch for 'Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren'">
                    <main>
                        Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Royal Collection Trust.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>March 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>December 2014</date>
               <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;                  
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and                    
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill                    
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin, </name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Adam Engel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham, </name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime, </name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff, </name>
                    <name>Eric Loy, </name>
                    <name>Kate Massie, </name>
                    <name>Adam McCune, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis, </name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer, </name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner, </name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.F">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>33.5 x 45.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>33.5 x 45.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Royal Collection Trust</name>
                <date>c. 1862</date>
                <dealer>Richard Fisher</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 166 with three other works by Blake (10s. to Richard Fisher, probably a dealer); apparently sold c. 1862 to the Royal Collection, now the Royal Collection Trust and housed at Windsor Castle, Berkshire, England.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Royal Collection Trust</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">RCIN 913599</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but159r.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT159.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 159 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>33.5 x 45.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Another monochrome wash *Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"* is on the verso of this work.  Both are preliminary drawings for the water color, *Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren* (Butlin 157).</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure of this reunion scene is Joseph, who faces to the right and appears to have descended from a chair or throne, the edge of which is visible atop the raised platform at left. Joseph kneels on the platform with his right knee and lunges forward, stepping down from the platform with his left leg. Part of his bare left foot can be seen planted on the floor in front of the platform. He wears a long-sleeved gown beneath a draping cloth the covers his entire body except for his left foot and his right arm and shoulder. Long, curly hair flows down his back. Joseph leans forward, his head out in front with his eyes lowered and his mouth open. He brings his upper body nearly horizontal as his right arm extends downward and to the right, grasping the left leg of the younger man next to him, likely his brother Benjamin. Joseph's left arm may come alongside his head, and his left hand wraps around Benjamin's left shoulder. Joseph appears to be embracing Benjamin. Second from left, Benjamin kneels with his legs together and his arms crossed over his chest, right over left. His body faces forward and to the left, and his head turns left toward Joseph. Benjamin leans away from Joseph, perhaps resisting his embrace. Benjamin's head tilts downward; his mouth is open, and he may look at Joseph. Benjamin wears a long gown and has long, curly hair that partly covers Joseph's left hand. At right of these figures are the other brothers. Nearest Joseph and Benjamin, three men bow, facing left, in postures of supplication. The most prominent male figure, who is nearest the viewer, stretches his long torso to the left as he extends his forearms along the ground and places his palms flat on the ground. He is nude from the chest up, revealing a muscular back and shoulders. He may wear a skirt over his lower body, which is mostly hidden by the figures at right. The man's lowered head is covered by short, curly hair. Behind this man are two others who also kneel and bow but do not prostrate themselves in the same manner. Both appear to wear gowns or shirts. The nearer of the two men has long hair and a beard. He faces left, hunches his shoulders, and lowers his head. The man further from the viewer has short, curly hair. He also lowers his head, but his face is mostly hidden as he raises his hands to either side of his head, covering it with spread fingers. Behind these kneeling men, a group of seven recoiling figures occupies the right third of the drawing. In the foreground, two men kneel on the ground and lean away from the scene. The man nearer the viewer faces leftward. He bends his knees sharply as both rest on the ground, and he sits on the heels of his bare, flexed feet. As he leans backward over his heels, the man bends both arms at near 90-degree angles as he raises his hands at waist level. His fingers are spread, and his palms face each other. His mouth may open slightly as he stares toward the figures at left with knit brows. He is covered from the waist down by a skirt or draping cloth; his nude chest and arms are muscular. The man has long, wavy hair that extends down his back. The man behind him has short, curly hair and wears a gown that covers him to the elbows. His knees also face left and are bent at a similar angle as both rest on the ground; however, his torso twists away from the scene at left to face the viewer. His shoulders twist even further, nearly facing the right side of the drawing as his right arm bends upward and crosses over his body toward his left side. The man's left arm crosses beneath it so that his left hand touches his right shoulder. His fingers curl into a loose fist. The man's head faces forward and to the left as he looks at the scene in the left two-thirds of the drawing. His mouth opens in astonishment or horror. Behind these men are five others brothers who are only visible from the waist up. They are, from left to right: a long-haired man who faces left and bows his head, closing his eyes and holding his hands in a prayerful posture; another long-haired man who bows his head and raises his hands alongside it, palms facing inward; a short-haired man who faces forward and to the left, raising his right arm horizontally as he leans to the right; the head and short, curly hair of a man who faces forward and to the right, gazing in fear toward the viewer; and a curly-haired man who faces left and lifts his hand to cover his mouth in a contemplative posture. This drawing's setting appears to be a large room or portico with bare floors, a low step at left, and at least one large column in the background. There may be a door or window at right, but otherwise the lines in the background are unclear. Much of this background space is shadowy, with particularly dark areas appearing in the upper lefthand corner, at right of the large column, and in the upper righthand corner. Other shadows appear on both sides of the kneeling woman in the center, beneath the foremost bowing man, and behind the leaning pair at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Joseph</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure of this reunion scene is Joseph, who faces to the right and appears to have descended from a chair or throne, the edge of which is visible atop the raised platform at left. Joseph kneels on the platform with his right knee and lunges forward, stepping down from the platform with his left leg. Part of his bare left foot can be seen planted on the floor in front of the platform. He wears a long-sleeved gown beneath a draping cloth the covers his entire body except for his left foot and his right arm and shoulder. Long, curly hair flows down his back. Joseph leans forward, his head out in front with his eyes lowered and his mouth open. He brings his upper body nearly horizontal as his right arm extends downward and to the right, grasping the left leg of the younger man next to him, likely his brother Benjamin. Joseph's left arm may come alongside his head, and his left hand wraps around Benjamin's left shoulder. Joseph appears to be embracing Benjamin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Second from left, Benjamin kneels with his legs together and his arms crossed over his chest, right over left. His body faces forward and to the left, and his head turns left toward Joseph at left. Benjamin leans away from Joseph, perhaps resisting his embrace. Benjamin's head tilts downward; his mouth is open, and he may look at Joseph. Benjamin wears a long gown and has long, curly hair that partly covers Joseph's left hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms reaching downward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stretched</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on arms</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of Joseph and Benjamin are three more brothers who bow, facing left, in postures of supplication. The most prominent male figure, who is nearest the viewer, stretches his long torso to the left as he extends his forearms along the ground and places his palms flat on the ground. He is nude from the chest up, revealing a muscular back and shoulders. He may wear a skirt over his lower body, which is mostly hidden by the figures at right. The man's lowered head is covered by short, curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the central man are two others who also kneel and bow but do not prostrate themselves in the same manner. Both appear to wear gowns or shirts. The nearer of the two men has long hair and a beard. He faces left, hunches his shoulders, and lowers his head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the central man are two others who also kneel and bow but do not prostrate themselves in the same manner. Both appear to wear gowns or shirts. The man further from the viewer has short, curly hair. He also lowers his head, but his face is mostly hidden as he raises his hands to either side of his head, covering it with spread fingers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the three kneeling men, a group of seven recoiling figures occupies the right third of the drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground at right, two men kneel on the ground and lean away from the scene. The man nearer the viewer faces leftward. He bends his knees sharply as both rest on the ground, and he sits on the heels of his bare, flexed feet. As he leans backward over his heels, the man bends both arms at near 90-degree angles as he raises his hands at waist level. His fingers are spread, and his palms face each other. His mouth may open slightly as he stares toward the figures at left with knit brows. He is covered from the waist down by a skirt or draping cloth; his nude chest and arms are muscular. The man has long, wavy hair that extends down his back.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground at right, two men kneel on the ground and lean away from the scene. The further of the two has short, curly hair and wears a gown that covers him to the elbows. His knees also face left and are bent at a similar angle as both rest on the ground; however, his torso twists away from the scene at left to face the viewer. His shoulders twist even further, nearly facing the right side of the drawing as his right arm bends upward and crosses over his body toward his left side. The man's left arm crosses beneath it so that his left hand touches his right shoulder. His fingers curl into a loose fist. The man's head faces forward and to the left as he looks at the scene in the left two-thirds of the drawing. His mouth opens in astonishment or horror.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the mid-ground at right are five other men who are only visible from the waist up. Leftmost is a long-haired man who faces left and bows his head, closing his eyes and holding his hands in a prayerful posture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the mid-ground at right are five other men who are only visible from the waist up. Second from left is a long-haired man who faces left and bows his head, lowering his eyes to the ground. As he does so, he raises his hands alongside his head with his palms facing inward. The man appears to wear a long-sleeved gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the mid-ground at right are five other men who are only visible from the waist up. Third from left--and most prominent in the group--is a short-haired man who faces forward and to the left. He raises his right arm horizontally as he leans to the right, away from the drawing's primary scene. His mouth opens slightly as he gazes leftward. The man appears to wear a cloth draped from his left shoulder across his otherwise bare chest.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the mid-ground at right are five other men who are only visible from the waist up. Second from right appears the head and short, curly hair of a man who faces forward and to the right, gazing in fear toward the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the mid-ground at right are five other men who are only visible from the waist up. Rightmost is a curly-haired man who faces left and is seen in profile. He lifts his right hand to cover his mouth, and he looks straight ahead (and perhaps slightly downward) in a contemplative posture. This man appears to wear a gown or cloak.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Emerging from the left edge of the drawing is a chair or throne. Only the right, front leg is visible, and it curves outward from the set and armrest above.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This drawing's setting appears to be a large room or portico with bare floors, a low step at left, and at least one large column in the background. There may be a door or window at right, but otherwise the lines in the background are unclear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Much of the drawing's background space is shadowy, with particularly dark areas appearing in the upper lefthand corner, at right of the large column, and in the upper righthand corner. Other shadows appear on both sides of the kneeling woman in the center, beneath the foremost bowing man, and behind the leaning pair at right.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
