<bad id="but120v.1" type="mono" work="St. John the Evangelist before a Vision of Christ" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="120v">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="St. John the Evangelist before a Vision of Christ">
                    <main>
                        St. John the Evangelist before a Vision of Christ</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>                
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>November 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                     <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                     <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                     <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                     <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                     <name>Kirk V. Hastings</name>
                    and <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                     <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                     <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                     <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                     <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        St. John the Evangelist before a Vision of Christ
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1781.A">c. 1781<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations and its role as the preliminary drawing for Blake's engraving in *The Royal Universal Family Bible*, vol. 2, Bentley Plate 5, signed "Blake. d &#38; sc" and dated Feb. 1782 in the imprint.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>16.2 x 10.8 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>30.7 x 19.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and monochrome washes</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.143</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but120.1.1v.wd.01" dbi="BUT120.1.1v.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">St. John the Evangelist before a Vision of Christ</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 120 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This is a preliminary drawing for Blake's engraving in *The Royal Universal Family Bible*, vol. 2, Bentley Plate 5, signed "Blake. d &#38; sc" and dated Feb. 1782 in the imprint.  This monochrome wash drawing is on the verso of a pen and ink drawing, *The Good Farmer*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>16.2 x 10.8 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design illustrates Revelation 1:12-16, in which St. John the Evangelist sees a vision of Christ while exiled on the isle of Patmos. The island setting is indicated by a sandy ground in the lower half of the design, large rocks in the lower righthand and lower lefthand corners, some indeterminate vegetation in the shadowy region at lower left, and a body of water at left, behind John's back. In the lower half of the design, near the center, John kneels, facing forward and to the right. His long hair is gathered behind him, perhaps into a ponytail, and his face is partly covered by a short beard. John wears a long-sleeved gown with an additional piece of cloth draped around his back and over each knee. John's legs bend underneath him, though he does not quite sit on his heels; his bare right foot appears below the hem of his gown. His garments gather in piles on the ground. John leans forward over his knees with both arms bent and raised out in front of him. Though slightly staggered, his hands rise together with the palms facing one another and the fingers spread. John turns his head over his left shoulder, looking to the right and upward toward the vision of Christ that appears in the clouds above. John's cowering body position and open mouth suggest fear or awe. The Christ figure in the upper right quadrant of the design appears more faintly than John, and seems to be floating in the clouds above the ocean. Long-haired and bearded, Christ wears a long-sleeved gown that is secured by a belt at the waist and gathers in folds at his feet. He stands, facing forward and to the left, and leans slightly toward the left with his left knee bent inward. He may step forward with his left foot, though both feet are hidden by the gown. In customary fashion, Christ's arms are bent slightly and raised outward from his sides at approximately 45 degrees; his hands are open with his palms facing in front of him. His head turns toward the left, and he appears to gaze over John's head rather than at John himself. As described in Revelation 1:16, a sharp two-edged sword emerges from Christ's open mouth, extending downward and to the left. John's vision also contains at least two candlesticks (likely some of the seven candlesticks mentioned in Revelation 1:20), which appear at right of the Christ figure. The candlestick in front is approximately the same height as Christ's knee. It features a flat, circular base with decoration around the post at several levels. Lines extending upward above the candlestick suggest that it may hold a tall candle that nearly reaches Christ's left hand. A second candlestick appears faintly above and to the right of this one. John's vision appears among clouds of varying darkness. The cloud shape behind Christ is slightly darker than those immediately around it, and even darker clouds appear along the design's left and upper-left borders. Additional shadowy regions appear at John's back, below and to his left, and on the large stone in the lower righthand corner of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>John of Patmos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>John the Evangelist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>John</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower half of the design, near the center, John kneels, facing forward and to the right. His long hair is gathered behind him, perhaps into a ponytail, and his face is partly covered by a short beard. John wears a long-sleeved gown with another piece of cloth draped around his back and over each knee. John's legs bend underneath him, though he does not quite sit on his heels; his bare right foot appears below the hem of his gown. His garments gather in piles on the ground. John leans forward over his knees with both arms bent and raised out in front of him. Though slightly staggered, his hands rise together with the palms facing one another and the fingers spread. John turns his head over his left shoulder, looking to the right and upward toward the vision of Christ that appears in the clouds above. John's cowering body position and open mouth suggest fear or awe.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The Christ figure in the upper right quadrant of the design appears more faintly than John, and seems to be floating in the clouds above the ocean. Long-haired and bearded, Christ wears a long-sleeved gown that is secured by a belt at the waist and gathers in folds at his feet. He stands, facing forward and to the left, and leans slightly toward the left with his left knee bent inward. He may step forward with his left foot, though both feet are hidden by the gown. In customary fashion, Christ's arms are bent slightly and raised outward from his sides at approximately 45 degrees; his hands are open with his palms facing in front of him. His head turns toward the left, and he appears to gaze downward, over John's head, rather than at John himself. As described in Revelation 1:16, a sharp two-edged sword emerges from Christ's open mouth, extending downward and to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>candlestick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candle holder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>John's vision also contains at least two candlesticks (likely some of the seven candlesticks mentioned in Revelation 1:20), which appear at right of the Christ figure. The candlestick in front is approximately the same height as Christ's knee. It features a flat, circular base with decoration around the post at several levels. Lines extending upward above the candlestick suggest that it may hold a tall candle that nearly reaches Christ's left hand. A second candlestick appears faintly above and to the right of this one.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>island</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ocean</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>John's vision occurs while he is exiled on the Isle of Patmos. The island setting is indicated by a sandy ground in the lower half of the design, large rocks in the lower righthand and lower lefthand corners, and a body of water at left, behind John's back.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Some small, indeterminate vegetation appears in the shadowy region at lower left, behind John's back. It emerges from a rock at left, and it has several branches.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>John's vision appears among clouds of varying shades. The cloud shape behind Christ is slightly darker than those immediately around it, and even darker clouds appear in the sky along the design's left and upper-left borders.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadowy regions appear at John's back, below and to his left, and on the large stone in the lower righthand corner of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
