<bad id="but191.1" type="wc" work="A Breach in a City, the Morning After the Battle" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ackland" catalog="butlin" catid="191">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Breach in a City, the Morning After the Battle">
                    <main>
                        A Breach in a City, the Morning After the Battle</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 38KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Ackland Art Museum, University of North Carolina.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *A Breach in a City, the Morning After the Battle*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1784.A">c. 1784<note>Butlin 191 dates this work to c. 1795-1800.  We believe that a date of c. 1784 is indicated by the documentary record of Blake's exhibition of works in 1784 and the sequence of "Breach in a City" and "Pestilence" designs.  See Joseph Viscomi, "*A Breach in a City the Morning After the Battle*: Lost or Found?," *Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly*, 28.2 (fall 1994): 44-61.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>32.9 x 47.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>32.9 x 47.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color<note>The design is mostly executed as a monochrome wash drawing with only slight touches of colors other than gray and black.  The inscriptions by Blake lower right are in pen and ink.</note></medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Ackland Art Museum</name>
                <date>1962</date>
                <dealer>Martin Breslauer</dealer>
                <price>&#163;2850</price>
                <note>Acquired at an unknown time by Alfred Aspland (1816-80); sold by his estate, Sotheby's, 27 Jan. 1885, lot 62 (&#163;4.4s. to the dealer Pincott); offered by Henry Young and Sons, Liverpool, July-Aug. 1900 catalogue, page 8 (&#163;25); Bernard Quaritch, offered March 1904 catalogue 228, item 313 (&#163;30); acquired in 1904 by W. Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 53 (&#163;157.10s. to the dealer Thomas Agnew and Sons); H. C. Green; sold Sotheby's, 18 Oct. 1961, lot 14 (&#163;1850 to the dealer Osmond acting for Kerrison Preston); offered by Martin Breslauer, 1962 catalogue 96, item 18 (&#163;2850); acquired 1962 by the Ackland Art Museum, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, North Carolina.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Ackland Art Museum, University of North Carolina</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">62.16.1</repositoryid>
            </repository>
                
        </source>
        <desc id="but191.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT191.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Breach in a City, the Morning After the Battle</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 191)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This is probably the work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784.  Butlin 188 lists the exhibited work as "untraced since 1784."  For discussion of this work, its dating and exhibition, see Joseph Viscomi, "*A Breach in a City the Morning after the Battle*: Lost or Found?," *Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly*, 28.2 (fall 1994): 44-61.  Another water color of the same design in the Museum of Art, Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh (Butlin 189) may be a preliminary for this more finished version.  The inscriptions lower right are by Blake.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>32.9 x 47.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design shows the desolation of an unnamed city after the breach of its stone wall. The breached portion appears in two jagged segments, one protruding from the design's left border, and the other in its center. Between these two broken segments of wall, in the upper left quarter, the field of battle comes into view. The arrangement of lines and circles on the field suggests it is covered with dozens of bodies, and a woman walks among the dead as if searching for someone. She has long, wavy hair and wears a full-length gown. She strides leftward with her knees bent, back hunched over, and arms slightly raised away from her sides. Her head leans forward, and she looks at the ground before her. Above and to the left of this woman appears the head, neck, and left wing of a giant bird. A crest appears atop the bird's head, and its tongue extends from an open beak. The landscape behind the woman and bird includes a grove of trees at left, a plain at right, and mountains behind. Dark clouds fill the sky above. In the design's foreground, at least six bodies spill into the city through the breach in its wall. Nearest to the broken stone pieces are, at left, the chest and head of a man who lies on his back with his inverted head facing the viewer; and, at right, the head of a man who lies supine, facing right, with his mouth open. Between these two men, a figure of indeterminate gender lies face down, draped over a piece of broken stone, a trunk, or some other box-shaped object with decorative lines on its front side. The figure appears to be mostly nude, perhaps with a cloth draped around the waist. The figure's left arm extends alongside a head of long hair. Shadowy marks on the torso may suggest ribs. Below and to the left of this prone figure lies a man whose body is covered by rubble except for his head and right arm. His head lies near the left edge of the design, and his right arm wraps around his head so that his hand appears to be grasping his left ear. The most prominent body in the group is that of a man who lies supine along the lower border of the design. He lies with his feet extended at left, his head tilted backward at right; his mouth is open, and his eyes are closed. He is covered from chest to knees with a skirt or other item of clothing that may be fastened with a belt. His muscular left arm extends along his side and grasps the handle of a large, oval-shaped shield that lies flat on the ground. A pool of blood or water may gather next to the shield, beneath the man's head. Above this man's waist may appear the short, curly hair of another man. Over his chest appears the body of a male figure who faces left and is covered with armor from head to wrist. He also lies supine with his head tilted back and mouth open. His right arm extends along the ground by his side. Above the armored man kneels a woman in a contracted posture. She faces left and bends over him, lowering her face to his and wrapping her arms around his head in mourning. Her mouth opens in an expression of grief. Behind her stand two other adult figures, along with an infant. At left, directly above the kneeling woman, stands another long-haired female figure. This woman's torso faces the viewer, but her head turns to the right as she gazes toward the older man beside her or at something behind him. Her arms cross in front of her chest to cradle an infant. The child lies on its back, facing upward, with its head toward the right. Both woman and child have open mouths. To the right of this pair is an old man with long, wavy hair, a long beard, and a mustache. He stands, facing forward and to the left, with his head lowered and eyes downcast. He leans forward with knees bent, supported by two crutches under his arms. His left arm crosses his body, and his right supports his head. Behind these standing figures are two round pillars, which appear to terminate in capitals. The design is filled with shadows, most prominently in the clouds outside, on the insides of the broken wall, and beneath the dead figures in the foreground.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A woman walks among the dead as if searching for searching for someone. She has long, wavy hair and wears a full-length gown. She strides leftward with her knees bent, her back hunched over, and her arms slightly raised away from her sides. Her palms face the ground, and her fingers may be spread. Her head leans forward, and she looks down at the ground before her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="A">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crest</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>neck</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the left of this woman appears the head, neck, and left wing of a giant bird. It faces right and may look down at the woman and bodies below. A feathery crest appears atop the bird's head, and its tongue extends from an open beak. Its wing rises overhead and extends along the top edge of the design, merging with the shadowy clouds above the landscape. The bird may be flying.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The arrangement of lines and circles on the background field suggests it is covered with dozens of bodies, and the foreground shows at least six bodies spilling into the city through the breach in its wall.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chest</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head toward viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Nearest to the broken wall at left appear the chest and head of a man who lies on his back. He appears to be nude or partly nude, and his head is bent back, facing the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                    	<characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Nearest to the right piece broken wall is the head of a man who lies supine with his head toward the right. His mouth is open, and his eyes are closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribs</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between the broken pieces of wall is a figure of indeterminate gender. The figure lies face down, his(?) head facing left and his body draped over a piece of broken stone, a trunk, or some other box-shaped object. The figure appears to be mostly nude, perhaps with a cloth draped around the waist. His left arm extends alongside a head of long hair. Shadowy marks on the torso may suggest ribs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand to ear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner of the design lies a man whose body is covered by rubble. He appears to lie on his right side with his head toward the left and his face turned toward the viewer. He appears to have long hair and a beard. His right arm wraps around his head so that his hand appears to be grasping his left ear. The arm is covered by a long sleeve, suggesting he may wear a shirt, and a cloth of similar color drapes over the man's left shoulder. His eyes are closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Along the lower border of the design, a man lies supine with his feet extended at left and his head at right. His head tilts backward, his mouth is open, and his eyes are closed. He has short, curly hair, and is covered from chest to knees with a skirt or other item of clothing that may be fastened with a belt. His muscular left arm extends along his side, and his left hand grasps the handle of a large, oval-shaped shield that lies flat on the ground. His palm faces upward. He may be a soldier.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above this waist of the soldier in front may appear the short, curly hair of another man.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the chest of the man in front appears the body of another soldier, lying supine with his head toward the left. He wears a plumed helmet and is covered with armor from head to the wrist of his visible right arm, which extends along the ground by his side. His head is tilted back, his eyes are closed, and his mouth is open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the armored man kneels a woman in a contracted posture. She faces left and bends over him, lowering her face to his and wrapping her arms around his head in mourning. Her hands come together above his head, and her fingers appear to curl around the plume of his helmet. Her mouth opens in an expression of grief, or perhaps to kiss the dead man. The woman has long, curly hair. She wears a long gown fastened with a belt, and a piece of cloth above her head may serve as a veil.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Directly above the kneeling woman stands another gowned female figure with long hair. The woman's torso faces the viewer, and her arms bend upward and cross in front of her chest to cradle an infant. She may be the child's mother. Her slightly lowered right shoulder suggests that she leans leftward to support the child. The woman points toward the right edge of the design, and her head turns to the right as she gazes toward the older man beside her or at something behind him. Her mouth is open in an expression of fear or grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The standing woman cradles an infant with short, curly hair. The child appears to be nude, and its gender is unclear. The infant lies on its back, facing upward, with its head toward the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crutch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the woman and child stands an old man with long, wavy hair, a long beard, and a mustache. He wears a long gown, a robe, and some other garment draped across his chest. He faces forward and to the left as he leans forward with his knees bent. One of his feet appears beneath the hem of his gown. The old man is supported by two crutches under his arms. His left arm bends sharply across his chest, sliding his hand beneath his beard. His right arm appears to bend upward and may support his head, which tilts downward. His downcast eyes are nearly closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ruin</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The left half of the design shows a breach in the thick stone wall of a city. Two large, jagged segments of ruined wall appear, one protruding from the design's left border, and the other in its center, where the remaining portion of the wall reaches to the top of the design and extends across to its right border. Behind the standing figures at right are two round pillars, which appear to terminate in capitals. The ground below the figures appears to be bare.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>box</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>One of the dead figures in the foreground lies face down over a piece of broken stone, a trunk, or some other box-shaped object with decorative lines on its front side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>blood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> A pool of blood or water may gather next to the shield, beneath a soldier's head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>plain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mountains</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape behind the battlefield in the design's background includes a grove of trees at left, a plain at right, and mountains behind.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>trees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape behind the battlefield in the design's background includes a grove of trees at left, a plain at right, and mountains behind.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>clouds</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Dark clouds fill the sky above the battlefield scene in the design's background.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design is filled with shadows, most prominently on the insides of the broken wall and beneath the dead figures in the foreground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            
            <phystext><vspace extent="9"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but191.1.1.wc.01" justify="left" indent="36">A Breach in A City the Morning<note>These pen and ink inscriptions, lines 1-3, are by Blake.  In line 1, the first three capital letters (A, B, A) are written over lower-case versions.</note></l>
                    <l n="but191.1.1.wc.02" justify="left" indent="39">after the Battle</l>
                    <l n="but191.1.1.wc.03" justify="left" indent="42">W Blake inv &#38; d<note>A loop extends from the terminal letter to just above the first letter in "inv &#38; d".</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
