<bad id="but199r.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for 'Tiriel Denouncing his Sons and Daughters'"
    copy="1" copyid="1" institution="whitworth" catalog="butlin" catid="199r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Sketch for 'Tiriel Denouncing his Sons and Daughters'">
                    <main>Sketch for "Tiriel Denouncing his Sons and Daughters"</main> : electronic
                    edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work copyright © 2018 Whitworth Art Gallery </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>January 2003</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Amy Havlan, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Sketch for "Tiriel Denouncing his Sons and Daughters"* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1789">c. 1789<note>Some scholars have argued for a slightly earlier
                        date for Blake's *Tiriel* manuscript and the wash drawings illustrating it,
                        and hence by implication a slightly earlier date for all preliminary
                        sketches for those wash drawings. See David Bindman, *Blake as an Artist*
                        (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977) 43-44.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>17.9 x 23.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.9 x 23.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Whitworth Art Gallery</name>
                <date>1914</date>
                <dealer>William Ward</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by
                    Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold Sotheby's,
                    29 April 1862, lot 200 with 14 other works, or lot 201 with 17 other works (2s.
                    or 3s. to the dealer Francis Harvey); William Ward, offered in his 1914
                    *Catalogue of Drawings, Engravings and Books*, item 1 (&#163;8.8s.); purchased
                    by the Whitworth Art Gallery in 1914.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Whitworth Art Gallery</institution>
                <addressline>University of Manchester</addressline>
                <addressline>Oxford Road</addressline>
                <addressline>Manchester, M15 6ER</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 161-275-7450</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 0161 275-7451</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.whitworth.manchester.ac.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: whitworth@manchester.ac.uk</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <collection>Whitworth Art Gallery, University of Manchester</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">D.1914.29</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but199r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT199.1.1r.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketch for "Tiriel Denouncing his Sons and
                    Daughters"</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 199 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This pencil drawing is a preliminary sketch for the monochrome wash drawing,
                        *Tiriel Denouncing His Sons and Daughters* (Butlin 198.8), an illustration
                        to Blake's manuscript poem, *Tiriel*.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>17.9 x 23.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Near the center of the composition, Tiriel, an old man with a long
                        beard, stands in profile facing right with both arms extended horizontally.
                        He wears a gown. A straight-backed chair (perhaps a throne?) is visible
                        behind him at left and some sort of drapery above. Two female figures,
                        Tiriel's daughters, kneel in front of him with arms wrapped around his legs.
                        These figures are also gowned and each extends one leg backward. A third
                        gowned female, presumably another daughter, crouches in the lower left
                        corner facing right and wraps her arms around her knees. To the right of a
                        pillar or part of a wall, three male figures, Tiriel's sons, stand facing
                        forward against the right margin of the composition. The rightmost figure
                        has short curly hair and turns his head left, likely to look at the central
                        old man. His mouth is open and both arms are crossed in front of his chest.
                        With his right hand, he holds a sword aloft. The middle figure has short
                        curly hair and a beard and wears a spiky crown. His mouth is open. With both
                        arms bent upward, he clutches his face (or perhaps covers his ears?). The
                        leftmost male has short hair that appears to stand on end and a beard. With
                        an open mouth, he turns left, likely to look at Tiriel. The expressions of
                        all three figures suggest terror or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Tiriel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the center of the composition, Tiriel, an old man with a
                            long beard, stands in profile facing right. He has long hair and wears a
                            gown. He extends both arms horizontally to the right with hands raised
                            and palms facing out; his fingers are spread. Tiriel is depicted in the
                            act of denouncing his sons at right and daughters below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two gowned female figures, Tiriel's daughters, who kneel in
                            supplicating postures facing left, cling to the knees of the old male,
                            their father. The figure closer to the viewer has long curly hair and,
                            with head down, bends forward to touch the standing figure's right leg
                            with her raised left arm. Her left leg is extended backward, and she may
                            push into the ground with the toes of her left foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two gowned female figures, Tiriel's daughters, who kneel in
                            supplicating postures facing left, cling to the knees of the old male,
                            their father. The figure further from the viewer bends forward with head
                            down and likely touches the standing figure with her right arm (her hand
                            is visible directly above her companion's left hand). One of her legs is
                            extended backward, and she may push into the ground with the toes of her
                            foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around knees</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A third gowned female figure, presumably another of Tiriel's
                            daughters, crouches in the lower left corner facing right but with head
                            turned to face away. Bending forward, she wraps her arms around her
                            knees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures, Tiriel's sons, stand facing forward
                            against the right margin of the composition. The expressions of all
                            three figures suggest terror or despair. The rightmost figure has short
                            curly hair and turns his head left, likely to look at the central old
                            man. His mouth is open and both arms are crossed in front of his chest.
                            With his right hand he holds a sword aloft.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost male figure holds a sword in his right hand,
                            which is crossed in front of his body. The sword is pointed
                            upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures, Tiriel's sons, stand facing forward
                            against the right margin of the composition. The expressions of all
                            three figures suggest terror or despair. The middle figure has short
                            curly hair, a beard, and wears a spiky crown. His mouth is open. With
                            both arms bent upward, he clutches his face (or perhaps covers his
                            ears?). The details of his clothing are indistinct, though he may wear a
                            serpentine belt(?) and a robe or cape, most visible along the left side
                            of his body.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures, Tiriel's sons, stand facing forward
                            against the right margin of the composition. The expressions of all
                            three figures suggest terror or despair. The leftmost male has short
                            hair that appears to stand on end and a beard. With an open mouth, he
                            turns left, likely to look at the old man. His right arm is likely
                            extended to the right and thus obscured behind his companions. The
                            details of his clothing are indistinct, though he may wear a robe or
                            gown (the hem of which is visible near his right knee) and a shirt whose
                            circular patterning may suggest armor(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A straight-backed chair (perhaps a throne?) is visible against
                            the left margin behind the central male figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A pillar, or part of a wall, stands between the outstretched
                            hands of the older male figure and the group of three men at right in
                            this design. It may indicate the threshold between an interior space at
                            left and an exterior one at right or, alternatively, two different
                            rooms. The rectangular forms, one vertical and one diagonal, above the
                            heads of the figures on the right are not easily identified; they may be
                            part of the background wall or doorway.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>curtain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Along the top margin of the design from the upper left corner
                            to the central pillar, a series of diagonal lines may suggest some kind
                            of curtain or drapery, either of which would indicate that the
                            demarcated space is an interior one.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
