<bad id="but167.1" type="mono" work="Daniel" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="167">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Daniel">
                    <main>
                        Daniel</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
                </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 24KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 739KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries
                <date>August 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <notesstmt/>
            </filedesc>
            <userestrict>Copyright © 
                <date>2024</date> 
                by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. 
                Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. 
                Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires 
                express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher.
                Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
                granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Textual transcription, final proofing, revisions, and publication</change>
                <date>September 2023-August 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
                    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher Catanese, </name>
                    <name>Emily English, </name>
                    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>
                    <name>Liam Kusmierek, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
                    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
                    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
                    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
                    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
                    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Illustration markup</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Adam Engel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                    <name>Michael Fox, </name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham, </name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime, </name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff, </name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley, </name>
                    <name>Eric Loy, </name>
                    <name>Kate Massie, </name>
                    <name>Adam McCune, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis, </name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan, </name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai, </name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner, </name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones, </name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston, </name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Daniel
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake 
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1785.I">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>14.2 x 10.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>JWHATMAN</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick 
                    Tatham, probably upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold by Tatham to the British Museum in Oct. 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Museum number">1867,1012.203</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but167.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT167.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Daniel</title>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 167)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>This is one of seven monochrome wash drawings (Objects 37-43) by Blake of figures painted by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel. They were very probably copied from the engravings of Adamo Ghisi, after drawings by Giorgio Ghisi, published in *Pitture dipinte nella Volta della Capella Sistina nel Vaticano* (1773).</p>
                    <p>Frederick Tatham added a pen and ink inscription in the lower right corner of the leaf bearing this wash drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing after Michelangelo shows the biblical figure Daniel with two smaller figures. In the drawing's center, Daniel sits on a low step or platform in the corner of a room with bare walls and a bare floor. Daniel has short, wavy hair and wears many layers of clothing: a long gown, a cape over his shoulders, and a fringed piece of draping cloth over his legs. Daniel sits with his knees bent and spread. His right leg is drawn up near to his body, and his right foot rests on the ground at the base of the step on which he sits. Daniel's left leg bends outward and extends forward, toward the viewer, and his prominent left foot rests on the ground at the lower edge of the drawing (which curves inward at the edges). Daniel's body faces the viewer but bends leftward at the waist, leaning to the side and dropping his right shoulder as he writes on a tablet next to him. The tablet is angled away from Daniel and rests on a stand. The upper portion of the stand is triangular in shape and is supported by a smaller rectangular piece, leaving an open area near Daniel's cape. In that empty space is a small scroll. On the left side of the stand, some other object is attached. It may provide storage for writing utensils. Daniel's right forearm extends outward along the tablet, and he grasps a quill or other implement as he writes near the top of the tablet. Daniel's head leans toward this tablet and tilts downward, but he does not appear to look at the tablet but instead at the ground. His eyes may even be closed. His mouth may be open. Daniel's left arm extends forward and to the right, bending sharply at the wrist. His left hand rests on the edge of another tablet; his index and middle fingers point downward. This second tablet is much larger than the first. It rests in Daniel's lap and leans out ward from him (toward the viewer). Beneath this tablet, perhaps hanging on it or supporting it, is a nude male child. This child, much smaller than Daniel, faces forward and to the left. His right leg nearly straightens as his foot rests on the ground near Daniel's right foot. The child's left leg bends inward, and his right foot is hidden behind the draping of Daniel's gown. The child's genitals appear between his slightly spread legs. He bends forward as if holding the tablet on his back. The child's right arm bends sharply as his elbow rises into the air beside his head and his right hand reaches toward his back. The child's left arm reaches upward, and he grasps the edge of the tablet with his left hand. His head lowers, and his eyes close. The child has short hair. A second child appears above Daniel's left shoulder. Now absent from Michelangelo's fresco, this child is almost entirely covered by a large cloak which extends from Daniel's neck at left to his elbow at right. The child faces the viewer and leans forward but looks to the left, perhaps toward Daniel's writing. The child's gender is uncertain. The left wall and rise of the step or platform are shaded; shadows appear at right of Daniel's neck and in the lower right-hand corner of the drawing beneath the larger tablet and Daniel's left leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Daniel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the drawing's center, Daniel sits on a low step or platform in the corner of a room with bare walls and a bare floor. Daniel has short, wavy hair and wears many layers of clothing: a long gown, a cape over his shoulders, and a fringed piece of draping cloth over his legs. Daniel sits with his knees bent and spread. His right leg is drawn up near to his body, and his right foot rests on the ground at the base of the step on which he sits. Daniel's left leg bends outward and extends forward, toward the viewer, and his prominent left foot rests on the ground at the lower edge of the drawing (which curves inward at the edges). Daniel's body faces the viewer but bends leftward at the waist, leaning to the side and dropping his right shoulder as he writes on a tablet next to him. Daniel's right forearm extends outward along the tablet, and he grasps a quill or other implement as he writes near the top of the tablet. Daniel's head leans toward this tablet and tilts downward, but he does not appear to look at the tablet but instead at the ground. His eyes may even be closed. His mouth may be open. Daniel's left arm extends forward and to the right, bending sharply at the wrist. His left hand rests on the edge of another tablet; his index and middle fingers point downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hanging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath the larger tablet, perhaps hanging on it or supporting it, is a nude male child. This child, much smaller than Daniel, faces forward and to the left. His right leg nearly straightens as his foot rests on the ground near Daniel's right foot. The child's left leg bends inward, and his right foot is hidden behind the draping of Daniel's gown. The child's genitals appear between his slightly spread legs. He bends forward as if holding the tablet on his back. The child's right arm bends sharply as his elbow rises into the air beside his head and his right hand reaches toward his back. The child's left arm reaches upward, and he grasps the edge of the tablet with his left hand. His head lowers, and his eyes close. The child has short hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>faces forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second child appears above Daniel's left shoulder. Now absent from Michelangelo's fresco, this child is almost entirely covered by a large cloak which extends from Daniel's neck at left to his elbow at right. The child faces the viewer and leans forward but looks to the left, perhaps toward Daniel's writing. The child's gender is uncertain.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>easel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The drawing contains two tablets. The first appears at left of Daniel and rests on a stand; it is angled away from him. The upper portion of the stand is triangular in shape and is supported by a smaller rectangular piece, leaving an open area near Daniel's cape. In that empty space is a small scroll. On the left side of the stand, some other object is attached. It may provide storage for writing utensils. The second tablet is much larger than the first. It rests in Daniel's lap and leans out ward from him (toward the viewer).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Daniel sits on a low step or platform in the corner of a room with bare walls and a bare floor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>The left wall and rise of the step or platform are shaded; shadows appear at right of Daniel's neck and in the lower right-hand corner of the drawing beneath the larger tablet and Daniel's left leg.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
        <phystext>
            <lg>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.01"><space extent="18" unit="character"/>DANIEL</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="10" unit="character"/>
            <lg><l n="but167.1.wd.01.02" justify="left"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen"><space extent="35" unit="character"/>William Blake</hi></l>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.03" justify="left"><space extent ="37.5" unit="character"/><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">After<choice>
                    <orig>Michael Angelo</orig>
                    <reg>Michelangelo</reg>
                </choice>
                </hi>
                </l>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.04" justify="left"><space extent="42" unit="character"/><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Frederick Tatham</hi></l>
                <l n="but167.1.wd.01.05" justify="left"><space extent="49.5" unit="character"/><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">&#8212;&#8212;</hi></l>
            </lg>
        </phystext>
    </objdesc>
</bad>