<bad id="but101.1" type="mono" work="Satan, Sin and Death" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ransom" catalog="butlin" catid="101">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Satan, Sin and Death">
                    <main>Satan, Sin and Death</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>August 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>May 2012</date>
                 <respstmt>
                         <resp>Editors: </resp>
                         <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;                  
                         <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                         University of California, Riverside; and                    
                         <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                         University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill                    
                         <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                         <name>William Shaw</name>
                         <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                         <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                         <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                         <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                         <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester</resp>
                         <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                         <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                         <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                         <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                         <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                         <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                         <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                         <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                         <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                         <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                         <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                         <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                         <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                         <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                         <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                         <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Satan, Sin and Death
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.C">c. 1780<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>25.5 x 29.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>25.5 x 29.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin</name>
                <date>1965</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
            
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 174 with seven other works by Blake (9s. to Gould Weston); Mrs. Hunter-Weston, probably by inheritance; Nora Hunter, probably by inheritance; sold Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 17 (&#163;47.5s. to the dealer Jacob Schwartz); Thomas Edward Hanley; given by Hanley in 1965 to the University of Texas and now housed in the Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">70.8</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but101.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT101.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Satan, Sin and Death</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 101)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>25.5 x 29.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Satan, the nude male figure at left, lunges or runs with arms raised toward the two figures at right, the nude female figure Sin and the crowned male figure Death. Satan and Death appear prepared to spear one another while Sin attempts to intervene. Satan has short hair and his mouth is open. He holds a spear in his right hand and a shield in his left. Facing right, he looks toward the pair of figures at right as he steps toward them with his extended right leg. The female figure Sin stands near the right side of the design and faces left to look toward Satan. She has long curly hair and is nude, at least above the waist. She raises both arms, which are slightly bent, and extends them left toward Satan. Her mouth is open. Her right leg appears to be raised and bent, as if she is stepping to the left. Her lower body is partially obscured by the heads of three dogs, most likely representing the three-headed Cerberus, who faces left with three open mouths. The details of the lower right corner are unclear, though Cerberus may be in a low boat atop an area of water(?). The third figure Death, who is nude, stands behind and to the left of Sin facing left as he walks or lunges to the left. He wears a spiky crown and has a beard. His mouth is open and his eyes are turned down and to the left. He may look toward Satan. Both arms are raised over his head where he holds a spear with at least his right hand. Shadows appear on Death's right leg and left arm as well as in the upper right corner behind him. Also in the upper right corner, several vertical lines, suggesting an indistinct architectural form such as a pillar, are visible. Flames are visible in the lower left corner of the design behind Satan.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Satan, the nude male figure at left, has short hair and his mouth is open. Facing right, he lunges or steps to the right with his right leg forward and left leg extended backward. Both of his arms are raised and he holds a spear in his right hand and a shield in his left. His left arm is bent. He appears to look at and point his spear at Death.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sin</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure Sin stands or walks facing left near the right side of the design. She has long curly hair and is nude, at least above the waist. She raises both arms, which are slightly bent, and extends them horizontally to the left toward Satan, at whom she also looks. Her mouth is open. Her right leg appears to be raised and bent, as if she is stepping to the left. Her lower body is partially obscured by the heads of three dogs, most likely representing the three-headed dog Cerberus.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="D">
                        <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>teeth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Cerberus</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The heads of three dogs, most likely representing the three-headed Cerberus, face left beneath the female figure Sin. Their mouths are open and their teeth visible. The details of the lower right corner are unclear but the Cerberus may be in a boat atop water.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The details of the lower right corner are unclear, though Cerberus may be in a low boat atop an area of water(?). Alternatively, drapery may extend down from the hips of Sin into the lower right corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Death</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third figure Death, who is nude, stands behind and to the left of Sin facing left as he walks or lunges to the left. He wears a spiky crown and has a beard. His mouth is open and his eyes are turned down and to the left. He may look toward Satan. Both arms are raised over his head where he holds a spear with at least his right hand. The spear is pointed toward Satan.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadows appear on Death's right leg and left arm as well as in the upper right corner behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper right corner, several vertical lines, suggesting an indistinct architectural form such as a pillar, are visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Flames are visible in the lower left corner of the design behind Satan and extend across the lower half of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
