<bad id="but170v.1" type="mono" work="Aminadab, Called 'The Reposing Traveller'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="170v">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Aminadab, Called 'The Reposing Traveller'">
                    <main>
                        Aminadab, Called "The Reposing Traveller"</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
                </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt></respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                and the University of Rochester
                </sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 261KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries
                <date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
             <updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>
        <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
        and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
        shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
        Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
        express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
        publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
        granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>                
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>August 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Aminadab, Called "The Reposing Traveller"
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
            <compdate value="1785.O">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
      </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>14.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>24.4 x 17.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>Fragments of a single framing line extend around the image.</note></framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; 
                    acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; 
                    sold by Tatham to the British Museum in October 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Museum number">1867,1012.205</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but170v.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT170.1.1v.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Aminadab, Called "The Reposing Traveller"</title>
                <title type="alt">The Reposing Traveller</title>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 170 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>24.4 x 17.3 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>The pencil inscription immediately below the design, "The Reposing Traveller," was written by Blake.  The British Museum collection stamp appears lower left. This is one of seven monochrome wash drawings (Objects 37-43) by Blake of figures painted by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel. They were very probably copied from the engravings of Adamo Ghisi, after drawings by Giorgio Ghisi, published in *Pitture dipinte nella Volta della Capella Sistina nel Vaticano* (1773). The wash drawing, *Manasses*, is on the recto of this leaf.</p>
                   <p>Frederick Tatham added a pen and ink inscription in the lower right corner of the leaf bearing this drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing, after a portion of Michelangelo’s Sistine Ceiling, is presumably of the biblical figure Aminadab, identified as a “Reposing Traveller” in the inscription below the image. He sits forward, directly facing the viewer on a large block. The slope of his shoulders suggests that he is hunched slightly forward. His arms extend downwards so that his elbows rest on his thighs and his hands dangle between his bare legs. His hands cross at the wrist, with his right hand in the front and index finger pointed down. He left hand is turned to the side and touches his right knee. Both hands hold a piece of fabric, probably part of his tunic, that drapes in between his legs. His prominent, bare knees are parallel to his shoulders and his legs meet at the ankles to form a triangular shape with the left foot crossed in front of the right. Four toes of his left foot rest on the ground and the heel is slightly raised, while the right foot appears to rest against the block. He wears a short tunic with a scooped neckline that reveals a portion of chest, and a long-sleeved shirt is visible under the tunic sleeves. Part of the tunic drapes down the left side of the block. His mouth is closed and his brows are furrowed. His long, wavy hair appears to be fastened with a headband, but wisps break free and frame the right side of his face. The block on which the figure sits rests on a bare floor. The background is plain, perhaps representing a bare wall behind the figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Aminadab</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head toward viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>band</characteristic>  
                        <illusobjdesc>The man seated on the block is presumably the biblical figure Aminadab, identified as a “Reposing Traveller” in the inscription below the image. He sits forward, directly facing the viewer on a large block. He sits forward, directly facing the viewer on a large block. The slope of his shoulders suggests that he is hunched slightly forward. His arms extend downwards so that his elbows rest on his thighs and his hands dangle between his bare legs. His hands cross at the wrist, with his right hand in the front and index finger pointed down. He left hand is turned to the side and touches his right knee. Both hands hold a piece of fabric, probably part of his tunic, that drapes in between his legs. His prominent, bare knees are parallel to his shoulders and his legs meet at the ankles to form a triangular shape with the left foot crossed in front of the right. Four toes of his left foot rest on the ground and the heel is slightly raised, while the right foot appears to rest against the block. He wears a short tunic with a scooped neckline that reveals a portion of chest, and a long-sleeved shirt is visible under the tunic sleeves. Part of the tunic drapes down the left side of the block. His mouth is closed and his brows are furrowed. His long, wavy hair appears to be fastened with a headband, but wisps break free and frame the right side of his face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>box</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The large block on which the figure sits has a plain face. It could be made of stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The block on which the figure sits rests on a bare floor. The background is plain, perhaps representing a bare wall behind the figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Shadows appear on the man’s right arm, chest, and behind his right leg.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left"> 
                    <l n="but170.v.1.01" justify="left" indent="27"><unclear resp="LK">5</unclear>The Reposing
                        <choice>
                            <orig>Traveller</orig>
                            <reg>Traveler</reg>
                        </choice><note>A character that resembles the number “5” precedes the “T” in “The”.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="7"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left"> 
                    <l n="but170v.1.wd.01.02" justify="left" indent="45"> 
                        <hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Blakes writing &amp; Drawing</hi></l></lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
