<bad id="but146.1" type="wc" work="Enoch Walked with God" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="cincinnati" catalog="butlin" catid="146" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Enoch Walked with God"><main>Enoch Walked with God</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 55KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 256KB to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>July 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel Copy N</hi> and <hi rend="i">Enoch Walked with God</hi>, both in the Cincinnati Art Museum. We have also republished <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> Copy U with a more authoritative arrangement of the plates and an enhanced Copy Information page.   
                <lb/><lb/><hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is dated 1789 by Blake on the title page, but the first plate (Thel's Motto) and the last (her descent into the netherworld) appear to have been completed and first printed in 1790, while Blake was working on <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>. Copy N, never before reproduced, was printed and colored c. 1818 along with Copy O. It is one of sixteen extant copies, ten of which are in the Blake Archive—including Copy O—and four of which are in
                    preparation for future publication. Like Copy O, Copy N was printed in orange ink on Ruse &amp; Turners paper, watermarked 1815, beautifully colored, numbered by Blake in pen and ink, and bound with Thel's Motto as the last instead of the first of the book's eight plates. Unlike Copy O, its plates have a single orange line framing them. 
                <lb/><lb/>
                        Blake included the book in his advertisement "To the Public" of October 1793: "The Book of Thel, a Poem in Illuminated Printing. Quarto, with 6 designs, price 3s." He listed it again in 1818, in a letter to Dawson Turner, in which he priced it for £2.2.0., the price for which Copy N almost certainly sold. This letter is also in preparation for future publication.
                <lb/><lb/><hi rend="i">Enoch Walked with God</hi>, at 17.5 x 24 inches, is one of Blake's largest early designs. It was executed c. 1780-85 in water colors and pen and ink over pencil and charcoal. It joins sixty-four other water color drawings in the Archive illustrating the Bible.  
                <lb/><lb/> 
                                This is the first time that works from the Cincinnati Art Museum have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the museum's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.
                <lb/><lb/>
                                    Additionally, with this publication, the Archive has implemented a new feature on its main viewing page to enable users to rotate the image, a particularly salient feature for Blake's texts written upside down or vertically.
                <lb/><lb/>
                                        The Archive has also updated its General and Specific Bibliographies, which now incorporate links to many Google Books.
                <lb/><lb/>
                                            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                                           
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This work copyright © 2014 Cincinnati Art Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>July 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>April 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and color correction</change><date>January 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Enoch Walked with God</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>45.4 x 61.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>45.4 x 61.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and water color over pencil and possibly charcoal</medium><support>laid paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Cincinnati Art Museum</name><date>1977</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Offered by the London dealer Bernard Quaritch, May 1887 offer according to Butlin 146 (£10), June 1893 *Miscellaneous Catalogue* 62, page 30, "A superb early scriptural drawing" (£10), and Jan. 1895 *Rough List* 147, page 46,  "A superb early scriptural drawing" (£10); Francis William Bourdillon; his son, Francis Bernard Bourdillon, probably by inheritance in 1921; offered Sotheby's, 14 Nov. 1934, lot 551, described as a Job design, "backed by a sheet of similar size covered with a fine pencil sketch of an allegorical figure, seated, arms outstretched, a variant of the last plate of *Urizen*" (bought in at £128 by "Marcus"); the dealer C. A. Stonehill; sold 1935 to John W. Warrington; given by Warrington to the Cincinnati Art Museum in 1977.  The drawing on the backing sheet (see the Sotheby's sale above) is very probably not by Blake (see Butlin 146).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Cincinnati Art Museum</institution><addressline>953 Eden Park Drive</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, Ohio 45202</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-513-639-2941</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.cincinnatiartmuseum.org</addressline><addressline>Email, Photo Services: photo_services@cincyart.org</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">1977.214</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but146.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT146.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Enoch Walked with God</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 146)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The subject of the design has often been described as Job and his family (see Related Works in the Archive).  Butlin 146, however, identifies the subject as Genesis 5:24.  An earlier passage, Genesis 5:22, seems more likely: "And Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuselah three hundred years, and begat sons and daughters."  The identification of the design's subject and its textual basis are tentative.</p></objnote><objsize>45.4 x 61.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="780" height="600"/></physdesc><related objectid="but550.1.wc.02"/><related objectid="but551.1.wc.02"/><related objectid="but557.1.penc.08"/><related objectid="bb421.1.spb.04"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The subject of the design may be Genesis 5:22: "And Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuselah three hundred years, and begat sons and daughters."  A low dais or plinth consisting of two steps runs most of the way across the bottom of this design, from the lower left corner nearly to the lower right corner.  It forms a kind of stage for the scene.  Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais, starting from the left edge of the design and proceeding to the right edge of the dais.  Each tree bears a leafy canopy just visible below the upper edge of the design.  Vines climb the three rightmost trees.  Indeterminate, perhaps leafy vegetation fills much of the space between the two leftmost tree trunks.  Between the three leftmost trunks a distant landscape of low grassy hills is visible.  A lake may be located just below the hills, and a near bank below that.  Wash above the hills, between the third and fourth trees, and to the right of the fourth tree suggests the sky.  An old man, apparently Enoch, is seated near the center of the design, on a kind of dais.  His body faces forward, with his bent knees out toward the viewer.  He turns his head to the right and tilts it back slightly, so that his face is visible in profile looking up to the right.  His slightly bent left arm is forward, and he rests his left hand on his right knee.  His bent right arm is also drawn forward, and he grasps one edge of a book loosely with this hand.  The opposite edge of the book is propped against the folds of his garment on his right thigh; his left hand may also help to support the book.  The old man casts a dark shadow on the dais to the right.  To the left of the old man reclines a young woman, probably one of Enoch's daughters.  Her lower body extends to the left along a bench or couch, and the shape of her garments suggests that her bent right leg may be crossed over her left.  She twists her upper body forward at the waist and rests against a pillow or similar support to the right, visible beneath the old man's right elbow.  Her right arm is down and bent across her torso.  She turns her head slightly to the right.  A young man, probably one of Enoch's sons, rests in a similar position just to the left of her.  Two children sit between them.  The man's lower body extends to the left, but he twists at the waist so that his torso faces forward.  He turns his head right so that his face is visible in profile.  The man wears a long gown and has long curly hair.  His right arm is bent and drawn forward, and rests on the right shoulder of the foremost child, a girl.  The girl's shoulders face forward though she turns her head slightly right.  Her right upper arm is extended down to the left, while her left upper arm is down.  She has long hair and wears a shirt or gown.  The rightmost child is a boy whose head and left shoulder are visible to the right of the leftmost child.  The boy's shoulder faces forward, but he turns his head to the right.  He has short curly hair, and may be nude.  The partly erased head and upper body of an additional figure appears, facing right, above and slightly to the left of the head of the female just left of Enoch.  The couch on which the four people sit extends to the left.  Shadow fills the area beneath the couch.  Two youths stand together near the left edge of the design.  One is slightly to the left of the other, and partially hides his companion.  The leftmost youth faces right and rests his weight on his right leg, which is planted on the lower step of the dais; his left leg is bent forward and drawn up, and his left foot rests on tiptoe on a higher step.  His right arm is down by his side but drawn forward slightly.  He holds an object, perhaps a book, in his right hand.  He is nude with visible genitals and has long curly hair.  The partly hidden youth to the right stands on the highest step of the dais, facing forward, but turns his head to the right.  His left arm is by his side and seems to be bent behind his back at the elbow.  He may be nude or may wear a short tunic.  He has short curly hair.  A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The foremost angel hovers or flies facing forward and left, but turns his head farther left so that his face is seen in profile looking left.  His left arm is down by his side and bent forward at the elbow, and he holds one corner of a piece of paper, possibly a scroll, with his left hand.  The angel wears a gown or tunic draped over his right shoulder, leaving his torso partly nude.  His mouth is slightly open and his long hair flies behind his head.  He partially hides a second angel, whose head, right arm, and right shoulder are just visible above and to the left of the first.  This second angel's right shoulder may face partly forward, but his head faces left and is bent down slightly.  He has short curly hair, and may be nude or may wear a gown or tunic.  His slightly bent right arm is extended forward from his body at roughly 135 degrees and he holds the other end of the large paper with this hand.  Marks on the paper suggest a text, possibly Hebrew letters.  The third angel from the right in the front group of three, who is partly hidden by the other two, stands or hovers facing forward and slightly left.  This angel's slightly bent right arm is extended and drawn across his torso to the right; it is hidden below the elbow.  His right leg, visible below the paper the two foremost angels hold, seems similarly to extend down to the right.  He has short curly hair and may have a small mustache.  The heads and shoulders of two more angels appear together in the upper right corner.  Of these, the shoulders of the angel on the right face left, but he turns his head away so that his face is not visible.  He partially hides the angel on the left, whose left shoulder seems to face away though he turns his head back towards the viewer.  Shadow fills the upper right corner of the design, extending down the right edge.  Shadow also fills the space beneath the foremost angel's gown.  A few odd forms upper right, only sketched in outline, hint at serpents.  There may be a chair sketched in outline just right of Enoch.
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="CD"><characteristic>dais</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A low dais or plinth consisting of two steps runs most of the way across the bottom of this design, from the lower left corner nearly to the lower right corner.  It forms a kind of stage for the scene.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais, starting from the left edge of the design and proceeding to the right edge of the dais.  Each tree bears a leafy canopy just visible below the upper edge of the design.  The leftmost tree sprouts one branch.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais.  A vine climbs the tree second from left, circling around the trunk once.  It bears several sketched leaves to the right.  It may send a thin branch up the trunk above the loop.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais.  An ascending vine loops tightly several times around the rightmost tree.  It may bear several sketchy leaves.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais.  Indeterminate, perhaps leafy vegetation fills much of the space between the two leftmost tree trunks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>lake</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>bank</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais.  Between the three leftmost trunks a distant landscape of low grassy hills is visible.  A lake may be located just below the hills, and a near bank below that. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four tree trunks rise at regular intervals above the dais.  Between the three leftmost trunks a distant landscape of low grassy hills is visible.  Wash above the hills, between the two rightmost trees, and to the right of the fourth tree suggests the sky.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Enoch</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>lap</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old man, apparently Enoch, is seated near the center of the design, on a kind of dais.  His chair or support is not visible.  His body faces forward, with his bent knees out toward the viewer.  He turns his head to the right and tilts it back slightly, so that his face is visible in profile looking up to the right.  His eyes may be raised.  His slightly bent left arm is forward, and he rests his left hand on his right knee.  His bent right arm is also drawn forward, and he grasps one edge of book loosely with this hand.  The opposite edge of the book is propped against the folds of his garment on his right thigh; his left hand may also help to support the book.  He wears a long gown that falls to the floor.  The toes of his right foot emerge from beneath its hem.  His left foot may be just visible to the right.  He has a full beard and long white hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>page</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old man, apparently Enoch, is seated near the center of the design, on a kind of dais.  He holds a book in his lap.  We see the top or bottom edges of the book, its pages surrounded by the binding.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old man is seated near the center of the design, on a kind of dais.  He casts a dark shadow on the dais to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old man is seated near the center of the design, on a kind of dais.  To the left reclines a young woman, possibly one of Enoch's daughters.  Her lower body extends to the left along a bench or couch, and the shape of her garments suggests that her bent right leg may be crossed over her left.  She twists her upper body forward at the waist and rests against a pillow or similar support to the right, visible beneath the old man's right elbow.  Her right arm is down and bent across her torso; her right hand is hidden.  She turns her head slightly to the right, so that her face is visible in three-quarters profile looking right.  Her eyes are raised and her mouth is open slightly.  She wears a long gown that seems to have a high waist or perhaps a belt.  A scarf or cloak covers her head, falls behind her shoulders, and drapes down her lower body over her gown.  Her long hair hangs over her shoulders.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>couch</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young woman reclines along a bench or couch to the left of the old man who sits at the center of the design.  The low seat extends to the left on the dais.  A pillow or similar support rests on the bench or couch at the right end.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young woman reclines along a bench or couch to the left of the old man who sits at the center of the design.  Shadow fills the area beneath the couch.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young woman reclines along a bench or couch to the left of the old man who sits at the center of the design.  A young man, possibly one of Enoch's sons, rests in a similar position just to the left of her.  Two children sit between them.  The man's lower body extends to the left, but he twists at the waist so that his torso faces forward.  He turns his head right so that his face is visible in profile.  His right arm is bent and drawn forward, and rests on the right shoulder of the foremost child, a girl.  His right hand may dangle, or may rest against her arm.  The man wears a long gown and has long curly hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>face</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young woman reclines along a bench or couch to the left of the old man who sits at the center of the design.  A young man rests in a similar position just to the left of her.  The heads and shoulders of two children are visible between them.  The leftmost child is a girl whose shoulders face forward though she turns her head slightly right.  Her right upper arm is extended down to the left, while her left upper arm is down.  She has long hair and wears a shirt or gown.  Her mouth may be open slightly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>pentimento</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The partly erased head and upper body of a figure, facing right, appears just above and slightly to the left of the head of the reclining female left of the bearded old man.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young woman reclines along a bench or couch to the left of the old man who sits at the center of the design.  A young man rests in a similar position just to the left of her.  The heads and shoulders of two children are visible between them.  The rightmost child is a boy whose head and left shoulder are visible to the right of the leftmost child.  The boy's shoulder faces forward, but he turns his head to the right.  His mouth is open and his eyes may be raised.  He has short curly hair, and may be nude.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two youths stand together near the left edge of the design.  One is slightly to the left of the other, and partially hides his companion.  The leftmost youth faces right and rests his weight on his right leg, which is planted on a lower step of the dais; his left leg is bent forward and drawn up, and his left foot rests on tiptoe on a higher step.  His right arm is down by his side but drawn forward slightly.  He holds an object, perhaps a book, in his right hand.  He is nude with visible genitals and has long curly hair.  His eyes are raised.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>book</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two youths stand together near the left edge of the design.  One is slightly to the left of the other, and partially hides his companion.  The leftmost youth holds an object, perhaps a book, in his raised right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>tunic</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two youths stand together near the left edge of the design.  One is slightly to the left of the other, and partially hides his companion.  The partly hidden youth stands on the highest step of the dais, facing forward, but turns his head to the right.  His left arm is by his side and seems to be bent behind his back at the elbow.  He may be nude, or may wear a short tunic.  He has short curly hair.  His mouth seems to be open slightly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>tunic</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The foremost angel hovers or flies facing forward and left, but turns his head farther left so that his face is seen in profile looking left.  His left arm is down by his side and bent forward at the elbow, and he holds one corner of a parchment with his left hand.  Text written on the parchment faces out.  The angel wears a gown or tunic draped over his right shoulder, leaving his torso partly nude.  The skirts of the garment swirl around his legs.  His left foot is visible dangling in tiptoe position below.  His mouth is slightly open and his long hair flies behind his head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>arm</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>tunic</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The foremost angel hovers or flies facing forward and left.  He partially hides a second angel, whose head, right arm, and right shoulder are just visible above and to the left of the first.  This second angel's right shoulder may face partly forward, but his head faces left and is bent down slightly.  His slightly bent right arm is extended forward from his body at roughly 135 degrees and he holds one end of a large parchment paper with this hand.  He has short curly hair, and may be nude or may wear a gown or tunic.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>paper</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The foremost angel hovers or flies facing forward and left, and holds one corner of a piece of paper, possibly an unrolled scroll, with his left hand.  This angel partially hides a second angel, whose head, right arm, and right shoulder are just visible above and to the left of the first.  The second angel's slightly bent right arm is extended forward from his body at roughly 135 degrees and he holds the other end of the large paper with this hand.  Marks on the paper suggest a text, possibly Hebrew letters.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>tunic</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mustache</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The third angel from the right in the front group of three, partially hidden by the other two, stands or hovers facing forward and slightly left.  This angel's slightly bent right arm is extended and drawn across his torso to the right; it is hidden below the elbow.  His right leg, visible below the parchment the two foremost angels hold, seems similarly to extend down to the right.  He seems to wear a tunic that leaves his right shoulder nude.  The folds of its skirts are visible to the left of the angel's right leg.  He has short curly hair and may have a small mustache.  His eyes are slightly raised and his mouth is open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The heads and shoulders of two appear together in the upper right corner.  Of these, the shoulders of the angel on the right face left, but he turns his head away so that his face is not visible.  He has rather long, curly hair and wears a gown or cloak.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  The heads and shoulders of two appear together in the upper right corner.  The angel on the right partially hides the angel on the left, whose left shoulder seems to face away though he turns his head back towards the viewer.  This angel's mouth is open.  He has curly hair.  Other details are not clear.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A grouping of five angels is visible at the right side of the design.  Shadow fills the upper right corner of the design, extending down the right edge.  Shadow also fills the space beneath the foremost angel's gown.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Some curving lines upper right corner of the design hint at the bodies and heads of one or two serpents.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>