<bad id="but168v.1" type="mono" work="Abias" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="168v">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Abias">
                    <main>
                        Abias</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Abias
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.K">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>16.5 x 11.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>JWHATMAN</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold by Tatham to the British Museum in Oct. 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1867,1012.206</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but168v.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT168.1.1v.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Abias</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 168 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>16.5 x 11.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>This is one of seven monochrome wash drawings (Objects 37-43) by Blake of figures painted by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel.  They were very probably copied from the engravings of Adamo Ghisi, after drawings by Giorgio Ghisi, published in *Pitture dipinte nella Volta della Capella Sistina nel Vaticano* (1773).  The wash drawing, *Matthan*, is on the recto of this drawing.  The British Museum collection stamp appears lower left on the leaf bearing this wash drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing shows two male figures: in front is a muscular, partly nude man seated on a large block; behind is a young boy who appears upright, as if on alert. The man is presumably the Abias of the title, a biblical figure listed in Matthew's genealogy of Jesus. Abias faces right as he sits on the block in a contracted posture. His right knee bends at 90 degrees, and Abias's right foot is drawn up the side of the block toward his body. His left leg also bends, but it extends outward from the block so that his left foot rests on the floor. Both feet are bare. A skirt or other garment covers Abias from the waist down; it features some small, jagged pieces near the waist. Abias's body folds in half at the waist, his bare torso leaning over his legs as his muscular right arm dangles toward the ground. A bracelet or cord encircles his wrist. His left hand crosses over to rest on top of his right knee with the fingers curving toward the viewer. Abias's head lowers, turns away from the viewer, and may rest on his right knee. He has short hair, and a cord or other object may wrap around the back of his head and over his right knee. Behind Abias, rising over his hunched back, is a young male figure who does not now appear in Michelangelo's fresco. The boy's torso faces forward and to the right, but his head turns to the left as he looks backward over his right shoulder. The boy appears to wear a shirt or other garment, and there may be a cape or draped cloth over his shoulder. The boy's hair is short and curly. It hovers leftward, over his forehead, as if blown by the wind. The boy and Abias's legs are fainter than Abias's body; shadows appear beneath Abias's torso, along the back of his dangling right arm, and at the boy's back. The block on which the figures sit rests on a bare floor. The background is plain, perhaps representing a bare wall behind the figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Abias</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bracelet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on knee</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man seated on the block is presumably the Abias of the title, a biblical figure listed in Matthew's genealogy of Jesus. Abias faces right as he sits on the block in a contracted posture. His right knee bends at 90 degrees, and Abias's right foot is drawn up the side of the block toward his body. His left leg also bends, but it extends outward from the block so that his left foot rests on the floor. Both feet are bare. A skirt or other garment covers Abias from the waist down; it features some small, jagged pieces near the waist. Abias's body folds in half at the waist, his bare torso leaning over his legs as his muscular right arm dangles toward the ground. A bracelet or cord encircles his wrist. His left hand crosses over to rest on top of his right knee with the fingers curving toward the viewer. Abias's head lowers, turns away from the viewer, and may rest on his right knee. He has short hair, and a cord or other object may wrap around the back of his head and over his right knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>com
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind Abias, rising over his hunched back, is a young male figure who does not now appear in Michelangelo's fresco. The boy's torso faces forward and to the right, but his head turns to the left as he looks backward over his right shoulder. The boy appears to wear a shirt or other garment, and there may be a cape or draped cloth over his shoulder. The boy's hair is short and curly. It hovers leftward, over his forehead, as if blown by the wind.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>box</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The large block on which the figures sit has a plain face. It could be made of stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The block on which the figures sit rests on a bare floor. The background is plain, perhaps representing a bare wall behind the figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Shadows appear beneath Abias's torso, along the back of his dangling right arm, and at the boy's back.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>