<bad id="but153.1" type="mono" work="The Mourners" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="153">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Mourners">
                    <main>
                        The Mourners</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Mourners
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.E">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.0 x 24.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.0 x 24.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Collection of Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1984</date>
                <dealer>Christie's</dealer>
                <price>$8117</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; Anne Gilchrist by 1863; Mrs. Butcher by no later than 1876; sold Christie's, 1 Aug. 1963, lot 48 (&#163;5.5s. to Hugh Geddes); sold Christie's, 5 June 1973, lot 113 (&#163;2520 to the dealer Coulter acting for E. Taubman); offered Christie's, 15 June 1982, lot 86 (not sold); acquired by Robert N. Essick from Taubman, Christie's acting as Taubman's agent, in Sept. 1984 for $8117.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but153.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT153.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Mourners</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 153)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>18.0 x 24.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Four female mourners sit in the drawing's foreground, huddled together in front of a large set of stairs. The two mourners in front partially obscure the women behind them, who may sit on top of the lower steps. The woman at lower left sits on the ground in a contracted posture, her body facing forward and to the right. She hunches forward and lowers her elbows over her knees. Her legs cross at the ankles, left over right, as the toes of her bare feet touch the ground. Her arms bend upward, and her right hand appears to support the back of her head, which turns away to face one of the figures behind her. The other arm is partially hidden behind her head, and it may touch or cover her face. The sleeves of her long gown cover her hands. Long, wavy hair flows down her back, over her right shoulder, and between her arms to cover her face. Immediately above this woman are the shoulders and head of another, who presumably sits behind her on one of the lower steps. She also appears to wear a gown, though little of it is visible. Her body faces forward and to the right, but her head--visible from the nose up--is turned toward the viewer and tilts slightly to the left. Uplifted hands frame her face, perhaps covering her ears. Her eyes close in an expression of grief. The woman appears to have bangs, but the length of the rest of her hair is unclear. At right of this woman is another who sits on the steps, facing forward and to the right as she leans out from behind the other figures. Her head tilts downward and rests on her raised left hand; the elbow of her bent left arm rests on her left knee. Below, her long gown covers her legs and extends to the ground. Her sleeve culminates in a prominent cuff. The woman's long, curly hair cascades over her left shoulder. Her mouth opens, and her eyes lower toward the ground in an expression of grief or despair. She may be looking at the woman who sits below and to the right of her. This rightmost figure sits lower than the other three mourners. She faces left and sits on the ground in a contracted posture with her knees bent sharply upward and her head and arms hidden behind or between them. At left, her bare left foot emerges from the hem of her long gown. Long hair covers her face. At left of her knees may appear part of her hands; if so, it seems they also cover her face. Behind the figures is a set of six steps, which appear to be made of stone. Below them is a bare floor, and above them rises a plain wall; these may also be made of stone. Prominent shadows appear at left of the group of figures and below their feet, on the rises of the lower two steps at right, and on the wall at upper right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four female mourners sit in the drawing's foreground, huddled together in front of a large set of stairs. The two mourners in front partially obscure the women behind them, who may sit on top of the lower steps.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The woman at lower left sits on the ground in a contracted posture, her body facing forward and to the right. She hunches forward and lowers her elbows over her knees. Her legs cross at the ankles, left over right, as the toes of her bare feet touch the ground. Her arms bend upward, and her right hand appears to support the back of her head, which turns away to face one of the figures behind her. The other arm is partially hidden behind her head, and it may touch or cover her face. The sleeves of her long gown cover her hands. Long, wavy hair flows down her back, over her right shoulder, and between her arms to cover her face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately above this woman are the shoulders and head of another, who presumably sits behind her on one of the lower steps. She also appears to wear a gown, though little of it is visible. Her body faces forward and to the right, but her head--visible from the nose up--is turned toward the viewer and tilts slightly to the left. Uplifted hands frame her face, perhaps covering her ears. Her eyes close in an expression of grief. The woman appears to have bangs, but the length of the rest of her hair is unclear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand under head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of this woman is another who sits on the steps, facing forward and to the right as she leans out from behind the other figures. Her head tilts downward and rests on her raised left hand; the elbow of her bent left arm rests on her left knee. Below, her long gown covers her legs and extends to the ground. Her sleeve culminates in a prominent cuff. The woman's long, curly hair cascades over her left shoulder. Her mouth opens, and her eyes lower toward the ground in an expression of grief or despair. She may be looking at the woman who sits below and to the right of her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">  
                    	<characteristic>female</characteristic>                     							
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This rightmost figure in the group sits lower than the other three in the group. She faces left and sits on the ground in a contracted posture with her knees bent sharply upward and her head and arms hidden behind or between them. At left, her bare left foot emerges from the hem of her long gown. Long hair covers her face. At left of her knees may appear part of her hands; if so, it seems they also cover her face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures is a set of six steps, which are large in size and appear to be made of stone. Below them is a bare floor, and above them rises a plain wall; these may also be made of stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Prominent shadows appear at left of the group of figures and below their feet, on the rises of the lower two steps at right, and on the wall at upper right.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>