<bad id="but175.1" type="penink" work="Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="175" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery">
                    <main>Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake's attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake's customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake's <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2015 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author, </role>
                    <role>delineator.  Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription, lower right.</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1779">c. 1778-85?<note>The date of this work is far from certain.  Blake may have executed this drawing while still an apprentice to James Basire, 1772-79.  See also the companion drawing, *Figures from a Greek Vase, after D'Hancarville: The Apotheosis of Bacchus*, Butlin 174.  The reference to Alexander Gilchrist's biography of Blake, first published in 1863, in Tatham's inscription suggests that he did not write this note until that date or later.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>27.4 x 41.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>28.2 x 20.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink over pencil<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>J WHATMAN</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none recorded</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Apparently inherited by Catherine Blake upon the death of her husband, William Blake, in 1827; inherited by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold by Tatham to the British Museum in October 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1867,1012.208</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but175.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT175.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 175)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>27.4 x 41.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  The bull occupies the center of the composition where it moves rightward with both front legs raised.  This animal represents Bacchus in the form of a bull.  In front of Bacchus is a winged female figure wearing a long gown and a spiky crown.  She walks rightward with her right leg and appears to pull with both hands on a string or rope attached to the bull's head.  This figure represents Genius, either Acratus in female guise or Ariadne.  In addition to the bull Bacchus and the female figure, there are four male attendants, all of whom have short curly hair, prominent genitals, and are nude except for a length of drapery and a hat or crown. The first attendant stands to the right of the bull, which he attempts to lead rightward with his right arm.  He holds a long torch in his left hand.  A second male attendant, upper left, faces and strides right.  He holds what appears to be a torch in his right hand (though the flame is not visible) and raises his bent left arm, which is draped.  The third male attendant stands directly above the bull in the center of the composition.  Although his body faces left, he turns his head to the right and extends both arms horizontally with hands raised and palms facing outward.  Drapery covers both of his shoulders.  The fourth male attendant, upper right, stands facing left with a torch in his left hand and drapery covering both shoulders.  This drawing is a copy of an engraving of a Greek vase painting in D'Hancarville (P. F. Hugues), <hi rend="i">Antiquités etrusques, grecques et romaines, tirées du cabinet de M. Hamilton</hi> , Naples 1766-67, volume 3, plate 36.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sacrifice</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hoof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Bacchus</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  The bull occupies the center of the composition where it walks (or perhaps is pulled) rightward with both front legs and hooves raised.  Its head is turned to face forward.  Its tail is curled upward and its horns and genitals are prominent.  This animal represents Bacchus in the form of a bull.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>string</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Genius</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Acratus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ariadne</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  In front of the bull is a winged female figure wearing a long, intricately decorated gown and a spiky crown.  She has short, curly hair and faces right.  With right leg extended forward and left bent back at the knee, she appears to walk right, perhaps leading the bull.  Both of her arms are bent at the elbow, and she holds a length of string or rope in both hands that is attached to the bull's head.  She may be pulling this rope, forcing the bull to meet her downward gaze.  This figure represents Genius, either Acratus in female guise or Ariadne.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  In addition to the bull Bacchus and the female figure, there are four male attendants, all of whom have short curly hair, prominent genitals, and are nude except for a length of drapery and a particular hat or crown.  The first of these stands to the right of the bull, which he attempts to lead rightward with his right arm.  This arm is extended and he may grasp or hold the horns of the bull.  In his left hand, the figure holds a long torch.  Facing right but looking left at the bull, this figure bends his left leg at the knee and extends his right backward, which suggests he is walking.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  In addition to the bull Bacchus and the female figure, there are four male attendants, all of whom have short curly hair, prominent genitals, and are nude except for a length of drapery and a particular hat or crown.  The second attendant stands or walks in the upper left corner of the scene.  Facing right, he carries what is likely a torch (though the flame is not visible) in his right hand with bent right arm while he raises his bent left arm horizontally.  Drapery covers this arm as well as his left shoulder.  Both legs are slightly bent and suggest he is walking.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  In addition to the bull Bacchus and the female figure, there are four male attendants, all of whom have short curly hair, prominent genitals, and are nude except for a length of drapery and a particular hat or crown.  The third attendant stands directly above the bull Bacchus in the center of the composition.  Though his body faces left, he turns his head to look right and extends both arms horizontally with hands raised and palms facing outward, fingers spread.  His left leg is slightly bent at the knee and drapery covers both of his shoulders.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five mythological figures and one animal, a bull, stand or walk in this scene representing a Bacchic Mystery.  In addition to the bull Bacchus and the female figure, there are four male attendants, all of whom have short curly hair, prominent genitals, and are nude except for a length of drapery and a particular hat or crown.  The fourth attendant stands facing left beside the upper right margin of the scene.  His left arm is bent and he holds a torch in his left hand; his right arm is bent upward with hand pointed toward the right, perhaps in a directional gesture for the other figures.  His left leg is slightly bent and raised, resulting in a contrapposto stance.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>torch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three of the four male attendant figures hold or carry torches.  The fires atop the two rightmost torches are clearly visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="49">This is an original drawing-</l>
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="49">most likely by Blake after</l>
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="63">Cumberland -</l>
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.04" justify="left" indent="42">William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.05" justify="left" indent="39">I suppose these figures were taken from</l>
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.06" justify="left" indent="39">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Cumberlands designs - vide Gilchrists life</l>
                    <l n="but175.1.penink.01.07" justify="left" indent="45">Frederick Tatham -<note>Frederick Tatham penned this inscription, although the drawing is in fact not "after [George] Cumberland" but a copy from a plate of a Greek vase painting in D'Hancarville (P.F. Hugues), *Antiquités etrusques, grecques et romaines, tirées du cabinet de M. Hamilton*, Naples 1766-67, volume 3, plate 36.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>