<bad id="but157.1" type="wc" work="Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="butlin" catid="157">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren">
                    <main>
                        Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 35KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Fitzwilliam Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.D">c. 1785</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>40.5 x 56.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>40.5 x 56.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1900</date>
                <dealer>Robert Dunthorne</dealer>
                <price>&#163;55 for all three finished water colors based on the story of Joseph and his brethren.</price>
                <note>According to Alexander Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake* (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1:57, "the three *Joseph* drawings [this work and *Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him* and *Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound*, Butlin 155 and 156] turned up within the last ten years in their original close rose-wood frames (a far from advantageous setting), at a broker's in Wardour Street [London], who had purchased them at a furniture-sale in the neighbourhood"; sold from the collection of "An Old-Established Printseller" (Walter E. Tiffin, according to Butlin 155), Sotheby's, 8 March 1860, lot 1826, with the two other *Joseph* designs noted above (&#163;10.5s. to the dealer H. Palser acting for James H. Chance); John Duke Coleridge, 1st Baron Coleridge, by 1862 (according to Butlin 155; listed in the collection of "Mr. J. D. Coleridge" by W. M. Rossetti in Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake*, 1863, 2:202); sold anonymously, Christie's, 12 Dec. 1898, lot 64, this drawing only (&#163;9.9s. to the dealer Robert Dunthorne); all three *Joseph* works sold by Dunthorne in 1900 for &#163;55 to the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, England.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">456C</repositoryid>
            </repository>
            
        </source>
        <desc id="but157.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT157.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(BUT157)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>40.5 x 56.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This watercolor depicts a biblical scene from Genesis 45:1-4 and features twelve male figures: Joseph and eleven of his brothers. Near the design's left edge, Joseph rises from a chair or throne positioned on a low platform or single step. Only the seat and front two legs of the chair are visible. Joseph faces right as he steps down from the platform with his right foot. His knee bends slightly, and his foot rests firmly on the ground. His left leg extends back behind him. Joseph wears a long-sleeved gown, the hem of which billows around and mostly covers his left leg. A narrow cord or belt may be fastened around his waist. A cape covers his shoulders, drapes across his chest, and extends down his back. Joseph leans forward, and his torso twists toward the viewer. He raises both arms from his sides and bends his elbows to hold both hands above his head. His palms face the viewer, and his fingers are spread. Joseph extends his neck and head forward; his mouth opens, suggesting that he is speaking to the brothers in front of him. Joseph's long hair falls along his neck and curls at his shoulders. Between Joseph and the right edge of the design, a group of eleven men kneel, most of them facing toward Joseph. Leftmost of this group is a man who faces left and kneels in a lunging position with his right leg bent forward at a ninety-degree angle and his left leg extended back behind him.  This is may be Benjamin, Joseph's youngest brother. The man leans forward, toward Joseph, in a posture of supplication. His bare left arm reaches upward, and his left hand may rest on Joseph's waist. The man's head tilts upward sharply as he looks toward Joseph's face. His mouth is open, and his facial expression may indicate surprise. Long, wavy hair falls down his back. The man wears a gown that covers him from the chest down but leaves his back and visible shoulder bear. The gown also coveres his right knee and gathers on the ground behind his right heel, near Joseph's right foot. Another part of the gown flows behind him before the rest of the group. Immediately behind this man, at his left knee, is an older man with short, curly, white hair and a beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown. The man kneels, facing left, and bends forward in a bowing or contracted posture. His shoulders hunch forward, and his arms bend sharply as he raises his hands toward his lowered face in a prayerful posture or to hide his face from Joseph. He gazes at the ground in front of his knees. The man sits on his heels, and both feet are visible resting beneath him on the folds of his gown. Directly above this man's head is the first of nine other kneeling brothers. They are, from left to right: a gowned and bearded man who clasps his hands and looks upward toward Joseph; a long-haired man who hunches forward and places his head in his hands; the head and shoulders of another brother with long, curly hair; a man with long hair and a beard who raises his hands in front of him as he turns back toward the brothers behind him; a frightened-looking man with short, curly hair who leans away and crosses his arms over his chest; the tops of two heads behind this man; a man with long, curly hair who leans back and sits on his heels as he raises both hands out in front of him; and, behind him, a curly-haired man in a similar posture but whose hands are not visible. The scene takes place in a room with a bare floor and a low step or platform at left (which bears the chair and from which Joseph descends). At right, behind the last of the kneeling brothers, is a vertical line that may indicate an angle in the wall or a change in its material. A similarly colored rectangle is visible on the wall at center and is flanked by what may be two fluted pilasters at right and left. Much of the design is brightly lit, but prominent shadows appear behind and below Joseph, behind the last of the kneeling brothers, and in the upper righthand corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Joseph</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cape</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stepping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the design's left edge, Joseph rises from a chair or throne positioned on a low platform or single step. Joseph faces right as he steps down from the platform with his right foot. His knee bends slightly, and his foot rests firmly on the ground. His left leg extends back behind him, and the toe of his foot pushes from the ground just in front of the chair. Joseph wears a long-sleeved gown, the hem of which billows around and mostly covers his left leg. A narrow cord or belt may be fastened around his waist. A cape covers his shoulders, drapes across his chest, and extends down his back. Joseph leans forward as he strides with bare feet onto the main floor, and his torso twists toward the viewer. He raises both arms from his sides and bends his elbows to hold both hands above his head. His palms face the viewer, and his fingers are spread. Joseph extends his neck and head forward; his mouth opens, suggesting that he is speaking to the brothers in front of him. Joseph's long hair falls along his neck and curls at his shoulders.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between Joseph and the right edge of the design, a group of eleven men kneel, most of them facing toward Joseph.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Benjamin</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Leftmost of the group of brothers is a man who faces left and kneels in a lunging position with his right leg bent forward at a ninety-degree angle and his left leg extended back behind him.  This may be Benjamin, Joseph's youngest brother. The proximity to Joseph suggests as much, since in Genesis 45:14 Joseph "fell upon his brother Benjamin's neck, and wept; and Benjamin wept upon his neck." The young man leans forward, toward Joseph, in a posture of supplication. His bare left arm reaches upward, and his left hand may rest on Joseph's waist. The man's head tilts upward sharply as he looks toward Joseph's face. His mouth is open, and his facial expression may indicate surprise. Long, wavy hair falls down his back. The man wears a gown that covers him from the chest down but leaves his back and visible shoulder bear. The gown also coveres his right knee and gathers on the ground behind his right heel, near Joseph's right foot. Another part of the gown flows behind him before the rest of the group.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately behind the lunging man, at his left knee, is an older man with short, curly, white hair and a beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown. The man kneels, facing left, and bends forward in a bowing or contracted posture. His shoulders hunch forward, and his arms bend sharply as he raises his hands toward his lowered face in a prayerful posture or to hide his face from Joseph. He gazes at the ground in front of his knees. The man sits on his heels, and both feet are visible resting beneath him on the folds of his gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Leftmost in this group is a gowned and bearded man who faces left and clasps his hands below his chin. He tilts his head backward and looks up toward Joseph; his mouth may open slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Second from left is a long-haired man who hunches forward and places his head in his hands. He faces left, toward Joseph. Only his upper body is visible, but he likely wears a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Third from left appears the head and shoulders of another brother with long, curly hair. He faces left and appears to wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Fourth from left is a man with long, curly hair and a beard who faces the viewer but turns over his left shoulder to look at the brothers behind him. He raises both hands vertically in front of him, facing each other, as if about to clap. He may be partly nude with a cloth draped over his left shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Next to the bearded man who looks over his shoulder is a frightened-looking man with short, curly hair. He wears a long-sleeved gown with a cloth draping across from his left shoulder. His torso faces the viewer, but his head turns to the left to look at Joseph. He leans away from Joseph and crosses his arms over his chest in a defensive gesture. The fingers of his right hand are spread. His mouth opens.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nose</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>forehead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Behind the man with crossed arms appear the tops of two heads. The left has short, curly hair, and the nose and eyes are barely visible behind the man in the foreground. It turns downward, perhaps looking at the ground. Only the forehead and long, straight hair of the other head are visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Benjamin</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Eighth from left is a young man with long, curly hair who faces left and leans backward to sit on his heels. His feet are flexed below, and he leans backward slightly. He bends both arms, raising his hands out in front of him with palms facing one another. His fingers are spread. The man is nude from the chest up, and is covered by a gown below. He stares toward the left edge of the design with an open mouth.  His youth might suggest that this is Joseph's youngest brother, Benjamin, but he is more probably the young man closest to Joseph and reaching up toward him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
						<characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the older man's head are nine other kneeling brothers. Behind the man sitting on his heels, at the end of the line of brothers, is a another curly-haired man who faces left and sits on his heels but hunches forward. His feet are flexed below, and he leans backward slightly. He appears to wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pilaster</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room with a bare floor and a low step or platform at left (from which Joseph descends). The room's back wall appears to be made of smooth stone. Two wide pilasters or divided panels frame a large blue square that may represent a window. At right, behind the last of the kneeling brothers, is a vertical line that may indicate an angle in the wall or a change in its material.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the platform or plinth from which Joseph descends, emerging from the left edge of the design, is the front of a four-legged chair or throne with a thick, likely cushioned seat. Only the front edge and the two curved front legs are visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> Much of the design is brightly lit, but prominent shadows appear behind and below Joseph and behind the last of the kneeling brothers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
