<bad id="but1.1" type="penink" work="The Body of Edward I in His Coffin, Two Rough Drawings" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin" catid="1" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Body of Edward I in His Coffin, Two Rough Drawings">
                    <main>The Body of Edward I in His Coffin, Two Rough Drawings</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 Society of Antiquaries
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>March 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Laura Bell,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
                    <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Edward Scheinman,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Bihan Zhang</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Body of Edward I in His Coffin, Two Rough Drawings
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>anonymous<role>Some of the inscriptions, such as the roman numerals above each image and the measurements above and on the left side of the left image may have been inscribed by someone other than Blake.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1774.A">1774<note>The design shows the body of King Edward I when his coffin was opened on 2 May 1774.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>20.0 x 14.3 cm.<note>Each of the two individual drawings on this leaf are approximately 16.5 x 5.5 cm.</note>
                </objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>20.0 x 14.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and pencil<note>The major lines in the design are in pen and ink, some over pencil.  Some shading and interior lines are in pencil, as are the measurements above and on the left side of the image on the left.  All other inscriptions are in pen and ink.  The collection mark of the Society of Antiquaries, stamped in black ink, appears bottom right.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>The drawing is pasted to a backing leaf of blue-gray paper, inscribed below the drawing "EDWARD I." in pen and ink and, lower right in pencil, "William Blake" following by two undecipherable words on a second line.  These mount inscriptions are not by Blake.</note>
                </support>
                <watermark>none visible</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>"I" and "II"<note>These numbers appear above each image.  They do not represent a sequence of drawings.</note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none<note>There are no frame lines on the drawing itself, but a single frame line in pen and ink appears on the backing leaf.</note>
                </framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1774</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its execution.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries</institution>
                <addressline>Burlington House</addressline>
                <addressline>Piccadilly</addressline>
                <addressline>London W1J 0BE</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)207 479 7080</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)207 287 6967</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: https://www.sal.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: admin@sal.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Library: +44 (0)207 479 7084</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Library: +44 (0)207 287 6967</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Library: library@sal.org.uk</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 16</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but1.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT1.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Body of Edward I in His Coffin, Two Rough Drawings</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.0 x 14.3 cm</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The Body of King Edward I lying in his coffin is shown in two views.  Shadows (or perhaps fabric lining the coffin?) darken the area around the figures' head and shoulders.  The figure wears a crown and holds a scepter in his left hand in both views.  The figure at left is more heavily draped with a shroud that covers his face.  The features and accoutrements of the figure at right are visible in greater, though still indistinct, detail.  These include closed eyes, a nose, mouth, and short hair.  Both hands hold scepters in the right view, the left topped with an indistinguishable form and the right in the shape of a cross.  Both feet are visible. The inscriptions above the views identify both bodies as Edward I, the left as he "appeard on first opening the Coffin" and the right "when some of the vestmen/ were remov'd-" (see the Textual Transcription, lines 2, 5-6).</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Edward the First</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shroud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The Body of King Edward I lying in his coffin is shown in two views.  The figure at left wears a crown and holds a scepter in his left hand.  A shroud covers his face and body.  The inscription above this view identifies the figure as Edward I, as he "appeard on first opening the Coffin" (lines 2).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>Edward the First</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shroud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The Body of King Edward I lying in his coffin is shown in two views.  The figure at right, though still presumably shrouded, is less heavily draped than in the view on the left.  His features and accoutrements are visible in greater, though still indistinct, detail.  These include closed eyes, a nose, mouth, and short hair.  He wears a crown and both hands hold scepters, the left topped with an indistinguishable form and the right in the shape of a cross.  Both feet are visible.  The inscription above this view identifies the figure as Edward I, "when some of the vestmen/ were remov'd-" (lines 5-6).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>coffin</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bodies of two dead figures, presumably male, lie in open coffins.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadows (or perhaps fabric lining the coffins?) darken the area around the figures' head and shoulders.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <columns>
                    <column>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.penink.01.01" justify="left">The body of Edward y.<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> 1.<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> as it</l>
                            <l n="but1.1.penink.01.02" justify="left">appeard on first opening the Coffin.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <vspace extent="1"/>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="3">I<note>This inscription may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                            <l n="but1.1.writtennumbers.01.04" justify="left" indent="4">2-7<note>This inscription in pencil is written upside down just above the top of the left coffin, for which it may be a measurement.  It may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <vspace extent="4"/>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.writtennumbers.01.05" justify="left" indent="2">6-7<note>This inscription in pencil is written vertically (read top to bottom) to the left of the left coffin, for which it may be a measurement.  It may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                            <l n="but1.1.writtennumbers.01.06" justify="left" indent="4">2-3<note>This inscription in pencil is written upside down across the middle of the left coffin, for which it may be a measurement.  It may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <vspace extent="4"/>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.writtennumbers.01.07" justify="left" indent="3">3<note>This inscription in pencil is written upside down within the left wall of the left coffin approximately three-quarters of the way down the leaf.  It is likely a measurement for the width of the coffin's walls.  It may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <vspace extent="4"/>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.writtennumbers.01.08" justify="left" indent="?">1-10<note>This inscription in pencil is written upside down jut above the bottom edge of the left coffin, for which it may be a measurement.  It may not be by Blake.  To the left of this inscription are some pencil marks that may include the letter "V", but this is uncertain.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </column>
                    <column>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.penink.01.09" justify="left">The body as it appeard</l>
                            <l n="but1.1.penink.01.10" justify="left">when some of the vestmen</l>
                            <l n="but1.1.penink.01.11" justify="left">were remov'd-</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but1.1.pennumbers.01.12" justify="left" indent="?">II<note>This inscription may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </column>
                </columns>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>