<bad id="but141.1" type="mono" work="Robinson Crusoe Outside His Encampment" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="141">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Robinson Crusoe Outside His Encampment">
                    <main>
                        Robinson Crusoe Outside His Encampment</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Robinson Crusoe Outside His Encampment
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.Q">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>17.4 x 22.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.4 x 22.7 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.135</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but141.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT141.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Robinson Crusoe Outside His Encampment</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 141)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>17.4 x 22.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>For another illustration by Blake to Daniel Defoe's 1719 novel, *Robinson Crusoe*, see Butlin 140 recto, *Robinson Crusoe Discovers the Footprint in the Sand*.  The reasons for Blake illustrating Defoe's novel are not known.  Perhaps he was commissioned to illustrate a new edition, but this project never went beyond these two wash drawings.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The subject of this drawing has been identified as the encampment of Robinson Crusoe, the protagonist of Daniel Defoe's 1719 novel. In the lower left-hand quarter is a circular palisade constructed with stakes, some of which have sprouted into small trees. Their branches merge above the structure, creating a canopy of leaves. A small patch of indeterminate vegetation appears on the ground at the palisade's base, around its right side. Further to the right, a small ladder leans against the wall. Its sides and eight rungs appear to be made of wood. The ground around the palisade is otherwise bare. Above the center of the structure three straight lines merge into a point, perhaps suggesting the edge of a roof behind the leafy canopy. Behind the palisade, occupying most of the design's background, is a large rock formation. At left the rock forms a wall behind the palisade, and several trees spring outward in different directions from a ledge near the center of the design. Furthest left are three palm trees: one that shoots upward at nearly 135 degrees, and two that extend horizontally toward the design's left edge. Each tree has many pointed leaves; the lower two have segmented trunks and appear to bear coconuts. Above and to the right of the three palms is a large deciduous tree with a thicker, curving trunk and much darker leaves. The tree leans leftward, over the palisade, and three branches extend to the right; two bear leaves. In the right half of the design, the rock formation separates into numerous round boulders that protrude at various angles from the rock wall. Between two of these is another deciduous tree, alike in shape and shade to the large one at left, though smaller. The tree leans right, outward from the rock formation, and it bears four large groups of leaves. From this tree's base extends the trunk of another, smaller tree that lays over toward the design's right border. The tree is nearly horizontal and may be damaged. It still bears leaves, however, and appears to be of the same deciduous variety as those around it. Above and to the right of these trees is a similar one; its lighter shade suggests that it is farther away. It has two main branches, each with large groups of leaves that extend nearly to the upper and right borders of the design. Behind the cluster of trees, beyond the edge of the rock formation, is a shadowy backdrop. Below the cluster of trees are more rounded boulders, which frame a small, rectangular door in the rock wall. The door appears to have a wooden frame; no doorknob is visible. Below and to the right of the door, in the design's lower right-hand corner, stands a small Crusoe figure. Left unfinished, in pencil alone, the figure stands with legs spread and arms crossed (left over right). He faces forward and may be striding forward and to the right with his left leg; his head may tilt downward and to the right, as if looking toward the ground near his left foot. The figure appears to be nude. Lines above and around his head may suggest motion or may represent a head covering of some sort. It has been suggested that Crusoe is shown discovering--or sowing--the barley and rice that sprang up from discarded husks of corn. These plants may be indicated by a series of short, scattered lines in the lower right corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="structure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>hut</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fence</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ladder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left-hand quarter is a circular palisade constructed with stakes, some of which have sprouted into small trees. Their branches merge above the structure, creating a canopy of leaves. At the right side of the palisade, a small ladder leans against the wall. Its sides and eight rungs appear to be made of wood. Above the center of the structure three straight lines merge into a point, perhaps suggesting the edge of a roof behind the leafy roof.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                        <characteristic>trees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaves</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Some of the palisade's stakes have sprouted into small trees. Their branches merge above the structure, creating a canopy of leaves. A small patch of indeterminate vegetation exists on the ground at the palisade's base, around its right side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>The ground around the palisade is mostly bare. Behind the palisade, occupying most of the design's background, is a large rock formation. In the right half of the design, the rock formation separates into numerous round boulders that protrude at various angles from the rock wall.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coconut</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several trees spring outward in different directions from the ledge of the rock wall. Furthest left are three palm trees: one that shoots upward at nearly 135 degrees, and two that extend horizontally toward the design's left edge. Each tree has many pointed leaves, and the lower two appear to bear coconuts. Above and to the right of the three palms is a large deciduous tree with a thicker, curving trunk and much darker leaves. The tree leans leftward, over the palisade, and three branches extend to the right; two bear leaves. Between two of the boulders in right side of the design is another deciduous tree, alike in shape and shade to the large one at left, though smaller. The tree leans right, outward from the rock formation, and it bears four large groups of leaves. From this tree's base extends the trunk of another, smaller tree that lays over toward the design's right border. The tree is nearly horizontal and may be damaged. It still bears leaves, however, and appears to be of the same deciduous variety as those around it. Above and to the right of these trees is a similar one; its lighter shade suggests that it is farther away. It has two main branches, each with large groups of leaves that extend nearly to the upper and right borders of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Behind the cluster of trees, beyond the edge of the rock formation, is a shadowy backdrop.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the cluster of trees are more rounded boulders, which frame a small, rectangular door in the rock wall. The door appears to have a wooden frame; no doorknob is visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Robinson Crusoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>planting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below and to the right of the door, in the design's lower right-hand corner, stands a small Crusoe figure. Left unfinished, in pencil alone, the figure stands with legs spread and arms crossed (left over right). He faces forward and may be striding forward and to the right with his left leg; his head may tilt downward and to the right, as if looking toward the ground near his left foot. The figure appears to be nude. Lines above and around his head may suggest motion or may represent a head covering of some sort. It has been suggested that Crusoe is shown discovering--or sowing--the barley and rice that sprang up from discarded husks of corn.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>It has been suggested that Crusoe is shown discovering--or sowing--the barley and rice that sprang up from discarded husks of corn. These plants may be indicated by a series of short, scattered lines in the lower right corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
