<bad id="but112.1" type="mono" work="Moses and Aaron(?) Flanked by Angels" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="princeton" catalog="butlin" catid="112">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Moses and Aaron(?) Flanked by Angels">
                    <main>
                        Moses and Aaron(?) Flanked by Angels</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Princeton University Library.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Moses and Aaron(?) Flanked by Angels
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.H">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>45.5 x 59.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1<note>The leaf has been folded vertically down the center.</note></numberleaves>
                <leafsize>45.5 x 59.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and monochrome washes</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Princeton University Library</name>
                <date>1975</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired by William A. White no later than 1905; the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach probably by c. 1927; Rosenbach's successor, the dealer John Fleming, probably c. 1952; sold to Caroline Newton in 1957; bequeathed by Newton in 1975 to Princeton University Library.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Princeton University Library</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">GC115 wooden drawer 8</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but112.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT112.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Moses and Aaron(?) Flanked by Angels</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 112)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>45.5 x 59.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design is set in a room or other space with bare floors and walls. Two wide steps appear in the center, and on the top step sit two men, presumably Moses and Aaron, on chairs or thrones. Both wear long-sleeved, floor-length gowns and face forward as they hold tablets or books. The man at left (Moses) has long, white hair and a long, white beard. His left foot emerges from below the hem of his gown, and he appears to hold a tablet diagonally with both hands in front of his torso. Moses turns his head slightly to the right and gazes toward the angels near the design's right border. At right, Aaron has darker, curlier hair. He holds his book or tablet in his lap, gripping the upper corners with curved fingers. Aaron tilts his head downward to gaze at the book. The head and shoulders of an angel with long, curly hair appear between Moses and Aaron. The angel stands, sits, or hovers behind the seated brothers and turns his head slightly to the left, looking toward Moses or toward the child who stands at left. This young boy stands contrapposto, his torso facing forward with his left foot in front and his left hand on his hip. The boy may be nude or wear a transparent gown; he has short, curly hair. His head turns sharply to the right, and his chin tilts upward as he gazes toward Moses or toward the angel behind him. Seated below the boy, on the top of two large steps that extend across the lower portion of the design, is another child. This boy has long hair and appears to wear a knee-length gown. He sits, facing forward and to the right, with both legs extended and his feet resting on the top of the lower step. In his lap he holds a tablet on which he writes or draws with his right hand. His left hand holds the left side of the tablet near his left knee. The boy's head faces downward as he looks at his work. These five central figures are flanked by two groups of angels--four on the left and five on the right--who hover over the steps. The four angels at left face the right side of the design and lean in toward Moses and the others. The angel nearest the viewer wears a long skirt and a draped cloth across his chest. His right foot appears below the hem of his skirt, and his short, curly hair flows behind him. The angel's right arm bends to hold a cloth or large sheet of paper out in front of him. His left arm may extend to support the object. Immediately to the right of this angel is another, similarly clothed in a long skirt or gown. His left foot extends downward toward the step below him, his left arm rises slightly in font of him, and his head tilts downward as he looks toward the floor. The third angel, of uncertain gender, also faces right and hovers over the stairs. Above these three, in the upper left-hand corner of the design, appear the loosely sketched head and upper body of another angel. This angel faces directly right and appears to have long, straight hair. The five angels at right appear in a cluster with the two in front more clearly defined. The angel in front faces away and to the left as he hovers over the steps. His left foot extends downward from the billowing hem of his long gown. His body curves to the left, his hip nearing Aaron's left hand, and his shoulders curve back to the right. He holds a large book at his side, underneath his right arm. His left arm may be bent in front of him. The angel's long hair extends down his back and across his right shoulder as he turns to look at Moses and Aaron. To the right of this angel is another facing left. He has short, curly hair and wears a long gown or cape. Behind these angels are three more. At left, an angel faces forward but turns his head rightward to face his neighbor whose head can be seen facing left. The third angel's head appears in the very upper right-hand corner of the design. He appears to have short hair, and his head tilts downward slightly as if looking toward the human figures in the center.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Moses</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the top step sit two men, presumably Moses and Aaron, on chairs or thrones. The man at left (Moses) has long, white hair and a long, white beard. He wears a gown that touches the floor, revealing only his left foot. Moses's legs are spread, and his knees bend as his sits, facing forward. Both his arms bend to hold a tablet diagonally in front of his torso with his right hand lower and left hand higher. Moses turns his head slightly to the right and may gaze toward the group of angels near the design's right border. The young figure left of Moses may lean on his right leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>Aaron</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the top step sit two men, presumably Moses and Aaron, on chairs or thrones. At right, Aaron has darker, curlier hair and wears a floor-length gown. His feet emerge from beneath the hem. He faces forward with his knees and arms bent symmetrically. Aaron holds his book or tablet in his lap, gripping the upper corners with curved fingers. Aaron tilts his head downward to gaze at the book. He may be reading.  A few lines on the open book or tablet suggest a text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of an angel with long, curly hair appear between Moses and Aaron. The angel stands, sits, or hovers behind the seated brothers. He faces forward but turns his head slightly to the left to look toward Aaron or toward the child who stands at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Next to Moses, a young boy stands contrapposto, his torso facing forward with his left foot in front and his left hand on his hip. His left arm bends, and he may lean slightly to rest his elbow on Moses's right knee. His right arm dangles behind his back. The boy may be nude or wear a transparent gown. He has short, curly hair. His head turns sharply to the right, and his chin tilts upward as he gazes toward Moses or toward the angel behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drawing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another child sits on the top of two large steps that extend across the lower portion of the design. This boy has long hair and appears to wear a knee-length gown. He sits, facing forward and to the right, with both legs extended and his feet resting on top of the lower step. His arms are bent, and in his lap he holds a tablet on which he writes or draws with his right hand. His left hand holds the left side of the tablet, near his left knee. The boy's head faces downward as he looks at his work.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The five central figures are flanked by two groups of angels--four on the left and five on the right--who hover over the steps, facing toward the design's center.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>page</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four angels at left face toward the right side of the design and lean in toward Moses and the others. The angel nearest the viewer wears a long skirt and a draped cloth across his chest. His right foot appears below the hem of his skirt, and his short, curly hair flows behind him. His mouth is open. The angel's right arm bends to hold a cloth or large sheet of paper out in front of him. His left arm may extend to support the object.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four angels at left face toward the right side of the design and lean in toward Moses and the others. Next to the angel holding the cloth or paper is another, similarly clothed in a long skirt or gown. He also has short, curly hair. This angel's left foot extends downward toward the step below him as he hovers toward the center group; alternatively, it could be the left foot of the angel behind him at right. His left arm rises slightly in font of him, and his head tilts downward as he looks toward the floor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four angels at left face toward the right side of the design and lean in toward Moses and the others. The third angel, of uncertain gender, also appears to wear a long gown. He(?) faces forward and to the right and hovers over the stairs near the children. His left foot may be visible below his gown; alternatively, it could be the left foot of the angel in front of him at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four angels at left face toward the right side of the design and lean in toward Moses and the others. Above the three angels in the front of this group, in the upper left-hand corner of the design, appears the loosely sketched head and upper body of another angel. This angel faces directly right and appears to have long, straight hair. Evidence of drapery or a gown is visible around the figure's right arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The five angels at right appear in a cluster with the two in front more clearly defined. The angel nearest the viewer faces away and to the left as he hovers over the steps. His left foot extends downward from the billowing hem of his long gown. His body curves to the left, his hip nearing Aaron's left hand, and his shoulders curve back to the right. He holds a large book at his side, underneath his right arm. His left arm appears to be bent in front of him. The angel's long hair extends down his back and across his right shoulder as he turns to look at Moses and Aaron. His mouth may open slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The five angels at right appear in a cluster with the two in front more clearly defined. To the right of the angel with the book is another facing left. He has short, curly hair and wears a long gown or cape. This angel also looks toward Moses and Aaron.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two foregrounded angels at right are three more. At left, an angel faces forward but turns his head rightward to face his neighbor whose head can be seen facing left. He has short hair and may wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two foregrounded angels at right are three more. The center angel appears to face left, but only part of his head is visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two foregrounded angels at right are three more. The third angel's head appears in the very upper right-hand corner of the design. He appears to have short hair, and his head tilts downward slightly as if looking toward the human figures in the center.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design is set in a room or other space with bare floors and walls. Two wide steps appear in the center and form a platform or stage on which Moses and Aaron sit.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Moses and Aaron likely sit on chairs or thrones atop the stairs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>