<bad id="but104.1" type="mono" work="Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="philadelphia" catalog="butlin" catid="104">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan">
                    <main>Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Philadelphia Museum of Art.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
           <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>September 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>December 2011</date>
                <respstmt>
                         <resp>Editors: </resp>
                         <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;                   
                         <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                         University of California, Riverside; and                    
                         <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                         University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill                    
                         <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                         <name>William Shaw</name>
                         <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                         <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                         <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                         <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                         <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester</resp>
                         <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                         <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                         <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                         <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                         <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                         <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                         <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                         <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                         <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                         <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                         <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                         <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                         <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                         <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                         <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                         <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.E">c. 1780<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>25.4 x 28.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>25.4 x 28.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Philadelphia Museum of Art</name>
                <date>1972</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
            
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 174 with seven other works by Blake (9s. to Gould Weston); Mrs. Hunter-Weston, probably by inheritance; Nora Hunter, probably by inheritance; sold Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 18 (&#163;136.10s. to the dealer Charles Sessler, probably acting for Mrs. William T. Tonner); given by Tonner to the Philadelphia Museum of Art in 1964 but not received until 1972.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Philadelphia Museum of Art</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1964-110-6</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but104.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT104.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 104)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>25.4 x 28.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Two groups of warring angels led by Satan at left and Michael at right confront each other in the center of this composition. The largest figure on the right is the muscular male figure Michael who flies or hovers facing forward. Leaning to the left, he turns his head to face left and down to look toward Satan at left. Michael has long hair and is nude except for a thin strip of cloth or drapery that covers his right hip and genitals. His arms are bent and raised in front of his chest where he holds and extends a sword forward. His right leg is straight and his left is bent backward slightly. He may wear a shield on his back; alternatively, the shield could be held by the figure behind him at left. This figure, who appears to be male, hovers or flies behind Michael facing left. He appears to have short hair and raises his bent right arm while brandishing a sword. One of his legs is bent forward. An additional shield is visible in front of this figure at left. A group of four figures are distinct within a larger crowd of warring angels to the right of Michael in the upper right corner. The rightmost of these figures faces forward but twists his head to look right. He has short hair and may wear a gown or shirt. His right arm is bent and he holds a spear, which points to the left. The second figure from the right also faces forward but twists to look right. He has short curly hair. Only the head of the third figure from the right is visible. This figure faces left and may wear a helmet. The fourth figure in this group hovers directly above the rightmost figure and appears to face forward and wear a helmet. Many diagonal lines and circular forms in the upper right corner suggest a larger, though indistinct, crowd of warring angels bearing spears and shields. The largest figure leading the group of warring angels at left is Satan, who flies or hovers facing forward and right with head turned to look down, perhaps toward the pair of figures flying below him. He has long hair and a beard and is nude. His left arm is at his side and he may hold a shield in his left hand; his bent right arm is raised vertically to hold a spear aloft. He bends to the right and his left leg is bent and extended forward. A pair of figures fly in horizontal position facing right beneath Satan. The rightmost figure appears to be a nude male with a strip of drapery around his waist that extends below his right leg. He has long hair and his body is horizontal facing down. His head is raised to look right, perhaps toward Michael. His right arm is raised horizontally, and he holds a shield in his right hand. His left arm is raised horizontally and extended backward; he holds two arrows or small spears in his left hand. His right leg is bent backward and up. The second figure in the pair flies or hovers slightly behind the first figure and has a similar horizontal body position facing down. This figure's right arm appears to be extended forward and right with a shield in its right hand. Drapery is visible around this figure's waist. This figure, whose gender is indeterminate, turns its head back to look left and extends its left arm toward another figure at left. This short-haired figure flies in from the left side of the composition with body horizontal facing down with head turned away and left. Its right arm is bent and extended forward. Its bent left arm may be visible above its body; alternatively, a second figure with only its head and one arm visible, may fly or hover above this figure. A third male figure is visible above this figure or pair near the left margin. He flies or hovers facing right and has short hair and perhaps a beard. He holds a shield in front of his body. As on the right side of the composition, the indistinct bodies and weapons of several additional figures are visible behind and to the right of Michael in the left half of the design. All appear to face right. The clearest of these figures are two warring angels with bodies positioned horizontally directly right of Michael. The lower figure in the pair has short hair and an open mouth. He points a spear toward Michael and his warriors. The higher figure in the pair faces down and raises a sword behind his right shoulder with his bent right arm. A large banner or flag waves above the group of warring angels on the left side of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Michael</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of warring angels led by Satan at left and Michael at right confront each other in the center of this composition. The largest figure on the right is the muscular male figure Michael who flies or hovers facing forward. Leaning to the left, he turns his head to face left and down to look toward Michael at left. Satan has long hair and is nude except for a thin strip of cloth or drapery that covers his right hip and genitals. His arms are bent and raised in front of his chest where he holds and extends a sword forward. His right leg is straight and his left is bent backward slightly. He may wear a shield on his back; alternatively, the shield could be held by the figure behind him at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind and above Michael flies or hovers a figure who appears to be male and faces left. He is likely a warring angel. He has short hair and raises his bent right arm while brandishing a sword. One of his legs is bent forward. A shield is visible in front of this figure at left, and he may hold an additional shield in his right hand, though this shield may alternatively be worn by Michael in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of four figures are distinct within a larger crowd of warring angels to the right of Michael in the upper right corner. The rightmost of these figures faces forward but twists his head to look right. He has short hair and may wear a gown or shirt. His right arm is bent and he holds a spear, which points to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of four figures are distinct within a larger crowd of warring angels to the right of Michael in the upper right corner. The second figure from the right also faces forward but twists to look right. He has short curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of four figures are distinct within a larger crowd of warring angels to the right of Michael in the upper right corner. Only the head of the third figure from the right is visible. This figure faces left and may wear a helmet.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of four figures are distinct within a larger crowd of warring angels to the right of Michael in the upper right corner. The fourth figure in this group hovers directly above the rightmost figure and appears to face forward and wear a helmet.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Many diagonal lines and circular forms in the upper right corner suggest a larger, though indistinct, crowd of warring angels bearing spears and shields.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of warring angels led by Satan at left and Michael at right confront each other in the center of this composition. The largest figure leading the group of warring angels at left is Satan, who flies or hovers facing forward and right with head turned to look down, perhaps toward the pair of figures flying below him. He has long hair and a beard and is nude. His left arm is at his side and he may hold a shield in his left hand; his bent right arm is raised vertically to hold a spear aloft. He bends to the right and his left leg is bent and extended forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arrow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A pair of figures fly in horizontal position facing right beneath Satan near the left lower margin of the design. The rightmost figure appears to be a nude male with a strip of drapery around his waist that extends below his right leg. He has long hair and his body is horizontal facing down. His head is raised to look right, perhaps toward Michael. His right arm is raised horizontally, and he holds a shield in his right hand. His left arm is raised horizontally and extended backward; he holds two arrows or small spears in his left hand. His right leg is bent backward and up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A pair of figures fly in horizontal position facing right beneath Satan near the left lower margin of the design. The second figure in the pair flies or hovers slightly behind the first figure and has a similar horizontal body position facing down. This figure's right arm appears to be extended forward and right with a shield in its right hand. Drapery is visible around this figure's waist. This figure, whose gender is indeterminate, turns its head back to look left and extends its left arm, perhaps to reach toward another figure at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least two figures fly or hover against the left margin of the composition. The lowest figure is a short-haired figure who flies in from the left side of the composition with body horizontal facing down with head turned away and left. Its right arm is bent and extended forward, perhaps to reach toward the flying figure below at right. Its bent left arm may be visible above its body; alternatively, a second figure with only its head and one arm visible, may fly or hover above this figure. Curling drapery extends downward from this figure's torso.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least two figures fly or hover against the left margin of the composition. The highest figure in this group flies or hovers facing right and has short hair and perhaps a beard. He holds a shield in front of his body.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>As on the right side of the composition, the indistinct bodies and weapons of several additional figures are visible behind and to the right of Michael in the left half of the design. All appear to face right. The clearest of these figures are two warring angels with bodies positioned horizontally directly right of Michael. The lower figure in the pair has short hair and an open mouth. With left arm bent across his body, he points a spear toward Michael and his warring angels.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands behind head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>As on the right side of the composition, the indistinct bodies and weapons of several additional figures are visible behind and to the right of Satan in the left half of the design. All appear to face right. The clearest of these figures are two warring angels with bodies positioned horizontally directly right of Michael. The higher figure in the pair faces down and raises a sword behind his right shoulder with his bent right arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>flag</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>banner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flagpole</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A large banner or flag on a pole waves above the group of warring angels on the left side of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
