<bad id="but154v.1" type="penc" work="A Warrior in Armour Kneeling Before a Bearded Elder" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="butlin" catid="154v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Warrior in Armour Kneeling Before a Bearded Elder">
                    <main>A Warrior in Armour Kneeling Before a Bearded Elder</main> : electronic
                    edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work courtesy Fitzwilliam Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
             <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>August 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired</change>
                <date>February 2005</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Conversion: </resp>
                    <name>Aziza Technology Associates</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *A Warrior in Armour Kneeling Before a Bearded Elder* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Anonymous<role>inventor. The fleur-de-lis lower right, or at least its
                        coloring, may not be by Blake.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>37.8 x 52.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>37.8 x 52.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The fleur-de-lis, lower right, is tinted with water color. This
                        motif, or at least its coloring, may not be by Blake.</note></medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1982</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by
                    Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; possibly the
                    dealer Joseph Hogarth, sold from his stock, Southgate and Barrett auction,
                    London, 7-30 June 1854, lot 5082, with 21 other works by Blake, on the twelfth
                    evening (16s. to "Edsall," probably a dealer); Richard Johnson; sold from
                    Johnson's collection, Platt's auction, London, 25 April 1912, lot 702 with 16
                    other works (&#163;11.11s. to Archibald G. B. Russell); sold Sotheby's, 28 May
                    1934, lot 171 with another pencil drawing (wrongly?) attributed to Blake
                    (&#163;5.10s. to Geoffrey Keynes); bequeathed by Keynes in 1982 to the
                    Fitzwilliam Museum and accessioned by the Fitzwilliam in 1985.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline>
                <addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)1223 332900</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)1223 332923</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/index.html</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints:
                    fitzmuseum-pdp@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints:
                    http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/pdp</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 332927</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 768591</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Image Library:
                    fitzmuseum-photography@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Photographic Service:
                    http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/photography</addressline>
                <department>Paintings, Drawings, and Prints</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">PD.170-1985</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but154v.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT154.1.1v.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Warrior in Armour Kneeling Before a Bearded
                    Elder</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 154 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The fleur-de-lis lower right, or at least its coloring, may not be by
                        Blake.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>37.8 x 52.2 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A young man dressed as a knight kneels in the center of this
                        composition facing right where an older gowned and bearded man who wears a
                        crown stands facing him. This man may have just risen from a chair or throne
                        faintly visible against the right margin of the drawing. He may be a king.
                        At far left, a pair of figures&#8212;a second bearded old man and an
                        adolescent (perhaps a page?)&#8212;stand facing right. Between this pair and
                        the kneeling knight, three figures appear to stand, float, or hover slightly
                        above the other figures. The figure on the left of this group may be holding
                        a staff of some sort. The central knight may petition the king on behalf of
                        the two figures standing behind him at left. Curving lines upper left may
                        represent clouds or a curtain. The fleur-de-lis lower right may not be by
                        Blake.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knight</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A young man dressed as a knight with a helmet, armor, and a
                            long cape kneels in the center of this composition facing right. The
                            helmet may be adorned with feathers. His left arm is bent at a right
                            angle in front of his chest, and with his right, which is by his side,
                            he points or gestures toward the pair of figures standing behind him. He
                            appears to look toward the older man (a king?) in front of him and may
                            petition on behalf of the two figures behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the drawing, an old man with long hair
                            and a beard stands facing left. He wears a gown with a long cape or
                            cloak (secured with a prominent knot above his left shoulder) and a
                            crown. He may have arisen from the chair or throne visible along the
                            right margin of the drawing. He may be a king. Both arms are extended by
                            his side with palms facing up and fingers spread. His left leg, visible
                            beneath the folds of his gown, is bent, indicating the figure may step
                            or walk forward with his left leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At far left, a pair of figures&#8212;a second bearded adult
                            man and an adolescent (perhaps a page?)&#8212;stand facing right. The
                            gowned adult figure has long hair and a beard and turns his head down,
                            perhaps to look toward the kneeling knight. His left arm is bent at a
                            right angle across his chest, and his right arm is by his side; he may
                            be holding the hand of the adolescent to the left. His left foot appears
                            to be extended slightly behind his right suggesting a contrapposto
                            stance.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At far left, a pair of figures&#8212;a second bearded adult
                            man and an adolescent (perhaps a page?)&#8212;stand facing right. The
                            younger figure, who is likely male, stands with his head slightly
                            lowered, perhaps to look toward the knight in front of him. His left arm
                            is bent, and with his left, he may hold the hand of his older companion.
                            He may wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between the pair of figures at far left and the kneeling
                            knight, three (gowned?) figures appear to stand, float, or hover
                            slightly above the other figures. The figure on the left of this group
                            may hold a staff next to the right side of its body.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The knight in the center of the drawing kneels on a slightly
                            elevated object (perhaps part of the king's throne or chair?) and a
                            fleur-de-lis, colored golden brown, is visible right of the knight's
                            foot. The fleur-de-lis, or at least its coloring, may not be by Blake. A
                            chair or throne is faintly visible against the right margin of the
                            drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curtain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The curving lines upper left may represent clouds or a
                            curtain.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
