<bad id="but122v.1" type="penink" work="The Good Farmer" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="122v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Good Farmer">
                    <main>The Good Farmer</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 William Blake Archive
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Good Farmer*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85<note>The monochrome wash drawing of the same subject and basic design on the recto probably dates from the same period.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>33.0 x 47.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>33.0 x 47.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink over pencil<note>Touched with wash on the child lower left.  The wash over and above the faces of the adult figures lower left is haphazard and may be an error.  Several figures are in pencil only.  The inscription (not by Blake) top left is in pencil; see the Textual Transcription.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>The work was seriously damaged in 1977; see the Note on Provenance.  The leaf was subsequently repaired.</note>
                </support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>See the Textual Transcription of the pencil inscription, not by Blake.</note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Collection of Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1977</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>$159</price>
                <note>Early history not known; Alexander Macmillan by 1876; William Augustus White; acquired by the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach from White's estate in 1927; George C. Smith, Jr., sold from his collection, Parke-Bernet auction, New York, 2 Nov. 1938, lot 103 ($375 to the dealer R. Allan, possibly acting for the vendor's sister Mrs. Artemas Holmes); Dorothy S. Holmes by inheritance; offered from the estate of Dorothy S. Holmes, Sotheby's, 18 Nov. 1976, lot 163 (not sold on an estimate of £3000-4000); agreement to purchase made between the estate of Dorothy S. Holmes and Robert N. Essick in summer 1977 but seriously damaged during transport from Sotheby's New York to Sotheby's Los Angeles; the drawing, now in several separate pieces, acquired by Sotheby's insurance company, late summer 1977; acquired by Essick from the insurance company for $159 in Oct. 1977 and subsequently repaired.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena, California</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but122v.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT122.1.1v.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Good Farmer</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 122 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    Blake developed this subject and basic composition through a series of eight further drawings, including Butlin 120 recto, 120A recto and verso, 121, 122 recto, 123 recto, 124, and possibly untraced 125, *Christ as the Good Shepherd.
                </objnote>
                <objsize>33.0 x 47.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <related objectid="but120r.1.penink.01"/>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The general theme and subject of this composition were probably influenced by several biblical passages, including Ruth 2:1-17, I Samuel 12:16-19, and Matthew 9:38.  Christ stands facing right in the center of the composition with both arms extended, at least the right palm facing out to the right.  His right foot is prominent beneath his cloak and gown.  He turns his head to the left to look down toward a group of three figures—two adults and one child—who kneel in the lower left corner of the scene.  The leftmost figure, who is female and nude above the waist, reaches both arms toward the standing figure while a kneeling child leans against her bent legs.  The second adult figure also appears to kneel and rest at least one arm by his(?) side.  This figural group may represent a family.  In the lower right corner another gowned figure, seen from the back, appears to walk or run right with both arms extended.  Many other partial and/or indistinct pencil sketches fill the scene, including the suggestion of another small standing figure (perhaps wearing a gown?) to the left of the rightmost figure in the corner, two figures standing above and behind the kneeling group, and, most prominently, another depiction of the central standing figure immediately to the left of the pen-and-ink version.  These figures lightly drawn in pencil may be alternative positions for the more prominent figures outlined in pen and ink.  Horizontal lines near the midpoint of the right side of the composition may suggest a horizon line or distant fields.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>button</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brooch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>farmer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Christ, with long hair and a beard, stands facing right in the center of the composition with both arms raised at 45 degrees, at least the right palm facing out to the right.  His right foot is prominent beneath his gown and elaborate cloak, held with a button or brooch at his right shoulder.  He turns his head to the left to look down toward a group of three figures who kneel in the lower left corner of the scene.  Pencil lines indicate a slightly different position for the figure's arms.  The figure lightly sketched in pencil to the left may be an alternative position for Christ.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of three figures—two adults and one child—kneel in supplicating postures in the lower left corner.  They may represent a family.  Pencil lines indicate slightly different outlines for their bodies or clothing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Facing right, the leftmost figure in the group of three lower left kneels on her bent right knee and prominent right foot and raises her arms horizontally, perhaps reaching toward the standing figure, at whom she also looks, in a gesture of supplication.  She wears drapery around her lower body but her bared breasts are prominent.  She may be the mother of the child in front of her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A child sits or kneels on bent legs facing left and away from the viewer, leaning against the female figure's legs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of three figures—two adults and one child—kneel in the lower left corner.  Partially obscured by his companions in front of him, the rightmost figure appears to be male and, like the female figure, draped below the waist but nude above.  In a posture of supplication, he kneels facing right and rests his left arm by his side with hand on his knee.  He looks up toward the standing male figure.  If this group represents a family, he may be the father.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner a gowned figure, drawn in pencil and seen from the back, appears to walk or run right with both arms extended, the right bent at the elbow.  This figure has long hair and appears to turn its head to look back and up at the standing male figure.  The small stature of this figure in comparison with the others may suggest it is a child.  The figure outlined to the left may be an alternative position for this figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>farmer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several partial and/or indistinct pencil sketches fill the scene, including a second depiction of, or alternative position for, the central standing figure of Christ immediately to the left of the pen and ink version.  His left arm is indistinct in this pencil version.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several partial and/or indistinct pencil sketches fill the scene, including the suggestion of another small standing figure (perhaps wearing a gown?) to the left of the child-like figure in the lower right corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several partial and/or indistinct pencil sketches fill the scene, including the heads and torsos of two figures above the kneeling group at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines near the midpoint of the right side of the composition may suggest a horizon line or distant fields.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but122v.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">The good Farmer giving his fields<note>This pencil inscription is not by Blake but would appear to be in a nineteenth-century hand.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but122v.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="3">in Famine</l>
                    <l n="but122v.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="5">both sides.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>