<bad id="but139A.1" type="mono" work="Travellers Receiving Succour(?)" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="vanda" catalog="butlin" catid="139A">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Travellers Receiving Succour(?)">
                    <main>
                        Travellers Receiving Succour(?)</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Victoria and Albert Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Travellers Receiving Succour(?)
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.P">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>23.0 x 21.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>23.0 x 21.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name>
                <date>1926</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>note recorded</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; W. Hunn; sold 1926 to the Victoria and Albert Museum.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Victoria and Albert Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">E.211-1926</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but139A.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT139A.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Travellers Receiving Succour(?)</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 139A)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>23.0 x 21.0 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Inscribed "P"(?) lower left; inscribed "Flaxman" on the verso.  These inscriptions are not by Blake.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing depicts two travelers, a man and a woman, kneeling for succor at the door of a building and being offered drink by two figures who emerge from the design's left edge. At right, nearer the viewer, the woman traveler faces left and kneels with both knees on the ground. Her prominent left leg bends sharply and is drawn up underneath her; in the design's lower left-hand corner, her bare left foot flexes to support her. Her right leg and foot appear to be hidden by the left, and by the folds of her long gown. She may sit on her heels. The woman bends at the waist and hunches her shoulders as she extends both arms leftward toward the proffered drink. Her palms face inward, and her fingers are spread around a large goblet. As the woman leans toward the benevolent figures in the doorway, her head and eyes lift to gaze at them. Her mouth opens, perhaps in speech, in exhaustion, or in preparation for drinking. She has long, wavy hair that has been gathered into a ponytail. Her sleeveless gown appears to be secured at the waist by a belt or cord, and it gathers in folds below her visible left foot. Her male companion appears behind and slightly to the left of her, and he kneels with only his left knee on the ground. It is hidden behind the woman, but his right knee bends forward, making a near right angle as his leg extends and his foot rests on the ground in front of him. This leg is bare, but the man appears to be covered from at least the waist down by a skirt or gown. A rod or stick leans against the visible leg, crossing from the inside of his right ankle over his right thigh and behind his torso. Like the woman, the man hunches his shoulders and leans toward the doorway; rather than reaching for the goblet, though, he bends his bare arms upward and raises his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. The man's eyes are raised, and his mouth is open. He appears to have short hair. At left of the travelers are two other figures who emerge from a doorway at the edge of the design to offer them drink. Nearer the viewer appear the arms and one leg of a figure of indeterminate gender, facing right. The figure's right hand grasps the handle of a large goblet, and his(?) left hand reaches around the back of the vessel to support it as he gives it to the kneeling woman. Both arms are covered by long sleeves, and the figure's gown reaches nearly to the ankles. His bare left foot rests on the ground, pointing toward the right side of the design. The design has been torn down the left side, removing the figure's body from view. At right of the figure holding the goblet is a woman who pours water into it from a pitcher of similar size. She faces forward and to the right, tilting her head downward as she pours. Her left arm bends sharply and crosses her body--she appears to grasp the pitcher's handle with both hands. The woman has long hair that has been gathered into a bun. She appears to wear a long-sleeved shirt or gown. Her lower body may have been erased or otherwise obscured. Alternatively, she may lean into the drawing's frame from the left. Immediately to the right of this woman is a vertical line that appears to represent the edge of the building; a diagonal line from its base toward the design's lower left corner marks the front limit of the building or its door. About one-third of the way up from the bottom of the design--around the height of the kneeling figures' waists--is a horizontal line. Above it, in the design's background, is a landscape of two low hills disrupted by a rough, curving pair of lines. These may represent a river or path that extends from upper right to lower left. A cloudless sky rises above the hills. Noteworthy shadows appear on the ground between the feet of the two men, at back of the pouring women's head, down the front of the travelers' bodies, and at the edge of the woman traveler's hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ponytail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>goblet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>exhausted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the right half of the design, nearer the viewer, a woman traveler faces left and kneels with both knees on the ground. Her prominent left leg bends sharply and is drawn up underneath her; in the design's lower left-hand corner, her bare left foot flexes to support her. Her right leg and foot appear to be hidden by the left, and by the folds of her long gown. She may sit on her heels. The woman bends at the waist and hunches her shoulders as she extends both arms leftward toward the proffered drink. Her palms face inward, and her fingers are spread around a large goblet. As the woman leans toward the benevolent figures in the doorway, her head and eyes lift to gaze at them. Her mouth opens, perhaps in speech, in exhaustion, or in preparation for drinking. She has long, wavy hair that has been gathered into a ponytail. Her sleeveless gown appears to be secured at the waist by a belt or cord, and it gathers in folds below her visible left foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rod</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>exhausted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind and slightly to the left of the kneeling woman appears her male companion, who also kneels but with only his left knee on the ground. It is hidden behind the woman, but his right knee bends forward, making a near right angle as his leg extends and his foot rests on the ground in front of him. This leg is bare, but the man appears to be covered from at least the waist down by a skirt or gown. A rod or stick leans against the visible leg, crossing from the inside of his right ankle over his right thigh and behind his torso. Like the woman, the man hunches his shoulders and leans toward the doorway; rather than reaching for the goblet, though, he bends his bare arms upward and raises his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. The man's eyes are raised, and his mouth is open. He appears to have short hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>giving</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>goblet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>jar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>handle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the travelers are two other figures who emerge from a doorway at the edge of the design to offer them drink. At left, nearer the viewer, appear the arms and one leg of a figure of indeterminate gender, facing right. The figure's right hand grasps the handle of a large goblet, and his(?) left hand reaches around the back of the vessel to support it as he gives it to the kneeling woman. Both arms are covered by long sleeves, and the figure's gown reaches nearly to the ankles. His bare left foot rests on the ground, pointing toward the right side of the design. The design has been torn down the left side, removing the figure's body from view.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pitcher</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>handle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pouring</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>giving</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the travelers are two other figures who emerge from a doorway at the edge of the design to offer them drink. At right of the figure holding the goblet is a woman who pours water into it from a pitcher of similar size. She faces forward and to the right, tilting her head downward as she pours. Her left arm bends sharply and crosses her body--she appears to grasp the pitcher's handle with both hands. The woman has long hair that has been gathered into a bun. She appears to wear a long-sleeved shirt or gown. Her lower body may have been erased or otherwise obscured.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ground</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately to the right of this woman is a vertical line that appears to represent the edge of the building; a diagonal line from its base toward the design's lower left corner marks the front limit of the building or its door. About one-third of the way up from the bottom of the design--around the height of the kneeling figures' waists--is a horizontal line that defines the floor or ground on which the figures stand and kneel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>path</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>road</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>In the design's background appears a landscape of two low hills disrupted by a rough, curving pair of lines. These may represent a river or path that extends from upper right to lower left. A cloudless sky rises above the hills.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>A cloudless sky rises above the hills.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Noteworthy shadows appear on the ground between the feet of the two men, at back of the pouring women's head, down the front of the travelers' bodies, and at the edge of the woman traveler's hair.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
