<bad id="but127.1" type="wc" work="An Allegory of the Bible" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="127">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="An Allegory of the Bible">
                    <main>
                        An Allegory of the Bible</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 33KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Tate Collection.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *An Allegory of the Bible*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.C">c. 1780-85</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>61.5 x 34.9 cm.<note>This measurement includes a narrow strip of paper, 8.9 cm. tapering to 8.0 cm. on the left, added at the top.</note></objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>61.5 x 34.9 cm.<note>This measurement includes a narrow strip of paper, 8.9 cm. tapering to 8.0 cm. on the left, added at the top.</note></leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1969</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Acquired by Alexander Macmillan no later than 1876; his granddaughter, Rachel M. Dyer, probably by inheritance in 1896; bequeathed by Dyer in 1969 to the National Portrait Gallery, London, and transferred to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">T01128</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but127.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT127.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">An Allegory of the Bible</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 127)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>A few marks on both pages of the open book at the top of this water color suggest a text, but these marks are illegible.  A pencil drawing of two legs, trimmed so that they are pictured only from the knees to the ankles, appears on a strip of paper pasted to the verso of this work.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>61.5 x 34.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design's setting is a large room, perhaps in a temple or church. At the top, a large, translucent book or tablet (likely representing the Bible) sits atop a parapet or altar. There appear to be some markings on the book's pages, but no words appear legibly. Beams of light emanate from the book in all directions, but especially from the right side. The side of the parapet altar, facing the viewer, is decorated with lines and circles. Its upper edge appears to be decorated with gold. Below the parapet or altar are two tiled floor spaces separated from the parapet or altar and each other by two staircases (each with five steps). Ten figures sit, kneel, stand, or walk at various points on or near the two sets of stairs. Seven of the design's figures are clustered on the top set. Uppermost, a young boy with short, curly hair stands at the edge of the parapet or altar, looks up at the book, and reaches toward it with his left hand. He may rest his hand on the edge of the parapet or altar. His gown is long, but his left shoulder and arm are bare. Below him, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. There appear to be one adult woman and five children. They are, from left to right, as follows: a young girl in a long gown and with braided hair who stands, facing right, looking down at a book in her hands; a woman who sits facing forward with legs crossed and a book sitting on her lap, while her head and shoulders turn back to look at the larger book on the parapet or altar; a young boy with short, curly hair who sits facing forward with a book in his lap; a young girl who kneels next to him, facing left, and appears to be pointing at the book; and a pair of children (one boy and one girl) who embrace and turn up and to the left to gaze at the  book on the parapet or altar. Down the lower set of stairs walks a tall man with long hair and wearing a long gown. He strides down the stairs with his left foot forward, and appears to be looking at the figures below him. His arms are raised at nearly forty-five degrees from his sides, and his palms face the viewer. This posture suggests that the man may represent Christ in this allegory; alternatively, he may be preparing to embrace the woman toward whom he walks. In the lower lefthand corner of the design, a woman and young girl hold hands and walk toward the man descending the lower stairs. The woman's long hair streams down and away from her back, and she wears a long gown with a bold (floral?) pattern. The young girl at her left wears a skirt or knee-length gown that leaves most of her back exposed, and she has her hair pulled into a ponytail. The girl reaches up to take the woman's hand but appears to be looking toward the woman-and-child pair who are seated on the upper stairs.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven of the design's ten figures are clustered on the top set of stairs. One boy stands on the top step, nearest the book, and the others sit, stand, or kneel on the lower steps. There appear to be one adult woman and six children. Most of them look upward toward the large book or are reading smaller books of their own. All of them appear to wear gowns.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
						<characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
						<characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven of the design's figures are clustered on the top set. Uppermost, a young boy with short, curly hair stands at the edge of the parapet or altar. His left leg is bent slightly, and extends backward, revealing his left foot below the hem of his long gown (the male figure below him may touch his left foot). The boy's left shoulder and arm are bare. He raises his bent left arm upward and to the left, perhaps reaching toward the book. He may rest his left hand on the edge of the parapet or altar. His head tilts upward slightly, and his eyes are raised to look at the large book above him and to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>braid</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes lowered</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the boy at top, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. Farthest left, a young girl wears a long gown; her long hair appears to be braided. She stands, facing right, with her arms bent upward to hold a small book in front of her. Her head tilts downward, and her eyes are lowered to look at the book. She may be reading.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>braid</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the boy at top, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. Second from left is a woman in a gown and with long (braided?) hair who sits on the facing forward with her legs crossed at the ankles (left over right). A large book sits on her lap, and her arms bend downward to hold it on the sides. The woman's torso twists to the right, and her upper body faces upward and to the right. She appears to be looking back over her left shoulder toward the larger book on the parapet or altar.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the boy at top, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. Third from left is a young boy with short, curly hair who wears a long-sleeved gown. He sits facing forward with a book in his lap; he holds it on both sides. He faces down and to the right, perhaps looking downward to read or to follow the direction of the young girl who kneels at his left side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the boy at top, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. Fourth from left, next to the boy holding the book, is a young girl who kneels and faces left. She bends forward and bends her left arm upward; she appears to be pointing at the book with her left hand. Her eyes may be lowered to look at the book with her companion. The girl has long, curly hair and wears a long-sleeved gown</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the boy at top, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. Farthest right, past the boy who stands at the edge of the parapet or altar, is a pair of children (one boy and one girl) who embrace and turn up and to the left to gaze at the large book on the parapet or altar. The boy on the left has short, curly hair and wears a shirt and pants, or perhaps a long-sleeved gown that has become wrapped around his legs. He crosses his legs in front of him (right over left); his body faces forward, but he twists to the left and raises his head and eyes to look at the book. The boys arms are raised from his sides at forty-five degrees. His right hand rests on the step where he sits (where he may brace himself or touch the figure standing above him at left), and his left rests on his left knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the boy at top, six figures occupy the upper set of stairs. Farthest right, past the boy who stands at the edge of the parapet or altar, is a pair of children (one boy and one girl) who embrace and turn up and to the left to gaze at the large book on the parapet or altar. The girl on the right has long hair and wears a long-sleeved gown. She sits with her lower body facing forward and her legs extended to the right down the stairs. Her upper body twists to her right as she embraces the boy from the side and behind, her left arm wrapped around his waist or leg. Her face is hidden behind the boy's head, but the position of her hair suggests that she, too, may turn to look up at the book atop the parapet or altar.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Down the lower set of stairs walks a tall man with long hair and wearing a long gown. He strides down the stairs with his left foot forward, and appears to be looking at the figures below him. His arms are raised at nearly forty-five degrees from his sides, and his palms face the viewer. This posture suggests that the man may represent Christ in this allegory of the Bible; alternatively, he may be preparing to embrace the woman toward whom he walks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower lefthand corner of the design, a woman and young girl hold hands and walk toward the man descending the lower stairs. The woman's long hair streams down and away from her back, and she wears a long gown with a bold (floral?) pattern. She strides forward with her left foot, and her right leg extends behind her toward the viewer, who sees her from behind. The woman faces away and to the right, tilting her head upward to look at the man descending the stairs. She reaches toward him with her bent right arm. Her fingers are spread. Her left arm is raised slightly away from her side, and she holds the hand of the child who follows her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower lefthand corner of the design, a woman and young girl hold hands and walk toward the man descending the lower stairs. The young girl at left wears a skirt or knee-length gown that leaves most of her back exposed, and she has her shoulder-length hair pulled into a ponytail. The girl strides forward with her left foot, extending her right leg behind her. Her left arm dangles at her side, and she reaches up with her right arm to take the woman's hand. Based on the angle of her head, she appears too look not at the man on the stairs but at the woman-and-child pair who are seated on the upper stairs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Bible</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the top of the design, a large, translucent book or tablet (likely representing the Bible) sits atop a parapet or altar. There appear to be some markings on the book's pages, suggesting a text, but the marks are illegible. Beams of light emanate from the book in all directions, but especially from the right side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>temple</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>church</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>altar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design is set in a large room, perhaps in a temple or church. At the top, a large, translucent book or table (likely representing the Bible) sits atop a parapet or altar. Beams of light emanate from the book, but especially from the right side. The side of the parapet, facing the viewer, is decorated with a pattern of lines and circles. Its upper edge appears to be decorated with gold.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stairs</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design is set in a large room, perhaps in a temple church. Below the parapet are two tiled floor spaces separated from the parapet and each other by two sets of stair cases (each with five steps).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
