<bad id="but102r.1" type="mono" work="Satan Approaching the Court of Chaos" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ycba" catalog="butlin" catid="102r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Satan Approaching the Court of Chaos">
                    <main>Satan Approaching the Court of Chaos</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Yale Center for British Art.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Satan Approaching the Court of Chaos
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.D">c. 1780<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>23.6 x 33.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>23.6 x 33.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Yale Center for British Art</name>
                <date>1975</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
            
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 174 with seven other works by Blake (9s. to Gould Weston); Mrs. Hunter-Weston, probably by inheritance; Nora Hunter, probably by inheritance; sold Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 19 (&#163;94.10s. to the dealer Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons); sold 1958 to Lady Melchett; sold from her collection, Christie's, 9 Nov. 1971, lot 78 (&#163;1155 to the dealer Baskett and Day acting for Paul Mellon); given by Mellon to the Yale Center for British Art in 1975.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Yale Center for British Art</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1975.4.1459</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but102r.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT102.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Satan Approaching the Court of Chaos</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 102 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>23.6 x 33.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>A variant pencil sketch of this design is on the verso of this monochrome wash drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Satan, the male figure flying or hovering at right, looks left toward a group of at least fourteen figures representing the Court of Chaos who hover on clouds at left. Satan is nude except for a ribbon or drapery that descends from his right shoulder, crosses in front of his torso, and curls near his left hip. His hair is short and his mouth is open. He leans left and looks directly toward the central figures in the group at left. His right arm is raised and bent upward over his head, and he holds a shield aloft in his right hand. His left hand is raised at 45 degrees and extended to the right. In his left hand, he holds a long object that could be a pole, stick, or spear with the pointed tip outside the right margin of the design. His right leg is extended backward. Faint pentimento lines are visible below his waist and around his left shoulder. At least fourteen figures are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. Two male figures in the lower left corner of the group who both have short, curly hair and beard are visible only above their torsos. Both look right and have open mouths. The lower figure holds his right arm at his side and bends his left arm upward to rest on the cloud in front of him. The figure above him turns his head up and raises his left arm horizontally to rest on the cloud in front of him or, alternatively, to hold the right knee of the figure above him at right. Above this pair of figures, four larger figures sit facing right. The leftmost of these is an old, male figure with long hair and a beard. He wears a long-sleeved shirt and bends his right arm upward near his face. He may point toward himself with his right index finger. His thighs are visible in front of him, and the figure below him may hold his right knee. To the right of this figure, a female figure with long hair and a veil or drapery over her hair sits and looks to the right although her torso is twisted forward. Her expression may be of fear or despair. Her left arm is bent and wrapped around her body, perhaps to touch the male figure at left. Her right leg is bent slightly and extended in front of her, where it disappears into the clouds. The third figure in this group from left is a male figure who sits facing forward and right. He has short curly hair and a beard. He looks directly toward Satan at right. His left arm is at his side and bent upward near his face, and he may touch the left shoulder of the female figure at left. His lower body is obscured by the clouds around him. Only the head of the fourth figure in this group from the left is visible just above the left shoulder of the third male figure. This figure appears to have short hair and closed eyes with head bent turned down slightly. The head of an additional, smaller figure is visible to the left of the leftmost large figure in this group. Only the right eye of this figure is visible facing forward and right. The heads of three smaller figures can be seen to the right of the large group of four figures. The leftmost head faces forward and left, perhaps to look back at the figures at left. The second head faces right, perhaps to look toward Satan, and has an open mouth. The third and rightmost figure in this group may face forward, though details of this figure are unclear. A group of four male figures are the uppermost figures in the Court of Chaos group. All face right and look down, perhaps toward Satan at right, with open mouths. The leftmost figure in this group has long hair and a beard. His right arm is visible near the shoulder, and his right arm may be extended forward slightly. Only the heads of the three rightmost figures are visible. The second figure from the left has short, curly hair. The details of the other two figures are not clear.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Satan, the male figure flying or hovering at right, faces forward but twists to look left toward a group of at least fourteen figures representing the Court of Chaos who hover on clouds at left. Satan is nude except for a ribbon or drapery that descends from his right shoulder, crosses in front of his torso, and curls near his left hip. His hair is short and his mouth is open. He leans left and down and looks directly toward the central figures in the group at left. His right arm is raised and bent upward over his head, and he holds a shield aloft in his right hand. His left hand is raised at 45 degrees and extended to the right. In his left hand, he holds a long object that could be a pole, stick, or spear with the pointed tip outside the right margin of the design. His right leg is extended backward. Faint pentimento lines are visible below his waist and around his left shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chaos</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos hover or sit on clouds visible in the sky in the left half of the design. The clouds are dark and may indicate a storm, or may represent the chaos of the imagery.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. Two male figures in the lower left corner of the group who both have short, curly hair and beard are visible only above their torsos and appear to be nude. Both look right, perhaps toward Satan, and have open mouths. The lower figure holds his right arm at his side and bends his left arm upward to rest on the cloud in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. Two male figures in the lower left corner of the group who both have short, curly hair and beard are visible only above their torsos and appear to be nude. Both look right and have open mouths. The second figure from the left turns his head up and raises his left arm horizontally to rest on the cloud in front of him or, alternatively, to hold the right knee of the figure above him at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The four largest figures in this group sit at center and face right. The leftmost of these is an old, male figure with long hair and a beard. He wears a long-sleeved shirt and bends his right arm upward near his face. He may point toward himself with his right index finger and look toward Satan. His legs are visible to the knee in front of him and appear to be bent. The figure below him may hold his right knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The four largest figures in this group sit at center and face right. The second figure in this group from the left is a gowned female figure with long hair and a veil or drapery over her hair sits and looks to the right although her torso is twisted forward. Her expression may be of fear or despair. Her left arm is bent and wrapped around her body, perhaps to touch the male figure at left. Her right leg is bent slightly and extended in front of her, where it disappears into the clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand near head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The four largest figures in this group sit at center and face right. The third figure in this group from left is a male figure who sits facing forward and right. He has short curly hair and a beard. He looks directly toward Satan at right. His left arm is at his side and bent upward near his face, and he may touch the left shoulder of the female figure at left whom he leans toward. His lower body is obscured by the clouds around him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The four largest figures in this group sit at center and face right. Only the head of the fourth figure in this group from the left is visible just above the left shoulder of the third male figure. This figure appears to have short hair and closed eyes with head bent turned down slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The four largest figures in this group sit at center and face right. The head of an additional, smaller figure is visible to the left of the leftmost large figure in this group. Only the right eye of this figure is visible facing forward and right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The heads of three smaller figures can be seen to the right of the large group of four figures. The leftmost head faces forward and left, perhaps to look back at the figures at left. The figure may have long hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The heads of three smaller figures can be seen to the right of the large group of four figures. The middle head faces right, perhaps to look toward Satan, and has an open mouth. Lines and shadows around the lower part of this figure's face may suggest a veil.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. The heads of three smaller figures can be seen to the right of the large group of four figures. The third and rightmost figure in this group may face forward, though details of this figure are unclear. The figure may wear a hat, veil, or have long hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. A group of four male figures are the uppermost figures in the Court of Chaos group. All face right and look down, perhaps toward Satan at right, with open mouths. The leftmost figure in this group has long hair and a beard. His right arm is visible near the shoulder, and his right arm may be extended forward slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>Chaos</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fourteen figures who represent the Court of Chaos are visible hovering or sitting on clouds near the left side of the design. A group of four male figures are the uppermost figures in the Court of Chaos group. All face right and look down, perhaps toward Satan at right, with open mouths. Only the heads of the three rightmost figures are visible. The second figure from the left has short, curly hair. The details of the other two figures are not clear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
