<bad id="but161.1" type="wc" work="Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="161">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing">
                    <main>Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of Blake’s water color illustrations to the plays of William Shakespeare. 
                 <lb/>
                <lb/>     
Although less extensive and well known than his illustrations of John Milton’s poems, Blake’s water colors based on Shakespeare’s plays constitute a significant group of designs. The earliest, dating from c. 1779, is probably one of Blake’s illustrations of English history but nonetheless evokes Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi>. The series of seven small ovals picturing characters from the plays also dates from Blake’s early years. The concentrated focus on just one or two figures filling most of the pictorial space may be Blake’s response to popular interest in miniature portraiture. The reason for his execution of this group is not known; like the English history designs, they may have been intended for eventual publication as engravings.  The series of Shakespeare character portraits by John Hamilton Mortimer, published as engravings in the mid-1770s, may have influenced Blake’s similar project.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
<hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> is one of Blake’s largest water colors of the 1780s. Its size and quality suggest that it may have been intended for exhibition, like the water colors illustrating the life of Joseph displayed at the Royal Academy in 1785. The circle of dancers and Puck’s stance with arms raised echo similar motifs in George Romney’s <hi rend="i">Leveson-Gower Family</hi>, painted in 1776-77 and published as a mezzotint by John Raphael Smith in 1781.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Blake was clearly attracted to the vision of Queen Katherine in <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, act 4, scene 2, for he executed four versions beginning c. 1783-90 and concluding with the highly finished and complex water color of c. 1825-26. Blake’s water color of Queen Katherine’s dream dated 1809 is part of a series of six illustrations to Shakespeare’s plays commissioned by Joseph Thomas, the clergyman who had earlier employed Blake to illustrate Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. In a letter of 31 July 1801 to William Hayley, John Flaxman added a postscript to Blake, including the following: “he [Thomas] also desired you [Blake] will make two designs in bister or Indian Ink, from Shakespeare’s Troylus &amp; Cressida, Coriolanus, either of the 3 plays of Henry 6.<sup>th</sup> Richard the 3.<sup>d</sup> or Henry the 8.<sup>th</sup> each design for one play for which he will give a Guinea each, the dimensions as follow the paper. an upright square of 12 Inches &amp; half by 8 Inches, within this Space leaving a moderate margin, the principal figure not exceeding 6 Inches high” (Butlin 547). Blake’s designs (most now trimmed) roughly follow these size requirements, necessitated by Thomas’s desire to create an extra-illustrated copy of the 1632 second folio of Shakespeare’s plays, but Blake waited eight years before completing the commission, changed the medium from monochrome drawings to water colors, and illustrated only two plays, <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi> and <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, specified by Flaxman. Blake may have chosen the other passages for illustration, at some point convincing Thomas of their appropriateness.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Many of Blake’s Shakespeare designs show his predilection for scenes dealing with perceptions that extend beyond the world of the physical senses. The four versions of Queen Katherine’s dream epitomize this lifelong interest in imaginative and visionary experiences. A corollary is Blake’s attraction to representations of the arts, demonstrated by <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> and his portrayal of Pegasus, the classical embodiment of poetic inspiration, in <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi> among the designs for Thomas.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, editors <lb/>
                Joseph Fletcher, managing editor, Michael Fox, assistant editor<lb/>
                 The William Blake Archive<lb/>     
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 Tate Collection </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February - March 2020</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies,</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Dan Gorman</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose</name>
                    <name>Jake Ruta</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>     
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>March 2016</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Laura Bell</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Rachel Lee,</name>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Adam Engel,</name>
<name>Andrea Everett,</name>
<name>Grant Glass,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Eric Loy,</name>
<name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
<name>Adam McCune,</name>
<name>Scott Robinson,</name>
<name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
<name>Miles Simon,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
<name>Alia Wegner,</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
           <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>March 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1785">c. 1785<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>47.5 x 67.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>47.5 x 67.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1910</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; sold by Catherine
                    Blake c. 1829 to Henry Francis Cary; sold Christie's, 13 March 1895, lot 16
                    (&#163;3.10s. to the dealer Leggatt Bros.); Alfred A. de Pass; given by de Pass
                    in 1910 to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <addressline>Millbank</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 20-7887-8888</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images: 20-7887-8871/4933</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images: 20-7887-8805</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Images: tate.images@tate.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, General: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Images: http://www.tate-images.com</addressline>
                <department/>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">N02686</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but161.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT161.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 161)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>47.5 x 67.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night in
                        this design that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi
                            rend="i">A Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. Two figures with blonde hair
                        stand beside the left margin. Facing right, the male figure at left has
                        short curly hair, a beard, and a mustache. He wears a spiky crown and a long
                        gown with additional drapery, probably a cloak, visible behind him. His left
                        leg is bent and crossed over his right. His right arm is slightly bent and
                        by his side. A staff and flower (perhaps a lily) are visible near his right
                        hand, though it seems more likely that these are held by his female
                        companion, whose left arm is wrapped around his body. This figure has long
                        hair and wears a headband or perhaps a diadem(?) as well as a long gown. She
                        faces forward but turns her head to look down and to the right as she leans
                        against her male companion at left. Her right leg is visibly bent beneath
                        her gown. This pair is Oberon, king of the Fairies, and Titania, queen of
                        the fairies, who together lead the other fairies in song and dance at the
                        end of the play. To the right of this pair, a male figure, nude from the
                        waist up, faces forward and looks toward the pair at left with a smile. He
                        has short brown hair and wears knee-length pants or breeches. Blue leaves
                        decorate his hair and waist; he also wears a necklace or ribbon tied around
                        his neck. With elbows bent, he raises both arms vertically and appears to
                        hold small instruments around the ring fingers of each hand, possibly
                        castanets or finger cymbals. His left palm faces forward while he touches
                        his thumb to his other fingers with the other hand. Both legs are bent with
                        the right extended forward, perhaps to suggest dancing. This figure is Puck,
                        also known as Robin Goodfellow, who is a hobgoblin in Oberon's service. Puck
                        acts as a wise yet mischievous character throughout the play, and he states
                        the final lines of the play: "So good night unto you all./ Give me your
                        hands, if we be friends,/ And Robin shall restore amends (Act 5, Scene 1,
                        453-5). On the right side of the scene, four figures (who may all be
                        female?) dance and hold hands in a circle. These are likely the other
                        fairies in the trains of Titania and Oberon. The leftmost figure in the
                        group faces right and wears a gown as well as a decorative headdress that
                        resembles butterfly wings. Her hair is either short or arranged in a bun.
                        She leans forward but also twists her body to raise her left arm vertically,
                        where she touches her companion with her left hand, and extend her bent
                        right arm forward to hold the hand of her other companion at right. Her left
                        leg is extended backward as she appears to move in a clockwise direction.
                        The next figure clockwise to her right faces forward but looks left and back
                        toward her companion. She also wears a long gown that includes a circular
                        flourish of fabric behind her back. Red petal-like objects adorn her head as
                        her long hair streams to the left. She raises both bent arms horizontally
                        with palms facing upward to touch the hands of her companions on either
                        side. Her right leg is extended to the left as she moves in a clockwise
                        direction. The third dancer at far right is the least distinct, though
                        she(?) also wears a gown and has leafy decorations in her short hair and
                        perhaps also around her waist. This figure faces right but turns her head to
                        look left; her mouth may be slightly open. Both arms are extended (though
                        the majority of the left is not visible), and she holds the hand of her
                        companion at left. Her left leg is extended backward. Immediately in front
                        of this figure, a disconnected arm is visible emerging from the right margin
                        of the design to hold the right hand of the final figure, which suggests the
                        complete circle of dancers contains five rather than four figures. The fully
                        visible fourth figure, however, faces left and leans forward with right leg
                        bent and left leg extended backward. She(?) wears a knee-length skirt and,
                        like the figure behind her, has leafy foliage decorating her short hair and
                        extending down her back. She extends her right arm backward to hold the
                        otherwise disembodied arm and her left forward to touch the first dancer at
                        left. The nighttime landscape in which these figures stand includes grassy
                        ground, overhead leaves and vines, and perhaps the trunks of trees upper
                        right and left. There are stars in the sky. A shadowy circle appears on the
                        ground below the dancers. This is probably Blake's imaginative version of a
                        fairy ring.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Oberon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. Two figures with blonde hair stand
                            beside the left margin. Facing right, the male figure at left has short
                            curly hair, a beard, and a mustache. He wears a spiky crown (suggesting
                            he may be a king) and a long gown with additional drapery (probably a
                            cloak) visible behind him. His left leg is bent and crossed over his
                            right. His right arm is slightly bent and by his side. A staff and
                            flower are visible near his right hand, though it seems more likely that
                            these are held by his female companion, whose left arm is wrapped around
                            his body. He appears to look toward the scene of dancing in front of him
                            at right. This figure is Oberon, king of the Fairies, who with his wife
                            Titania, queen of the fairies, lead the other fairies in song and dance
                            at the end of the play.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Titania</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. Two figures with blonde hair stand
                            beside the left margin. The female figure at right has long hair and
                            wears a headband or perhaps a diadem(?) as well as a long gown. She
                            faces forward but turns her head to look down and to the right as she
                            leans against and embraces her male companion at left. It is likely that
                            she holds in her left hand the staff or scepter and flower that are
                            visible near her companion's right hand. Her right leg is visibly bent
                            beneath her gown. This figure is Titania, queen of the Fairies, who with
                            her husband Oberon, king of the fairies, lead the other fairies in song
                            and dance at the end of the play.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A staff or scepter and the blossom of a flower, possibly a
                            lily, are visible near the right hand of the male figure standing at far
                            left though these are likely held by his female companion who wraps her
                            left arm around his body. The staff is topped with a flower, possibly a
                            fleur-de-lis.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>necklace</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Puck</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Robin Goodfellow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. Two figures with blonde hair stand
                            beside the left margin. The third figure from the left, a male figure,
                            nude from the waist up, faces forward and looks toward the pair at left
                            with a smile. He has short brown hair and wears knee-length breeches.
                            Blue flowers decorate his hair and waist; he also wears a necklace or
                            ribbon tied around his neck with a loose knot. With elbows bent, he
                            raises both arms vertically and appears to hold small musical
                            instruments around the ring fingers of each hand, possibly castanets or
                            finger cymbals. His left palm faces forward while he touches his thumb
                            to his other fingers with the other hand. Both legs are bent with the
                            right extended forward, perhaps to suggest dancing. This figure is Puck,
                            also known as Robin Goodfellow, who is a hobgoblin in Oberon's service.
                            Puck acts as a wise yet mischievous character throughout the play, and
                            he states the final lines of the play: "So good night unto you all./
                            Give me your hands, if we be friends,/ And Robin shall restore amends
                            (Act 5, Scene 1, 453-5).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Blue leaves and vines decorate the hair and waist of the third
                            figure from the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>cymbal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>castanets</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third figure from the left raises both arms vertically and
                            appears to hold small musical instruments, possibly castanets or finger
                            cymbals, around the ring fingers of each hand, which he likely
                            plays.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. On the right side of the image, four
                            figures (who may all be female?) dance and hold hands in a circle. These
                            are likely the other fairies in the trains of Titania and Oberon. The
                            leftmost figure in the group faces right and wears a gown as well as a
                            decorative headdress that resembles butterfly wings. Her hair is either
                            short or arranged in a bun. She leans forward but also twists her body
                            to raise her left arm vertically, where she touches her companion with
                            her left hand, and extend her bent right arm forward to hold the hand of
                            her other companion at right. Her left leg is extended backward and her
                            right is on tiptoe as she appears to move in a clockwise
                            direction.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>petal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. On the right side of the image, four
                            figures (who may all be female?) dance and hold hands in a circle. These
                            are likely the other fairies in the trains of Titania and Oberon. The
                            second figure in this circle clockwise to the right faces forward but
                            looks left back toward her companion. She also wears a long gown that
                            includes a circular flourish of fabric behind her back. Red petal-like
                            objects adorn her head as her long hair streams to the left. She raises
                            both bent arms horizontally with palms facing upward to touch the hands
                            of her companions on either side. Her right leg is extended to the left
                            and her left foot is on tiptoe as she moves in a clockwise
                            direction.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. On the right side of the image, four
                            figures (who may all be female?) dance and hold hands in a circle. These
                            are likely the other fairies in the trains of Titania and Oberon. The
                            third dancer at far right is the least distinct, though she(?) also
                            wears a gown and has leafy decorations in her short hair and perhaps
                            also around her waist. This figure faces right but turns her head to
                            look left; her mouth may be slightly open. Both arms are extended
                            (though the majority of the left is not visible), and she holds the hand
                            of her companion at left. Her left leg is extended
                            backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the right margin, a disconnected arm is
                            visible and appears to hold the right hand of the fourth dancer in the
                            foreground, which suggests the complete circle of dancing fairies
                            contains five rather than four figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a grassy landscape at night
                            that represents the final scene in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A
                                Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>. On the right side of the image, four
                            figures (who may all be female?) dance and hold hands in a circle. These
                            are likely the other fairies in the trains of Titania and Oberon. In the
                            lower right corner of the scene, the fourth figure faces left and leans
                            forward with right leg bent to stand on tiptoe and left leg extended
                            backward. She(?) wears a knee-length skirt and, like the figure behind
                            her, has leafy foliage decorating her short hair and extending down her
                            back. She extends her right arm backward to hold the otherwise
                            disembodied arm and her left forward to touch the first dancer at
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Blue flowers, leaves, and vines decorate the hair and waists
                            of the two rightmost dancers in the scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ivy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Seven figures stand or dance in a nighttime landscape that
                            includes grassy ground, overhead leaves and vines, and perhaps the
                            trunks of trees upper right and left. The large leaves upper left are
                            probably ivy. Pen and ink lines lower left and above the head of the
                            fairy with petal-like decorations in her hair suggest
                            reeds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ring</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A shadowy circle of light appears on the ground below the
                            dancers. This is probably Blake's imaginative version of a fairy
                            ring.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The dark coloring of the scene suggests the time is night.
                            There are stars in the sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
