<bad id="but124.1" type="mono" work="The Good Farmer" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ransom"
    catalog="bentley" catid="124">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Good Farmer"><main>The Good Farmer</main><copy> Copy 1</copy>:
                    electronic edition </title>
                <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB
                to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>November 2013</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
            only.<lb/><lb/> This work copyright © 2024 Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.
            
            <lb/><lb/></userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator,
                        University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura
                        Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project
                        Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine
                        Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea
                        Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Michael
                        Fox,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon
                        Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Morgan
                        Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam
                        McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia
                        Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair
                        Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret
                        Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa
                        Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia
                        Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants:
                        </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit
                        Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah
                        Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle
                        Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne
                        C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, and</name><name>Sarah
                    Tolf</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants:
                        </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>The Good Farmer</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780.N">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>23.5 x 39.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>23.5 x 39.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin</name>
                <date>1965</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
                
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 169 with four other works by Blake (5s. to Rowbotham, probably a dealer); Anne Gilchrist by 1863; her son, Herbert H. Gilchrist, probably by inheritance in 1885; sold Sotheby's, 24 June 1903, lot 29 (&#163;3.5s. to the dealer Dobell); Paul Carlton, sold from his collection Sotheby's, 11 Dec. 1935, lot 623 (&#163;29 to the dealer C. J. Sawyer); offered in Sawyer's 1936 catalogue 128, item 55 (&#163;63); Henry Mond, 2nd Baron Melchett; sold Sotheby's, 23 May 1951, lot 3 (&#163;90 to the dealer Jacob Schwartz); Thomas Edward Hanley; given by Hanley in 1965 to the University of Texas and now housed in the Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">65.239</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but124.1.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT124.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Good Farmer</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1"
                        >Object 1</objnumber><objcode code="U1"
                    >(Butlin 124)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>23.5 x 39.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Blake developed this subject and basic composition through a series of seven or eight further drawings, including Butlin 120 recto, 120A recto and verso, 121, 122 recto and verso, 123, and possibly untraced 125, *Christ as the Good Shepherd*.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The general theme and subject of this composition were probably influenced by several biblical passages, including Ruth 2:1-17, I Samuel 12:16-19, and Matthew 9:38.  This monochrome wash drawing depicts a gathering of people of different
                        ages, male and female, separated into different groups, but all of them are
                        in a field. The figures with the most details are in the foreground, while
                        those in the background are more sketched, holding no discernable features.
                        The largest of the background group is a collection of five figures, whom
                        all besides one are raising their arms (the other figure has their arms down
                        and out as they bend, as if to move away) to a figure descending from the
                        storm clouds above them. The figure is possibly sending out a bolt of
                        lightning as they reach toward the crowd. Opposite of this crowd are two
                        figures huddled together with their arms curled against their chest,
                        possibly walking away from the event. They are also walking toward the
                        figure standing even further to the left. The figure might be wearing a
                        cloak, and is watching the scene play out from afar. On top of the hill
                        closest to these three there is a building, likely a barn. The man in the
                        center foreground, probably Christ, is bearded with curly hair. He is standing and
                        looking down at the group of figures to the left of the piece while his arms
                        are gesturing to the field of what might be wheat beside him. He is wearing
                        a multiple layered robe, the outer layer pinned or tied at the shoulders so
                        the fabric cascades down around his arms and front like a smock. There is
                        another older male to the right of the central figure. His hair and beard
                        are long and curly. He holds his arms up with his hands held closely
                        together. He seems to be wearing a long cloak that pools on the ground above
                        his long-sleeve robes. To the left of the central male figure are about nine
                        people: seven adults of varying ages, a child, and an infant. The two
                        figures closest to the male are a kneeling woman who has a young child of
                        indeterminable gender huddled against her knees. Her arm is down at her side
                        to support the child, and her eyes are raised toward the central male
                        figure. The child sits on their side with their legs curled up. Both she and
                        the child have long hair that falls down their backs. The figure kneeling
                        beside them is almost entirely obscured, save for a head of curly hair and
                        their hands, which are held with fingers clasped together as if to plead or
                        to pray. Due to the length of his hair, it is possible the figure is male.
                        There is another male figure beside them has his eyes turned up to look at
                        the central male figure. Behind them is an elderly male with a long beard
                        that has his shoulders hunched over as he supports himself with a walking
                        stick that he holds in his right hand. His eyes are closed. Standing beside
                        him is a woman wearing a wimple, her curly hair poking out and resting
                        across her forehead. She is carrying an infant in her arms. Her eyes are
                        closed or her face is bowed slightly as she turns toward the old man and the
                        other members of the gathering. The infant has curly hair and is turned away
                        from the viewer. Next to the woman carrying the infant is possibly a couple.
                        One figure has short curly hair and the start of a beard (though it might be
                        because of the shading on his face). He has his arms crossed as he looks to
                        the right, possibly over at the background group. The other figure might be
                        female, though her face is partially warped. She has long hair, and is
                        turned away as she waves one of her hands up while her other hand rests over
                        her chest.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man in the center foreground of the wash is bearded with
                            curly hair.  This is probably Christ. He is standing and looking down at the group of figures to
                            the left of the piece while his arms are gesturing to the field of what
                            might be wheat beside him. He is wearing a multiple layered robe, the
                            outer layer pinned or tied at the shoulders so the fabric cascades down
                            around his arms and front like a smock.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There is another older male to the right of the central
                            figure. His hair and beard are long and curly. He holds his arms up with
                            his hands held closely together. He seems to be wearing a long cloak
                            that pools on the ground above his long-sleeve robes.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms reaching downward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The largest of the background group is a collection of five
                            figures, whom all besides one are raising their arms (the other figure
                            has their arms down and out as they bend, as if to move away) to a
                            figure descending from the storm clouds above them.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Their is a figure descending from the storm clouds that is
                            possibly sending out a bolt of lightning as they reach toward the
                            crowd.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two figures closest to the central male are a kneeling
                            woman who has a young child of indeterminable gender huddled against her
                            knees. Her arm is down at her side to support the child, and her eyes
                            are raised toward the central male figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There is a young child of indeterminable gender with long hair
                            is leaning against the woman's knees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> The figure kneeling beside the woman and child is almost
                            entirely obscured, save for a head of curly hair and their hands, which
                            are held with fingers clasped together as if to plead or to
                            pray.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There is another male figure kneeling with short hair that has
                            his eyes turned up to look at the central male figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking stick</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the kneeling figures is an elderly male with a long
                            beard that has his shoulders hunched over as he supports himself with a
                            walking stick that he holds in his right hand. His eyes are
                            closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>walking stick</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The elderly man holds a walking stick in his right
                            hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing beside him is a woman wearing a wimple, her curly
                            hair poking out and resting across her forehead. She is carrying an
                            infant in her arms. Her eyes are closed or her face is bowed slightly as
                            she turns toward the old man and the other members of the
                            gathering.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The infant held by the woman has curly hair and is turned away
                            from the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Next to the woman carrying the infant is possibly a couple.
                            One figure has short curly hair and the start of a beard (though it
                            might be because of the shading on his face). He has his arms crossed as
                            he looks to the right, possibly over at the background
                            group.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The other figure in the couple might be female, though her
                            face is partially warped. She has long hair, and is turned away as she
                            waves one of her hands up while her other hand rests over her
                            chest.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Based on the sketching in the middle of the piece of a grain
                            stem and tassel, this wash is likely in wheat or other grain field that
                            is ready to be reaped.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>barn</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On top of the hill closest to the three far background figures
                            on the left there is a building, likely a barn.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lightning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The sky appears to be dark with storm clouds. Lightning or
                            parts of the clouds extend toward and touch the field or towards the
                            group in the background.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
