<bad id="but185.1" type="wc" work="Pestilence" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="185">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Pestilence">
                    <main>
                        Pestilence</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 49KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Pestilence</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.B">c. 1780-84</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.3 x 27.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.3 x 27.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1976</date>
                <dealer>Andrew Edmunds</dealer>
                <price>$5000</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Joseph Hogarth, sold from his collection, Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 15 June 1854, lot 2784 (&#163;1 to "Olwen," possibly a dealer); George Thomas Nicholson of Waverley Abbey by 1863; the dealer Henry Stevens, Son, and Robert Stiles; offered anonymously, Sotheby's, 18 Dec. 1933, lot 84 (bought-in by Stevens at &#163;92); Tracy W. McGregor by c. 1933; given c. 1935 to Mrs. Clarence Cobb; offered from her collection, Christie's, 2 March 1976, lot 97 (bought-in at &#163;2400); acquired from Cobb's collection through Christie's by the dealer Andrew Edmunds, acting as agent for Robert N. Essick, April 1976 ($5000).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but185.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT185.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Pestilence</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 185)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>18.3 x 27.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design shows a scene of pestilence in a town square or other common area. The background is made up of a large building supported by heavy columns, four of which rest on a set of stairs leading to an entry way.  This might be St. Paul's Cathedral in London. Between the distant columns and the nearer one at left is a tall, arched doorway. The middle ground is a street, probably of dirt, and paving stones appear at lower left. The design's upper right quadrant contains another building, much less ornate than the columned structure at left. The second building appears to be constructed partly of brick and partly of wood, and it is covered with a sloping tile roof. An open doorway appears in the center of the building's lower level. At left of the structure the back right wheel and one side of a cart or wagon are visible. The scene is populated by at least sixteen figures, many of which are clustered into groups. In the lower left corner, a couple sits propped up against the design's largest column. At left, immediately against the column's base, is a man with short, curly hair who wears a short-sleeved shirt. He faces right, hunches his shoulders forward, and leans his head downward to rest against the head of the woman in front of him, whom he appears to support. His eyes are cast downward toward her, and his mouth opens slightly, perhaps in an expression of pity or grief. His right arm dangles at his side. He may be caring for the sick woman in front of him or may be dying himself. Sitting in front of this man, or perhaps in his lap, is a woman with long, curling hair. She wears a gown, the long skirt of which drapes over her legs and onto the ground. The woman's right leg bends sharply, and her right foot is drawn up under her hip, her toes extended toward the ground. Her left leg bends slightly and extends out in front of her, her foot flat on the ground. The woman's shoulders hunch forward as she leans against the man behind her with her arms dangling loosely at her sides. She faces forward, but her head leans toward her left shoulder. Her mouth opens slightly, and her face shows despair or resignation. She appears to be sick and may be dying. Above and to the right of the couple, in the background of the design, a man in black robes and a bicorn hat walks leftward, ringing a bell at his waist. He strides forward with his right foot and holds the bell in his right hand. He appears to hold his left arm horizontally at his waist and may have his left hand thrust into his pocket or into the folds of the robe. His head tilts downward slightly, and his eyes look toward the ground as he walks. He may be a town crier warning of the plague or calling for residents to bring out their dead. Above and to the right of the town crier, in the doorway of the columned building, are at least two nude (male?) figures who kneel at the door, facing left and raising their arms above their heads. They may be begging for entrance to the building. Moving to the right and returning to the design's foreground, a group of three figures appears near the cart or wagon. A short-haired man in a sleeveless shirt and tights(?) faces right and kneels with his left knee on the ground and his left foot flexed to support his weight. The man's right leg bends sharply out in front, and his right foot is drawn back under his right hip. On his right knee, and in his arms, is the body of a woman who faces up. His right arm bends slightly to support her, and his upper body leans backward with her weight. The man's shoulders are hunched forward, and his head tilts downward, his eyes downcast. His mouth opens slightly in an expression of pity, despair, or grief. The woman in his arms wears a long gown, and there is suggestion of some drapery or other part of her garment dangling behind the man's back. She is reclined on the man's knee with her knees bent under her slightly. Her head and arms are not visible, thought her breasts appear prominently near the man's right shoulder. She appears to be dead or dying. Above and to the right of this pair, a man wearing a shirt as well as a scarf or other head covering crouches in the bed of the cart or wagon. He faces left and holds his body in a contracted position with his left leg bent but extended forward slightly, and his left foot on the ground. His back is nearly horizontal but curves such that his shoulders hunch forward toward the ground. His left arm extends downward and bends at a near-ninety-degree angle. He may reach behind the other man, toward the unseen head of the woman, perhaps to lift her into the cart or wagon. He faces the ground, and his mouth opens slightly.  He holds a pipe in his mouth; smoke emerges from the pipe. Below this group of figures, near the lower edge of the design, a horse and a man lie prone on the ground. Both appear to be dead. The horse faces leftward with its head, neck, and front left leg extended along the ground. Its eyes and mouth are closed, and a wavy mane covers most of its neck. The man lies below or in front of the horse, facing right. He has short hair, and wears a sleeveless shirt and pants. The man lies face down with his visible right arm extended backward along the ground. To the right of these figures stands another couple. The man has short, curly hair and wears a short-sleeved gown or tunic that falls just above his knees. He stands, facing forward, with his right knee bent slightly as he supports a woman who appears to be fainting, perhaps from illness. The man's right arm bends around the woman's left shoulder and supports her back; his left arm bends slightly and extends downward to hold her waist. His head faces left and turns downward as he looks at her. His brows are furrowed, and his mouth opens slightly, suggesting pity or grief. The woman in his arms has long, curly hair and wears a short-sleeved gown that is mostly covered by a cloth that appears to be secured over her left shoulder and draped behind and across her body to gather in folds between her feet. The woman stands, facing right, with her left leg extended forward and her right bent back underneath her. Her left foot rests flat on the ground, and her right foot flexes such that the tips of her toes touch the ground directly beneath her hips. Her right arm dangles at her side with her fingers curled backward. Her hips and torso angle backward. Though her shoulders are upright, presumably supported by the man standing behind her, her neck bends backward, and her head faces directly upward. She may be fainting from illness. At right of this couple, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures: one man, three women, and a child. Leftmost is an old man with curly hair and a long beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown and faces right. He may stand or kneel, and he bends his right arm upward to place the back of his right hand on or near the face of the woman in front of him. His palm is directed back toward his own face, which tilts downward slightly as he looks at the woman. She appears to be sitting, though it is unclear what supports her. She has long hair and wears a long-sleeved gown that is gathered at the waist by a cord or belt. The woman faces forward and to the left, gazing over her right shoulder toward the old man with her mouth slightly open. He may support her. The woman's legs bend to the right, and the toes of her left foot appear below the hem of her long gown, which changes color just below the waist (or may be shadowed). On her lap rests the body of a child that may be dead or dying. The (male?) child is nude and has short hair. He lies supine with his head toward the left, dangling over the edge of the woman's right knee, and his feet toward the right, bent so that his feet dangle over her left knee. His right arm rests along his side. His mouth is open, and his eyes appear to be closed. To the right of the woman and child are two other women who face left and appear to be mourning. The woman at left has long, curly hair. She tilts her head downward, perhaps looking at the woman with the child on her lap. The woman at right wears a long-sleeved gown and has her long hair pulled into a bun. She faces left, bends forward at the shoulders, and tilts her head to face the ground. Her left arm bends upward, and she holds her left hand near her face. Her right hand may join it in a prayerful posture. She appears to be sitting and looking downward at the dead child. A cloud of smoke appears between the two buildings, perhaps suggesting a fire behind the smaller building. Shadowy regions appear in the smaller building's doorway, beneath the man in the center group, and behind the leftmost man who leans against the column.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pity</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower lefth corner, a couple sits propped up against the largest column of the building behind them. At left, immediately against the column's base, is a man with short, curly hair who wears a short-sleeved shirt. He faces right, hunches his shoulders forward, and leans his head downward to rest against the head of the woman in front of him, whom he appears to support. His eyes are cast downward toward her, and his mouth opens slightly, perhaps in an expression of pity or grief. His right arm dangles at his side and touches the arm of the women in front of him. He may be caring for the sick woman in front of him or may be dying himself.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner, a couple sits propped up against the largest column of the building behind them. Sitting at right, in front of the man, or perhaps in his lap, is a woman with long, curling hair. She wears a gown, the long skirt of which drapes over her legs and onto the ground. The woman's right leg bends sharply, and her right foot is drawn up under her hip, her toes extended toward the ground. Her left leg bends slightly and extends out in front of her, her foot flat on the ground. Her left foot may touch the figure lying prone at right. The woman's shoulders hunch forward as she leans against the man behind her with her arms dangling loosely at her sides. She faces forward, but her head leans toward her left shoulder. Her mouth opens slightly, and her face shows despair or resignation. She appears to be sick and may be dying.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bellman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of the couple, in the background of the design, a man in black robes and a bicorn hat walks leftward, ringing a bell at his waist. He strides forward with his right foot and holds the bell in his right hand. He appears to hold his left arm horizontally at his waist and may have his left hand thrust into his pocket or into the folds of the robe. His head tilts downward slightly, and his eyes look toward the ground as he walks. He may be a town crier warning of the plague or calling for residents to bring out their dead.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                    	<characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the right of the town crier, in the doorway of the columned building, are at least two nude (male?) figures who kneel at the door, facing left and raising their bent arms above their heads. They may be begging for entrance to the building.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures appear in or behind the cart or wagon visible at left of the brick wall of the smaller building. A short-haired man in a sleeveless shirt and tights(?) faces right and kneels with his left knee on the ground and his left foot flexed to support his weight. The man's right leg bends sharply out in front, and his right foot is drawn back under his right hip. On his right knee, and in his arms, is the body of a woman who may be dead or dying. His right arm bends slightly to support her, and his upper body leans backward with her weight. The man's shoulders are hunched forward, and his head tilts downward, his eyes downcast. His mouth opens slightly in an expression of pity, despair, or grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures appear in or behind the cart or wagon visible at left of the brick wall of the smaller building. In the arms of the kneeling man is the body of a woman with her head toward the left. She wears a long gown, and there is suggestion of some drapery or other part of her garment dangling behind the man's back. She is reclined on the man's knee with her knees bent under her slightly. Her head and arms are not visible, though her breasts appear prominently near the man's right shoulder. She appears to be dead or dying, and may be in the process of being placed in the cart or wagon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent at 90 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures appear in or behind the cart or wagon visible at left of the brick wall of the smaller building. Above and to the right of the man supporting the woman's body, a man who wears a shirt as well as a scarf or other head covering appears to crouch in the bed of the cart or wagon. He faces left and holds his body in a contracted position with his left leg bent but extended forward slightly, and his left foot on the ground. His back is nearly horizontal but curves such that his shoulders hunch forward as he leans toward the woman at left. His left arm extends downward and bends at a near-ninety-degree angle, perhaps touching the woman. He faces the ground, and his mouth opens slightly.  He holds a pipe in his mouth from which smoke emerges. He may be helping move the woman into the cart or wagon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mane</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the lower edge of the design a horse and a man lie prone on the ground. Both appear to be dead. The horse faces leftward with its head, neck, and front left leg extended along the ground. Its eyes and mouth are closed, and a wavy mane covers most of its neck.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the lower edge of the design a horse and a man lie prone on the ground. Both appear to be dead. The man lies below or in front of the horse, facing right. He has short hair, and wears a sleeveless shirt and pants. The man lies face down with his visible right arm extended backward along the ground, perhaps touching the foot or leg of the woman at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>man</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pity</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the dead horse and man stands another couple. The man has short, curly hair and wears a short-sleeved gown or tunic that falls just above his knees. He stands, facing forward, with his right knee bent slightly as he supports a woman who appears to be fainting, perhaps from illness. The man's right arm bends around the woman's left shoulder and supports her back; his left arm bends slightly and extends downward to hold her waist. His head faces left and turns downward as he looks at her. His brows are furrowed, and his mouth opens slightly, suggesting pity or grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fainting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the dead horse and man stands another couple. The woman has long, curly hair and wears a short-sleeved gown that is mostly covered by a cloth that appears to be secured over her left shoulder and draped behind and across her body to gather in folds between her feet. The woman stands, facing right, with her left leg extended forward and her right bent back underneath her. Her left foot rests flat on the ground, and her right foot flexes such that the tips of her toes touch the ground directly beneath her hips. Her right arm dangles at her side with her fingers curled backward. Her hips and torso angle backward. Though her shoulders are upright, presumably supported by the man standing behind her, her neck bends backward, and her head faces directly upward. She may be fainting from illness.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the fainting woman, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures. Leftmost is an old man with curly hair and a long beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown and faces right. He may stand or kneel, and he bends his right arm upward to place the back of his right hand on or near the face of the woman in front of him. His palm is directed back toward his own face, which tilts downward slightly as he looks at the woman.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the fainting woman, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures. The leftmost woman of the group appears to be sitting, though it is unclear what supports her. She has long hair and wears a long-sleeved gown that is gathered at the waist by a cord or belt. The woman faces forward and to the left, gazing over her right shoulder toward the old man with her mouth slightly open. He may support her. Both arms are at her sides and appear to be bent slightly. The woman's legs bend to the right, and the toes of her left foot appear below the hem of her long gown, which changes color just below the waist (or may be shadowed). On her lap rests the body of a child that may be dead or dying. Her facial expression shows grief or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the fainting woman, in front of the smaller building's doorway, is a group of five figures. On the lap of one of the women rests the body of a child that may be dead or dying. The (male?) child is nude and has short hair. He lies supine with his head toward the left, dangling over the edge of the woman's right knee, and his feet toward the right, bent so that his feet dangle over her left knee. His right arm rests along his side. His mouth is open, and his eyes appear to be closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the woman and child are two other gowned women who face left and appear to be mourning. The woman at left has long, curly hair. She tilts her head downward, perhaps looking at the woman with the child on her lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the woman and child are two other gowned women who face left and appear to be mourning. The woman at far right wears a long-sleeved gown and has her long hair pulled into a bun. She faces left, bends forward at the shoulders, and tilts her head to face the ground. Her left arm bends upward, and she holds her left hand near her face. Her right hand may join it in a prayerful posture. She appears to be sitting and looking downward at the dead child.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stairs</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>St. Paul's Cathedral</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>London</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background contains a large building supported by heavy columns, four of which rest on a set of stairs leading to an entry way. Between the distant columns and the nearer one at left is a tall, arched doorway. Another door appears faintly atop the stairs at right.  This might be St. Paul's Cathedral in London.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right, a second building appears to be constructed partly of brick and partly of wood, and it is covered with a sloping tile roof. An open doorway appears in the center of the building's lower level. There may be windows or other partitions in the building's upper level.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>cart</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wagon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wheel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the structure in the right foreground, the back right wheel and one side of a cart or wagon are visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>street</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design's middle ground is a street, probably of dirt. Paving stones appear at lower left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plague</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows a scene of pestilence in a town square or other common area. Many figures appear to be sick, dying, or dead from plague.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cloud of smoke appears between the two buildings, perhaps suggesting a fire behind the smaller building.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadowy regions appear in the smaller building's doorway, beneath the man in the center group, and behind the leftmost man who leans against the column.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
