<bad id="but139A.1" type="mono" work="Travellers Receiving Succour(?)" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="vanda" catalog="butlin" catid="139A">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Travellers Receiving Succour(?)">
                    <main>
                        Travellers Receiving Succour(?)</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Victoria and Albert Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>February 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>May 2003</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
<name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Andrea Dickens</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
<name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
<name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Travellers Receiving Succour(?)
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.P">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>23.0 x 21.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>23.0 x 21.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name>
                <date>1926</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>note recorded</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; W. Hunn; sold 1926 to the Victoria and Albert Museum.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Victoria and Albert Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">E.211-1926</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but139A.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT139A.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Travellers Receiving Succour(?)</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 139A)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>23.0 x 21.0 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Inscribed "P"(?) lower left; inscribed "Flaxman" on the verso.  These inscriptions are not by Blake.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing depicts two travelers, a man and a woman, kneeling for succor at the door of a building and being offered drink by two figures who emerge from the design's left edge. At right, nearer the viewer, the woman traveler faces left and kneels with both knees on the ground. Her prominent left leg bends sharply and is drawn up underneath her; in the design's lower left-hand corner, her bare left foot flexes to support her. Her right leg and foot appear to be hidden by the left, and by the folds of her long gown. She may sit on her heels. The woman bends at the waist and hunches her shoulders as she extends both arms leftward toward the proffered drink. Her palms face inward, and her fingers are spread around a large goblet. As the woman leans toward the benevolent figures in the doorway, her head and eyes lift to gaze at them. Her mouth opens, perhaps in speech, in exhaustion, or in preparation for drinking. She has long, wavy hair that has been gathered into a ponytail. Her sleeveless gown appears to be secured at the waist by a belt or cord, and it gathers in folds below her visible left foot. Her male companion appears behind and slightly to the left of her, and he kneels with only his left knee on the ground. It is hidden behind the woman, but his right knee bends forward, making a near right angle as his leg extends and his foot rests on the ground in front of him. This leg is bare, but the man appears to be covered from at least the waist down by a skirt or gown. A rod or stick leans against the visible leg, crossing from the inside of his right ankle over his right thigh and behind his torso. Like the woman, the man hunches his shoulders and leans toward the doorway; rather than reaching for the goblet, though, he bends his bare arms upward and raises his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. The man's eyes are raised, and his mouth is open. He appears to have short hair. At left of the travelers are two other figures who emerge from a doorway at the edge of the design to offer them drink. Nearer the viewer appear the arms and one leg of a figure of indeterminate gender, facing right. The figure's right hand grasps the handle of a large goblet, and his(?) left hand reaches around the back of the vessel to support it as he gives it to the kneeling woman. Both arms are covered by long sleeves, and the figure's gown reaches nearly to the ankles. His bare left foot rests on the ground, pointing toward the right side of the design. The design has been torn down the left side, removing the figure's body from view. At right of the figure holding the goblet is a woman who pours water into it from a pitcher of similar size. She faces forward and to the right, tilting her head downward as she pours. Her left arm bends sharply and crosses her body--she appears to grasp the pitcher's handle with both hands. The woman has long hair that has been gathered into a bun. She appears to wear a long-sleeved shirt or gown. Her lower body may have been erased or otherwise obscured. Alternatively, she may lean into the drawing's frame from the left. Immediately to the right of this woman is a vertical line that appears to represent the edge of the building; a diagonal line from its base toward the design's lower left corner marks the front limit of the building or its door. About one-third of the way up from the bottom of the design--around the height of the kneeling figures' waists--is a horizontal line. Above it, in the design's background, is a landscape of two low hills disrupted by a rough, curving pair of lines. These may represent a river or path that extends from upper right to lower left. A cloudless sky rises above the hills. Noteworthy shadows appear on the ground between the feet of the two men, at back of the pouring women's head, down the front of the travelers' bodies, and at the edge of the woman traveler's hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ponytail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>goblet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>exhausted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the right half of the design, nearer the viewer, a woman traveler faces left and kneels with both knees on the ground. Her prominent left leg bends sharply and is drawn up underneath her; in the design's lower left-hand corner, her bare left foot flexes to support her. Her right leg and foot appear to be hidden by the left, and by the folds of her long gown. She may sit on her heels. The woman bends at the waist and hunches her shoulders as she extends both arms leftward toward the proffered drink. Her palms face inward, and her fingers are spread around a large goblet. As the woman leans toward the benevolent figures in the doorway, her head and eyes lift to gaze at them. Her mouth opens, perhaps in speech, in exhaustion, or in preparation for drinking. She has long, wavy hair that has been gathered into a ponytail. Her sleeveless gown appears to be secured at the waist by a belt or cord, and it gathers in folds below her visible left foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rod</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>exhausted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind and slightly to the left of the kneeling woman appears her male companion, who also kneels but with only his left knee on the ground. It is hidden behind the woman, but his right knee bends forward, making a near right angle as his leg extends and his foot rests on the ground in front of him. This leg is bare, but the man appears to be covered from at least the waist down by a skirt or gown. A rod or stick leans against the visible leg, crossing from the inside of his right ankle over his right thigh and behind his torso. Like the woman, the man hunches his shoulders and leans toward the doorway; rather than reaching for the goblet, though, he bends his bare arms upward and raises his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. The man's eyes are raised, and his mouth is open. He appears to have short hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>giving</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>goblet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>jar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>handle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the travelers are two other figures who emerge from a doorway at the edge of the design to offer them drink. At left, nearer the viewer, appear the arms and one leg of a figure of indeterminate gender, facing right. The figure's right hand grasps the handle of a large goblet, and his(?) left hand reaches around the back of the vessel to support it as he gives it to the kneeling woman. Both arms are covered by long sleeves, and the figure's gown reaches nearly to the ankles. His bare left foot rests on the ground, pointing toward the right side of the design. The design has been torn down the left side, removing the figure's body from view.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pitcher</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>handle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pouring</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>giving</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the travelers are two other figures who emerge from a doorway at the edge of the design to offer them drink. At right of the figure holding the goblet is a woman who pours water into it from a pitcher of similar size. She faces forward and to the right, tilting her head downward as she pours. Her left arm bends sharply and crosses her body--she appears to grasp the pitcher's handle with both hands. The woman has long hair that has been gathered into a bun. She appears to wear a long-sleeved shirt or gown. Her lower body may have been erased or otherwise obscured.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ground</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately to the right of this woman is a vertical line that appears to represent the edge of the building; a diagonal line from its base toward the design's lower left corner marks the front limit of the building or its door. About one-third of the way up from the bottom of the design--around the height of the kneeling figures' waists--is a horizontal line that defines the floor or ground on which the figures stand and kneel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>path</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>road</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>In the design's background appears a landscape of two low hills disrupted by a rough, curving pair of lines. These may represent a river or path that extends from upper right to lower left. A cloudless sky rises above the hills.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>A cloudless sky rises above the hills.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Noteworthy shadows appear on the ground between the feet of the two men, at back of the pouring women's head, down the front of the travelers' bodies, and at the edge of the woman traveler's hair.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
