<bad id="but153.1" type="mono" work="The Mourners" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="153">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Mourners">
                    <main>
                        The Mourners</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
    <updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>        
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>March 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>May 1999</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
               <name>David Cosca</name> and
               <name>Robert Bingler</name>
               <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Mourners
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.E">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.0 x 24.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.0 x 24.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Collection of Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1984</date>
                <dealer>Christie's</dealer>
                <price>$8117</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; Anne Gilchrist by 1863; Mrs. Butcher by no later than 1876; sold Christie's, 1 Aug. 1963, lot 48 (&#163;5.5s. to Hugh Geddes); sold Christie's, 5 June 1973, lot 113 (&#163;2520 to the dealer Coulter acting for E. Taubman); offered Christie's, 15 June 1982, lot 86 (not sold); acquired by Robert N. Essick from Taubman, Christie's acting as Taubman's agent, in Sept. 1984 for $8117.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but153.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT153.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Mourners</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 153)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>18.0 x 24.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Four female mourners sit in the drawing's foreground, huddled together in front of a large set of stairs. The two mourners in front partially obscure the women behind them, who may sit on top of the lower steps. The woman at lower left sits on the ground in a contracted posture, her body facing forward and to the right. She hunches forward and lowers her elbows over her knees. Her legs cross at the ankles, left over right, as the toes of her bare feet touch the ground. Her arms bend upward, and her right hand appears to support the back of her head, which turns away to face one of the figures behind her. The other arm is partially hidden behind her head, and it may touch or cover her face. The sleeves of her long gown cover her hands. Long, wavy hair flows down her back, over her right shoulder, and between her arms to cover her face. Immediately above this woman are the shoulders and head of another, who presumably sits behind her on one of the lower steps. She also appears to wear a gown, though little of it is visible. Her body faces forward and to the right, but her head--visible from the nose up--is turned toward the viewer and tilts slightly to the left. Uplifted hands frame her face, perhaps covering her ears. Her eyes close in an expression of grief. The woman appears to have bangs, but the length of the rest of her hair is unclear. At right of this woman is another who sits on the steps, facing forward and to the right as she leans out from behind the other figures. Her head tilts downward and rests on her raised left hand; the elbow of her bent left arm rests on her left knee. Below, her long gown covers her legs and extends to the ground. Her sleeve culminates in a prominent cuff. The woman's long, curly hair cascades over her left shoulder. Her mouth opens, and her eyes lower toward the ground in an expression of grief or despair. She may be looking at the woman who sits below and to the right of her. This rightmost figure sits lower than the other three mourners. She faces left and sits on the ground in a contracted posture with her knees bent sharply upward and her head and arms hidden behind or between them. At left, her bare left foot emerges from the hem of her long gown. Long hair covers her face. At left of her knees may appear part of her hands; if so, it seems they also cover her face. Behind the figures is a set of six steps, which appear to be made of stone. Below them is a bare floor, and above them rises a plain wall; these may also be made of stone. Prominent shadows appear at left of the group of figures and below their feet, on the rises of the lower two steps at right, and on the wall at upper right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four female mourners sit in the drawing's foreground, huddled together in front of a large set of stairs. The two mourners in front partially obscure the women behind them, who may sit on top of the lower steps.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The woman at lower left sits on the ground in a contracted posture, her body facing forward and to the right. She hunches forward and lowers her elbows over her knees. Her legs cross at the ankles, left over right, as the toes of her bare feet touch the ground. Her arms bend upward, and her right hand appears to support the back of her head, which turns away to face one of the figures behind her. The other arm is partially hidden behind her head, and it may touch or cover her face. The sleeves of her long gown cover her hands. Long, wavy hair flows down her back, over her right shoulder, and between her arms to cover her face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately above this woman are the shoulders and head of another, who presumably sits behind her on one of the lower steps. She also appears to wear a gown, though little of it is visible. Her body faces forward and to the right, but her head--visible from the nose up--is turned toward the viewer and tilts slightly to the left. Uplifted hands frame her face, perhaps covering her ears. Her eyes close in an expression of grief. The woman appears to have bangs, but the length of the rest of her hair is unclear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand under head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of this woman is another who sits on the steps, facing forward and to the right as she leans out from behind the other figures. Her head tilts downward and rests on her raised left hand; the elbow of her bent left arm rests on her left knee. Below, her long gown covers her legs and extends to the ground. Her sleeve culminates in a prominent cuff. The woman's long, curly hair cascades over her left shoulder. Her mouth opens, and her eyes lower toward the ground in an expression of grief or despair. She may be looking at the woman who sits below and to the right of her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">  
                    	<characteristic>female</characteristic>                     							
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This rightmost figure in the group sits lower than the other three in the group. She faces left and sits on the ground in a contracted posture with her knees bent sharply upward and her head and arms hidden behind or between them. At left, her bare left foot emerges from the hem of her long gown. Long hair covers her face. At left of her knees may appear part of her hands; if so, it seems they also cover her face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures is a set of six steps, which are large in size and appear to be made of stone. Below them is a bare floor, and above them rises a plain wall; these may also be made of stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Prominent shadows appear at left of the group of figures and below their feet, on the rises of the lower two steps at right, and on the wall at upper right.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
