<bad id="but11.1" type="mono" work="Anne of Cleves's Monument" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin" catid="11">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Anne of Cleves's Monument">
                    <main>Anne of Cleves's Monument</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Society of Antiquaries, London.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Anne of Cleves's Monument
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1775.C">c. 1775</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>25.7 x 43.5 cm. (including frame lines); 28.4 x 43.5 cm. (including inscriptions)</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>28.5 x 46.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>1</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>3, closely spaced</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>    
                
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing for publication as an engraving in Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, 1780.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its execution.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries, London</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 10</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but11.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT11.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Anne of Cleves's Monument</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 11)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>28.4 x 43.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>The image includes a horizontal scale in feet, numbered 1 through 18.  The writer of the inscriptions is not known.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The composition depicts the tomb monument to Anne of Cleves in Westminster Abbey. The monument has three main components, all of which sit on a narrow, low platform. The three sections are of equal height, appear to be made of stone, and have undecorated, flat tops. A long, rectangular central structure is flanked by two narrower structures at right and left. The side of the central structure facing the viewer is divided into rectangular panels and intricately decorated. Two vertical panels on the right and left ends of the structure protrude slightly outward and span the monument's height. The left panel includes a central circle with the initials "AC" for Anne of Cleves. The insignia is topped by a crown with three visible trefoils. Additional vegetative and other motifs decorate the panel. The rightmost panel also contains a central circle topped by a crown surrounded by vegetative and other decorative motifs. Inside the circle here is a eight-pointed star or compass. The central section of the monument is divided into two horizontal sections with three large panels in each. The three panels in the upper section are undecorated; however, the four smaller spaces separating them are filled with vegetative or other abstract motifs. The three panels in the lower section each contain a skull and crossbones as well as a winding ribbon. The central skull faces forward while the skull at left faces right and the skill at right faces left. Four tall, slender vases, each with different decorations, are visible in the spaces separating these lower panels. The monument's narrower structures at left and right have identical decorations on the side facing the viewer: a central oval encircling the head of a lion with an open mouth surrounded above and below by vegetative or other decorative motifs. On both structures, a second decorative panel is visible on the side facing the longer middle structure; however, the details of this design are indistinguishable. Triangular areas of shadow are visible on the monument's supporting platform to the left of both the left most structure and the central structure. A scale measuring eighteen feet is visible near the bottom edge of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="structure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>tomb</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The composition depicts the tomb monument to Anne of Cleves in Westminster Abbey. The monument has three main components, all of which sit on a narrow, low platform. The three sections are of equal height, appear to be made of stone, and have undecorated, flat tops. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skull</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vase</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A long, rectangular central structure is flanked by two narrower structures at right and left. The side of the central structure facing the viewer is divided into rectangular panels and intricately decorated. Two vertical panels on the right and left ends of the structure protrude slightly outward and span the monument's height. The left panel includes a central circle with the initials "AC" for Anne of Cleves. The insignia is topped by a crown with three visible trefoils. Additional vegetative and other motifs decorate the panel. The rightmost panel also contains a central circle topped by a crown surrounded by vegetative and other decorative motifs. Inside the circle here is a eight-pointed star or compass. The central section of the monument is divided into two horizontal sections with three large panels in each. The three panels in the upper section are undecorated; however, the four smaller spaces separating them are filled with vegetative or other abstract motifs. The three panels in the lower section each contain a skull and crossbones as well as a winding ribbon. The central skull faces forward while the skull at left faces right and the skill at right faces left. Four tall, slender vases, each with different decorations, are visible in the spaces separating these lower panels.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>lion</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The monument's narrower structures at left and right have identical decorations on the side facing the viewer: a central oval encircling the head of a lion with an open mouth surrounded above and below by vegetative or other decorative motifs. On both structures, a second decorative panel is visible on the side facing the longer middle structure; however, the details of this design are indistinguishable.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Many of the decorative panels on the three structures of this monument contain representations of vegetation, including vines, leaves, and other indeterminate forms.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Triangular areas of shadow are visible on the monument's supporting platform to the left of both the left most structure and the central structure. A scale measuring eighteen feet is visible near the bottom edge of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="right">
                    <l n="but11.1.wd.01.01" justify="right">feet</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but11.1.wd.01.02" justify="right">Basire. del.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but11.1.wd.01.03" justify="center">The Monument of Anne of Cleves, fourth
                        wife of King Henry VIII, on the South side of the Altar in Westminster
                        Abbey. Vide Velurt. Mon. Vol. II. Plate XXXV.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
