<bad id="but123r.1" type="mono" work="The Good Farmer" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="123r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Good Farmer"><main>The Good Farmer</main><copy> Copy
                        1</copy>: electronic edition </title>
                <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB
                to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
            only.<lb/><lb/> This work copyright © 2024 Tate Collection.
            <lb/><lb/></userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>December 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>July 2007</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>William Shaw</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>William Shaw</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Sarah Jones, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>The Good Farmer</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780.M">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>26.7 x 37.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>26.7 x 37.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1940</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; Alice G. E. Carthew by 1918; bequeathed by Carthew in 1940 to the Tate Gallery, now Tate Collection.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">N05198</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but123r.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT123.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Good Farmer</title>, <objid><objnumber
                        code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                        <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 123 recto)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>26.7 x 37.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Blake developed this subject and basic composition through a series of seven or eight further drawings, including Butlin 120 recto, 120A recto and verso, 121, 122 recto and verso, 124, and possibly untraced 125, *Christ as the Good Shepherd*.  The verso of this monochrome wash drawing bears a pencil drawing titled by Butlin 123 verso as *Rough Sketch of Two or Three Figures in a Landscape*.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The general theme and subject of this composition were probably influenced by several biblical passages, including Ruth 2:1-17, I Samuel 12:16-19, and Matthew 9:38.  This monochrome wash depicts a gathering of seven people of
                        different ages, male and female, in the foreground. There are other figures
                        in less detailed sketch near the upper left of the wash. The group furthest
                        back consists of eight or nine figures, two of whom raise their arms to the
                        sky. They stand in front of a building, possibly a barn. In front of the
                        group of figures, two figures with more discernible features walk together.
                        At least one figure is male. They appear to be disgruntled and may be
                        arguing. The figures may be standing in a field. Positioned prominently in
                        the center of the wash, a man, probably Christ, with a beard and curly hair stands and looks
                        down toward the group of figures to his left. He extends his arms across his
                        body, to the right, and his palms face up. He may gesture toward the girl to
                        his right. The girl has her long hair in what appears to be a loose plait.
                        She bends her left leg to kneel on the ground. Her right leg is not visible
                        and likely extends in front of her. She appears to have a bushel of wheat in
                        her lap. An older bearded male stands to the right of the central figure. He
                        extends and raises his arms toward the sky, holding his hands closely
                        together. To the left of the central figure, three adults and one child
                        kneel on the ground. Of this group, the two figures on the left are male.
                        One male figure has long white hair and a beard. His eyes are closed. To his
                        right there is a male figure with curly hair, but his face is not visible.
                        To his right a female figure with her right arm extended in front of her and
                        her head bowed in supplication. Her hair is long and curled. A child with
                        curly hair and of indiscernible gender kneels in front of her with its head
                        resting in her lap. The sky appears to be dark with storm clouds. Lightning
                        or parts of the clouds extend toward and touch the field in the background.
                        If looked at closely, there also appears to be the barely-discernible sketch
                        of a figure wrapped within the clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E"> start here
                            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man with a beard and curly hair at the center of the wash
                            is bearded with curly hair stands and looks down toward the group of
                            figures to his left.  This is probably Christ. He extends his arms across his body, to the right,
                            and his palms face up. He may gesture toward the girl to his
                            right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An older bearded male stands to the right of the central
                            figure. He extends and raises his arms toward the sky, holding his hands
                            closely together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The group furthest back consists of eight or nine figures, two
                            of whom raise their arms to the clouded sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frowning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>anger</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> In front of the group of figures, two figures with more
                            discernible features walk together. At least one figure is male. They
                            appear to be disgruntled and may be arguing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>harvesting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The girl has her long hair in what appears to be a loose
                            plait. She bends her left leg to kneel on the ground. Her right leg is
                            not visible and likely extends in front of her. She appears to have a
                            bushel of wheat in her lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Among the group that kneels near the central figure, the
                            furthest male figure has long white hair and a beard. His eyes are
                            closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the elderly kneeling man's right there is a male figure
                            with curly hair, but his face is not visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the younger man's right is a woman with her right arm held
                            out to the central figure as her head bows in supplication. Her hair is
                            long and curled.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A child with curly hair and of indiscernible gender kneels in
                            front of the woman with its head resting in her lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Based on the sketching in the middle of the piece of a large,
                            even-cut field, this wash is likely in wheat or other grain field that
                            is ready to be reaped.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>barn</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background group stands in front of a building, possibly a
                            barn.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lightning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The sky appears to be dark with storm clouds. Lightning or
                            parts of the clouds extend toward and touch the field in the background.
                            If looked at closely, there also appears to be the barely-discernible
                            sketch of a figure wrapped within the clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
