<bad id="but119.1" type="mono" work="Saul and David" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="119">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Saul and David">
                    <main>
                        Saul and David</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
           <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>May 1999</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
               <name>David Cosca</name> and
               <name>Robert Bingler</name>
               <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Saul and David
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.J">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.8 x 24.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.8 x 24.7 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and monochrome washes</medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>Theodore Besterman's blind-stamped collection mark, an overlapping "T" and "B," appears lower left.</note></support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1982</date>
                <dealer>Stanhope Shelton</dealer>
                <price>&#163;1650</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; at one time in the collection of E. J. Shaw, active as a collector c. 1900-25; A. C. J. Wall; sold from Wall's collection, Christie's, 17 Nov. 1970, lot 29 (&#163;577.10s. to the dealer Thomas Agnew and Sons acting for Theodore Besterman); sold Christie's, 17 Nov. 1981, lot 66 (&#163;1210 to the dealer Stanhope Shelton); offered by Shelton in his April 1982 list 17, item T.9118 (&#163;1650); acquired Sept. 1982 by Robert N. Essick</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick, Altadena, California</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but119.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT119.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Saul and David</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 119)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>18.8 x 24.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design, a more complex development of Butlin 118 recto, depicts Saul granting David permission to fight Goliath (I Samuel 17: 32-37). Near the design's center stands a nude (or partially draped) man with short, curly hair and a beard. A crown sits atop his head, suggesting that he is the biblical figure Saul. Saul faces forward and to the right with his right leg straight and his left bent slightly, as if stepping forward. Saul's left arm dangles at his side, nearly straight, but his right is raised vertically. His fingers gather into a fist in a gesture that suggests power or dominance. Saul's head turns rightward to look at David and the figures that appear in the right half of the design. Immediately to the left of Saul, another male figure sits on a chair or throne. He also has short, curly hair and a beard, but he appears to be wearing a skirt or other garment from the waist down and a cape or cloth draped over his right shoulder. The man faces forward and sits with his legs spread at the knees but crossed at the ankles, right over left. His right foot is planted on the ground, and his hands rest on his knees as his arms bend close to his sides. He turns his head to the right, watching the figures that move in that half of the design. Both this man and Saul appear atop a stage or raised platform. To the right of Saul, a gowned old man steps from this platform onto the floor beneath. The man has long, wavy hair, a long beard, and a prominent mustache. He gazes forward with wide eyes as he strides forward, stepping down with his bare right foot. His arms are lowered at his sides, held outward slightly with palms forward in a posture of openness or perhaps supplication. To the right and in front of the old man is a younger male figure who likewise steps from the raised platform down onto the floor below. This man, presumably David, is nude except for a cape or drapery visible at right. He has shoulder-length hair that flows behind him. His torso faces the viewer, but his hips turn slightly to the left as he steps downward with his right foot. David's left arm bends slightly, bringing his hand near his left hip; his right arm extends downward, held approximately 45 degrees from his body. The fingers of his right hand spread wide but appear to be wrapped with some sort of string or cord. David's head turns sharply to the left, and he appears to gaze toward the throned man. These four prominent figures are surrounded by six more that are less clearly defined. They are, from left to right: an old, bearded man who sits or kneels, facing right, with his arms folded upward; three gowned figures of indeterminate gender who stand behind this man and the throne, facing forward and to the right; a bearded man who stands behind and to the right of Saul, gazing toward him; and a long-haired, bearded man who stands along the design's right border, facing left. Each of these figures stands, sits, or kneels atop the raised platform, which extends horizontally across from the design's left border until it reaches a right angle and approaches the viewer near the lower right-hand corner of the design. Both this platform and the floor appear to be bare, as do the room's walls. The upper portion of the back wall, above and to the right of Saul, is shaded darker than the rest. Other shadowy areas appear underneath the throned man's legs, at Saul's left arm, along the left side of the long-haired old man, and behind David's feet.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Saul</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the design's center stands a nude (or partially draped) man with short, curly hair and a beard. A crown may sit atop his head, suggesting that he is the biblical figure Saul. Saul faces forward and to the right with his right leg straight and his left bent slightly, as if stepping forward and possibly descending from the platform. Saul's left arm dangles at his side, nearly straight, but his right is raised vertically. His fingers gather into a fist in a gesture that suggests power or dominance. Saul's head turns rightward to look at the figures that appear in the right half of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately to the left of Saul, another male figure sits on a chair or throne. He also has short, curly hair and a beard, but he appears to be wearing a skirt or other garment from the waist down and a cape or cloth draped over his right shoulder. The man faces forward and sits with his legs spread at the knees but crossed at the ankles, right over left. His right foot is planted on the ground, and his hands rest on his knees as his arms bend close to his sides. He turns his head to the right, watching the figures that move in that half of the design. His mouth appears to be open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of Saul, a gowned old man steps from this platform onto the floor beneath. The man has long, wavy hair, a long beard, and a prominent mustache. He gazes forward with wide eyes as he strides forward, stepping down with his bare right foot. His arms are lowered at his sides, held outward slightly with palms forward in a posture of openness or perhaps supplication.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>David</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>string</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right and in front of the old man is a younger male figure who likewise steps from the raised platform down onto the floor below. This man, presumably David, is nude except for a cape or drapery visible at right. He has shoulder-length, wavy hair that flows behind him. His torso faces the viewer, but his hips turn slightly to the left as he steps downward with his right foot. David's left arm bends slightly, bringing his hand near his left hip; his right arm extends downward, held approximately 45 degrees from his body. The fingers of his right hand spread wide but appear to be wrapped with some sort of string or cord. David's head turns sharply to the left, and he appears to gaze toward the throned man. His mouth may open slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four prominent figures are surrounded by six more that are less clearly defined. Leftmost is an older, bearded man wearing a long-sleeved gown that may have a hood or other collar. He sits or kneels, facing right, with his right arm folded upward so that his chin rests on his hand. His left arm is not visible. The man appears to be staring at the throned man in front of him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four prominent figures are surrounded by six more that are less clearly defined. At left, behind the two seated men, appear three gowned figures of indeterminate gender. All three figures face forward and to the right, as if looking toward Saul and David.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Thee four prominent figures are surrounded by six more that are less clearly defined. Fifth in this group from left is a bearded man who stands behind and to the right of Saul, gazing toward him. The man wears a long gown and appears to have a beard. His body faces forward and to the right, but his head turns sharply to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four prominent figures are surrounded by six more that are less clearly defined. Farthest right is a long-haired, bearded man who wears a long garment, perhaps a gown or cloak. He stands along the design's right border, facing left, and looking toward Saul.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man immediately left of Saul sits on a chair or throne. It may be constructed of wood; no prominent decoration appears.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figures appear atop (or step down from) a stage or raised platform that which extends horizontally across from the design's left border until it reaches a right angle and approaches the viewer near the lower right-hand corner of the design. Both this platform and the floor appear to be bare, as do the room's walls.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>The upper portion of the back wall, above and to the right of Saul, is shaded darker than the rest. Other shadowy areas appear underneath the throned man's legs, at Saul's left arm, along the left side of the long-haired old man, and behind David's feet.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
           <phystext>
    <vspace extent="20"/>
    <lg type="prose" justify="left">
        <l n="but119.1.wd.01.01" justify="left" indent="40">WBlake</l>
        <l n="but119.1.wd.01.02" justify="left" indent="45">inven</l>
    </lg>
</phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
