<bad id="but147.1" type="mono" work="A Young Woman Reclining on a Couch, Writing in a Book" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="147">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Young Woman Reclining on a Couch, Writing in a Book">
                    <main>
                        A Young Woman Reclining on a Couch, Writing in a Book</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        A Young Woman Reclining on a Couch, Writing in a Book
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.T">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>22.9 x 33.8 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22.9 x 33.8 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Collection of Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1993</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>$30,000</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Joseph Hogarth, sold from his stock Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 22 June 1854, in lot 5082 with twenty-one other works by Blake (16s. to Edsall, probably a dealer); Richard Johnson, sold from his collection, Platt auction, London, 25 April 1912, probably in lot 702 with sixteen other works by or attributed to Blake (&#163;11.11s. to Archibald G. B. Russell); sold Sotheby's, 28 May 1934, lot 170 (10s. to M. W. F. Fuller); sold Sotheby's, 29 July 1964, in lot 214 with a work not by Blake (&#163;15 to David Bindman); sold Dec. 1993 by Bindman to Robert N. Essick for $30,000.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but147.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT147.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Young Woman Reclining on a Couch, Writing in a Book</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 147)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>22.9 x 33.8 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The drawing portrays a young woman who writes in a book while reclining on a couch or bed. She lies on her left side with her upper body at the right end of the couch and her legs extended to the left, facing upward and toward the viewer. Her left leg is straight, and her right leg bends to cross over it. The woman's body bends at the hips and waist, curving upward as she leans to the right against a pillow. Her torso faces the viewer. Her left arm bends to support her upper body, and the fingers of her left hand hold open the book that rests on the couch before her. The woman's right arm is also bent; it is lowered across her waist, and she holds a pen or other writing implement in her right hand. Two lines of text at the top of the book's open page suggest that the woman is in the act of writing; however, she does not look down at the book. Instead, she lifts her head to almost meet the viewer's gaze, though she appears to look slightly down and to the right. Her mouth is closed tightly. The woman wears a long-sleeved gown that is fastened at the waist with a belt or sash, and that gathers in folds below her legs and around her feet. Her right foot is partially exposed. The woman has long, curly hair that cascades over her shoulders and down her back. She wears a short crown on her head but is otherwise unidentified. The piece of furniture on which the woman reclines may be a couch or small bed. Its frame and two visible legs are likely made of wood, and it may be topped with a blanket, sheet, or cushion. At the right end of the couch is a cylindrical pillow, or perhaps a blanket that has been rolled and secured with two straps. Behind the woman may appear the wooden back of the piece of furniture, suggested by horizontal and zigzag lines that could represent wood grain. Alternatively, this area could be part of the drawing's shadowy background. Underneath the couch, along the base of the drawing, is a dark strip that may be a shadow or may represent the ground or floor. Just inside of the couch's leg at far right are markings that suggest another leg, perhaps the right rear one, which may have been erased. Near the couch's left leg are three short, dark lines; their import is unclear. Above the couch and writing woman is a dark background that grows darker in the upper right-hand portion, above the woman's head. A much lighter, curved section appears in the upper right-hand corner, perhaps representing a cloud and suggesting that the scene may take place outdoors. Light may come from this upper left corner since shadows appear at right of the women's head and neck, and beneath her left arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>page</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The drawing portrays a young woman who writes in a book while reclining on a couch or bed. She lies on her left side with her upper body at the right end of the couch and her legs extended to the left, facing upward and toward the viewer. Her left leg is straight, and her right leg bends to cross over it. The woman's body bends at the hips and waist, curving upward as she leans to the right against a pillow. Her torso faces the viewer. Her left arm bends to support her upper body, and the fingers of her left hand hold open the book that rests on the couch before her. The woman's right arm is also bent; it is lowered across her waist, and she holds a pen or other writing implement in her right hand. Two lines of text at the top of the book's open page suggest that the woman is in the act of writing; however, she does not look down at the book. Instead, she lifts her head to almost meet the viewer's gaze, though she appears to look slightly down and to the right. Her mouth is closed tightly. The woman wears a long-sleeved gown that is fastened at the waist with a belt or sash, and that gathers in folds below her legs and around her feet. Her right foot is partially exposed. The woman has long, curly hair that cascades over her shoulders and down her back. She wears a short crown on her head but is otherwise unidentified.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blanket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The piece of furniture on which the woman reclines may be a couch or small bed. Its frame and two visible legs are likely made of wood, and it may be topped with a blanket, sheet, or cushion. At the right end of the couch is a cylindrical pillow, or perhaps a blanket that has been rolled and secured with two straps.  Just inside of the couch's leg at far right are markings that suggest another leg, perhaps the right rear one, which may have been erased. Near the couch's left leg are three short, dark lines; their import is unclear. Behind the woman may appear the wooden back of the piece of furniture, suggested by horizontal and zigzag lines that could represent wood grain. Alternatively, this area could be part of the shadowy background.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ground</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Underneath the couch, along the base of the drawing, is a dark strip that may be a shadow or may represent the ground or floor. Above the couch and writing woman is a dark background that grows darker in the upper right-hand portion, above the woman's head. A combination of horizontal and zigzag lines break up the shadowy background, though they could be part of the couch itself. Smaller shadows appear at right of the women's head and neck, and beneath her left arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The dark strip that runs along the base of the drawing, underneath the couch, may be a shadow, but it may also represent the ground or floor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="A">
                            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>light</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>A lighter, curved area appears in the drawing's upper right-hand corner, perhaps representing a cloud and suggesting that the scene may take place outdoors. Light may come from this upper left corner.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>