<bad id="but168r.1" type="mono" work="Matthan" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="168r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Matthan">
                    <main>
                        Matthan</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Matthan
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.J">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>15.7 x 10.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>JWHATMAN</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold by Tatham to the British Museum in Oct. 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1867,1012.206</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but168r.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT168r.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Matthan</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 168 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>24.4 x 17.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>This is one of seven monochrome wash drawings (Objects 37-43) by Blake of figures painted by Michelangelo in the Sistine Chapel.  They were very probably copied from the engravings of Adamo Ghisi, after drawings by Giorgio Ghisi, published in *Pitture dipinte nella Volta della Capella Sistina nel Vaticano* (1773).  The wash drawing, *Abias*, is on the verso of this drawing.</p><p>Frederick Tatham added a pen and ink inscription in the lower right corner of the leaf bearing this drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The drawing contains three figures: a woman, a male child, and an old man (presumably Matthan). Most prominent is the woman, who sits on a step or block that rests on the floor (or perhaps a low platform) in the lower right-hand corner of the frame. The woman faces left and sits with her legs bent at near-90-degree angles. Her bare feet point so that only her toes touch the ground near the block's left edge. The women's lower legs are also bare, but a sleeveless gown covers her from the thighs upward. The woman may have short hair, or she may have long hair that is gathered beneath the scarf that is tied around her head and that extends down her back. She leans backward, toward the right edge of the design, but holds her head erect as she gazes straight ahead, toward the design's left edge. Her mouth may open slightly. The woman extends her left arm horizontally toward the left side of the drawing, presumably to support the child in her lap. Her fingers point leftward as she does so. The child faces right, toward the woman, and kneels or lunges with his left knee on her right knee and his right foot planted on her upper left thigh. Both legs are bent at 90 degrees. The child's torso twists toward the viewer somewhat as his right arm bends backward. He places his right hand on the woman's left wrist, spreading his fingers to grasp her hand. The child's left arm extends horizontally toward the woman's face. He may touch her with his fingertips near eye level. The child leans forward, holds his head up, and looks at the woman. He has short, curly hair, and he is nude apart from a cloth that drapes around his hips and covers his left foot as it extends toward the ground. Between the woman and child appears the head (and perhaps the body) of an older man, presumably the Matthan of the title. The faintness of this figure--along with the absence of his feet--suggests that he may be an apparition. The man's head is covered by a hood or scarf, and a short, curly beard covers his chin. He faces forward and to the right, leaning his head toward the woman's as he looks at her with an expression of sorrow. The drawing's setting is unclear. The back wall, the floor, and the block on which the woman sits are all plain, and their material is undetermined. Prominent shadows appear beneath the woman's raised arm, around the child's legs, and on his face.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The most prominent figure in the drawing is the woman, who sits on a step or block that rests on the floor (or perhaps a low platform) in the lower right-hand corner of the frame. The woman faces left and sits with her legs bent at near-90-degree angles. Her bare feet point so that only her toes touch the ground near the block's left edge. The women's lower legs are also bare, but a sleeveless gown covers her from the thighs upward. The woman may have short hair, or she may have long hair that is gathered beneath the scarf that is tied around her head and that extends down her back. She leans backward, toward the right edge of the design, but holds her head erect as she gazes straight ahead, toward the design's left edge. Her mouth may open slightly. The woman extends her left arm horizontally toward the left side of the drawing, presumably to support the child in her lap. Her fingers point leftward as she does so.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The child in the woman's lap faces right, toward the woman, and kneels or lunges with his left knee on her right knee and his right foot planted on her upper left thigh. Both legs are bent at 90 degrees. The child's torso twists toward the viewer somewhat as his right arm bends backward. He places his right hand on the woman's left wrist, spreading his fingers to grasp her hand. The child's left arm extends horizontally toward the woman's face. He may touch her with his fingertips near eye level. The child leans forward, holds his head up, and looks at the woman. He has short, curly hair, and he is nude apart from a cloth that drapes around his hips and covers his left foot as it extends toward the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Matthan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pity</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between the woman and child appears the head (and perhaps the body) of an older man, presumably the Matthan of the title. The faintness of this figure--along with the absence of his feet--suggests that he may be an apparition. The man's head is covered by a hood or scarf, and a short, curly beard covers his chin. He faces forward and to the right, leaning his head toward the woman's as he looks at her with an expression of sorrow.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The drawing's setting is unclear. The back wall, the floor, and the block on which the woman sits are all plain, and their material is undetermined.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Prominent shadows appear beneath the woman's raised arm, around the child's legs, and on his face.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but168r.1.wd.01.01" justify="left" indent="46"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Drawn by 
                        <choice>
                            <orig>B lake</orig>
                            <reg type="split_word">Blake</reg>
                        </choice></hi></l>
                    <l n="but168r.1.wd.01.02" justify="left" indent="47"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">from the print from</hi></l>
                    <l n="but168r.1.wd.01.03" justify="left" indent="49.5"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>Michael Angelo</orig>
                            <reg type="alt_name">Michelangelo</reg>
                        </choice></hi></l>
                    <l n="but168r.1.wd.01.04" justify="left" indent="54.5"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Vouched by Fred.<hi rend="superscript">k</hi> Tatham</hi></l>
                    <l n="but168r.1.wd.01.05" justify="left" indent="69"><hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; <space extent="56" unit="character"/></hi></l>                     
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>