<bad id="but178r.1" type="penink" work="Charon, Copy from the Antique (?)" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="178r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Charon, Copy from the Antique (?)">
                    <main>Charon, Copy from the Antique (?)</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 Tate Collection
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>May 2012</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester</resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                    <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                    <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Bihan Zhang</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Charon, Copy from the Antique (?)
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author.  Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription, lower right.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1779">c. 1779-80(?)<note>The dating is uncertain.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>26.0 x 38.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>29.4 x 40.8 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1922</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Apparently inherited by Catherine Blake upon the death of her husband, William Blake, in 1827; by inheritance to Frederick Tatham upon the death of Catherine Blake in 1831; Tatham's brother-in-law George Richmond, sold from Richmond's collection, Christie's, 29 April 1897, lot 147 with 21 other works by Blake as listed in Butlin 77 (£2.10s. to Richard Sisley); his daughter, Mrs. John Richmond; given by Mrs. Richmond to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection) in 1922.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <addressline>Millbank</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 20-7887-8888</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images: 20-7887-8871/4933</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images: 20-7887-8805</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Images: picture.library@tate.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, General: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Images: http://www.tate.org.uk/research/researchservices/picturelibrary/#copy</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">A00045</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but178r.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT178.1.1r.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Charon, Copy from the Antique (?)</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 178 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>26.0 x 38.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A single figure shown in three-quarter length occupies this composition.  With torso and head twisted rightward to face the viewer, the male figure extends his left arm horizontally to the right, hand raised and palm out with fingers spread.  With his bent right arm, he grasps a sizeable staff, which he holds vertically.  The detail included in the figure's face and hair contrasts with the relative simplicity of the larger drawing.  His hair is short and curly, as is his beard, which tapers into two bushy spirals.  His brow is furrowed and his lips downturned, giving the figure an aged, angry appearance.  His eyes are blank, suggesting that the figure is copied from a classical sculpture (although no antique prototype or dependent engraving for this figure has been identified).  A diagonal strap is visible across the figure's torso and likely holds in place the cape or drapery billowing behind the figure at left.  He may also wear drapery around his waist.  The figure's lower body is obscured by a horizontal line that may indicate the decorated edge of a boat or, alternatively, the surface of water.  The presence of a boat would suggest this figure is Charon; however, the Blind Orion may be the subject, as Blake did a number of copies after antique sculptures for engravings.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>anger</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Charon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Orion</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A single figure shown in three-quarter length occupies this composition.  With torso and head twisted rightward to face the viewer, the male figure extends his left arm horizontally to the right, hand raised and palm out with fingers spread.  With his bent right arm, he grasps a sizeable staff, which he holds vertically.  The detail included in the figure's face and hair contrasts with the relative simplicity of the larger drawing.  His hair is short and curly, as is his beard, which tapers into two bushy spirals.  His brow is furrowed and his lips downturned, giving the figure an aged, angry appearance.  His eyes are blank, suggesting that the figure is copied from a classical sculpture (although no antique prototype or dependent engraving for this figure has been identified).  A diagonal strap is visible across the figure's torso and likely connects to the cape or drapery billowing behind the figure at left.  He may also wear drapery around his waist.  The figure's lower body is obscured by a horizontal line that may indicate the decorated edge of a boat or, alternatively, the surface of water.  The presence of a boat would suggest this figure is Charon; however, the Blind Orion may be the subject, as Blake did a number of copies after antique sculptures for engravings.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The single figure in this drawing grasps with his right hand a sizeable staff, which he holds vertically.  This staff looks like the branch or trunk of a tree.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure's lower body is obscured by a horizontal line that may indicate the decorated edge of a boat or, alternatively, the surface of water.  If water, this may be a small wave.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but178r.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="46">Charon - by William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but178r.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="46">copied from something else</l>
                    <l n="but178r.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="53">not designed by him</l>
                    <l n="but178r.1.penink.01.04" justify="left" indent="64">Fred<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>. Tatham<note>This inscription was penned by Frederick Tatham.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>