<bad id="but121.1" type="mono" work="The Good Farmer" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="121">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Good Farmer">
                    <main>
                        The Good Farmer</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>
			: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
             <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>		
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                     <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                     <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                     <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                     <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                     <name>Kirk V. Hastings</name>
                    and <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                     <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                     <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                     <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                     <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Good Farmer
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.K">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>14.0 X 21.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>14.0 X 21.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and monochrome washes</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.127</repositoryid>
            </repository>
            
        </source>
        <desc id="but121.1.wd.01" dbi="but121.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Good Farmer</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 121)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>Blake developed this subject and basic composition through a series of seven or eight further drawings, including Butlin 120 recto, 120A recto and verso, 122 recto and verso, 123 recto, 124, and possibly untraced 125, *Christ as the Good Shepherd*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>14.0 X 21.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Part of a sequence of seven interrelated drawings, this design depicts a field of grain and, near it, a Christ-like figure surrounded by other figures who seek his aid. This particular drawing has been tentatively identified as an illustration of Ruth 2: 1-17 because of the addition of a gleaning woman in the foreground. The Ruth figure stands before a large area of waist-high grain (perhaps wheat). She faces left, bending over at the waist and striding forward with her right leg. Her left leg bends and extends backward; her left arm bends slightly and extends downward as she points toward the ground in front of her. Ruth's head also tilts downward as she gazes at the ground. Her long hair is gathered into a bun. She is nude from the waist up, her left breast appearing prominently below her extended arm, and she wears a long skirt. In front of Ruth, at the left edge of the grain field, stands the "good farmer," who, if the design illustrates part of the book of Ruth, may represent Boaz. The farmer has also been identified with Christ. The farmer has short hair; he wears a long-sleeved shirt and a skirt that reaches his ankles. The farmer's body faces forward and to the right; his right leg extends forward as if walking toward Ruth, and he extends both arms toward her with his palms up. The farmer turns his head to the left to look back at the group of figures behind him. These three figures face forward and to the right. They are, from left to right: a shorter figure, perhaps a woman or child, who wears a knee-length skirt and walks toward the farmer with left leg forward and arms extended out in front; a gowned, long-haired man who kneels with arms held at his sides, palms up, and fingers spread; and an older, bearded man who kneels and raises his left arm into the air, almost touching the farmer's shoulder with his hand. To the right of the farmer, behind the edge of the grain field, stands another male figure who faces forward and crosses his right arm over his chest. He faces the viewer, and his right hand may rest on his left shoulder. In the upper left corner of the design, a set of small buildings appears in the background. Against the left border is a simple structure with a slanted roof and no visible doors or windows. In front of the house, a four-legged animal (possibly a horse?) appears to be eating from a raised trough or bucket. Below and to the right of this animal may be a pile of feed, another animal, or some other object; even further to the right, a human figure or animal appears to crawl along the ground. It may be dead or dying. Behind the house and these figures is a longer building. The haphazard lines at the right of this building may suggest that it is on fire or in some way damaged. Further in the background, immediately behind the long building, is a smaller house with a chimney. Smoke rises from the chimney and floats to the right. In the upper righthand corner, another field of grain appears in the distance. Curved lines at the edges of the field suggest that it may be partially surrounded by other vegetation. Alternatively, these lines may suggest fire, as harsher diagonal lines appear atop the grain, and darkened clouds (perhaps smoke) appear above it. To the right of the field stand six(?) figures. They are, from left to right: a figure who faces left and raises his(?) arms horizontally toward the field, holding some sort of tool; another figure standing beside him, also facing the field; a figure that faces the viewer but turns her(?) head to the right and holds something in her arms (perhaps an infant); the babe in arms; a curved line suggesting the head of another figure; and a figure who faces forward and to the right, as if looking toward something beyond the design's right border. Mountains fill the center of the design's background, just above the farmer's head. Dark clouds rise above the mountains, perhaps mingling with smoke from the chimney at left and the fire at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>Ruth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breast</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>harvesting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The Ruth figure stands before a large area of waist-high grain (perhaps wheat). She may be gathering this grain. Ruth faces left, bending over at the waist and striding forward with her right leg. Her left leg bends and extends backward; her left arm bends slightly and extends downward as she points toward the ground in front of her. Ruth's head also tilts downward as she gazes at the ground. Her long hair is gathered into a bun. She is nude from the waist up, her left breast appearing prominently below her extended arm, and she wears a long skirt.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>farmer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of Ruth, at the left edge of the grain field, stands the "good farmer," who, if the design illustrates part of the book of Ruth, may represent Boaz. He has also been identified as Christ. The farmer has short hair; he wears a long-sleeved shirt and a skirt that reaches his ankles. The farmer's body faces forward and to the right; his right leg extends forward as if walking toward Ruth, and he extends both arms toward her with his palms up. The farmer turns his head to the left to look back at the three figures behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," three figures face forward and to the right. They appear to be asking him for aid. Leftmost stands a shorter figure, perhaps a woman or child, who wears a knee-length skirt but appears to be nude from the waist up. Her hair may be pulled into a bun. The figure strides rightward with her left foot forward; her right leg extends backward, and she stands on the toes of her right foot as she leans in the farmer's direction. Her arms extend in front of her, nearly horizontally, and her hands are cupped together, palms up, as if asking for food or alms. She gazes toward the right side of the design, looking toward the field grain.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," three figures face forward and to the right. The middle figure is a gowned, long-haired man or woman who kneels in supplication before the farmer. The figure holds his(?) bent arms slightly out and forward from his sides, with fingers spread and palms facing out. He gazes up toward the farmer.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At left of the "good farmer," three figures face forward and to the right. They appear to be asking him for aid. Rightmost kneels an older, bearded man wearing a long-sleeved gown. He kneels, leans forward, and raises his bent left arm into the air. The fingers of his left hand touch or almost touch the farmer's right shoulder. The old man's mouth may open as he gazes upward toward the farmer's face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The Ruth and farmer figures in the foreground stand near a large area of waist-high grain (perhaps wheat). A second grain field appears in the background, near the design's upper righthand corner. This second field may be on fire, as smoke appears to rise from it. Curved lines at the edges of the field suggest that it may be partially surrounded by other vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>barn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stable</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chimney</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper lefthand corner of the design, a set of small buildings appears in the background. Against the left border is a simple structure, perhaps a house or barn, with a slanted roof and no visible doors or windows. Behind the house is a longer building. The haphazard lines at the right of this building may suggest that it is on fire or in some way damaged. Further in the background, immediately behind the long building, is a smaller house with a chimney. There may be a window on the side of this house, near its roof.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="A">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crawling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of the three buildings at upper left, a four-legged animal (possibly a horse?) faces to the right and appears to be eating from a raised trough or bucket. Below and to the right of this animal may be a pile of feed or some other object, perhaps another animal; even further to the right, a human figure or animal appears to be lying down or crawling along the ground. It could be dead or dying.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the smaller field in the design's upper righthand corner are six(?) figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rod</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scythe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sickle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>harvesting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are six(?) figures. Leftmost stands a figure who faces left and raises his arms horizontally toward the field, holding some sort of tool. He may be harvesting the grain with a scythe or sickle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are six(?) figures. To the right of the man holding the tool stands another figure, of indeterminate gender, also facing left toward the field.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are six(?) figures. In the center of the group is a figure who faces the viewer but turns her(?) head to the right and holds something in her arms (perhaps an infant). She could be the child's mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are six(?) figures. The woman in the center of the group may hold an infant in her arms. Vertical lines may suggest that the child reaches upward toward its mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are six(?) figures. Above and to the right of the woman in infant appears a curved line that suggests the head of another figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the field at upper right are six(?) figures. Rightmost stands a figure of indeterminate gender who faces forward and to the right, as if looking toward something beyond the design's right border.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>mountains</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Distant mountains fill the center of the design's background, just above the farmer's head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Smoke rises from the chimney in the cluster of buildings at left and floats to the right. Dark clouds fill the sky above the mountains, perhaps mingling with smoke from the chimney at left and the fire at right.</illusobjdesc>
					</component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
