<bad id="but159v.1" type="mono" work="Sketch for 'Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="royal" catalog="butlin" catid="159v">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Sketch for 'Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren'">
                    <main>
                        Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
  <updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>          
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Royal Collection Trust.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>April 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>December 2014</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;                  
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and                    
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill                    
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin, </name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Adam Engel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham, </name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime, </name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff, </name>
                    <name>Eric Loy, </name>
                    <name>Kate Massie, </name>
                    <name>Adam McCune, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis, </name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer, </name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner, </name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.G">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>33.5 x 45.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>33.5 x 45.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Royal Collection Trust</name>
                <date>c. 1862</date>
                <dealer>Richard Fisher</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 166 with three other works by Blake (10s. to Richard Fisher, probably a dealer); apparently sold c. 1862 to the Royal Collection, now the Royal Collection Trust and housed at Windsor Castle, Berkshire, England.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Royal Collection Trust</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">RCIN 913599</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but159v.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT159.1.1v.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"</title>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 159 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>33.5 x 45.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Another monochrome wash *Sketch for "Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren"* is on the recto of this work.  Both are preliminary drawings for the water color, *Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren* (Butlin 157).</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure of this reunion scene is Joseph, who faces to the right and steps in that direction from the drawing's left border. He strides forward with his right leg; his bare right foot is planted on the floor, but his left foot remains outside the frame. He wears a long-sleeved gown, the hem of which curls in a circular pattern as it floats near ankle height. Joseph wears a crown and his hair curls into ringlets at his shoulders. As he steps into the frame, Joseph leans forward, and his shoulders hunch as his head turns downward; his eyes are lowered, and his mouth is open. His arms extend downward and to the right, wrapping around the upper body of the younger man next to him, likely his brother Benjamin. Joseph's right arm appears prominently, but his left arm is signified only by the presence of his left hand behind Benjamin. Joseph's fingers are spread as he embraces his brother. Second from left, Benjamin rises to meet Joseph and return his embrace. He lunges to the left with his legs bent at near-right angles; his right leg bends forward with the right foot on the floor beside Joseph's. Benjamin's left foot flexes behind him. Benjamin's bare left arm extends upward to grasp Joseph around the ribs; his right arm is not visible but likely embraces Joseph on the other side. Benjamin's head tilts upward, and he gazes toward Joseph's face. Benjamin wears a long gown that is drawn aside to reveal most of his right leg. His wavy hair comes to shoulder length. At right of these figures are nine other men, presumably their brothers. They appear in two groups: near Joseph and Benjamin, four men bow, facing left, in postures of supplication; behind them, five men recoil from the scene. Immediately behind Benjamin's head, two brothers stand or kneel, facing left. Only the head of the brother at left is visible; he has long hair and looks downward. Some lines at left of his head could represent his hands. The brother at right also has long hair. He bends forward, tilting his head downward and raising his hands together in a prayerful posture. He appears to be looking at the ground. Below these two is the head of another brother who bows low but lifts his head to look forward. Below him, another man kneels in a contracted posture, lowering his head and covering his face with his hands. Behind these bowing men is a group of five others who lean backward as if recoiling from the scene before them. Nearest the viewer are two men who face leftward, kneel on the ground, and lean backward dramatically. The man nearer the viewer faces leftward. He bends his knees sharply as both rest on the ground, and he sits on the heels of his bare, flexed feet. The man appears to be nude, and his left arm extends downward to cover his genitals. His right arm bends upward across his body, and his right hand touches his left shoulder. The man has short, curly hair and a beard of similar texture. The man behind him, appearing at left, has long hair and a long beard. A gown covers most of his body but leaves his right shoulder bare. He also faces left and kneels, leaning backward; as he does so, the man's right arm extends downward near his right knee. His left arm wraps around the body of the short-haired brother beside him, and his left hand rests on this brother's left hip. Behind these men are at least three others brothers. Leftmost in this group is a man who with short, curly hair and a beard who faces forward and to the left. The man raises his hands out in front of him with his palms facing outward and his fingers spread. Below his right hand appears the cuff of his shirt or gown. Immediately to the right of this man is another who faces left and stares toward Joseph and Benjamin. He has long hair, and his back may be visible behind the kneeling pair below. Rightmost in the group is a man in similar posture. He faces left and may look toward the reunion scene, but his features are not as well defined and his eyes may be closed. Lines over and beside his head may represent hair, but they may also suggest the presence of another figure. This drawing's setting appears to be a large room or portico with bare floors. Some lines appear in the background, but their import is unclear. The only noteworthy shadows appear between Joseph and Benjamin's legs, and behind the group of figures at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Joseph</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure of this reunion scene is Joseph, who faces to the right and steps in that direction from the drawing's left border. He strides forward with his right leg; his bare right foot is planted on the floor, but his left foot remains outside the frame. He wears a long-sleeved gown, the hem of which curls in a circular pattern as it floats near ankle height. Joseph wears a crown and his hair curls into ringlets at his shoulders. As he steps into the frame, Joseph leans forward, and his shoulders hunch as his head turns downward; his eyes are lowered, and his mouth is open. His arms extend downward and to the right, wrapping around the upper body of the younger man next to him, likely his brother Benjamin. Joseph's right arm appears prominently, but his left arm is signified only by the presence of his left hand behind Benjamin. Joseph's fingers are spread as he embraces his brother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Second from left, Benjamin rises to meet Joseph and return his embrace. He lunges to the left with his legs bent at near-right angles; his right leg bends forward with the right foot on the floor beside Joseph's. Benjamin's left foot flexes behind him. Benjamin's bare left arm extends upward to grasp Joseph around the ribs; his right arm is not visible but likely embraces Joseph on the other side. Benjamin's head tilts upward, and he gazes toward Joseph's face. Benjamin wears a long gown that is drawn aside to reveal most of his right leg. His wavy hair comes to shoulder length.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of these figures are nine other men, presumably their brothers. They appear in two groups: near Joseph and Benjamin, four men bow, facing left, in postures of supplication; behind them, five men recoil from the scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">  
                    	<characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lines</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately behind Benjamin's head, two brothers stand or kneel, facing left. Only the head of the brother at left is visible; he has long hair and looks downward. Some lines at left of his head could represent his hands.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately behind Benjamin's head, two brothers stand or kneel, facing left. The brother at right has long hair; he bends forward, tilting his head downward and raising his hands together in a prayerful posture. He appears to be looking at the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind Benjamin's back are two more brothers who bow low to the ground. The head of one of these brothers lifts as he bows, and his eyes look forward. This man appears to have long hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind Benjamin's back are two more brothers who bow low to the ground. The lower of the two kneels in a contracted posture, dropping his head and covering his face with his hands. He has long hair and appears to wear a gown or shirt.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground at right, two men face leftward, kneel on the ground, and lean backward dramatically. The man nearer the viewer faces leftward. He bends his knees sharply as both rest on the ground, and he sits on the heels of his bare, flexed feet. The man appears to be nude, and his left arm extends downward to cover his genitals. His right arm bends upward across his body, and his right hand touches his left shoulder. The man has short, curly hair and a beard of similar texture. His mouth may open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground at right, two men face leftward, kneel on the ground, and lean backward dramatically. The man behind, appearing at left, has long hair and a long beard. A gown covers most of his body but leaves his right shoulder bare. He also faces left and kneels, leaning backward; as he does so, the man's right arm extends downward toward his right knee. His left arm wraps around the body of the short-haired brother beside him, and his left hand rests on this brother's left hip.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the kneeling men are at least three other brothers. Leftmost in this group is a man who with short, curly hair and a beard who faces forward and to the left. The man raises his hands out in front of him with his palms facing outward and his fingers spread. Below his right hand appears the cuff of his shirt or gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the kneeling men are at least three other brothers. The man in the center faces left and stares toward Joseph and Benjamin. He has long hair, and his back may be visible behind the kneeling pair below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the kneeling men are at least three other brothers. Rightmost in the group is a man in similar posture. He faces left and may look toward the reunion scene, but his features are not as well defined. Lines over and beside his head may represent hair, but they may also suggest the presence of another figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This drawing's setting appears to be a large room or portico with bare floors. Some lines appear in the background, but their import is unclear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="CD">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>The only noteworthy shadows appear between Joseph and Benjamin's legs, and behind the group of figures at right.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
