<bad id="but144.1" type="wc" work="The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="nypl" catalog="butlin" catid="144">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel">
                    <main>
                        The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 25KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 New York Public Library.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1783.A">1783<note>The work is dated and signed by Blake "1783 W Blake inv" lower right.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>28.3 x 42.3 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>28.3 x 42.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>New York Public Library</name>
                <date>1910</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, lot 175 (&#163;1.10s. to the dealer Toovey acting for Henry Cunliffe); sold from Cunliffe's collection, Sotheby's, 11 May 1895, lot 103 (&#163;6.10s. to the dealer Frederick Keppel); Mrs. Henry Draper; given by Draper in March 1910 to the New York Public Library.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>New York Public Library</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">54169</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but144.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT144.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Witch of Endor Raising the Spirit of Samuel</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 144)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The work is titled, signed, and dated by Blake along the lower margin; see the Transcription.  The verso is inscribed by Henry Cunliffe, "Purchased at Sotheby's 29 ap. 62."</p></objnote>
                <objsize>28.3 x 42.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design shows the raised spirit of Samuel and four figures who react to his presence. In the right half of the design, Samuel faces left and stands or walks, striding with his exposed left foot. He wears a long-sleeved gown similar in color to his long white hair and long beard, giving him a ghostly appearance. The hem of his gown drags on the floor behind him, and the sleeve gathers in folds at his left wrist. Samuel's left arm is raised slightly, and he appears to point at the ground in front of the other figures. His head is down, and his eyes appear to be closed. The figure nearest Samuel is a female with long hair who wears a gown or skirt that leaves her upper body exposed.  This is probably the Witch of Endor. The figure kneels with her right knee on the ground and her left leg bent in front of her. She faces to the right and looks toward the ghost of Samuel, but her upper body leans backward slightly. The figure's right arm bends and appears to wrap around her waist, and she appears to hold a long object, perhaps a stick(?) or magical rod, in her right hand. Her left arm extends across her body and may point at the men to her right. Her mouth is open, and her facial expression suggests fear. A long piece of drapery extends from the figure's left hip, circles over her head, and floats behind her, along with part of her hair. Below this figure's left hand, in the center of the design, a man kneels on the ground in a contracted posture. He wears a robe or other draped garment that leaves his right shoulder and arm bare. Long hair and a beard cover much of his head and face. The man bends forward, hunches his shoulders, and lies prone on the ground with his legs drawn up underneath him, perhaps bowing before the ghost of Samuel. His left arm is crossed in front of his face and appears to support the weight of his upper body. His left arm is bent and extends forward, toward the ghost. The fingers of his right hand are spread, and he faces right and looks toward Samuel's feet. Behind the bowing man kneel two others. The male figure at right has short, curly hair and a beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown with a robe or other cloth draped over it. The man faces forward and to the right, looking in Samuel's direction with an expression of fear. Only his upper body is visible. His left arm extends to the right; the palm of his left hand faces outward, and his fingers are spread. He leans away from the ghost of Samuel. At left, a male figure with long hair wears a long-sleeved gown and a robe or other draped cloth. His body faces away from the viewer, but his head turns to the right as he appears to look toward the ghost of Samuel. His legs are bent, and his legs extend behind him. His lower right leg and right foot emerge from the hem of his garment. The man leans slightly to the left and raises his bent right arm in a protective gesture. His fingers are spread, and his palm faces away from the viewer. His mouth opens in an expression of fear. The scene may be set in a cave. The floor, walls, and ceiling merge together and appear to be made of stone or earth. The right side of the design contains dark shadows, behind Samuel and extending toward the left side of the figure nearest him. There is also a smaller shadow behind the pair at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>Samuel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the right half of the design, Samuel faces left and stands or walks, extending or striding with his exposed left foot. He wears a voluminous long-sleeved gown similar in color to his long white hair and long beard, giving him a ghostly appearance. The hem of his gown drags on the floor behind him, and the sleeve gathers in folds at his left wrist. Samuel's left arm is at his side and raised slightly, and he appears to point at the ground in front of the other figures. His head is down, and his eyes appear to be closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>witch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Witch of Endor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rod</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure nearest Samuel is a female with long hair who wears a gown or skirt that leaves her upper body exposed.  This is probably the Witch of Endor. The figure kneels with her right knee on the ground and her left leg bent, her left foot out in front of her. She faces to the right and looks toward the ghost of Samuel, but her upper body leans backward slightly. The figure's right arm bends and appears to wrap around her waist, and she appears to hold a long object, perhaps a stick(?) or magical rod, in her right hand. Her left arm extends across her body and may point at the men to her right. Her mouth is open, and her facial expression suggests fear. A long piece of drapery extends from the figure's left hip, circles over her head, and floats behind her. Part of the figure's long hair floats alongside the ends of this cloth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, a man kneels on the ground in a contracted posture facing right. He wears a robe or other draped garment that leaves his right shoulder and arm bare. Long hair and a beard cover much of his head and face. The man bends forward, hunches his shoulders, and lies prone on the ground with his legs drawn up underneath him, perhaps bowing before the ghost of Samuel. His left arm is crossed in front of his face and appears to support the weight of his upper body. His left arm is bent and extends forward, toward the ghost. The fingers of his right hand are spread, and he faces right but looks at Samuel's feet rather than at his face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the bowing man kneel two others at left. The male figure at right has short, curly hair and a beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown with a robe or other cloth draped over it. The man faces forward and to the right, looking in Samuel's direction with an expression of fear. His left arm extends to the right; the palm of his left hand faces outward, and his fingers are spread. He leans away from the ghost of Samuel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the bowing man kneel two others. At left, a male figure with long hair wears a long-sleeved gown and a robe or other draped cloth. His body faces away from the viewer, but his head turns to the right as he appears to look toward the ghost of Samuel. His legs are bent, and his legs extend behind him. His lower right leg and right foot emerge from the hem of his garment. The man leans slightly to the left and raises his bent right arm, perhaps in a protective gesture. His fingers are spread, and his palm faces away from the viewer. His mouth opens in an expression of fear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene may be set in a cave made of stone or earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ceiling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene may be set in a cave in which the floor, walls, and ceiling merge and may be made of stone or earth. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The right side of the design contains dark shadows, behind Samuel and extending toward the left side of the figure nearest him. There is also a smaller shadow behind the pair at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext><vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but144.1.wc.01.01" justify="left">the witch of Endor raising the Spirit of Samuel         1783 W Blake inv</l>
                    
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
