<bad id="but174.1" type="penink" work="Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: The Apotheosis of Bacchus" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="174" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: The Apotheosis of Bacchus">
                    <main>Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: The Apotheosis of Bacchus</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake's attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake's customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake's <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: The Apotheosis of Bacchus*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                    </origination>
                    <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author, </role>
                        <role>delineator.  Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription, lower right.</role>
                    </origination>
                <compdate value="1779">c. 1778-85?<note>The date of this work is far from certain.  Blake may have executed this drawing while still an apprentice to James Basire, 1772-79.  The inscription by Tatham may not have been written until 1863 or later.  See the reference to Alexander Gilchrist's biography of Blake, first published in 1863, in Tatham's similar inscription on the companion drawing, *Figures from a Greek Vase, after D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery*, Butlin 175.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>27.3 x 42.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>247.5 x 44.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink over pencil<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none recorded</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Apparently inherited by Catherine Blake upon the death of her husband, William Blake, in 1827; inherited by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold by Tatham to the British Museum in October 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1867,1012.207</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but174.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT174.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Figures From a Greek Vase, After D'Hancarville: The Apotheosis of Bacchus</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 174)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>27.3 x 42.2 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  The leftmost figure, a nude female, sits or reclines on a length of drapery and turns her head to look right.  The horn of abundance in her right hand and the thyrsus in her left mark her as Ariadne.  The second female figure from the left faces right and wears a gown covered with eyes, identifying her as Iris.  In her left hand she holds ambrosia, which she may offer to the central figure of Bacchus. Directly below Iris stands a male figure, nude other than a hat and bit of drapery over his left shoulder, who raises a vase of wine in his left hand and holds another object, perhaps a wineskin, in his right.  This figure may be a faun.  In the center of the composition facing right but looking left sits a nude male figure crowned with laurels and holding a laurel branch.  The laurels and the lyre on which he sits are both attributes of Bacchus Musagetes.  To the immediate right of Bacchus stands a left-facing female figure wearing a long gown.  With her left hand, she like Iris offers Bacchus ambrosia; this figure may be Hebe.  The rightmost figure in the scene is a nude, bearded male who faces right but looks left.  His tail and the lyre in his left hand identify him as Silenus.  This drawing is a copy of an engraving of a Greek vase painting in D'Hancarville (P. F. Hugues), <hi rend="i">Antiquités etrusques, grecques et romaines, tirées du cabinet de M. Hamilton</hi>, Naples 1766-67, volume 2, plate 68.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ariadne</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  The leftmost figure, a nude female with prominent breasts and long, curly hair beneath a hat or scarf, sits or reclines on a length of drapery.  She faces forward but turns her head to look right.  Her right arm is bent upward and holds an upturned conical object, likely the horn of abundance. Bent at 90 degrees, her left arm holds a thyrsus.  These attributes identify her as Ariadne.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>thyrsus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tassel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost female figure sits or reclines on a length of drapery that is intricately decorated with geometrical patterns on both visible corners that end in tassels.  In her right hand she holds an upturned conical horn, likely the horn of abundance, and in her left, she holds a thyrsus, a type of staff.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Iris</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ambrosia</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  The second female figure from the left, visible only from approximately the knees up, faces and leans right. Her curly hair is primarily covered by a hat topped with laurels, and she wears a gown covered with eyes, which identifies her as Iris.  The intricate belt of the gown recalls the swirling volutes of a classical capital.  Her right arm is bent with the hand resting on her hip; in her bent left arm she holds a long, somewhat angular object that may be an offering of ambrosia for the central figure of Bacchus.  Her left leg appears to be bent forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backwards</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>faun</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  Directly below Iris stands a male figure, who is nude with prominent genitals.  He wears a large, pointed hat over short, curly hair and a length of drapery covers his left shoulder. With a bent, raised left arm, he carries a jug (perhaps a krater?) in his left hand and holds another object, perhaps a wineskin, in his right.  His left leg is bent at the knee and his right is extended backwards, suggesting he may be walking to the right, although his head is turned sharply to the left.  This figure may be a faun offering wine to Bacchus.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>vase</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bag</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wineskin</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the left at the bottom of the composition carries a container in his raised left hand (perhaps a krater or some kind of classical vase of wine?). In his right hand, he holds another object that may be a container or bag for the vase, perhaps a wineskin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Bacchus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upwards</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tassel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  In the center of the composition, a nude male figure with long, curly hair wearing a crown of laurels sits atop a large lyre.  Facing right but with head turned to the left, he rests his right arm on the instrument (which he may play) and holds a bifurcated laurel branch in his left hand with arm bent upwards.  The laurels and the lyre on which he sits are both attributes of Bacchus Musagetes.  A length of drapery covers his left shoulder and falls below the lyre where the decorated fabric ends in a tassel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The nude male figure in the center of the composition sits on a large lyre, which he may play with his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The nude male figure in the center of the composition wears a crown of laurels and also holds a bifurcated laurel branch in his left hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Hebe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ambrosia</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  The second figure from the right, a female figure with long hair and a crown stands or walks facing left.  She wears a long, intricately patterned gown with a large belt.  She extends her right hand downward with palm facing down and her left arm is bent upwards at the elbow.  With her left hand, she holds or carries an angular object that is likely an offering of ambrosia for the figure of Bacchus directly in front of her.  This figure is likely Hebe.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Silenus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six mythological figures, all identifiable by their appearance and attributes, stand or sit in this scene representing the Apotheosis of Bacchus.  The rightmost figure in the scene is a nude male (with prominent genitals) who stands or leans in the upper right corner of the drawing.  He has short, curly hair, a beard, and wears some sort of leafy crown.  His mouth may be slightly open.  The tail visible on his right side and the lyre that he holds (and may play) his left hand identify him as Silenus.  His body faces the right though he turns his head to the left.  His left arm is extended with palm facing down and nearly touches the head of the female figures below him.  His left arm is bent upwards, already him to finger the strings of the lyre.  Both legs are bent slightly at the knees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure, the nude male Silenus, holds a lyre in his left hand that he may play.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but174.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="45">William Blake   an <hi rend="underscore">original Drawing</hi>- Frederick Tatham-<note>This inscription by Tatham may not have been written until 1863 or later.  See the reference to Alexander Gilchrist's biography of Blake, first published in 1863, in Tatham's similar inscription on the companion drawing, *Figures from a Greek Vase, after D'Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery*, Butlin 175.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but174.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="47">I suppose these figures were taken from</l>
                    <l n="but174.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="49">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Cumberlands designs for Engraving<note>Frederick Tatham penned this inscription, although the drawing is in fact a copy from a plate of a Greek vase painting in D'Hancarville (P. F. Hugues), *Antiquités etrusques, grecques et romaines, tirées du cabinet de M. Hamilton*, Naples 1766-67, volume 2, plate 68.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>