<bad id="but109.1" type="wc" work="Abraham and Isaac" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="boston" catalog="butlin" catid="109">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Abraham and Isaac">
                    <main>
                        Abraham and Isaac</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Abraham and Isaac*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.A">c. 1780<note>The date ascribed by Butlin 109 is based on stylistic considerations, but this work may date from a slightly later period.  The drawing is inscribed on the verso, "Abraham and Isaac" and "Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 1783", not in Blake's hand.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>19.0 x 24.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>19.0 x 24.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>paper, probably wove</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name>
                <date>1890</date>
                <dealer>Bernard Quaritch</dealer>
                <price>&#163;1200 with thirty-two other works by Blake</price>
                <note>Acquired at an unknown time, probably directly from Blake, by Thomas Butts; Thomas Butts, Jr., probably by inheritance in 1845; possibly the work sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 26 June 1852, lot 182x (11s. to "Butts," possibly bought-in if Butts was the vendor); sold "the Property of Thomas Butts," Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, in lot 102 with seven Shakespeare subjects, Butlin 84 (&#163;1.3s. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); John C. Strange by 1863; the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his catalogues 350 of 10 August 1883, in item 13842 with thirty-two other works (&#163;1200), same group and price, May 1885 and November 1886 catalogues of "William Blake's Original Drawings," no item numbers, and the 1887 "General Catalogue of Books," item 13842 (same group and price); the group acquired in 1890 by the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">90.111</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but109.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT109.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Abraham and Isaac</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 109)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The drawing is inscribed on the verso, "Abraham and Isaac" and "Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> 1783", not in Blake's hand.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>19.0 x 24.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design features two male figures, Abraham and Isaac, who kneel facing one another next to a stone altar. At left, Abraham is an old man with long hair and a long beard. A gown or other garment appears to cover him from the waist down; his right shoulder and arm are bare. A robe covers Abraham's left arm, extends around his back, and drapes over and around his right leg. His flexed right foot is visible beneath the robe. Behind Abraham, its loose drapery appears to float away from his back. Abraham kneels, facing right, with his shoulders hunched forward. His right arm extends downward and slightly to the right, and he points at the ground with his index finger as he holds a dagger out in front. His left arm wraps around the body of his son Isaac, embracing him in a protective gesture. Abraham's left hand dangles downward. Abraham looks over his left shoulder and slightly upward toward the altar at right. His wrinkled face shows an expression of grief or despair. The much smaller Isaac figure at right is long-haired and nude. He faces left toward his father and kneels with legs together and feet flexed. He hunches forward and crosses his arms in front of his body, where they are bound with two loops of a thin rope. The index finger of his right hand points down at the ground. Isaac's head is down, and he appears to hide in his father's embrace. Isaac's face shows an expression of grief or despair. To the right of Abraham and Isaac, an altar appears, made of large stone blocks. Seven(?) pieces of wood stacked are on top, and there appears to be smoke rising from them. An indeterminate lighter shape above the altar may suggest a spirit or other presence, at which Abraham may stare. At the right side of the altar's base sits a small lamp with a flame extending upward from its top. Below and to the right of this lamp, in the corner of the design, is a small bundle of sticks that appears to be held together by rope. Blue-green washes along the lower edge of the design may suggest grass or earth. Much of the design is dark and shadowy. Particularly dark areas include the space behind Abraham and the corner where the bundle of sticks is laid.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Abraham</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dagger</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knife</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design features two male figures, Abraham and Isaac, who kneel facing one another next to an altar. At left, Abraham is an old man with long hair and a long beard. A gown or other garment appears to cover him from the waist down; his right shoulder and arm are bare. A robe covers Abraham's left arm, extends around his back, and drapes over and around his right leg. His flexed right foot is visible beneath the robe. Behind Abraham, its loose drapery appears to float away from his back. Abraham kneels, facing right, with his shoulders hunched forward. His right arm extends downward and slightly to the right, and he points at the ground with his index finger as he holds a dagger out in front. His left arm wraps around the body of his son Isaac, embracing him in a protective gesture. Abraham's left hand dangles downward. Abraham looks over his left shoulder and slightly upward toward the altar at right. His wrinkled face shows an expression of grief or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Isaac</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design features two male figures, Abraham and Isaac, who kneel facing one another next to an altar. The much smaller Isaac figure at right is long-haired and nude. He faces left toward his father and kneels with legs together and feet flexed. He hunches forward and crosses his arms in front of his body, where they are bound with two loops of a thin rope. The index finger of his right hand points down at the ground. Isaac's head is down, and he appears to hide in his father's embrace. Isaac's face shows an expression of grief or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>altar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of Abraham and Isaac, an altar appears, made of large stone blocks. Seven(?) pieces of wood stacked are on top, and there appears to be smoke rising from them.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>lamp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the right side of the altar's base sits a small lamp with a flame extending upward from its top.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>bundle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower righthand corner of the design is a small bundle of sticks that appears to be held together by rope.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Blue-green washes along the lower edge of the design may suggest grass or earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Blue-green washes along the lower edge of the design may suggest grass or earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Much of the design is dark and shadowy. Particularly dark areas include the space behind Abraham and the corner where the bundle of sticks is laid. An indeterminate lighter shape in the shadows above the altar may suggest a spirit or other presence, at which Abraham may stare.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
