<bad id="but171.1" type="mono" work="Pan Teaching a Boy to Play on the Pipes" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="171">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Pan Teaching a Boy to Play on the Pipes">
                    <main>
                        Pan Teaching a Boy to Play on the Pipes</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition
                </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 305KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries
                <date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
            </filedesc>
            <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date>
                by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. 
                Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
                Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
                express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher.
                Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
                granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
                This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>                
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>October 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian, </name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom, </name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Rob Rich, </name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl, </name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green, </name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer, </name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Pan Teaching a Boy to Play on the Pipes
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1785.P">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>10.5 x 7.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>21.0 x 16.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash<note>The slight indication of an arm below the main drawing is rendered in pencil.</note></medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1867</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; 
                    acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; 
                    sold by Tatham to the British Museum in October 1867.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Museum number">1867,1012.202</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but171.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT171.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Pan Teaching a Boy to Play on the Pipes</title>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 171)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>21.0 x 16.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>Frederick Tatham added a pen and ink inscription in the lower right corner of the leaf bearing this drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing depicts the Greek god Pan and another male figure, probably the shepherd Daphnis. Pan sits to the left in profile, his body facing right. He leans slightly back as he sits and hunches his shoulders forward. His head is down and slightly bent to the left, as if looking at the flute while leaning toward or listening to the male figure at his right. His right arm is bent at the elbow and he holds the bottom of the flute with his right hand. He appears to be teaching or showing Daphnis how to use the flute. Pan sits on an indeterminate object, perhaps a stump or a box, with his legs together and his left hoof crossed in front of the right hoof. His prominent right hindquarter is muscular, and part of his left hindquarter is visible behind it. His legs are covered in fur. He has long, swept back hair, a beard, and two small horns on his forehead. The shepherd Daphnis sits to the right, facing forward. The left side of his body is obscured by Pan. His arms are bent at the elbow and extended up. He holds the flute with both hands and brings it close to his face. He looks at Pan and sits close to him on the stump or box, twisting his body to turn toward him. His right leg is lifted up and bent at the knee, extending slightly outwards. His lower right leg might be resting between Pan’s hindquarters. His left leg crosses over and rests on his right ankle with his left foot placed next to Pan’s hooves. He has short curly hair. Both Pan and Daphnis are nude. The block or stump on which the figures sit has indeterminate decorative details running diagonally from top left to bottom right, including what may be a curved line and an outline that mimics the hindquarters of Pan. Shadows appear along Pan’s back and Daphnis’s chest. The block on which the figures sit rests on a bare floor. The background is plain, perhaps representing a bare wall behind the figures. A tentative pencil sketch depicts a portion of an arm below the main drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Pan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hoof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fur</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>teaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man seated on the left of the block is presumably the Greek god Pan. He sits in profile, his body facing right. He leans slightly back as he sits and hunches his shoulders forward. His head is down and slightly bent to the left, as if looking at the flute while leaning toward or listening to the male figure at his right. His right arm is bent at the elbow and he holds the bottom of the flute with his right hand. He appears to be teaching or showing Daphnis how to use the flute. Pan sits on an indeterminate object, perhaps a stump or a box, with his legs together and his left hoof crossed in front of the right hoof. His prominent right hindquarter is muscular, and part of his left hindquarter is visible behind it. His legs are covered in fur. He has long, swept back hair, a beard, and two small horns on his forehead. Both Pan and Daphnis are nude.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Daphnis</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The shepherd Daphnis(?) sits to the right, facing forward. The left side of his body is obscured by Pan. His arms are bent at the elbow and extended up. He holds the flute with both hands and brings it close to his face. He looks at Pan and sits close to him on the stump or box, twisting his body to turn toward him. His right leg is lifted up and bent at the knee, extending slightly outwards. His lower right leg might be resting between Pan’s hindquarters. His left leg crosses over and rests on his right ankle with his left foot placed next to Pan’s hooves. He has short curly hair. Both Pan and Daphnis are nude.</illusobjdesc></component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                            <characteristic>flute</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Both Pan and Daphnis hold a flute. Pan appears to be teaching or showing Daphnis how to play the flute.</illusobjdesc></component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>box</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                	    <characteristic>stump</characteristic>
                	    <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                	    <illusobjdesc>The large block or stump on which the figures sit has indeterminate decorative elements running diagonally from top left to bottom right, including a curved line and an outline that mimics the hindquarters of Pan. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The block or stump on which the figures sit rests on a bare floor. The background is plain, perhaps representing a bare wall behind the figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Shadows appear along Pan’s back and Daphnis’s chest.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    <component type="object" location= "CD">
                        <characteristic>arm</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tentative pencil sketch may depict a portion of an arm below the main drawing. </illusobjdesc></component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        <phystext>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                <l n="but171.1.wd.01.01" justify="left" indent="40">
                    <hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Drawn by William Blake</hi></l>
                <l n="but171.1.wd.01.02" justify="left" indent="42">
                    <hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">after the Antique supposed</hi></l>
                <l n="but171.1.wd.01.03" justify="left" indent="43">
                    <hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">for some work.</hi></l>  
                <l n="but171.1.wd.01.04" justify="left" indent="52">
                    <hi rend="handshift" medium="pen">Frederick Tatham<del type="overstrike">s</del></hi>
                    <note>Butlin reads the deleted character at the end of "Tatham" as an "s" (Butlin 171).</note></l>
            </lg>
        </phystext>
            </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
