<bad id="but148r.1" type="mono" work="Group of Men Seated in a Circle" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="148r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Group of Men Seated in a Circle">
                    <main>
                        Group of Men Seated in a Circle</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>                
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>March 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
<name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Andrea Dickens</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
<name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
<name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Group of Men Seated in a Circle
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.U">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>28.3 x 35.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>28.3 x 35.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; Alexander Macmillan by no later that 1876; probably a private collector or collectors; sold in an unidentified sale of 22 Dec. 1938 to the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach; sold (probably in 1939) to Lessing J. Rosenwald; given by Rosenwald to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C., in 1943.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.3.1723.a</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but148.1.1r.wd.01" dbi="BUT148.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Group of Men Seated in a Circle</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 148 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>28.3 x 35.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>A pencil sketch, *Sketch of Two or Three Figures*, is on this verso of this monochrome wash drawing.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing depicts a group of seven men seated in an incomplete circle (with an empty space nearest the viewer). The man at the left end of the arc, nearest the drawing's left edge, faces right and is seen in profile. He sits in a chair with his legs bent at 90-degree angles and both feet flat on the ground. His right arm bends along the angle of his body and rests in his lap, perhaps holding the staff which rises diagonally and rests atop the man's right shoulder. The man hunches forward slightly, lowering his head and eyes as he looks down at his lap or at the ground. The man wears knee-length tights and a long coat that covers his upper body and part of the chair below him. The man has short, curly hair. The second man from left also has short, curly hair; the nature of his garment is unclear. He faces forward and to the right, sitting back somewhat from the figures on either side of him. One of his legs bends and extends into the space between the circle, his foot resting on the floor. The man's head tilts downward, and his eyes are lowered toward the ground. Lines below his head may indicate some movement of his arms or a piece of his garment. Third from left sits a man whose body faces the viewer but whose head turns to the right. He has short, curly hair, and his face is darkened, perhaps by shadows. The man wears a shirt, a cravat or other decoration near his neck, and a bulky overcoat with large lapels covering his shoulders. The man bends both arms so that his elbows protrude and his hands clasp in front of his chest. His legs are hidden by those of the figures at left. The man in the drawing's center sits, facing the viewer, with his head held up and his eyes staring forward. His mouth may open slightly. This man also has short, curly hair, and he is dressed like the other men: in knee-length pants or tights, a shirt, and a collared overcoat. His knees bend so that his feet are flat on the ground, pointing toward the viewer. His right arm bends forward as he hods a staff near his right knee. (The staff extends to the floor at a leftward diagonal.) The man's left arm is bent and lowered so that his hand rests on his left knee. At the immediate right of this figure is another man who sits, facing forward and to the left, and turns his head to look at the central man. As he does so, this man bends his left arm upward across his body and may hold an angular, indistinct object in his left hand. His face displays a look of concern. The man's hair is long and curly, and it appears to be pulled back into a low ponytail. He wears a high-collared shirt and a coat; his legs are not visible. Second from right is a less defined male figure who sits, facing left, and looks straight ahead. He appears to have curly hair, and the collar of his shirt or coat is visible at the base of his neck. Rightmost in the group is a man in knee-length pants and a shirt or coat with a collar and large cuffs. This man sits, facing left, with his legs bent and crossed at the ankles, right over left. His feet are planted on the ground in front of him. The man's left arm bends along the curve of his body, and his left hand rests in his lap. He leans forward slightly, and his head tilts downward as his eyes lower in a look of sadness. The man has short, curly hair. The men at the far left and right ends of the group sit on simple wooden chairs; the other figures are likely seated on similar pieces of furniture. The floors and walls of the room in which this group gathers appear to be bare. Shadowy areas appear in the upper corners of the drawing, at left of the center man, and behind and below the rightmost man.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing depicts a group of seven men seated in an incomplete circle (with an empty space nearest the viewer).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man at the left end of the arc, nearest the drawing's left edge, faces right and is seen in profile. He sits in a chair with his legs bent at 90-degree angles and both feet flat on the ground. His right arm bends along the angle of his body and rests in his lap, perhaps holding the staff which rises diagonally and rests atop the man's right shoulder. The man hunches forward slightly, lowering his head and eyes as he looks down at his lap or at the ground. The man wears knee-length tights and a long coat that covers his upper body and part of the chair below him. The man has short, curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clothing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second man from left also has short, curly hair; the nature of his garment is unclear. He faces forward and to the right, sitting back somewhat from the figures on either side of him. One of his legs bends and extends into the space between the circle, his foot resting on the floor. The man's head tilts downward, and his eyes are lowered toward the ground. Lines below his head may indicate some movement of his arms or a piece of his garment.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Third from left sits a man whose body faces the viewer but whose head turns to the right. He has short, curly hair, and his face is darkened, perhaps by shadows. The man wears a shirt, a cravat or other decoration near his neck, and a bulky overcoat with large lapels covering his shoulders. The man bends both arms so that his elbows protrude and his hands clasp in front of his chest. His legs are hidden by those of the figures at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man in the drawing's center sits, facing the viewer, with his head held up and his eyes staring forward. His mouth may open slightly. This man also has short, curly hair, and he is dressed like the other men: in knee-length pants or tights, a shirt, and a collared overcoat. His knees separate and bend so that his feet are flat on the ground, pointing toward the viewer. His right arm bends forward as he hods a staff near his right knee. (The staff extends to the floor at a leftward diagonal.) The man's left arm is bent and lowered so that his hand rests on his left knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ponytail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the immediate right of this figure is another man who sits, facing forward and to the left, and turns his head to look at the central man. As he does so, this man bends his left arm upward across his body and may hold an angular, indistinct object in his left hand. His face displays a look of concern. The man's hair is long and curly, and it appears to be pulled back into a low ponytail. He wears a high-collared shirt and a coat; his legs are not visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Second from right is a less defined male figure who sits, facing left, and looks straight ahead. He appears to have curly hair, and the collar of his shirt or coat is visible at the base of his neck.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm in lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Rightmost in the group is a man in knee-length pants and a shirt or coat with a collar and large cuffs. This man sits, facing left, with his legs bent and crossed at the ankles, right over left. His feet are planted on the ground in front of him. The man's left arm bends along the curve of his body, and his left hand rests in his lap. He leans forward slightly, and his head tilts downward as his eyes lower in a look of sadness. The man has short, curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The men at the far left and right ends of the group sit on simple wooden chairs; the other figures are likely seated on similar pieces of furniture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The floors and walls of the room in which this group gathers appear to be bare.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="E">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Shadowy areas appear in the upper left- and righthand corners of the drawing, at left of the center man, and behind and below the rightmost man.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
