<bad id="but186r.1" type="mono" work="Sketch for 'War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="186r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Sketch for 'War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following'">
                    <main>
                        Sketch for "War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following"</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries <date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>September 2019</date>
                 <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian, </name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom, </name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Rob Rich, </name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl, </name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green, </name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer, </name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                 <date>May 1999</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
               <name>David Cosca</name> and
               <name>Robert Bingler</name>
               <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Sketch for "War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following"
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.A">c. 1780</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>17.7 x 22.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.7 x 22.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash with some scratching out</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1984</date>
                <dealer>Steigal Fine Art</dealer>
                <price>$7600</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife, Catherine, upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Joseph Hogarth; sold Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 7-30 June 1854, 11th evening, in lot 4624 with seven other works by Blake (13s. to Cowieson, possibly a dealer); Barron Grahame, sold from his collection Sotheby's, 15 March 1878, in lot 22 with five other works by Blake (&#163;2.11s. to Chalmers, probably a dealer), or in lot 23 with one other work by Blake (&#163;5.7s.6d. to Chalmers); Robert Carfrae; his son, Robert Carfrae, Jr., probably by inheritance in 1900; sold to Donald Davidson of Steigal Fine Art, Edinburgh; offered Christie's, 17 June 1975, lot 87 (not sold); acquired, with the assistance of Michael Phillips, from Steigal Fine Art, by Robert N. Essick in April 1984 ($7600).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but186.1r.wd.01" dbi="BUT186.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketch for "War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following"</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 186 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>17.7 x 22.1 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>This wash drawing, dated by Butlin 186 to c. 1780 on stylistic grounds, is probably a preliminary for a more finished work exhibited by Blake at the Royal Academy in 1784, *War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following* (Butlin 187, untraced).  The inscription lower right on the wash drawing, "June 1783," may have been added later than the execution of the drawing and may not be by Blake.  The verso contains pencil sketches, titled by Butlin 186 verso as *Studies of a Child, for the Frontispiece to Malkin's "Memoirs of His Child"* and dated to c. 1805.  The relationship to the frontispiece in Thomas Malkin, *A Father's Memoirs of His Child* (1806), is far from certain.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This wash drawing shows groups of figures in the foreground, mid ground, and background, each of which are engrossed in separate scenes of action. In the foreground, a presumably male figure floats or hovers prominently in the middle of the drawing. He twists his torso up and to the right, looking over his right shoulder. His long, curly hair flows behind him, suggesting that he is moving. Both arms are outstretched and his left hand is slightly raised with palm up and fingers extended. His right hand appears to be holding a sword with least four fingers of his hand extended. His legs extend behind him, nearly reaching the right margin of the plate. His left leg extends backward and is raised slightly at the knee and his right leg extends straight outward. His bare feet are visible and his right toes point to the ground. He wears a long gown that may or may not cover his arms and ends in several loops of fabric between his legs. He floats in front of what appears to be a thick, dark cloud or gust of wind. It follows the slope of his body, reaching from his left arm in the middle of the image to the edge of his feet at the bottom right of the image. He holds a flamberge sword, indicated by its wavy, flame-like blade. It is faintly outlined and is held at a 45-degree angle. A brick building stands to the left of the figure. A circular design, perhaps a window, is drawn into the visible right side of the building, near the floating figure’s head. A man, woman, and dead child – probably a family – huddle in what may be an open foyer or other unenclosed portion of the building. Only the upper body of the bearded male figure in the back of the group is visible. His is bent forward and extends his arms to either side, bending them slightly downward as if bracing for action or protecting the other two figures. The right arm is wrapped around the back of the middle, female figure. She kneels on the ground and bends to the left so that her upper body is nearly horizontal. Her visible left arm bends upward at the elbow and her hand is clenched in a fist near her ear. Her head is up and twisted over her shoulder to look behind her. Her hair may be pulled back and she wears a gown. A smaller nude figure, probably male, lies supine over her knees. It may be the child of the male and female figures and appears to be dead. His left leg extends straight and only the upper portion of his right leg is visible. His torso, supported by the female figure’s knee, twists so that his upper body faces the viewer. His right arm falls behind his back and his left arm dangles down the female figure’s leg and onto the ground. His head drops over his left shoulder, facing downward. The three figures crouch on a bare floor and a curtain appears to be parted behind them. A second building appears to the right of the floating figure. It has three visible pillars or columns and is topped by a frieze decorated with what may represent classical art. Although sparsely detailed, a group of figures is visible between the right-most and middle columns. In front, two figures face right and kneel, with their bodies bent forward, arms extended in front of them, and their heads to the ground. A group of at least three figures appear to be fighting behind them. One may hold what appears to be a shield and spear. A wall or other structure appears in the background, between the two main buildings. There are at least two figures stand on the wall. They both hold what may be swords or spears, held up and to the right at a 45-degree angle. They may be fighting with each other or running toward battle on the right. A third figure may be depicted to the left of this pair, also brandishing a sword or spear. The tops of three buildings appear behind the wall; a castle tower rises behind the two figures fighting on the wall, which is flanked by pointed arches on either side. Dark wash that may represent a dark cloud or smoke appears in the upper right-hand corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground, a presumably male figure floats or hovers prominently in the middle of the drawing. He twists his torso up and to the right, looking over his right shoulder. His long, curly hair flows behind him, suggesting that he is moving. Both arms are outstretched and his left hand is slightly raised with palm up and fingers extended. His right hand appears to be holding a sword with least four fingers of his hand extended. His legs extend behind him, nearly reaching the right margin of the plate. His left leg extends backward and is raised slightly at the knee and his right leg extends straight outward. His bare feet are visible and his right toes point to the ground. He wears a long gown that may or may not cover his arms and ends in several loops of fabric between his legs.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A thick, dark cloud of what may be smoke or a gust of wind curves below the hovering figure. It follows the slope of his body, reaching from his left arm in the middle of the image to the edge of his feet at the bottom right of the image.</illusobjdesc></component>
                   
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>handle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The hovering figure holds a sword with a simple handle or hilt. Its wavy, flame-like blade suggests that it is a flamberge sword. It is faintly outlined. </illusobjdesc></component>
                
                    <component type="structure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facade</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A brick building or structure with an A-frame roof encompasses the entire left half of the design. A circular design, perhaps a window, decorates the visible right side of the building and a foyer or portico creates an open façade. It has a bare floor and a curtain appears to open to another room or area.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type= "figure" location= "AC">
                         <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>arms braced</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>hands to ears</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A man, woman, and dead child – probably a family – huddle in what may be an open foyer or other unenclosed portion of the building. Only the upper body of the bearded male figure in the back of the group is visible. His is bent forward and extends his arms to either side, bending them slightly downward as if bracing for action or protecting the other two figures. The right arm is wrapped around the back of the middle, female figure. She kneels on the ground and bends to the left so that her upper body is nearly horizontal. Her visible left arm bends upward at the elbow and her hand is clenched in a fist near her ear. Her head is up and twisted over her shoulder to look behind her. Her hair may be pulled back and she wears a gown. A smaller nude figure, probably male, lies supine over her knees. It may be the child of the male and female figures and appears to be dead. His left leg extends straight and only the upper portion of his right leg is visible. His torso, supported by the female figure’s knee, twists so that his upper body faces the viewer. His right arm falls behind his back and his left arm dangles down the female figure’s leg and onto the ground. His head drops over his left shoulder, facing downward.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>curtain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A curtain appears to be parted behind the three huddled figures.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="structure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A building stands in the middle distance on the right side of the plate. It has three visible pillars or columns and is topped by a frieze decorated with what may represent classical art. </illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures are prominent between the right and middle columns. They both appear to be bald and gowned. They face right and kneel, bending their bodies forward to hold their heads down to the ground. Their arms are extended forward, with forearms and hands on the ground. They are scarcely detailed. </illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fighting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of at least three figures appear to be fighting behind the kneeling figures. One holds what appears to be a spear, and at least one shield is also visible. They are scarcely detailed.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fighting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand on a wall or other structure in the background. They both hold what may be swords or spears, held up and to the right at a 45-degree angle. They may be fighting with each other or running toward battle on the right. A third figure may be depicted to the left of this pair, also brandishing a sword or spear. The figures are scarcely detailed. </illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="structure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least two figures stand on a wall or other structure in the background.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="structure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>castle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>turret</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three building structures appear in the background of the plate. They are mostly likely the tops of a castle or multiple castles. There are two pointed turrets on either side and a columnar tower between them. There are two slender windows on the middle tower, and possibly two windows, faintly sketched, on the left turret. The thin, vertical structure on the right-hand turret may be a castle spire.</illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Dark wash that may represent a cloud or smoke appears in the upper right-hand corner. </illusobjdesc></component>
                    
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="right">
                    <l n="but186.1r.wd.01.01" justify="right">June 1783<note>The lower reaches of the letters and numbers are cut off by the edge of the leaf.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
            
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
