<bad id="but108.1" type="mono" work="Abraham and Isaac" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="philadelphia" catalog="butlin" catid="108">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Abraham and Isaac">
                    <main>
                        Abraham and Isaac</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Philadelphia Museum of Art.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>                
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>April 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco, </name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian, </name>
                    <name>Alison Harper, </name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom, </name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Rob Rich, </name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson, </name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>December 2011</date>
                <respstmt>
                         <resp>Editors: </resp>
                         <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;                
                         <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                         University of California, Riverside; and                 
                         <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                         University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                         <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                         <name>William Shaw</name>
                         <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                         <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                         <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                         <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                         <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester</resp>
                         <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                         <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                         <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                         <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                         <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                         <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                         <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                         <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                         <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                         <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                         <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                         <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                         <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                         <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                         <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                         <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Abraham and Isaac
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.F">c. 1780<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>13.4 x 17.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.4 x 17.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Philadelphia Museum of Art</name>
                <date>1972</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
                
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 174 with 7 other works by Blake (9s. to Gould Weston); Mrs. Hunter-Weston, probably by inheritance; Nora Hunter, probably by inheritance; sold Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 23 (&#163;294 to the dealer Davidge acting for the dealer Charles Sessler, the latter probably acting for Mrs. William T. Tonner); given by Tonner to the Philadelphia Museum of Art in 1964 but not received until 1972.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Philadelphia Museum of Art</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1964-110-8</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but108.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT108.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Abraham and Isaac</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 108)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>13.4 x 17.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design features two male figures, Abraham and Isaac, who kneel facing one another next to an altar. At left, Abraham is an old man with long hair and a long beard. A robe or other garment covers most of his body, except for his bare right shoulder and right arm. The garment extends from Abraham's left arm around his back and drapes over his right leg. Behind Abraham, the drapery appears to float away from his back. Abraham kneels, facing right, with his shoulders hunched forward. His right arm extends downward and slightly to the right, and he points at the ground with his index finger. His left arm wraps around the body of his son Isaac, embracing him in a protective gesture. Abraham's left hand dangles, his index finger pointing toward the ground. Abraham's mouth appears to be open slightly, and he looks straight ahead (toward the right edge of the design) with an expression of grief or despair. The much smaller Isaac figure at right has long hair and appears to wear a robe, gown, or other garment. He faces left toward his father and kneels with legs together and feet flexed. He hunches forward and holds his forearms horizontally, crossing them in front of his body. Isaac's head is down, and he appears to hide in his father's embrace. Isaac's face shows an expression of fear or despair. To the right of Abraham and Isaac, an altar appears, perhaps with wood stacked on top. The shape of the flames and smoke above the altar suggests a human-like figure, perhaps an angel. This figure's head and right arm (and perhaps left arm) are faintly visible. The right arm extends to the left, toward Abraham and Isaac, with fingers spread and the palm facing the viewer, as if reaching toward the pair. In the lower right corner, at the base of the altar, sits a small lamp, perhaps with a flame extending upward from its top. The lower portion of the altar, including the area with the lamp, is shaded. Other significant shadows appear at upper right, over the angel figure; behind Abraham's back and legs; below Isaac's knees; and over Isaac's chest and genitals.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Abraham</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design features two male figures, Abraham and Isaac, who kneel facing one another next to an altar. At left, Abraham is an old man with long hair and a long beard. A robe, gown, or other garment covers most of his body, except for his bare right shoulder and right arm. The garment extends from Abraham's left arm around his back and drapes over his right leg. Behind Abraham, the drapery appears to float away from his back. Abraham kneels, facing right, with his shoulders hunched forward. His right arm extends downward and slightly to the right, and he points at the ground with his index finger. His left arm wraps around the body of his son Isaac, embracing him in a protective gesture. Abraham's left hand dangles, his index finger pointing toward the ground. Abraham's mouth appears to be open slightly, and he looks straight ahead (toward the right edge of the design) with an expression of grief or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Isaac</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design features two male figures, Abraham and Isaac, who kneel facing one another next to an altar. The much smaller Isaac figure at right has long hair and appears to wear a robe, gown, or other garment. He faces left toward his father and kneels with legs together and feet flexed. He hunches forward and holds his forearms horizontally, crossing them in front of his body. Isaac's head is down, and he appears to hide in his father's embrace. Isaac's face shows an expression of fear or despair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The shape of the flames and smoke above the altar suggests a human-like figure, perhaps an angel. This figure's head and right arm (and perhaps left arm) are faintly visible. The right arm extends to the left, toward Abraham and Isaac, with fingers spread and the palm facing the viewer, as if reaching toward the pair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>altar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of Abraham and Isaac, an altar appears, perhaps with wood stacked on top, and flames and smoke above.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>lamp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner, at the base of the altar, sits a small lamp, perhaps with a flame extending upward from its top.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower portion of the altar, including the area with the lamp, is shaded. Other significant shadows appear at upper right, over the angel figure; behind Abraham's back and legs; below Isaac's knees; and over Isaac's chest and genitals.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
