<bad id="but10.1" type="wc" work="King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His Monument" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin"
    catid="10">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His Monument">
                    <main> King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His Monument</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 22KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB
                to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/> This image copyright © 2020 Society of Antiquaries, London.<lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                        Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                        Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His Monument* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1775.E">c. 1775</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>44.3 x 25.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>56.0 x 27.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>Fragments of the lower part of an inscription, almost completely trimmed off by the top edge of the leaf, appear top right.  Butlin 10 records this inscription as "N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 4".</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>4<note>The outer and inner lines in the frame are dark; the two within are much lighter.  Gray wash shades the area between the inner, lighter lines.</note></framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its engraving for Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, first published by the Society of Antiquaries in 1780.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries, London</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 28</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but10.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT10.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">King Sebert, Heads and Ornaments from His
                Monument</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 10)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The collection stamp of the Society of Antiquaries appears lower left just inside the framing lines.  A water color replica (Butlin 18) of this water color is in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.  An engraving of this design was published in Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, Plate 6 (1780), and in *Vetusta Monumenta*, volume 2 of c. 1789, Plate 34.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>56.0 x 27.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design collects figureheads and other ornaments featured on
                        the north side of the monument of King Sebert in Westminster Abbey. All
                        three heads have curly hair. The crowns on the two outer figureheads suggest
                        they may be kings. The central head wears a pointed collar and a crown or
                        hat resembling a miter, perhaps representing a bishop. Below the three heads
                        are two crowns, each embellished with leaves. The crown at right (presumably
                        belonging to King Henry III) is slightly taller and may bear gems. Below the
                        crowns, in the center of the design, are pictured two scepter heads. The
                        left, King Sebert's, is a golden Gothic structure. The right, King Henry
                        III's, contains gilded leaves. The four images in the lower half of the
                        design represent details from the kings' apparel or surroundings. First, the
                        top design is featured on the tops of Henry's gloves. It is a red flower or
                        cross surrounded by a diamond shape with four finials at the points. The
                        next two emblems, featured to the left and right below the glove decoration,
                        are details of the borders of the kings' robes. Finally, the center design
                        below these depicts the decorative corner pieces inside Sebert's
                        monument.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figureheads, perhaps made of stone, appear at the top of
                            the design facing forward. The leftmost head has a full face and a cleft
                            chin. Atop his short, curly hair is a crown, which suggests that he may
                            represent a king. The crown bears leaf designs and jewels. A split
                            collar extends below his chin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bishop</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figureheads, perhaps made of stone, appear at the top of
                            the design facing forward. The shape and headwear of the central head
                            differentiate it from the other two. Below the head extends a large,
                            pointed collar, and atop its short, curly head sits an ornate crown or
                            hat that resembles a miter. This headwear suggests that the figure may
                            represent a bishop.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figureheads, perhaps made of stone, appear at the top of
                            the design facing forward. The rightmost figure, similar to king at
                            left, has short, curly hair and wears a crown decorated with crosses and
                            jewels. A split collar appears below his chin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gold</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Henry the Third</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the three heads are two crowns, each embellished with
                            leaves of various sizes. The crown at right (presumably belonging to
                            King Henry III) is slightly taller and may bear gems.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gold</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Henry the Third</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the crowns, in the center of the design, are pictured
                            two scepter heads. The scepter head at right, King Henry III's, contains
                            six gilded leaves, the top two of which meet to form a
                            point.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>Gothic architecture</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the crowns, in the center of the design, are pictured
                            two scepter heads. The left, King Sebert's, is a golden Gothic structure
                            with six pinnacles and corresponding doors or windows. The two center
                            points terminate in finials, the others in rounded
                            toppers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>glove</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Henry the Third</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four images in the lower half of the design represent
                            details from the kings' apparel or surroundings. First, the top design
                            is featured on the tops of Henry's gloves. It is a red flower or cross
                            superimposed over an "X" and surrounded by a diamond shape with four
                            finials at the points.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>border</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four images in the lower half of the design represent
                            details from the kings' apparel or surroundings. The two emblems
                            featured to the left and right below the glove decoration, are details
                            of the borders of the kings' robes. Sebert's border, on the left,
                            features (from left to right) a row of circles and two narrow lines, a
                            design with finial-pointed arches over flowers, and two more narrow
                            lines. King Henry's border, on the right, has been folded over as it
                            appears in the full portrait. It also features circles and lines near
                            the left edge, but it contains a circle and "X" pattern in the center.
                            The fold is marked with a decorative square, which may hold the robe in
                            place.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>Gothic architecture</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The four images in the lower half of the design represent
                            details from the kings' apparel or surroundings. In the lowest center
                            portion of this arrangement is one of the decorative corner pieces
                            supporting the roof inside Sebert's monument. Beveled edges form a
                            corner at upper left, and the exterior points are connected with an
                            arch. The interior of the support features vegetation, perhaps leaves
                            and vines.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design collects figureheads and other ornaments featured
                            on the north side of the monument of King Sebert in Westminster
                            Abbey.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="10"/>
                <p n="but10.1.1.wc.01" justify="left">Heads &#38; Ornaments on the North Side of the Monument of King Sebert, in Westminster Abbey vide Vetust. Mon. Vol. II. plate 34.<note>This pen and ink inscription is probably not by Blake.  "Vetust. Mon. Vol. II. plate 34" is a reference to volume 2 of *Vetusta Monumenta*, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.  An engraving of this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published as plate 34 in that volume.</note></p>
                
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
