<bad id="but156" type="wc" work="" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="butlin" catid="156">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound">
                    <main>
                        Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 43KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Fitzwilliam Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.C">c. 1785</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>40.5 x 56.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>40.5 x 56.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1900</date>
                <dealer>Robert Dunthorne</dealer>
                <price>&#163;55 for all three finished water colors based on the story of Joseph and his brethren.</price>
                <note>According to Alexander Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake* (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1:57, "the three *Joseph* drawings [this work and *Joseph's Brethren Bowing Before Him* and *Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren*, Butlin 155 and 157] turned up within the last ten years in their original close rose-wood frames (a far from advantageous setting), at a broker's in Wardour Street [London], who had purchased them at a furniture-sale in the neighbourhood"; sold from the collection of "An Old-Established Printseller" (Walter E. Tiffin, according to Butlin 155), Sotheby's, 8 March 1860, lot 1826, with the two other *Joseph* designs noted above (&#163;10.5s. to the dealer H. Palser acting for James H. Chance); John Duke Coleridge, 1st Baron Coleridge, by 1862 (according to Butlin 155; listed in the collection of "Mr. J. D. Coleridge" by W. M. Rossetti in Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake*, 1863, 2:202); sold anonymously, Christie's, 12 Dec. 1898, lot 63, this drawing only (&#163;11.11s. to the dealer Robert Dunthorne); all three *Joseph* works sold by Dunthorne in 1900 for &#163;55 to the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, England.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">456B</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but156.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT156.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="B1">(BUT156.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>40.5 x 56.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design illustrates Genesis 42:19, 25. In the right third of the design, Joseph's brother Simeon is being bound at the wrists by another man, presumably one of Joseph's servants. Simeon kneels in a lunging position, facing the right edge of the design with his left leg forward and his right leg extended behind him with toes flexed. Both legs are bent at near-right angles and are bare from the knees down. Simeon is covered from waist to knees by a cloth that wraps around his back and drapes over each knee, gathering on the floor between his legs. He is nude from the waist up, and his torso faces forward and to the right. Both arms bend slightly and extend downward and to the right. Simeon's palms face one another, and his fingers are spread as the servant clasps manacles around both wrists. Simeon twists at the shoulders and neck, turning his head to the left and looking at the brothers behind him. He has a short beard and long hair. His mouth may open slightly. The man who binds Simeon stands to the right of him, facing the viewer and bending forward. He has short, curly hair and a beard; he wears a skirt or other garment that covers him from waist to knees. He stands with his left foot forward, just to the right of Simeon's. The servant's back foot, which extends behind him, can be seen between the two men's legs. He bends at the waist, lowering his left arm to secure the shackles around Simeon's wrists. His right arm bends at approximately ninety degrees, and he holds his forearm horizontally across his waist. The man's head is lowered and his eyes downcast, likely to look toward Simeon. To the left of Simeon and his captor, on a raised platform, a male figure (presumably Joseph) sits sideways on a throne-like chair and leans against its back. He faces right and sits with his left knee forward, his left foot drawn back underneath him, and his right leg bent and extended back behind him in a position that mimics Simeon's. Joseph leans forward and extends his bent arms in front of him to rest his elbows on the chair back. His hands are raised and clasped together in a prayerful posture, and he may bring his forehead forward to rest on them. Joseph stares at the right edge of the design; his mouth opens slightly, and his facial expression may suggest grief. Joseph wears a long-sleeved gown secured at the waist by a belt or sash. He has long, curly hair. Behind Joseph, in the left third of the design, the other nine brothers kneel or stand. Most of them look on as Simeon is bound. In the center of the kneeling group is an older-looking man with short, white, curly hair and a beard, both white. He is nude from the waist up and covered from the waist down with a skirt or other draping cloth. His lower body faces toward the right as his knees rest on the ground and his flexed feet support him. He leans backward slightly as his torso twists away from the viewer, who sees him from behind. His arms are lowered on either side and bend to embrace the brothers on his left and right. The man's head turns to the right to watch Simeon; his mouth may be open slightly. On his left is a younger man with long, curly hair. He faces right and kneels in a similar posture, though only his right foot is visible beneath the hem of his long, sleeveless gown. His muscular right arm extends down and forward so that his hand rests on the right hip of the older man. His fingers extend forward. The man's shoulders hunch forward as he leans against the older man with his head and eyes down. At the older man's right hand is another man(?) with long, curly hair. He faces forward and appears to kneel with his legs spread, though only his left knee is visible from behind the older man's embrace. His arms bend upward to cross in front of his chest, and the fingers of his right hand curve downward as if touching his left shoulder. The man's head turns to face right as he gazes at Simeon with an open mouth. Behind these three embracing figures are two more who also appear to kneel. One emerges at right of the group, just behind the figure with crossed arms. Only his bowed head and clasped hands are visible. He may be praying. At left and above the embracing trio is another male figure with long, curly hair who appears to wear a gown. He faces right and appears to be leaning forward as he looks ahead and up. Standing above these figures are four more brothers. They are, from left to right: a gowned man with long hair who faces right and leans his head on the shoulder of the man in front of him; a head of short, curly hair that appears just above this man; a man with short, curly hair and a beard who faces right and leans his head forward into his raised left hand in a gesture of grief; and a partly nude man who faces forward and to the right, and who points at Simeon with his left hand across his body. The scene takes place in a lavishly decorated room. The floor is divided into two levels and is covered with ornate flooring of paint, tile, or carpet. The single step up creates a platform, which holds the chair on which one of the brothers (probably Joseph) leans. Additional steps may appear in the background, below and to the right of Simeon. The wall may be constructed of wood or carved into stone. It features undefined vegetation in the upper left corner. Three fluted pillars rise against the back wall of the room, each with one snake coiled around it and arching vegetation-perhaps vines-between. Crosshatching represents scales on the two leftmost snakes, and the head of the snake is visible near the top of the center column. This snake's mouth appears to be open, and it may be preying on a frog or other animal above and to the left. The rightmost column and snake are less well defined. Three(?) smaller snakes appear amidst the vegetation. A lizard may crawl rightward along a leaf in the upper righthand corner of the design. The shading of the design's background obscures whether these are living animals and vegetation or decorations carved into the wooden or stone wall. The back wall of the design is shaded, but more defined shadows appear at back of the group of brothers, behind the feet of the older kneeling man at left, underneath Simeon's left leg and foot, and underneath Joseph's chair.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackles</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Simeon</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right, Simeon is being bound at the hands by another man, presumably one of Joseph's servants. Simeon kneels in a lunge facing the right edge of the design, his left leg forward and right leg extended behind him with his toes flexed. Both legs are bent at near-right angles, and are bare from the knees down. Simeon is covered from waist to knees by a cloth that wraps around his back and drapes over each knee, gathering on the floor between his legs. He is nude from the waist up, and his torso faces forward and right. Both arms bend slightly and extend downward and to the right. Simeon's palms face one another, and his fingers are spread as the servant clasps manacles around both wrists. Simeon twists at the shoulders and neck, turning his head to the left and looking at the brothers behind him. He has a short beard and long hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm lowered</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackles</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The man who binds Simeon stands to the right of him, facing the viewer and bending forward. He has short, curly hair and a beard; he wears a skirt or other garment that covers him from waist to knees. He stands with his left foot forward, just to the right of Simeon's. The servant's back foot, which extends behind him, can be seen between the two men's legs. He bends at the waist, lowering his left arm to secure the shackles around Simeon's wrists. His right arm bends at approximately ninety degrees, and he holds his forearm horizontally across his waist. The man's head is lowered and his eyes downcast, likely to look toward Simeon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Joseph</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the left of Simeon and his captor, on a raised platform, a male figure (presumably Joseph) sits sideways on a throne-like chair and leans against its back. He faces right and sits with his left knee forward, his left foot drawn back underneath him, and his right leg bent and extended back behind him in a position that mimics Simeon's. Joseph leans forward and extends his bent arms in front of him to rest his elbows on the chair's back. His hands are raised and clasped together in a prayerful posture, and he may bring his forehead forward to rest on them. Joseph stares upward and toward the right edge of the design. His mouth opens slightly, and his facial expression may suggest grief. Joseph wears a long-sleeved gown secured at the waist by a belt or sash. He has long, curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brothers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind Joseph, in the left half of the design, the other nine brothers kneel or stand. Most of them watch Simeon being bound.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knees bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the kneeling group is an older-looking man with short, curly hair and a beard, both white. He is nude from the waist up and covered from the waist down with a skirt or other draping cloth. His lower body faces toward the right as his knees rest on the ground and his flexed feet support him. He leans backward slightly as his torso twists away from the viewer, who sees him from behind. His arms are lowered on either side and bend to embrace the brothers on his left and right. The man's head turns to the right to watch Simeon; his mouth may be open slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the older man's left is a man with long, curly hair. He faces right and kneels with only his right foot visible beneath the hem of his long, sleeveless gown. His muscular right arm extends down and forward so that his hand rests on the right hip of the older man. His fingers extend forward. The man's shoulders hunch forward as he leans against the older man with his head and eyes down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the older man's right hand is another gowned man(?) with long, curly hair. He faces forward and appears to kneel with his legs spread, though only his left knee is visible from behind the older man's embrace. His arms bend upward to cross in front of his chest, and the fingers of his right hand curve downward as if touching his left shoulder. The man's head turns to the right as he gazes at Simeon with an open mouth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the three embracing figures are two more who also appear to kneel. One emerges at right of the group, just behind the figure with crossed arms. Only his bowed head and clasped hands are visible. His eyes are downcast or may be closed. He faces right and may be praying.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the three embracing figures are two more who may also be kneeling. At left and slightly above the embracing trio is another male figure with long, curly hair who appears to wear a gown. He faces right and leans forward as he looks ahead and up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Farthest left is a gowned man with long hair who faces right and leans his head on the shoulder of the man in front of him. He may look toward Simeon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Above the leftmost man appears a head of short, curly hair. The figure seems to be facing right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head in hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Third from left is a man with short, curly hair and a beard. He is covered by two draping cloths that cross in front of him. The man faces right and leans his head forward into his raised left hand in a gesture of grief. His eyes are downcast and he may look toward Simeon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing above these figures are four more brothers. Rightmost stands a partly nude man with long hair and a beard. He faces forward and to the right, crosses his arms in front of his chest, and points at Simeon with his left hand across his body. His head turns toward the right as he looks at Simeon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>paint</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vegetation</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a lavishly decorated room. The floor is divided into two levels and is covered with a ornate flooring of paint, tile, or carpet. The design features geometric shapes in a variety of colors. The single step up creates a platform, which holds the chair on which one of the brothers (probably Joseph) leans. Additional steps may appear in the background, below and to the right of Simeon. The wall may be constructed of wood or carved into stone. Three fluted pillars rise against the back wall of the room, each with one snake coiled around it. Between these columns rise arching designs, perhaps also made of leaves or other vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaves</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vines</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crossing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Indeterminate vegetation appears between the background columns and in the upper left corner of the back wall. At upper left there may be broad leaves intersecting to form a cross-hatched pattern. Between the columns, similar leaves rise alongside narrower vegetation-perhaps vines-and arch upward between the columns. There may be two bulbs near the center of the design, between the first and second columns from left. The shading of the design's background obscures whether these are actual leaves and vines or decorations carved into the wooden or stone wall.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coiled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>preying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frog</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lizard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crawling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three fluted pillars rise against the back wall of the room, each with one large snake coiled around it. Crosshatching represents scales on the two leftmost snakes, and the head of the center snake is visible near the top of its column. This snake's mouth appears to be open, and it may be preying on a frog or other animal above and to the left. The rightmost column and snake are less well defined. Three(?) smaller snakes appear amidst the vegetation. A lizard or snake may crawl rightward along a leaf in the upper righthand corner of the design. The shading of the design's background obscures whether these are living animals or decorations carved into the wooden or stone wall.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The center figure (probably Joseph) sits sideways on a chair, sofa, or throne and leans against its back. Only the right half of the chair is visible. The leg, side, and back of the chair appear to be made of wood, and some decorative carving appears at the right edge, underneath Joseph's elbow. A thick cushion covered in cloth or leather forms the seat, and a draping cloth covers part of the chair's back.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The back wall of the design is shaded, but more defined shadows appear at back of the group of brothers, behind the feet of the older kneeling man at left, underneath Simeon's left leg and foot, and underneath Joseph's chair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>