<bad id="but142.1" type="mono" work="Pastoral Scene" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="142">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Pastoral Scene">
                    <main>
                        Pastoral Scene</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Dani Garcia, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>February 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                     <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                     <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                     <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                     <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                     <name>Kirk V. Hastings</name>
                    and <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                     <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                     <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                     <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                     <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Pastoral Scene
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.R">c. 1780-85<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>34.2 x 41.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>34.2 x 41.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>Inscribed in pencil, "18," bottom center.  This inscription is not by Blake.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1937</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 165, with three other works by Blake (13s. to the dealer H. Palser), or in lot 167, with three other works by Blake (11s. to the dealer H. Palser); Alfred Aspland by no later than 1876; sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 27 Jan. 1885, lot 104 (14s. to the dealer Ogden of Oxford); Rhoda (Mrs. Arthur) Symons; bequeathed by her to the British Museum in Feb. 1937.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1937,0213.4</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but142.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT142.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Pastoral Scene</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 142)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>34.2 x 41.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>With its outdoor setting and close grouping of eight human figures and at least four animals, this drawing depicts a pastoral scene. In the lower left-hand corner, a woman kneels to milk a cow. She is nude from the waist up and covered by a long skirt from the waist down. Her long hair is gathered into a bun. The woman faces right, kneeling with both knees on the ground and her legs bent sharply so that she sits on the heels of her bare feet. Her shoulders hunch as she bends forward, lowering her head and eyes to watch her work. The woman's arms bend upward together, and her hands reach forward to hold the cow's udders. A large bucket appears below the woman's hands. The material of this bucket is unclear, but the smooth surface suggests that it is metal. Above and behind the woman, the head of a sheep is visible facing left. Wavy lines may suggest additional sheep standing behind this animal in the background. At right of the woman stands the cow, which faces forward and to the right. Only its front legs are visible; its back rises well above the woman's head. Near the cow's left shoulder some curved lines indicate rough or curly hair. Similarly, curly hair tops the cows head, from which two pointed horns extend above outward-pointing ears. The cow's head is lowered and cocked slightly to the left as its down turned muzzle meets that of the dog below. The dog lies on the ground and appears to roll onto its right side. Its tail extends along the ground to the left, coming underneath the milking woman's knees. Lines on the dog's body suggest long hair. Its head lifts upward and the dog points its nose directly upward to touch the cow's muzzle. The dog's ears point downward along its neck. Immediately to the right of the dog, a ram lies on the ground facing left. Its nose rests against the dog's back, and its visible left eye is closed as if in sleep. A large, curled horn sits just behind the ram's eye. Curved lines indicate thick, curly wool all over its body; the wool appears to cover the ram's legs as they fold underneath. Atop the ram sleeps a boy with short, curly hair. His bare shoulders suggest that he is at least partly nude. The boy faces forward and leans to the right, draping his upper body over the ram. His right arm bends upward as his hand supports his head, which is held horizontally with the crown facing right. His left arm extends behind his head, along the top of the ram, and then bends at ninety degrees so that his hand dangles; his fingers may touch the ground. The boy's eyes and mouth are closed. Above the sleeping boy sit three female figures, one of whom holds a small child. Leftmost and farthest from the viewer is a gowned woman with long hair who faces left and appears to be writing. Her right arm bends and extends forward; her right hand holds a reed or other writing implement. Her left arm may rest in her lap, and her head tilts downward toward her work. The woman in the center of the group holds a child in her lap. She wears a gown, and her hair appears to be pulled back from her face. The woman faces forward and to the left, wrapping her right arm around the child's neck and shoulders, and her left around its buttocks. She appears to kiss the child's face; she may be its mother. The babe-in-arms appears to be a nude child with short, curly hair. He(?) faces away and to the right, sitting in his mother's lap with his knees bent and his legs tucked underneath him. The soles of his feet face outward and upward. The child wraps his arms around his mother's neck and lifts his head to receive (and perhaps to return) her kiss. The woman sitting rightmost--nearest the viewer--holds a spindle, distaff, or some other object and looks at the other women. Her body faces forward and to the left, and her long gown drapes in folds over her lap. This gown may be decorated by a round collar, or the woman may wear a necklace with a bead or pendant in the center. Her long hair is gathered into a bun. The woman's bare right arm bends upward to grasp the spindle or distaff with her palm facing toward her. The spindle or distaff is held at an angle away from the woman. The woman's left arm may dangle at her side, her hand approaching the head of the sleeping boy. Her head appears in profile as she faces left and looks downward. At right of the three seated women stand two old men wearing long-sleeved gowns. Each has curly hair and a long beard. The man at left faces forward and slightly to the right, toward his companion. His eyes are closed, and his arm is lowered in front of his body, holding a set of graduated pipes. He may be a musician. The man at right faces forward and to the left. His left leg bends forward slightly, suggesting that he may be walking to the left; his bare left foot appears, also pointing left, beneath the hem of his gown. The man's lowered left arm bends as he holds a shepherd's crook across his body, from his right foot to his left shoulder. His right arm bends upward as he brings his hand to his chin, perhaps in a contemplative posture or to cover his mouth. The man bends forward slightly, and his head tilts downward as he looks out in front of him. He may be a shepherd. The ground beneath these figures and animals appears to be bare; in the upper half of the drawing, the background is filled with indeterminate vegetation--perhaps bushes and deciduous trees--and large panels of cloth that indicate a tent. Shadows appear beneath each of the figures kneeling or lying on the ground, in the lap of the rightmost woman, and beneath the shepherd's feet. </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>milking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>milkmaid</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left-hand corner, a woman kneels to milk a cow. She is nude from the waist up and covered by a long skirt from the waist down. Her long hair is gathered into a bun. The woman faces right, kneeling with both knees on the ground and her legs bent sharply so that she sits on the heels of her bare feet. Her shoulders hunch as she bends forward, lowering her head and eyes to watch her work. The woman's arms bend upward together, and her hands reach forward to hold the cow's udders. A large bucket appears below the woman's hands. The material of this bucket is unclear, but the smooth surface suggests that it is metal.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and behind the leftmost woman, the head of a sheep is visible facing left. Wavy lines may suggest additional sheep standing behind this animal in the background.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>cow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horns</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the milking woman stands a cow, which faces forward and to the right. Only its front legs are visible; its back rises well above the woman's head. Near the cow's left shoulder some curved lines indicate rough or curly hair. Similarly, curly hair tops the cows head, from which two pointed horns extend above outward-pointing ears. The cow's head is lowered and cocked slightly to the left as its down turned muzzle meets that of the dog below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>dog</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying on side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the cow, a dog lies on the ground and appears to roll onto its right side. Its tail extends along the ground to the left, coming underneath the milking woman's knees. Lines on the dog's body suggest long hair. Its head lifts upward, pointing its nose directly upward to touch the cow's muzzle. The dog's ears point downward along its neck.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately to the right of the dog, a ram lies on the ground facing left. Its nose rests against the dog's back, and its visible left eye is closed as if in sleep. A large, curled horn sits just behind the ram's eye. Curved lines indicate thick, curly wool all over its body; the ram's wool appears to cover its legs as they fold underneath.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Atop the ram sleeps a boy with short, curly hair. His bare shoulders suggest that he is at least partly nude. The boy faces forward and leans to the right, draping his upper body over the ram. His right arm bends upward as his hand supports his head, which is held horizontally with the crown facing right. His left arm extends behind his head, along the top of the ram, and then bends at ninety degrees so that his hand dangles; his fingers may touch the ground. The boy's eyes and mouth are closed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping boy sit three female figures. Leftmost and farthest from the viewer is a gowned woman with long hair who faces left and appears to be writing. Her right arm bends and extends forward; her right hand holds a reed or other writing implement. Her left arm may rest in her lap, and her head tilts downward toward her work.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around neck</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around waist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping boy sit three female figures. The woman in the center of the group holds a child in her lap. She wears a gown, and her hair appears to be pulled back from her face. The woman faces forward and to the left, wrapping her right arm around the child's neck and shoulders, and her left around his(?) waist and buttocks. She appears to kiss the child's face; she may be his mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping boy sit three female figures, one of whom holds a nude child who may be male(?) with short, curly hair. The child faces away and to the right, sitting in his mother's lap with his knees bent and his legs tucked underneath him. The soles of his feet face outward and upward. The child wraps his arms around his mother's neck and lifts his head to receive (and perhaps to return) her kiss.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>necklace</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spindle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>distaff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping boy sit three female figures. The woman sitting rightmost--nearest the viewer--holds a spindle, distaff, or some other object and looks at the other women. Her body faces forward and to the left, and her long gown drapes in folds over her lap. This gown may be decorated by a round collar, or the woman may wear a necklace with a bead or pendant in the center. Her long hair is gathered into a bun. The woman's bare right arm bends upward to grasp the handle of the spindle or distaff with her palm facing toward her; the thin handle is held at an angle away from the woman. The woman's left arm may dangle at her side, her hand approaching the head of the sleeping boy. Her head appears in profile as she faces left and looks downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                    	<characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>piper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the three seated women stand two old men wearing long-sleeved gowns. Each has curly hair and a long beard. The man at left faces forward and slightly to the right, toward his companion. His eyes are closed, and his arm dangles in front of his body, holding a set of graduated pipes. He may be a musician.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of the three seated women stand two old men wearing long-sleeved gowns. Each has curly hair and a long beard. The man at right faces forward and to the left. His left leg bends forward slightly, suggesting that he may be walking to the left; his bare left foot appears, also pointing left, beneath the hem of his gown. The man's lowered left arm bends as he holds a shepherd's crook across his body, from his right foot to his left shoulder. His right arm bends upward as he brings his hand to his chin, perhaps in a contemplative posture or to cover his mouth. The man bends forward slightly, and his head tilts downward as he looks out in front of him. He may be a shepherd.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper half of the drawing, the background is filled with indeterminate vegetation--perhaps bushes and deciduous trees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>tent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the drawing's background, large panels of cloth indicate the presence of a tent or other structure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                        <component type="object" location="CD">
                            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>Shadows appear beneath each of the figures kneeling or lying on the ground, in the lap of the rightmost woman, and beneath the shepherd's feet.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
