<bad id="but223v.1" type="penc" work="A Group of Figures Round a Table and a Seated Old Man"
    copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="223v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Group of Figures Round a Table and a Seated Old Man">
                    <main>A Group of Figures Round a Table and a Seated Old Man</main> : electronic
                    edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2018 British Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>October 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *A Group of Figures Round a Table and a Seated Old Man* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780<note>The date, based on stylistic considerations, is
                        far from certain.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.1 x 26.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>23.0 x 33.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The pencil letters lower right, "J D F," are the initials of
                        John Deffett Francis, the first recorded owner of the drawing. This
                        inscription may have been written by Francis.</note></medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The pencil letters lower right, "J D F," are the initials
                        of John Deffett Francis, the first recorded owner of the drawing. This
                        inscription may have been written by Francis. The British Museum collection
                        stamp appears upper right.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis and
                    given by him to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings:
                    prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.144</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but223v.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT223.1.1v.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Group of Figures Round a Table and a Seated Old
                    Man</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 223 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The recto of this leaf is a pencil drawing datable to c. 1793, *A Figure
                        Bending Over a Corpse in the Rain, with further Bodies Behind, Possibly for
                        the Title-Page of "America"*. The pencil letters lower right, "J D F," are
                        the initials of John Deffett Francis, the first recorded owner of the
                        drawing. This inscription may have been written by Francis. The British
                        Museum collection stamp appears upper right.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>23.0 x 33.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Two vertical lines in the center of the drawing divide the
                        compositional space into two seemingly unrelated halves. At right, a bearded
                        and gowned man with long hair sits in a chair facing forward. His bent left
                        arm rests on the arm of the chair (obscured by his drapery), and he points
                        down with the index finger of his left hand. His right arm is extended and
                        his right hand rests on his left knee; the index finger of his right hand is
                        extended down and to the right. Both legs are bent and spread. An object
                        whose significance is indeterminate is visible below his right foot. In the
                        scene at left, four figures sit and stand around a table. The rightmost
                        figure is an adult woman with long curly hair wearing a gown and veil who
                        sits in a chair. Facing forward, she bends her left arm upward to hold a
                        distaff and her right arm is bent and raised across her torso; she holds the
                        material she is spinning with both hands. The spindle(?) to which the
                        material is still attached rests on the table in front of her. Beside the
                        female figure at left, a smaller male figure, perhaps a child or adolescent
                        depicted from the waist up, is visible. He has short curly hair and wears a
                        long-sleeved shirt. Both of his arms rest on the table, and he appears to
                        rest his head on his raised right hand. A second smaller male figure stands
                        in the foreground, across the table from his companions, facing right. He
                        has short curly hair and wears a shirt with tights or breeches. His bent
                        left arm rests on the table and his right is at his side, slightly bent. He
                        stands in contrapposto with left leg extended backward, heel raised. Visible
                        from the shoulders up, the leftmost figure of the group is an adult male
                        figure with a beard. He faces right and wears a hat with a ribbon. This
                        group may be a family with a father, mother, and two male children. The
                        table around which they sit is round with one visible serpentine leg. Two
                        tall arched openings that may be doors or windows are visible in the right
                        side of the wall behind the group at left. Framing lines extend around three
                        sides of the composition and include the seated figure far
                        right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right, a bearded and gowned man with long curly hair sits
                            in a chair facing forward. His bent left arm rests on the arm of the
                            chair (which is obscured by his drapery). He points down with the index
                            finger of his left hand. His right arm is extended, and his right hand
                            rests on his left knee; the index finger of his right hand is extended
                            down and to the right. Both legs are bent and spread. He may wear tights
                            or breeches as well as shoes. An object whose significance is
                            indeterminate is visible below his right foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The chair on which the figure at far right sits is almost
                            entirely covered by his drapery; however, two straight legs are
                            partially visible at right. Horizontal lines below the figure indicate a
                            floor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of four figures&#8212;an adult male, an adult female,
                            and two male children or adolescents&#8212;sit around a table in the
                            scene at left. They may represent a family.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spinning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four figures sit and stand around a table in the scene at
                            left. The rightmost figure is an adult woman with long curly hair
                            wearing a gown and veil who sits in a chair. Facing forward with head
                            turned slightly left, she bends her left arm upward to hold a distaff
                            and her right arm is bent and raised across her torso; she holds the
                            material she is spinning with both hands. Her right leg is crossed over
                            her left with the heel of her right foot raised almost vertically off
                            the ground. If this group represents a family, she is likely the
                            mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>distaff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>thread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spindle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure at left holds a distaff in her left hand.
                            With both hands, she spins thread, which is attached to the spindle(?)
                            visible on the table in front of her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure at left sits in a chair. One of the chair
                            legs is visible front right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four figures sit or stand around a table in the scene at left.
                            The second figure from the right in this group is a smaller male figure,
                            perhaps a child or adolescent, depicted from the waist up. He has short
                            curly hair and wears a long-sleeved shirt. Both of his arms rest on the
                            table, left crossed over right, and he appears to rest his head on his
                            raised right hand. His eyes are raised.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four figures sit or stand around a table in the scene at left.
                            A male figure, who may be a child or adolescent, stands in the
                            foreground, across the table from his companions, facing right with head
                            turned down. He has short curly hair and wears a shirt with tights or
                            breeches. His bent left arm rests on the table and his right is at his
                            side, slightly bent. He stands in contrapposto (or perhaps leans on the
                            table) with left leg extended backward, heel raised.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four figures sit or stand around a table in the scene at left.
                            Visible from the shoulders up, the leftmost figure of the group is an
                            adult male figure with a beard. He faces right and wears a hat with a
                            ribbon. If this group represents a family, he is likely the
                            father.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The table around which the four figures sit in the scene at
                            left is round with one visible, rather serpentine leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two tall arched openings are visible in the right side of the
                            wall behind the group at left. These may be doors or
                            windows.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frame</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Framing lines extend around three sides of the composition and
                            include the seated figure far right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
