<bad id="but219.1" type="penc"
    work="A Standing and a Recumbent Figure, Both with Attendant Genii, Possibly for 'The Book of Thel'"
    copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="219" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title
                    reg="A Standing and a Recumbent Figure, Both with Attendant Genii, Possibly for 'The Book of Thel'">
                    <main>A Standing and a Recumbent Figure, Both with Attendant Genii, Possibly for
                        "The Book of Thel"</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work copyright © 2018 British Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>October 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>A Standing and a Recumbent Figure, Both with Attendant Genii, Possibly
                        for "The Book of Thel"</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1789">c. 1789<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations
                        and the possible association of this drawing with Blake's *The Book of
                        Thel*, dated 1789 on its title page.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>21.0 x 27.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>21.0 x 27.7 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The pencil letters lower right, "J D F," are the initials of
                        John Deffett Francis, the first recorded owner of the drawing. This
                        inscription may have been written by Francis.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The pencil letters lower right, "J D F," are the initials
                        of John Deffett Francis, the first recorded owner of the drawing. This
                        inscription may have been written by Francis.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis and
                    given by him to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings:
                    prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.133</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but219.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT219.1.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Standing and a Recumbent Figure, Both with Attendant
                    Genii, Possibly for "The Book of Thel"</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 219)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This drawing may be a rejected design for Blake's illuminated book, *The Book
                        of Thel*. The closest association with any of the published designs is with
                        the headpiece to plate 6. If that is indeed the case, then the standing
                        figure on the right might be Thel and the figure floating to the left might
                        be the Cloud. It is difficult to identify the supine figure, the two smaller
                        figures near her head, and the figure holding the hips of the standing
                        figure with any of the other characters in the poem. For another drawing
                        related to plate 6 of *The Book of Thel*, see *Sketch for "The Book of
                        Thel," Plate 6*, Butlin 218 verso.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>21.0 x 27.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Surrounded by vertical lines that suggest trees, a gowned female
                        figure stands on the right side of the composition while a second figure
                        lies on the ground at left. Each is accompanied by two smaller figures, one
                        holding the standing figure's waist and another hovering hear her extended
                        right arm. The pair of smaller figures at lower left are winged. A tree
                        stands far right; other vertical lines may be more tree trunks. This drawing
                        may be a rejected design for Blake's illuminated, *The Book of Thel*. The
                        closest association with any of the published designs is with the headpiece
                        to plate 6. If that is indeed the case, then the standing figure on the
                        right might be Thel and the figure floating to the left might be the Cloud.
                        It is difficult to identify the supine figure, the two smaller figures near
                        her head, and the figure holding the standing figure's hips with any of the
                        other characters in the poem.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Thel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned female figure stands on the right side of the
                            composition facing forward. She has long, curly hair that appears
                            somewhat flame-like and stands on end in a rightward direction. Her head
                            is turned slightly down and to the left. She frowns noticeably and her
                            eyes may be closed. Her left arm is at her side, her right raised
                            horizontally. Two smaller figures accompany the female figure: one wraps
                            its arms around her hips while the second hovers near her extended right
                            arm, perhaps in an attempt to lead her. This standing figure may be
                            touching the hovering figure to the left and possibly the leg of the
                            figure enbracing her hips. If indeed this drawing is associated with
                            Blake's illuminated book, *The Book of Thel*, this standing figure may
                            be Thel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A figure, likely a nude female due to the suggestion of
                            breasts, lies supine with head at left in the lower left corner of the
                            design. Her legs are extended and together; her right arm is bent but at
                            her side while her left is extended horizontally away from her body at a
                            45 degree angle. Her head is bent back and appears to be supported by
                            two smaller figures, both winged, on either side of her head. She may be
                            dead or dying.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>One of two smaller figures at right, a nude(?) figure facing
                            away from the viewer wraps its arms around the hips of the standing
                            female figure and extends both legs together (with knees bent?)
                            horizontally to the right. The standing figure may touch or hold this
                            figure's legs with her left hand. The smaller figure may turn its head
                            up to look at the woman it embraces. This figure, perhaps a spirit of
                            some sort, appears to hover in the air.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A small figure flies(?) or hovers in a horizontal position
                            with head at left while touching or holding(?) the standing female
                            figure's extended right arm. This figure may be nude and appears to face
                            forward, though the direction of the head is unclear. It extends one arm
                            horizontally to the left and points downward toward the other figural
                            group, lower left. Its other arm may be bent. Both legs may be extended
                            and possibly bent at the knee. If indeed this drawing is associated with
                            Blake's illuminated book, *The Book of Thel*, this hovering figure may
                            be the Cloud.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two smaller winged figures, perhaps spirits of putti,
                            accompany the supine figure in the lower left corner of the composition.
                            On the right side of the larger figure's head, the first of the smaller
                            figures sits (perhaps in a squat or crouch?) facing left but turns to
                            look forward. It bends forward and extends its bent left arm to touch or
                            hold the head of the large figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two smaller winged figures, perhaps spirits or putti,
                            accompany the supine figure in the lower left corner of the composition.
                            The figure furthest left faces away from the viewer and bends forward
                            with extended right arm to touch or hold the head of the female figure.
                            Its right leg appears bent forward at the knee and its left extended
                            backward; the figure may fly or hover just above the
                            ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branches</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several vertical lines across the width of the composition
                            suggest the trunks and branches of trees. The tree far right is by far
                            the largest.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>

        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
