<bad id="but246.1" type="wc" work="Oberon and Titania, Preceded by Puck" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="folger" catalog="butlin" catid="246">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Oberon and Titania, Preceded by Puck">
                    <main>Oberon and Titania, Preceded by Puck</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of Blake’s water color illustrations to the plays of William Shakespeare. 
                 <lb/>
                <lb/>     
Although less extensive and well known than his illustrations of John Milton’s poems, Blake’s water colors based on Shakespeare’s plays constitute a significant group of designs. The earliest, dating from c. 1779, is probably one of Blake’s illustrations of English history but nonetheless evokes Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi>. The series of seven small ovals picturing characters from the plays also dates from Blake’s early years. The concentrated focus on just one or two figures filling most of the pictorial space may be Blake’s response to popular interest in miniature portraiture. The reason for his execution of this group is not known; like the English history designs, they may have been intended for eventual publication as engravings.  The series of Shakespeare character portraits by John Hamilton Mortimer, published as engravings in the mid-1770s, may have influenced Blake’s similar project.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
<hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> is one of Blake’s largest water colors of the 1780s. Its size and quality suggest that it may have been intended for exhibition, like the water colors illustrating the life of Joseph displayed at the Royal Academy in 1785. The circle of dancers and Puck’s stance with arms raised echo similar motifs in George Romney’s <hi rend="i">Leveson-Gower Family</hi>, painted in 1776-77 and published as a mezzotint by John Raphael Smith in 1781.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Blake was clearly attracted to the vision of Queen Katherine in <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, act 4, scene 2, for he executed four versions beginning c. 1783-90 and concluding with the highly finished and complex water color of c. 1825-26. Blake’s water color of Queen Katherine’s dream dated 1809 is part of a series of six illustrations to Shakespeare’s plays commissioned by Joseph Thomas, the clergyman who had earlier employed Blake to illustrate Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. In a letter of 31 July 1801 to William Hayley, John Flaxman added a postscript to Blake, including the following: “he [Thomas] also desired you [Blake] will make two designs in bister or Indian Ink, from Shakespeare’s Troylus &amp Cressida, Coriolanus, either of the 3 plays of Henry 6.<sup>th</sup> Richard the 3.<sup>d</sup> or Henry the 8.<sup>th</sup> each design for one play for which he will give a Guinea each, the dimensions as follow the paper. an upright square of 12 Inches &amp half by 8 Inches, within this Space leaving a moderate margin, the principal figure not exceeding 6 Inches high” (Butlin 547). Blake’s designs (most now trimmed) roughly follow these size requirements, necessitated by Thomas’s desire to create an extra-illustrated copy of the 1632 second folio of Shakespeare’s plays, but Blake waited eight years before completing the commission, changed the medium from monochrome drawings to water colors, and illustrated only two plays, <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi> and <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, specified by Flaxman. Blake may have chosen the other passages for illustration, at some point convincing Thomas of their appropriateness.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Many of Blake’s Shakespeare designs show his predilection for scenes dealing with perceptions that extend beyond the world of the physical senses. The four versions of Queen Katherine’s dream epitomize this lifelong interest in imaginative and visionary experiences. A corollary is Blake’s attraction to representations of the arts, demonstrated by <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> and his portrayal of Pegasus, the classical embodiment of poetic inspiration, in <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi> among the designs for Thomas.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, editors <lb/>
                Joseph Fletcher, managing editor, Michael Fox, assistant editor<lb/>
                 The William Blake Archive<lb/>     
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 Folger Shakespeare Library </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
             <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February - March 2020</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies,</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Dan Gorman</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose</name>
                    <name>Jake Ruta</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>     
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued, BAD created</change>
                <date>March 2016</date>
               <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Laura Bell</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Rachel Lee,</name>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Adam Engel,</name>
<name>Andrea Everett,</name>
<name>Grant Glass,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Eric Loy,</name>
<name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
<name>Adam McCune,</name>
<name>Scott Robinson,</name>
<name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
<name>Miles Simon,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
<name>Alia Wegner,</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Oberon and Titania, Preceded by Puck* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1790.A">c. 1790-93<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>oval, 16.4 x 20.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>oval, 16.4 x 20.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>water color and pen and ink over pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Folger Shakespeare Library</name>
                <date>1932</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Possibly the work acquired at an unknown time by Samuel Prince and sold from
                    his collection, Sotheby's, 11 Dec. 1865, lot 277, titled "Oberon" (&#163;1.3s.
                    to "Willis," probably a dealer); G. E. Taylor by 1877; Brenda G. Warr, sold from
                    her collection Sotheby's, 17 Dec. 1928, lot 137 (&#163;65 to the dealer Gabriel
                    Wells acting for Henry Clay Folger and his wife Emily Jordan Folger); given to
                    the Folger Shakespeare Library upon its founding in 1932.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Folger Shakespeare Library</institution>
                <addressline>201 East Capitol Street, SE</addressline>
                <addressline>Washington, DC 20003</addressline>
                <addressline>USA</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-202-544-4600</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: www.folger.edu</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: info@folger.edu</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Librarian: eblake@folger.edu</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Photography: 1-202-675-0335</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Photography: photo@folger.edu</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Library Catalogue: www.hamnet.folger.edu</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">ART Box B636 no. 2 (size S)</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but246.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT246.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Oberon and Titania, Preceded by Puck</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 246.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>16.4 x 20.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Five figures fly or hover against a starry sky in this
                        illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night's
                            Dream</hi>. The rightmost figure flies right but turns to face forward
                        with both arms bent and raised, with palms facing forward and fingers
                        spread. The figure is male with short, perhaps curly hair and an open mouth.
                        He may be speaking and leading the other figures to the right. He wears a
                        shirt, breeches, and a red cape or cloak; a sword is visible against his
                        left hip. Both legs are bent slightly with his right leg extended backward
                        at left. He is likely Puck, the sprite assistant to Oberon, King of the
                        Fairies. In the center of the composition, a pair of figures fly to the
                        right or hover. They are likely Oberon and Titania, the king and queen of
                        the Fairies in the play. Titania, the female figure at right, has long hair
                        and wears a gown. Although she faces right, she turns forward perhaps to
                        look toward her companion. Her left arm is straight and by her side. Her
                        legs are together and extended horizontally at left. To her left, a male
                        figure, likely Oberon, faces right. He has long hair and a beard and wears a
                        crown, long gown, and red cape or cloak. With his right arm, which is bent
                        and at his side, he holds a scepter. His left arm may be bent by his side,
                        perhaps under his cape; he may hold an orb(?) with this hand in front of his
                        lower torso. Both legs are together and extended to the left. To the left of
                        this pair, two small gowned female figures, probably fairies, also fly right
                        and hold the trains of the king and queen's gowns with raised, bent arms.
                        The figure at right has long hair and may wear a garland on her head. She
                        turns her head to look left, likely toward her companion, who also has long
                        hair and wears a headband or garland on her head. Both figures extend their
                        legs to the left. Below the five figures, there appears to be an area of
                        dark ground or earth, and behind them, dark sky with stars, suggesting the
                        time is night, perhaps at the conclusion of the play when Oberon and Titania
                        lead the Fairies away and Puck concludes: "So good night unto you all./ Give
                        me your hands, if we be friends,/ And Robin shall restore amends." (Act 5,
                        Scene 1, 453-455).</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Puck</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Robin Goodfellow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures fly or hover against a starry sky in this
                            illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night's
                                Dream</hi>. Leading the procession, the rightmost figure flies right
                            but turns to face forward with both arms bent and raised, with palms
                            facing forward and fingers spread. The figure is male with short,
                            perhaps curly hair and an open mouth. He may be speaking and leading the
                            other figures to the right. He wears a shirt, breeches, and a red cape
                            or cloak; a sword is visible against his left hip. Both legs are bent
                            slightly with his right leg extended backward at left. He is likely
                            Puck, also called Robin Goodfellow, the sprite assistant to Oberon, king
                            of the Fairies.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure in the scene, likely Puck, wears a
                            downward-pointing sword against his left hip.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Titania</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures fly or hover against a starry sky in this
                            illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night's
                                Dream</hi>. In the center of the composition, a pair of figures fly
                            to the right or hover. They are likely Oberon and Titania, the king and
                            queen of the Fairies in the play. Titania, the female figure at right,
                            has long hair and wears a gown with a belt. She may wear a blue cloak,
                            as evinced by the blue cloth held by the small figure to the left and a
                            slender arc of blue below and to the right of Titania's left hip.
                            Although she faces right, she turns forward, perhaps even slightly left
                            to look toward her companion. Her left arm is straight and by her side.
                            Her legs are together and extended horizontally at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Oberon</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures fly or hover against a starry sky in this
                            illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night's
                                Dream</hi>. In the center of the composition, a pair of figures fly
                            to the right or hover. They are likely Oberon and Titania, the king and
                            queen of the Fairies in the play. At left, Oberon faces right. He has
                            long hair and a beard and wears a crown, long gown, and red cape or
                            cloak. With his right arm, which is bent and at his side, he holds a
                            scepter. His left arm may be bent by his side, perhaps under his cape or
                            cloak; he may hold an orb(?) with this hand in front of his lower torso.
                            Both legs are together and extended to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>orb</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The central male figure in this scene, Oberon, holds a scepter
                            in his right hand and may hold an orb(?) in his left hand, held near his
                            lower torso. These, along with his crown, likely attest to his status as
                            king of the Fairies.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>garland</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the left side of the design, two small gowned female
                            figures, probably fairies, fly right and hold the trains of the king and
                            queen's gowns with raised, bent arms. Their bodies are almost
                            horizontal. The figure at right has long hair and may wear a garland on
                            her head. She turns her head to look left, likely toward her companion.
                            Both figures extend their legs to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>garland</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fairy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the left side of the design, two small gowned female
                            figures, probably fairies, fly right and hold the trains of the king and
                            queen's gowns with raised, bent arms. Their bodies are almost
                            horizontal. The figure at left has long hair and wears a headband or
                            garland. She appears to look toward her companion. Both figures extend
                            their legs to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There appears to be an area of dark ground or earth along the
                            bottom edge of the design above which the five figures fly or
                            hover.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the five flying figures, there is dark sky with stars,
                            suggesting the time is night, perhaps at the conclusion of the play when
                            Oberon and Titania lead the Fairies away and Puck concludes: "So good
                            night unto you all./ Give me your hands, if we be friends,/ And Robin
                            shall restore amends." (Act 5, Scene 1, 453-455).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
