<bad id="but244.1" type="mono" work="Drawings for Wollstonecraft's Original Stories" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="lc" catalog="butlin" catid="244"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Drawings for Mary Wollstonecraft's &#34;Original Stories from Real Life&#34;"><main>Drawings for Mary Wollstonecraft's "Original Stories from Real Life"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
            </principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester
            
            </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 104KB; 20 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 65KB to 305KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives <date>August 2009</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an 
            electronic edition of Blake's ten monochrome wash drawings illustrating 
            Mary Wollstonecraft's <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi> and the first and 
            second editions of the book containing Blake's six engravings of his 
            designs. &#160;The designs and inscribed texts in all three series are fully 
            searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.
            <lb/><lb/>
            In 1788, Joseph Johnson published the first edition of Mary 
            Wollstonecraft's morally instructive narrative for children, <hi rend="i">Original 
               Stories from Real Life; with Conversations, Calculated to Regulate the 
               Affections, and Form the Mind to Truth and Goodness</hi>. &#160;A few years later, 
            Johnson decided to issue a new edition, for which he commissioned Blake to 
            prepare a series of illustrations. &#160;Blake's extant drawings, now in the 
            Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress, are datable to c. 1791. &#160;In 
            addition to these ten designs, Blake must have executed at least one 
            further drawing as a preliminary for his fifth plate; this drawing is 
            untraced. &#160;Six designs were selected for publication in the 1791 edition 
            of Wollstonecraft's book; Blake engraved the designs himself. &#160;The first 
            and second states of Blake's plates appear variously in copies of the 1791 
            edition.  The second edition to contain Blake's plates was published by 
            Johnson in 1796; it contains the third (final) states of Blake's plates. 
            The copy of the 1791 edition now in the Archive is from the Huntington 
            Library; it contains the second states of the plates.  The copy of the 
            1796 edition in the Archive is from the Essick collection and contains the 
            third (final) states of the plates.
            <lb/><lb/>
            Modern interpreters of the illustrations have detected a pictorial 
            critique of Wollstonecraft's stories. &#160;Blake appears to have found her 
            morality too calculating, rationalistic, and rigid. &#160;He represents 
            Wollstonecraft's spokesperson, Mrs. Mason, as a domineering presence. 
            &#160;From Blake's perspective, Mason's acts of charity are excessively 
            condescending and tend to reinforce the underlying social conditions that 
            create disparities between wealth and poverty. &#160;As Blake wrote in "The 
            Human Abstract," "Pity would be no more, / If we did not make somebody 
            Poor."
            <lb/><lb/>
            With this publication, the Archive adds a new set of scholarly tools. 
            These tools, known collectively as our Related Works system, are designed 
            to show relationships among works and individual objects in the Archive. 
            They function at two levels.  First, work index pages now include active 
            links to related materials in the Archive (for example, a set of 
            preliminary sketches for a group of engravings).  Second, the Show Me menu 
            on object view pages now includes Related Works in the Archive.  Like the work-level menu, this list includes active 
            links to the related objects and is meant to allow study of the related 
            materials side-by-side.  The Wollstonecraft illustrations are the first 
            publication in the Archive to use this feature.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access 
            restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible 
            by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the cooperation of 
            the international array of libraries and museums that have generously 
            given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the 
            Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2009</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This image copyright © 2009 William Blake Archive.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Publication prep</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD modified to include new Related Works protocols</change><date>April 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Natalie Moix,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Lily Todorinova,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation and illustration description</change><date>March 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
   <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Andrea Everett</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Natalie Moix,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Lily Todorinova,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>and Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image scanning and metadata cataloguing</change><date>May 1999</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
            <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
            <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

            <resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Jessica Kem,</name><name>Andrea Laue</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Drawings for Mary Wollstonecraft's "Original Stories from Real Life"</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake
               <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1791">c. 1791</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>10</numberobj><objorder>1-10</objorder><objsize>ranging between 10.8 x 6.0 cm. and 14.0 x 6.8 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>10</numberleaves><leafsize>ranging between 11.7 x 6.2 cm. and 14.2 x 6.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink with gray and black washes<note>Blake's inscriptions below the designs on Objects 1-3 and 5 are in pencil.</note></medium><support>laid paper</support><watermark>none visible<note>The drawings are hinged to backing mats and thus it is very difficult to check for watermarks.</note></watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress</name><date>1946</date><dealer>The Rosenbach Company (A. S. W. Rosenbach)</dealer><price>$1500</price><note>Possibly Joseph Johnson, who commissioned the drawings; acquired at an unknown time by Alexander Gilchrist; Mrs. Alexander Gilchrist, probably by inheritance in 1861; her son, Herbert H. Gilchrist, by gift or by inheritance no later than 1885; H. Buxton Forman, sold from his collection, Anderson Galleries auction, New York, 15 March 1920, lot 65, with five of the engravings and five letters by Herbert H. Gilchrist ($1000 to A. Edward Newton); sold from Newton's collection, Parke-Bernet auction, New York, 16 April 1941, lot 120, with the 5 engravings and 5 letters ($1500 to the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach acting for Lessing J. Rosenwald); given by Rosenwald to the Library of Congress in 1946.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Library of Congress</institution><addressline>101 Independence Avenue SE</addressline><addressline>Washington, DC 20540</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 202-707-3448</addressline><addressline>Fax: 202-707-4142</addressline><addressline>Email: rbref@loc.gov</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/</addressline><department>Rare Books and Special Collections</department><collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection><repositoryid label="Accession number">NC1115.B656</repositoryid><repositoryid label="Catalog number">1818</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but244.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT244.1.1.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Every Prospect Smiled</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 244.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing was not selected as one of the six to be engraved.  The pencil inscription below the design is in Blake's hand.</p></objnote><objsize>12.5 x 6.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An adult female (Mrs. Mason) stands on a path or road with two female children (Mary and Caroline) to her left and 
                  right.  They stand just outside a doorway to the right.  Mrs. Mason is gowned and wears a large hat.  She stands with her arms at her sides 
                  and looks towards the child to the 
                  right.  Her mouth appears to be slightly open and she may be speaking.  Both children have long hair, are gowned, and wear wide-brimmed 
                  hats.  The child to the left faces forward with her head turned to the right and up to look at Mrs. Mason.  The child's right arm is 
                  pictured at her side.  The child to the right is facing left in profile.  Her head is up and she also looks towards Mrs. Mason.  
                  The child's left arm is bent; she may be touching or holding Mrs. Mason's left arm in her left hand.  A large tree rises to the right of the 
                  adult figure and two more trees, possibly with a river or lake and a hill behind them, are seen to the left of the figures.  Wash above and to 
                  the left of the figures suggests a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms at sides</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An adult female (Mrs. Mason) stands in the center of the design with two children (Mary and Caroline).  
                  She is gowned and wears a large hat; her left shoe is visible.  There may be a shawl or large scarf over her shoulders, but perhaps this is part of her gown.  
                  Her body faces forward with her head turned to the right.  
                  She may be looking at the child to the right.  Her arms are down at her sides.  Her mouth appears to be slightly open and she 
                  may be speaking.  Her hair may be long, but tucked behind her neck.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the central figure stands a female child with long hair (either Mary or Caroline).  
                  She is gowned and wears a wide-brimmed hat.  One shoe (her right?) is visible.  She stands facing forward with her right 
                  arm at her side and her head turned up and to the right.  She is looking at the central figure (Mrs. Mason).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (either Mary or Caroline) stands to the right of the central figure.  She is gowned 
                  and wears a wide-brimmed hat.  One shoe (her left?) is visible.  She stands facing left with her head turned up; she is looking 
                  at the central figure (Mrs. Mason).  The child's left arm is bent upward; she may be touching or holding Mrs. Mason's left arm.  The fingers on her left 
                  hand appear to be spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A building, probably a house, stands on the right.  A large doorway and a roof are visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures appear to stand on a path or road.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaves</characteristic><characteristic>pine</characteristic><characteristic>cypress</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The trunk of a large tree rises to the right of the central figure.  The leaves of this tree 
                  hang over the figures, particularly to the left.  In the middle distance to the left of the figures are two more trees.  These may be a pine (furthest left) and a cypress.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Washes above and to the left of the figures suggests a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>stream</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There may be a body of water, possibly a river or lake, behind the trees on the left.  A hill rises further in the distance.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but244.1.wd.01.01" justify="left" indent="5">Every prospect smiled</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.02" dbi="BUT244.1.2.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">God Sent for Him</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="U2">(Butlin 244.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing was not selected as one of the six to be engraved.  The pencil inscription below the design is in Blake's hand.</p></objnote><objsize>12.2 x 6.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An adult female (Mrs. Mason) and her two charges (Mary and Caroline) stand on a winding path to the left of a large tree.  
               The tree has clearly visible roots, a large trunk, and leafy branches that arch to the left over the figures' heads.     
               All three figures are gowned and wear hats.  Mrs. Mason is the rightmost figure in the group.  Her body faces right, but her head is 
               turned back to the left; she looks down towards the children.  Her right arm is down at her side while her left arm is bent upward and she 
               points or gestures above.  The child furthest to the left is seen in profile facing right.  Her long hair may be drawn back into a braid.  
               Her right arm is bent; her left arm is not visible.  The middle figure also faces right and has long hair that falls onto her shoulders.  
               She is bending slightly forward.  Her right arm is bent with the palm facing out, and her left arm is at her side with the palm facing down.  These gestures, and her slightly-opened mouth, suggest surprise.  
               More distant trees (at least six in all) appear to the left and right of the group of figures.  Wash above the figures suggests a sky with 
               clouds.  Shadows extend from the feet of the figures to the right.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An adult female (Mrs. Mason) stands to the left of a large tree.  She is gowned and wears a large hat; one shoe (the right?) is pictured.  
                  Her right arm is down at her side, while her left arm is bent upward as she points or gestures to the tree or sky above.  
                  Her body faces to the right, but her head is turned back to the left and she looks down towards the two children.  Her hair may be long, but pulled back behind her neck.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary or Caroline) stands to the far left in the group of figures.  She is gowned and wears a hat; one shoe (the right?) is pictured.  
                  The girl has long hair that may be drawn back into a braid.  She faces left in profile.  Her right arm is bent and the fingers on 
                  her right hand are spread.  Her left arm is not visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary or Caroline) stands to the left of Mrs. Mason, in the center of the group of figures.  
                  She is gowned and wears a hat over her long hair; one shoe (the left?) is pictured.  She faces right and is slightly bent forward.  Her right arm is bent and 
                  her right palm faces out.  Her left arm is down at her side with the palm facing down.  These gestures, and her facial expression with mouth slightly open, suggest surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>winding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures stand on a path or road that is also shown in the background of the scene.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Shadows extend along the ground right of the figures' feet.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>root</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large tree with visible roots stands to the right of the group of figures; its leafy branches arch 
                  over the figures' heads to the left.  Other trees are shown in the background to the left and right of the figures.  At 
                  least six distinct tree trunks are visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Hills or mountains are vaguely suggested on the horizon.  Wash above the group of figures suggests a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but244.1.wd.02.01" justify="left" indent="5">God sent for Him</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.03" dbi="BUT244.1.3.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">How Delighted the Old Bird Will Be</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="U3">(Butlin 244.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing was not selected as one of the six to be engraved.  The pencil inscription below the design is in Blake's hand.</p></objnote><objsize>12.5 x 6.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Four figures stand on a winding path.  A gowned female child (Caroline) stands in the foreground facing 
                  right.  She is bent forward with both knees slightly bent with her arms extended and reaching towards the right.  With both 
                  hands she holds a small bird's nest.  A large bush (or possibly the low branches of a tree) 
                  is pictured to the right of the figure.  Above her stands a male child wearing a coat, shirt, and pants.  His right arm is bent upward 
                  with his hand positioned beside (or possibly touching) his head.  His left arm is extended and he points to the right.  
                  The trunk of a large tree is pictured behind and right of the boy.  This tree dominates the top half of the design.  To the left of 
                  these figures stand two females, an adult (Mrs. Mason, on the right) and child (Mary, on the left).  Both figures 
                  are gowned and wear hats.  The adult appears to be holding the child's upraised left hand.  Washes suggest distant trees left and right of these two figures.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the lower half of the design, a female child (Caroline) stands facing right. She 
                     wears a long gown and a hat.  She is bent forward at the waist with her legs apart and slightly bent.  
                     With both hands she holds a bird's nest.  Her arms are bent and extended forward as she replaces the 
                     bird's nest in the bush or tree to the right.  The shoe on her right foot is pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>nest</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The female child in the foreground holds a small bird's nest in her hands.  A few lines above the nest hint at baby birds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child with long hair stands behind the front-most female figure.  He wears a shirt, a long coat, 
                     and pants or breeches.  His right arm is bent with his hand positioned beside his head (possibly touching or pointing to his head).  His 
                     left arm is extended and he points towards the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure (Mrs. Mason) stands to the left of the male figure.  She is gowned and wears a large 
                     dark hat.  Her face is not pictured, but her head and body are turned slightly to the left, towards the child to 
                     her right.  She may be looking down toward the child.  Her right arm may be at her side, and she appears to hold the child's upraised left hand with her lowered left hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary) stands to the left of Mrs. Mason.  She is gowned and wears a hat.  
                     Her face is not pictured, but she faces right and her head is turned up towards Mrs. Mason.  The child's 
                     right arm is at her side.  Her left arm is bent upward, and she appears to hold the left hand of Mrs. Mason.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>bush</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The trunk of a large tree grows to the right of the male figure.  The indistinct leaves of this 
                     tree dominate the top half of the design.  A bush or possibly the low branches of another tree are pictured 
                     to the right of the central female child.  Washes to the left and right of Mrs. Mason suggest distant trees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>winding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures stand on a winding path or road.  It appears to extend behind the two figures in the middle distance on the left.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="9"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but244.1.wd.03.01" justify="left" indent="5">How delighted the old bird</l><l n="but244.1.wd.03.02" justify="left" indent="10">will be</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.04" dbi="BUT244.1.4.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">'Look What a Fine Morning It Is,' for Plate 1</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="U4">(Butlin 244.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The design was engraved as the frontispiece (plate 1) in the book.</p></objnote><objsize>13.3 x 6.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="700" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb514.3.comb.01"/><related objectid="bb514.2.comb.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A gowned female, Mrs. Mason, stands between two female children, Mary and Caroline.  
                  The adult wears a large hat with a bow, and a sash is tied around her waist.  Her long hair rests upon her shoulders.  
                  Her arms are raised horizontally over the heads of the other figures, slightly bent at the 
                  elbows, palms facing out and fingers spread.  Her eyes are cast down as if looking at the ground.  
                  The two female children to her left and right are both gowned and wear hats 
                  over their long hair.  The child on the right has her arms crossed in front of her chest while 
                  the child on the left has her arms bent upwards, palms vertical, with the fingers slightly spread.  
                  The figures stand in front of a doorway with a large, leafy, and branching vine to the left of the figures.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised palms out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female, Mrs. Mason, stands facing forward between two female children.  She wears a 
                     large hat with a bow, and a sash is tied around her waist.  We see both her shoes, the right most prominently.  Her long hair rests upon her shoulders.  Her 
                     arms are raised horizontally over the heads of the other figures, slightly bent at the elbows, palms 
                     facing out and fingers spread.  Her eyes are cast down as if looking at the ground.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female child stands to the left of the central figure.  She is one of Mrs. Mason's charges, either 
                     Mary or Caroline.  She has long hair and wears a hat and shoes.  The hem of her gown is ruffled.  She faces 
                     forward with her arms bent and raised in front of her.  Her palms are held vertically, with the fingers on at least her 
                     left hand spread.  Her eyes are raised slightly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms folded</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female child stands to the right of the central figure.  She is one of Mrs. Mason's charges, 
                     either Mary or Caroline.  She has long hair and wears a hat and shoes.  The hem of her gown is ruffled.  
                     She faces forward with her arms crossed over her chest.  Her eyes are raised as if looking at the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the group of figures is a building with a clearly defined door frame.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A branching vine rises to the left of the group of figures.  The vine bears large leaves, perhaps ten in all.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.05" dbi="BUT244.1.5.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">She Turned Her Eyes on Her Cruel Master</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="U5">(Butlin 244.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing was not selected as one of the six to be engraved.  The pencil inscription below the design is in Blake's hand.</p></objnote><objsize>12.5 x 6.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A small family occupies a room of a house with the floor, door, a back wall, and supporting beams pictured.  
                  A window with a lattice screen or pane design is shown in the upper right corner.  Through the doorway we see a fence.  Above the 
                  fence, dark shapes suggest trees and a lighter wash indicates clouds.  A young boy stands to the right of the doorway.  
                  He wears a coat, pants or breeches, and tights or stockings.  His right arm is bent towards his chest and he appears to hold the front of his 
                  coat.  To the right, an old woman sits in a chair.  She is gowned and wears a cap or bonnet on her head.  A blanket or apron is draped 
                  across her lap.  Her arms are extended with her hands on her knees.  Her palms are turned slightly out (towards the viewer) with the 
                  fingers on both hands spread.  Both figures wear an expression of fear or surprise.  The rightmost figure in the scene is a male seated 
                  in a chair.  He faces left and is seen in profile.  He wears a shirt or long coat, pants, and tall boots.  The figure's left arm is bent 
                  and rests in his lap.  He is looking at the female dog to the left.  The dog stands in profile facing right, and looks toward the man 
                  in the chair.  Between them on the ground is the corpse of a small dog; it is one of the female dog's young.  The dead dog lies on its 
                  side with its legs facing to the left and its head down closest to the viewer.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child or youth stands with his legs spread apart (only his right leg is clearly pictured).  
                     He wears a coat, breeches, probably a shirt, and tights or stockings.  His right arm is bent toward his chest, and he 
                     appears to hold his coat with his right hand.  His left arm is not pictured, but there is a slight 
                     indication that his left hand rests on the back of the chair to the right.  His expression suggests fear or surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>apron</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the male child is an old woman sitting in a chair.  She is gowned and wears 
                     a bonnet.  We see her right foot, probably wearing a shoe.  An apron or blanket is draped over her lap.  Her arms are extended with her hands on 
                     her knees.  Her palms are turned slightly out (towards the viewer) with the fingers on both hands spread.  
                     She wears an expression of fear or surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>boots</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure in the scene is a male seated in a chair.  He faces left and is seen in profile.  
                     He wears a shirt or (long?) coat, pants or breeches, and tall boots.  A bit of drapery hanging from the chair may be his coat or a 
                     blanket.  The figure's left arm is bent and rests in his lap.  He is looking at the dog to the left.  His hair is long.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female dog stands facing right and looks toward the seated male.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a small dog (one of the female dog's young) lies on the floor between the dog and the seated male.  
                     The body of the dog appears to lie on its side, with its legs to the left and its head down closest to the viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The old woman and adult male both sit in chairs.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in a room of a house with the floor, door, back wall, and supporting ceiling beams pictured.  
                     A window with a lattice screen or pane design is shown in the upper right corner.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>fence</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Through the doorway on the left side of the design we see a fence.  Above the 
                     fence, dark shapes suggest trees and a lighter wash indicates clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but244.1.wd.05.01" justify="left" indent="3">She turned her eyes on her</l><l n="but244.1.wd.05.02" justify="left" indent="8">cruel master</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.06" dbi="BUT244.1.6.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">'The Dog Strove to Attract His Attention,' for Plate 2</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="U6">(Butlin 244.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The design was engraved as plate 2 in the book.</p></objnote><objsize>11.7 x 6.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="660" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb514.3.comb.02"/><related objectid="bb514.2.comb.02"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A male figure stands in a room with the dead bodies of two children.  The man, Robin, is the father of the 
                  children, the boy Jacky (closest to the viewer) and the girl Nancy.  The adult has short, curly hair and wears breeches 
                  and a sleeveless shirt or vest.  His body faces forward with his head turned to the right and slightly down; he wears an 
                  expression of despair or grief and may be looking at the two children.  His muscular arms are down at his sides with both 
                  hands forming fists; his bare feet are prominent.  Two corpses—a male and female child—lay supine on a bed.  
                  Their eyes are closed and their heads are back; their heads seem to be resting on a bundle or pillow.  The male child has 
                  long curly hair and wears breeches and a shirt.  His left arm is pictured at his side with the palm down.  The female 
                  child is gowned and has long hair.  Her left arm is bent and rests on her chest.  A slight indication of her left hand 
                  suggests that her hands are clasped over her chest.  A dog with curly fur stands to the left of the male figure.  It stretches 
                  upward with its mouth open and tongue extended to lick the man's right fist.  Behind the male figure, a large casket or coffin 
                  rests on two benches or stools.   There is a single window high on the right-most wall.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>Robin</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>fist</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure stands in a room with the bodies of two dead children; he is Robin, their father.  
                     He has short, curly hair and wears breeches and a sleeveless shirt or vest.  His body faces forward 
                     with his head turned to the right and slightly down; he wears an expression of despair or grief and he may be looking 
                     at the two children.  His muscular arms are down at his side with both hands forming fists.  His bare feet are prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Jacky</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a male child (Jacky, closest to the viewer) lies supine on a bed with his head bent back and his eyes 
                     closed.  He wears breeches and a shirt.  His left arm is pictured at his side with the palm down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Nancy</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a gowned female child (Nancy, second from the viewer) lies supine on a bed with her head bent back 
                     and her eyes closed.  Her left arm is bent and rests on her chest.  Slight indications of her left hand suggest that her 
                     hands are clasped and resting on her chest.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>stretched</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dog with curly fur stands to the right of the male figure.  Its hind legs are on the ground or floor, 
                     while its front legs stand on the edge of the bed.  It stretches 
                     upward with its mouth open and tongue extended to lick the man's right fist.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>bier</characteristic><characteristic>bundle</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The two dead children lie on a bed, used here as a bier.  Their heads are supported by a bundle or pillow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="B"><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There is a single window high on the right-most wall.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>coffin</characteristic><characteristic>stool</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the male figure, a large casket or coffin rests on two benches or stools.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.07" dbi="BUT244.1.7.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">'Indeed We Are Very Happy,' for Plate 3</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="U7">(Butlin 244.7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The drawing was cut in half horizontally and the lower half cut vertically from the lower edge to its mid-point; the pieces of paper have been reattached.  The design was engraved as plate 3 in the book.</p></objnote><objsize>14.0 x 6.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb514.3.comb.03"/><related objectid="bb514.2.comb.03"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A gowned female (Mrs. Mason) sits in a chair on the left and faces right.  Her long curly hair falls 
                  onto her shoulders.  Her arms rest in her lap, with her hands on her knees.  Her eyes are down and 
                  she appears to be smiling; she looks at the two female children (Mary and Caroline) sitting to either side of her.  Both children 
                  have long hair; the figure on the left has hers drawn back into a braid.  The figure on the left is seen from the side, with her 
                  upper body turned away from the viewer.  Her right hand rests on top of the woman's right hand.  Her head is down and rests in the 
                  woman's lap in an apparent expression of sorrow.  The figure on the right mirrors this position; she holds the woman's left hand 
                  with her left hand.  To the right of this group, a male figure sits in a chair facing left.  He is Jack, a sailor, with two of his 
                  children near him.  He wears a coat, pants, shoes, and a scarf at his neck.  His left arm, and probably his right arm, are bent and rest in his lap.  His crutch lies horizontally on 
                  the floor below his left foot.  A child (possibly female and wearing a hat) stands behind and to the left of the seated man.  
                  She has her head down, and holds a scarf or cloth to her face.  The figure appears to stand, but her legs are not pictured.  A male 
                  child stands to the right of the seated male figure.  He may be leaning against the back of the chair.  He has short curly hair 
                  and his eyes are cast down.  His arms are crossed in front of his chest, with his left hand holding or 
                  resting on his right shoulder.  His legs are crossed at the ankles.  He wears a shirt and breeches.  The six 
                  figures appear in a room with a large fireplace.  A fire burns on a stack of wood kindling and smoke 
                  rises up the chimney.  Two model ships sit on a mantel above the fireplace; the ship on the 
                  right has sails.  Four indistinct objects, possibly candlesticks, stand between the two ships.  Two framed pictures 
                  hang on the wall to either side of the mantel.  The ceiling includes beams.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms on lap</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female (Mrs. Mason) sits in a chair facing right.  Her long, curly hair 
                     falls onto her shoulders.  Her arms rest in her lap, with her hands on her knees.  Her eyes are 
                     down and she appears to be smiling; she may be looking at the two female children sitting to either side of her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two gowned female children, Mary and Caroline, sit to either side of the adult female, Mrs. Mason.  Both figures 
                     have long hair; the figure on the left has hers drawn back into a braid.  The figure on the left is seen from the side, but 
                     her upper body is twisted away from the viewer as she bends forward towards the woman.  The girl's right arm rests in 
                     the woman's lap; her right hand rests on top of the woman's right hand.  This girl's head is down and also rests in the woman's lap in an apparent expression of 
                     sorrow or grief. The figure on the right mirrors this position.  Her left hand rests on or holds the woman's left hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>Jack</characteristic><characteristic>sailor</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms on lap</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure sits on the right in a chair and faces left.  He is Jack, a sailor, and the father of the two children 
                     near him.  He wears a coat, pants, shoes, and a scarf at his neck.  His hair (or wig?) is short and curly above his forehead and at the back of his neck.  His left arm, and probably his right, are bent and 
                     rest in his lap.  He may be holding his hands together.  His crutch rests on the floor beneath his left foot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A child, probably female, stands behind and to the left of the seated 
                     adult male.  She is wearing a hat or cap, has her head down, and holds a scarf or cloth to her face.  
                     Her posture suggests sorrow or grief.  The figure appears to be standing, but her legs are not 
                     pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child stands to the right of the seated male figure.  He may be leaning against the 
                     back of the chair.  He has short curly hair and his eyes are cast down.  His arms are crossed in front 
                     of his chest, with his left hand holding or resting on his right shoulder.  His legs are crossed at the 
                     ankles.  He may be wearing tights or a shirt and breeches.  His posture suggests melancholy or grief.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>stool</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The two adult figures in the scene are seated on chairs.  The leftmost child in the design 
                     sits on a stool.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>fireplace</characteristic><characteristic>chimney</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There is a fireplace in the center of the design.  A fire burns on a small stack of wood 
                     kindling and smoke rises up the chimney.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>mantel</characteristic><characteristic>ship</characteristic><characteristic>sail</characteristic><characteristic>candlestick</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two model ships sit on a mantel above the fireplace.  The ship on the right has sails.  
                     Four objects, possibly candlesticks (as in the engraving), stand between the two ships.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>picture</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two framed pictures hang to the left and right of the fireplace mantel.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>crutch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The man's crutch rests on the floor below his left foot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in a room with beams supporting the roof.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.08" dbi="BUT244.1.8.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Ruined House: 'Be Calm, My Child,' for Plate 4</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="U8">(Butlin 244.8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The design was engraved as plate 4 in the book.</p></objnote><objsize>13.0 x 6.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb514.3.comb.04"/><related objectid="bb514.2.comb.04"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>An adult female (Mrs. Mason) walks with two female children (Mary and Caroline).   The 
                  woman is seen from behind and walks away from the viewer, with her head turned in profile to the left and slightly down.  
                  She is gowned and wears a cloak or shawl around her shoulders; she also wears a large hat with a bow, 
                  and her long hair cascades out from under a bonnet or hair net.  Her arms are at her side and are slightly bent at 
                  the elbows.  With her left arm, she embraces or holds the child to the left; though not pictured, 
                  she may hold hands with the child to the right.  A female child stands to the right of the central figure.  
                  She is gowned and wears a hat.  Her head is turned to the right, away from the other figures.  She may 
                  be looking at something not pictured.  Part of her body is hidden by the central figure; her left arm 
                  is bent and she may hold the right hand of the central figure.  A second female child stands or walks to 
                  the left of the central figure.  She is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer.  She is gowned 
                  and wears a hat.  Her right arm is extended at 45 degrees and touches the 
                  left leg of the central figure.  On the left of the design stands a ruined house.  
                  The structure has two distinct windows and what might be a pilaster at its right corner.  The structure appears broken, particularly 
                  above the highest window.  Extending to the right is a wall or fence that is partially hidden by the 
                  figures and tree trunks.  A lake or stream is pictured to the left and right of the group of figures, below the 
                  ruined building.  Clumps of indeterminate vegetation, possibly water lilies, are pictured in the lake or stream lower left.  
                  Several trees with leaves and crossing trunks are pictured near the group of 
                  figures.  Dark wash right of the ruined building may indicate a distant forest of trees or other vegetation.  
                  Washes in the sky suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A central adult female (Mrs. Mason) walks with two children, Mary and Caroline.  The 
                     woman is seen from behind and walks away from the viewer, with her head turned in profile to the left and slightly down.  
                     She is gowned and wears a cloak or shawl around her shoulders; she also wears a large hat with a bow, 
                     and her long hair cascades out from under a bonnet or hair net.  Her arms are at her side and are slightly bent at 
                     the elbows.  With her left arm, she embraces or holds the child to the left; though not 
                     pictured, she may hold hands with the child to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary or Caroline) stands to the right of the central figure.  She is gowned 
                     and wears a hat.  Her body faces forward with her head turned to the right, away from the other figures.  She may 
                     be looking at something not pictured.  Her mouth may be slightly open.  Part of her body is hidden by the central figure; 
                     her right arm is bent and she may hold the left hand of the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female child (Mary or Caroline) stands or walks to the left of the central figure.  She is 
                     seen from behind and faces away from the viewer; her hair is long.  She is gowned and wears a hat.  
                     Her right arm is extended at 45 degrees and touches the left leg of the central figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>ruin</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>fence</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design stands a ruined house.  
                     The structure has two distinct windows and what may be a pilaster at its right corner.  The structure appears 
                     broken, particularly above the highest window.  Extending to the right is a wall or fence 
                     that is partially hidden by the figures and tree trunks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>lake</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>stream</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A lake or stream is pictured in the middle distance to the left and right of the group of figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>lily</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Clumps of indeterminate vegetation, possibly water lilies, are pictured in the lake or river.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>willow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several trees with leaves and crossing or intertwined trunks appear on either bank of the lake or stream.  
                     They may represent willows.  Dark wash to the right of the ruined house may indicate more distant trees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The wash at the top of the design suggests a sky with clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.09" dbi="BUT244.1.9.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">'Œconomy and Self-Denial are Necessary,' for Plate 6</title>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber><objcode code="U9">(Butlin 244.9)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>There is a repaired tear in the drawing, upper right.  The design was engraved as plate 6 in the book.</p></objnote><objsize>14.2 x 6.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb514.3.comb.06"/><related objectid="bb514.2.comb.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Mrs. Mason and her two charges, Mary and Caroline, visit a poor family.  Eight figures are pictured in 
                  a small room with a door, a fireplace with a grate (but no fire).   
                  We can also see the inside of the roof with two supporting beams.  On the left of the design, an adult 
                  female (Mrs. Mason) stands between two female children (Mary and Caroline).  
                  She is gowned and wears a hat.  She may be listening to the woman to the right.  She appears to 
                  be looking at the crouched figures in the lower half of the design with an expression of pity.  
                  She holds the hands of the children to her left and right.  The children  
                  are both gowned and wear hats.  The child on the left bends her left arm 
                  and holds the hand of the adult woman; the girl's right arm is down and the fingers of her right hand are 
                  slightly spread.  The child on the right is partially obscured.  She may hold hands (her right?) with the adult 
                  woman; her left arm is bent across her body.  Both children look towards the other figures in the scene with 
                  expressions suggesting pity or surprise.  Another female figure stands to the right of the doorway; she is the mother of 
                  the poor family that Mrs. Mason and her charges are visiting.  She is gowned  
                  and wears a tattered hat with a bonnet or cloth underneath.  She faces forward, but her head is turned in 
                  profile to the left.  Her mouth is open and she may be speaking to Mrs. Mason.  She holds an indistinct shape in her 
                  crossed arms; in the engraving this is more clearly an infant, seen from behind.  An adult male 
                  figure, the father, sits in a chair facing right in the lower half of the design.  He wears shoes, stockings(?), breeches, and a shirt.  
                  His hair is short and curly.  His right arm rests on his lap with his hand on his knee.  His left arm is bent 
                  and supports his head, which is bent down.  His eyes are closed, and he wears an expression of despair, melancholy, or 
                  grief.  To the right of the seated figure, a male child sits in an extremely contracted position and 
                  leans with his shoulder against the wall.  He is facing forward, with his head turned slightly to the 
                  right.  The figure appears to wear breeches.  His legs are drawn up and crossed at 
                  the ankles.  His left arm is seen at his side.  The child's eyes may be closed.  The rightmost figure in 
                  this design is a male child seated on the floor with 
                  his back against the wall.  He wears shoes, breeches, and a shirt or coat.  He faces to the left, with his legs 
                  extended together.  His left arm is at his side with his palm down.  His head is bent down, and he 
                  wears a rather blank expression.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>pity</characteristic><characteristic>listening</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design, an adult female (Mrs. Mason) stands between two female children.  
                     She is gowned and wears a hat; her long hair cascades onto her shoulders.  Her right shoe is pictured.  She faces forward with her head turned slightly to the right.  She may be 
                     listening to the woman to the right.  She appears to 
                     be looking at the crouched figures in the lower half of the design with an expression of pity.  
                     She holds the hands of the children to her left and right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pity</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two female children, Mary and Caroline, flank the adult woman standing on the left of the design.  
                     Both are gowned, have long hair, and wear hats.  
                     The child on the left holds the adult's hand with her left hand; her right arm is down with her 
                     fingers spread.  We see her left shoe and perhaps a bit of her right shoe.  The child on the right is partially obscured.  She may hold hands (with her right hand?) with the adult 
                     woman; her left arm is bent across her body.  Both children look towards 
                     the other figures in the scene with expressions suggesting pity.  The expression of the girl on the left also suggests surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, the mother of the family visited by Mrs. Mason and her charges, stands to the right of 
                     the doorway.  She is gowned and wears a tattered hat with a bonnet, cloth, or scarf underneath covering her hair.  
                     She faces forward, but her head is turned in 
                     profile to the left.  Her mouth is open and she may be speaking to Mrs. Mason.  She holds an indistinct shape in her 
                     crossed arms; in the engraving this is more clearly an infant, seen from behind.  Only the infant's head is clearly pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>stockings</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure, the father of the poor family, sits in a chair in the lower half of the design.  
                     He faces right and wears shoes, stockings(?), 
                     breeches, and a shirt.  His hair is short and curly; he may have a short, stubble beard.  His right arm rests on his lap with his 
                     hand on his knee.  His left arm is bent and supports his head, which is bent down.  His 
                     eyes are closed, and he wears an expression of despair, melancholy, or grief.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The adult male in the lower half of the design sits in a chair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the seated figure, a male(?) child sits in an extremely 
                     contracted position and leans with his shoulder against the wall.  The figure appears to wear breeches.  
                     His legs are drawn up and crossed at the ankles; his right foot is bare.  His left arm is shown  
                     at his side.  The child's eyes are closed and he wears an expression of  
                     despair or grief.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure in this design is a male child seated on the floor with 
                     his back against a wall.  He wears shoes, breeches, and a shirt.  He faces to the left, with his 
                     legs extended together.  His left arm is at his side with his palm down upon the floor.  His head is bent 
                     down, and he wears a blank expression.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>fireplace</characteristic><characteristic>grate</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is set in a small room with a doorway to the left on the back wall, a fireplace in the wall on the right, 
                     and a grate (but no fire) in the fireplace.  We can also see the inside of the roof with supporting beams.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but244.1.wd.10" dbi="BUT244.1.10.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">A Starving Woman with Two Children</title>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber><objcode code="U10">(Butlin 244.10)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing was not selected as one of the six to be engraved.</p></objnote><objsize>11.7 x 6.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="660" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The left half of the design depicts a starving woman and two children.  They are apparently pictured in a room, possibly with a door on the left.  The woman is gowned and wears a bonnet or 
                  cap and buckle shoes.  She faces forward with her head up and an expression of grief or despair on her face.  The woman's arms 
                  are bent upward and she holds a cloth in front of her chest with both hands.  A male child with curly hair stands to the woman's left.  
                  He faces right and holds both arms vertically, reaching upward and holding (or at least touching) the woman's gown.  A female child stands to the right of the woman, facing left.  
                  Her long hair may be drawn back in a loose braid.  Her left arm is bent upward and she holds the woman's skirt.  The right half of the design 
                  is a pencil sketch.  A woman (Mrs. Mason) wears a large hat and faces left.  Two female children 
                  (Mary and Caroline) stand near Mrs. Mason.  The figure closest to the viewer (below Mrs. Mason) wears a hat and faces left.  
                  The figure to the left reaches to the right with her bent right arm.  The two girls may be looking at each other.  All three figures in this sketch are gowned.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>emaciated</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>buckle</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design, an old(?) emaciated female stands facing forward.  She is gowned and wears a bonnet or cap 
                     and buckle shoes.  The woman's arms are bent upward and she holds a cloth in front of her chest with both hands.  Her mouth is open and 
                     she wears an expression of grief or despair.  She may be speaking or crying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male child with curly hair stands to the left of the woman, facing right with his head turned up towards her.  
                     He wears breeches and a shirt.  Both arms are raised vertically; he reaches upward and he holds (or at least touches) the skirt of the woman's gown with both hands.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female child stands to the right of the woman, facing left.  She has long hair that may be drawn back into 
                     a loose braid.  Her left arm is bent upward and she holds the skirt of the woman's gown with her left hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures on the left apparently stand in a room, possibly with a door on the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Mason, Mrs.</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female figure (Mrs. Mason) stands to the right of the starving woman and children.  She wears a large hat 
                     and faces to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Caroline</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two young gowned females (Mary and Caroline) stand to either side of Mrs. Mason.  The figure on the right 
                     wears a hat and faces left.  The figure to the left, apparently facing right, has her right arm extended and slightly bent.  The girls may be looking at each other.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>