<bad id="but220.1" type="penc" work="Three Figures in a Decorative Border" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="220" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Three Figures in a Decorative Border">
                    <main>Three Figures in a Decorative Border</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman
                page 549); "Let a Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture
                or Painting but if he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a
                Better Thing[.]" (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is
                Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws
                best must be the best Artist…." (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582);
                "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather madness, for I am really drunk with
                intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or graver into my hand…." (letter to
                William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake*
                (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6),
                Blake’s iconic vision of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches
                (Objects 34-36) for illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of
                finished drawings Blake composed for one of his own poems. Several sketches are
                early efforts at picturing events in the Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs
                throughout his life. This biblical cluster includes *The Resurrection of
                    the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul to the
                    People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches*
                (Object 31). Other studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its
                verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest
                for Blake. Only a few drawings for Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but
                studies such as *Sketches for “The Book of Thel”* and *A
                    Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating glimpses
                into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work copyright © 2018 Tate Collection </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>July 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William S. Shaw, </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Three Figures in a Decorative Border* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author. Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription,
                        lower right.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1790">c. 1790<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>9.9 x 16.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>12.2 x 20.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and
                        ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>Curving lines left and right suggest a decorative border or
                    frame.</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1922</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Apparently inherited by Catherine Blake upon the death of her husband, William
                    Blake, in 1827; by inheritance to Frederick Tatham upon the death of Catherine
                    Blake in 1831; Tatham's brother-in-law George Richmond, sold from Richmond's
                    collection, Christie's, 29 April 1897, lot 147 with 21 other works by Blake as
                    listed in Butlin 77 (&#163;2.10s. to Richard Sisley); his daughter, Mrs. John
                    Richmond; given by Mrs. Richmond to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection) in
                    1922.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <addressline>Millbank</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 20-7887-8888</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images: 20-7887-8871/4933</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images: 20-7887-8805</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Images: tate.images@tate.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, General: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Images: http://www.tate-images.com</addressline>
                <department/>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">A00042</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but220.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT220.1.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Three Figures in a Decorative Border</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 220)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>Butlin 220 titles this work *Two Figures in a Decorative Border*, but there
                        are clearly three figures pictured in the design.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>12.2 x 20.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, a female figure with long curly
                        hair is shown from the waist up and appears to wear some sort of gown. She
                        faces down and left, likely to look at a second figure, very lightly
                        sketched, who sits or reclines lower left. Depicted in less detail than the
                        first, this figure may extend one arm to the ground, where it is braced, and
                        may raise the other horizontally(?). Its legs are extended, at least in
                        part, to the right. Behind and to the right of the central figure is the
                        upper body and head of a hunched over, contracted figure facing right and
                        down. Her(?) long hair and elevated right knee obscure her face. her right
                        arm extends downward. A line on her back suggests that she may be gowned. A
                        decorative scroll-like border surrounds the figures on both sides of the
                        scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, a female figure with long
                            curly hair is shown from the waist up and appears to wear some sort of
                            gown. Most likely standing, she faces down and left, likely to look at a
                            second figure who reclines lower left. The upward-curving line to the
                            left may suggest her right arm is bent upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A lightly sketched figure sits or reclines with head at left
                            in the lower left corner. It may extend one arm to the ground, where it
                            is braced, and may raise the other horizontally(?). Its legs are
                            extended, at least in part, to the right. Other fine pencil lines below
                            and to the left of this figure do not picture a clearly identifiable
                            motif.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind and to the right of the central figure is the upper
                            body and head of a hunched over, contracted figure facing right and
                            down. Her(?) long hair and elevated right knee obscure her face. her
                            right arm extends downward. A line on her back suggests that she may be
                            gowned.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frame</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A decorative scroll-like border surrounds the pair of figures
                            on both sides and lower right and left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but220.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="46">William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but220.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="49">Frederick Tatham</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
