<bad id="but200r.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for ‘Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana’ (?)" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="200r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Sketch for ‘Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana’ (?)">
                    <main>Sketch for "Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana" (?)</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2018 Tate Collection
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>July 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William S. Shaw, </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Sketch for "Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana" (?)</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author.  Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription, lower right.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1789">c. 1789<note>Some scholars have argued for a slightly earlier date
                        for Blake's *Tiriel* manuscript and the wash drawings
                        illustrating it, and hence by implication a slightly earlier date for all
                        preliminary sketches for those wash drawings. See David Bindman, *Blake as an Artist* (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977) 43-44.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>29.1 x 45.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>29.1 x 45.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1922</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; Tatham's brother-in-law, George Richmond; sold from Richmond's collection, Christie's, 29 April 1897, lot 147 with 21 other works, most by Blake and his brother Robert (&#163;2.10s. to Richard Sisley); Sisley's daughter, Mrs. John Richmond, probably by gift or inheritance; given by Mrs. Richmond to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection) in 1922.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <addressline>Millbank</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 20-7887-8888</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images: 20-7887-8871/4933</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images: 20-7887-8805</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Images: tate.images@tate.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, General: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Images: http://www.tate-images.com</addressline>
                <department/>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">A00040</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but200r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT200.1.1r.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketch for "Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana" (?)</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 200 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote><p>Both the recto and verso pencil drawings on this leaf appear to be variant preliminary sketches for the monochrome wash drawing, *Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana and Cursing His Sons* (Butlin 198.1), an illustration to Blake's manuscript poem, *Tiriel*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>29.1 x 45.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Two groups of figures constitute this sketch.  At left, at least two (perhaps three) figures form a triangular arrangement of overlapping bodies.  The tallest leans diagonally to the right and appears to stretch its right arm in the same direction.  This may be Tiriel.  He may wear a hat or hood or have long hair.  This figure may wear a gown and may support a second figure in the foreground who crouches or sits facing away from the viewer.  This may be Tiriel's wife, Myratana.  This figure's right arm may be outstretched to the right.  Directly above this figure's arm, what may be a nude torso of a third figure is visible.  On the right side of the composition, at least three figures stand facing forward and left.  These are probably Tiriel's sons.  The leftmost of these wears a gown and has short(?) hair.  His left arm is bent at the elbow, and he holds an indeterminate object in his left hand.  His right arm is extended vertically with right hand possibly clasped in a fist.  To the right of this figure, a second figure who appears to wear a crown and gown also bends his left arm at the elbow.  The head of a third figure is visible at far right, and though this figure is the least detailed, it too may have its left arm bent at the elbow.  There are other lines and forms across the composition, but the significance of these is impossible to determine.  The scene is likely connected with the monochrome wash drawing, *Tiriel Supporting the Dying Myratana and Cursing His Sons* (Butlin 198.1), an illustration to Blake's manuscript poem, *Tiriel*.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Tiriel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least two (perhaps three) figures form a triangular arrangement of overlapping bodies.  The tallest leans diagonally to the right and appears to reach its right arm in the same direction.  This may be Tiriel.  He may wear a hat or hood or have long hair.  This figure may wear a gown and may be supporting a second figure in the foreground.  This figure is likely Tiriel in the act of cursing his sons at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Myratana</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second figure is visible in the foreground at left who crouches or sits facing away from the viewer.  This may be Tiriel's wife, Myratana.  She may tilt her head sharply to the left.  This figure's right arm may be outstretched to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>Myratana</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chest</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between the outstretched right arms of the two figures at left, what may be a nude torso of a third figure is visible.  The suggestion of breasts indicates the figure is likely female and thus perhaps identifiable as the dying Myratana.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, at least three figures stand facing forward and left.  These are Tiriel's sons.  The leftmost of these wears a gown and has short(?) hair.  His left arm is bent at the elbow, and he holds an indeterminate object in his left hand.  His right arm is extended vertically with right hand clasped in a fist(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, at least three figures stand facing forward and left.  These are Tiriel's sons.  The short-haired middle figure, who appears to wear a spiky crown and gown, bends his left arm at the elbow.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, at least three figures stand facing forward and left.  These are Tiriel's sons.  The head of a third figure is visible at far right, and though this figure is the least detailed, it too may have its left arm bent at the elbow and wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but200r.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="44">These few fine Lines by<note>This pen and ink inscription is by Frederick Tatham.</note></l>
                    <l n="but200r.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="43">William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but200r.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="46">vouched by Fred.<hi rend="superscript">k</hi> Tatham</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
