<bad id="but247.1" type="wc" work="The Vision of Queen Katharine, c. 1783-90" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="butlin" catid="247">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Vision of Queen Katharine, c. 1783-90">
                    <main>The Vision of Queen Katharine, c. 1783-90</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of Blake’s water color illustrations to the plays of William Shakespeare. 
                 <lb/>
                <lb/>     
Although less extensive and well known than his illustrations of John Milton’s poems, Blake’s water colors based on Shakespeare’s plays constitute a significant group of designs. The earliest, dating from c. 1779, is probably one of Blake’s illustrations of English history but nonetheless evokes Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi>. The series of seven small ovals picturing characters from the plays also dates from Blake’s early years. The concentrated focus on just one or two figures filling most of the pictorial space may be Blake’s response to popular interest in miniature portraiture. The reason for his execution of this group is not known; like the English history designs, they may have been intended for eventual publication as engravings.  The series of Shakespeare character portraits by John Hamilton Mortimer, published as engravings in the mid-1770s, may have influenced Blake’s similar project.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
<hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> is one of Blake’s largest water colors of the 1780s. Its size and quality suggest that it may have been intended for exhibition, like the water colors illustrating the life of Joseph displayed at the Royal Academy in 1785. The circle of dancers and Puck’s stance with arms raised echo similar motifs in George Romney’s <hi rend="i">Leveson-Gower Family</hi>, painted in 1776-77 and published as a mezzotint by John Raphael Smith in 1781.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Blake was clearly attracted to the vision of Queen Katherine in <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, act 4, scene 2, for he executed four versions beginning c. 1783-90 and concluding with the highly finished and complex water color of c. 1825-26. Blake’s water color of Queen Katherine’s dream dated 1809 is part of a series of six illustrations to Shakespeare’s plays commissioned by Joseph Thomas, the clergyman who had earlier employed Blake to illustrate Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. In a letter of 31 July 1801 to William Hayley, John Flaxman added a postscript to Blake, including the following: “he [Thomas] also desired you [Blake] will make two designs in bister or Indian Ink, from Shakespeare’s Troylus &amp Cressida, Coriolanus, either of the 3 plays of Henry 6.<sup>th</sup> Richard the 3.<sup>d</sup> or Henry the 8.<sup>th</sup> each design for one play for which he will give a Guinea each, the dimensions as follow the paper. an upright square of 12 Inches &amp half by 8 Inches, within this Space leaving a moderate margin, the principal figure not exceeding 6 Inches high” (Butlin 547). Blake’s designs (most now trimmed) roughly follow these size requirements, necessitated by Thomas’s desire to create an extra-illustrated copy of the 1632 second folio of Shakespeare’s plays, but Blake waited eight years before completing the commission, changed the medium from monochrome drawings to water colors, and illustrated only two plays, <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi> and <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, specified by Flaxman. Blake may have chosen the other passages for illustration, at some point convincing Thomas of their appropriateness.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Many of Blake’s Shakespeare designs show his predilection for scenes dealing with perceptions that extend beyond the world of the physical senses. The four versions of Queen Katherine’s dream epitomize this lifelong interest in imaginative and visionary experiences. A corollary is Blake’s attraction to representations of the arts, demonstrated by <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> and his portrayal of Pegasus, the classical embodiment of poetic inspiration, in <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi> among the designs for Thomas.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, editors <lb/>
                Joseph Fletcher, managing editor, Michael Fox, assistant editor<lb/>
                 The William Blake Archive<lb/>     
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 Fitzwilliam Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February - March 2020</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies,</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Dan Gorman</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose</name>
                    <name>Jake Ruta</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>     
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>January 2016</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Laura Bell</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Rachel Lee,</name>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Adam Engel,</name>
<name>Andrea Everett,</name>
<name>Grant Glass,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Eric Loy,</name>
<name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
<name>Adam McCune,</name>
<name>Scott Robinson,</name>
<name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
<name>Miles Simon,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
<name>Alia Wegner,</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2005</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Conversion: </resp>
<name>Aziza Technology Associates</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
<name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *The Vision of Queen Katharine* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>anonymous<role>delineator. The "WB" inscription lower right is probably
                        not by Blake.</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1783">c. 1783-90<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations. Butlin 247 dates the work to c. 1790-93; the date given here
                        is taken from David Bindman, *William Blake: Catalogue of the
                            Collection in the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge* (Cambridge: W.
                        Heffer and Sons for the Fitzwilliam Museum, 1970) 6.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>20.3 x 16.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>20.3 x 16.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color over some pencil<note>The inscribed initials,
                        lower right, are in pen and ink. This inscription was probably written by
                        someone other than Blake.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1935</date>
                <dealer>Maggs Bros.</dealer>
                <price>&#163;120</price>
                <note>Possibly acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts; possibly the work inherited by
                    Thomas Butts, Jr., in 1845 and sold Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June
                    1853, lot 137 (&#163;2.17s.6d. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); possibly James H.
                    Chance (John Linnell's nephew) by 1863; possibly the work sold from the
                    collection of Samuel Prince, 11 Dec. 1865, lot 276, titled "The Dream" (&#163;4
                    to "Halstead," probably a dealer); Stopford A. Brooke by 1876 and sold from his
                    collection, Sotheby's, 11 Dec. 1935, lot 621 (&#163;110 to the dealer Maggs
                    Bros., possibly acting for the Fitzwilliam Museum); acquired by the Fitzwilliam
                    Museum in Dec. 1935 for &#163;120. The association of this work with the
                    collection formed by Thomas Butts is speculative. </note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline>
                <addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)1223 332900</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)1223 332923</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/index.html</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints:
                    fitzmuseum-pdp@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints:
                    http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/pdp</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 332927</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 768591</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Image Library:
                    fitzmuseum-photography@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Photographic Service:
                    http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/photography</addressline>
                <department>Paintings, Drawings, and Prints</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1935-1771</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but247.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT247.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Vision of Queen Katharine</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 247)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.3 x 16.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Ten figures hover or fly above a recumbent female figure in this
                        image, which illustrates The Vision of Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of
                        Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. In the lower third of the
                        scene, a female figure lies supine with her head at right on a heavily
                        draped couch or bed. She has long hair and wears a gown. She may rest her
                        head on a pillow(?) and her eyes are closed, suggesting sleep. Dark round
                        forms, probably clouds, are visible near her feet lower left. This figure,
                        Queen Katharine, is the wife of King Henry VIII who wishes to divorce her
                        (as she has not born a male heir) and marry Anne Boleyn. Katharine becomes
                        ill, and it is during her sickness in which The Vision occurs. The Vision
                        itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures
                        (although only six figures appear in The Vision in the play). Near the left
                        margin, a pair of female figures face each other and appear to hover. Facing
                        forward, the gowned figure has long hair and bends both arms upward to hold
                        an object (perhaps a wicker basket or bowl?) on her head. Immediately in
                        front of her, a nude figure with long hair that may be braided faces away.
                        This figure bends both arms at right angles and in her right hand holds one
                        of the garlands mentioned in the play's text. A second pair of figures
                        occupy the upper center of the design. The higher figure appears to be nude
                        and female with long, flame-like hair that extends outward in spiky
                        tendrils. She faces forward but looks down and only the upper half of her
                        body is visible, as if she is emerging from the colorful cloud behind her.
                        Both arms are extended horizontally, palms facing down. Below her left arm,
                        a second figure, who appears to be a nude male figure with short hair,
                        mimics her posture with his left arm extended horizontally. His body,
                        however, may be twisted: though he faces forward and down, his left leg is
                        extended to the left and his right arm is by his side (perhaps touching the
                        female figure above him). A third pair of figures hover or float against the
                        right margin. The gender of neither figure is distinct. The closer figure
                        has short hair and likely wears a transparent gown. She(?) faces forward and
                        slightly left with his legs crossed at the ankle. With bent arms, she plays
                        a lyre; her open mouth suggests she may also sing. The second figure has
                        short hair and wears a gown. Facing forward, this figure bends its left arm
                        to hold a bowl or (wicker?) basket on its head, echoing the pose and
                        accoutrement of the long-haired figure at far left. Four additional figures
                        are visible in the center of the image. The two uppermost of these who are
                        both nude hold a circular garland or wreath between them with one extended
                        arm each. The body of the figure at right is horizontal with head at right
                        though its head is turned to look left, perhaps back toward its companion,
                        who faces forward but extends its legs left. Below this pair, a single male
                        figure with short hair and a blue shirt rides a horse facing forward and
                        slightly right. He bends his right arm to hold the horse's neck and leans
                        forward. Both horse and rider may look toward the final figure in The Vision
                        scene who hovers horizontally facing forward and right. This male figure,
                        who is nude but for a single swath of drapery covering his genitals, has
                        short hair and wears a quiver on his back with a bow and the end of at least
                        one arrow visible. He extends both arms horizontally, palms facing up, and
                        may hold or touch an object (perhaps another garland or branch?) visible
                        near his left hand and just above the sleeping figure's head. Blue sky is
                        visible along the upper edge of the image with colorful clouds and beams of
                        light below.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dreaming</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Katharine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Ten figures hover or fly above a recumbent female figure in
                            this image, which illustrates The Vision of Queen Katharine in Act 4,
                            Scene 2 of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. In the lower
                            third of the scene, a female figure lies supine with her head at right
                            on a heavily draped couch or bed. She has long hair and wears a gown.
                            She may rest her head on a pillow(?) and her eyes are closed, suggesting
                            sleep. Dark round forms (perhaps clouds or stones?) are visible near her
                            feet lower left. This figure, Queen Katharine, is the wife of King Henry
                            VIII who wishes to divorce her (as she has not born a male heir) and
                            marry Anne Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it is during her sickness
                            in which The Vision occurs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the bottom edge of the image, a female figure
                            representing the Shakespearean character Queen Katharine lies supine on
                            a bed or couch covered in sheets or drapery. She may rest her head on a
                            pillow at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the bottom edge of the image, a female figure
                            representing the Shakespearean character Queen Katharine lies supine on
                            a bed or couch. Dark round forms, probably clouds, are visible near her
                            feet lower left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            Near the left margin, a pair of female figures look toward each other
                            and appear to hover or float. Facing forward, the gowned figure on the
                            left has long hair and bends both arms upward to hold an object (perhaps
                            a basket or bowl?) on her head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wicker</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure in the upper portion of the image
                            representing The Vision holds an object on her head that appears to be a
                            (wicker?) basket or bowl decorated with vines, leaves, and perhaps
                            flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            Near the left margin, a pair of female figures look toward each other
                            and appear to hover or float. At right, a nude figure with long hair
                            that may be braided faces away. This figure bends both arms at right
                            angles and in her right hand holds one of the garlands mentioned in the
                            play's text. The figure's left leg is slightly bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>garland</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the left in the upper part of the image
                            illustrating The Vision holds a long garland in her right hand that may
                            contain flowers, vines, and leaves. The play describes the figures in
                            The Vision both wearing and holding garlands in Act 4, Scene
                            2.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            A pair of figures who may fly, float, or hover occupies the upper middle
                            of the design. The higher figure appears to be nude and female with
                            long, flame-like hair that extends outward in spiky tendrils. She faces
                            forward but looks down; her mouth may be open. Only the upper half of
                            her body is visible, as if she is emerging from the colorful cloud
                            behind her. Both arms are extended horizontally, palms facing
                            down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            A pair of figures who may fly, float, or hover occupies the upper middle
                            of the design. Below the upper figure's left arm, a second figure, who
                            appears to be a nude male figure with short hair, mimics her posture
                            with his left arm extended horizontally, palm facing down. His body,
                            however, may be twisted: though he faces forward and down, his left leg
                            is extended to the left and his right arm is by his side (perhaps
                            touching the female figure above him).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>singing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            A third pair of figures hover or float against the right margin. The
                            gender of neither figure is distinct. The closer figure has short hair
                            and likely wears a transparent gown. She(?) faces forward and slightly
                            left with her legs crossed at the ankle. With bent arms, she plays a
                            lyre; her open mouth suggests he may also sing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the right in the upper part of the
                            image representing The Vision holds a lyre that she(?) appears to
                            play.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            A third pair of figures hover or float against the right margin. The
                            gender of neither figure is distinct. The rightmost figure has short
                            hair and wears a gown. Facing forward, this figure bends its left arm to
                            hold a bowl or (wicker?) basket on its head, echoing the pose and
                            accoutrement of the long-haired figure at far left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wicker</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Echoing the pose and accoutrement of the leftmost figure in
                            the composition, the rightmost figure in the upper portion of the image
                            representing The Vision holds a bowl or (wicker?) basket on its head. A
                            few leaves appear on and above this basket or bowl.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            Four figures who may hover, float, or fly are visible in the center of
                            the image. The two uppermost of these who are both nude hold a circular
                            garland or wreath between them with one extended arm each. The body of
                            the figure at right is horizontal with head at right though its head is
                            turned to look left, perhaps back toward its companion. This figure has
                            long hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            Four figures who may hover, float, or fly are visible in the center of
                            the image. The two uppermost of these, who are both nude and positioned
                            horizontally, hold a circular garland or wreath between them with one
                            extended arm each. The short-haired figure at left faces forward but
                            extends its legs left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>laurel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wreath</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>garland</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two nude figures hover, float, or
                            fly above the sleeping Queen Katharine and hold a garland, perhaps of
                            laurels, between them. This object may represent one of the garlands
                            mentioned in the play's text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>riding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            Four figures are visible in the center of the image, one of whom rides a
                            horse. The rider appears to be male, with short hair and an open mouth.
                            He wears a shirt and breeches(?). Facing forward and slightly right, he
                            bends forward and touches the horse's neck with his bent right arm,
                            perhaps encouraging his horse toward the figure in front of them. Both
                            horse and rider may look toward this figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the upper part of the image representing The
                            Vision, a male figure rides a horse forward and to the right. Clouds
                            obscure most of the animal's lower body, but its tail swishes
                            prominently. Both horse and rider may look toward the male figure in
                            front of them at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throwing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the sleeping figure of Queen Katharine, The Vision
                            itself constitutes the upper part of the image and includes ten figures.
                            Four figures who may hover, float, or fly are visible in the center of
                            the image. The lowest of these is a male figure, who is nude but for a
                            single swath of drapery covering his genitals, has short hair, and wears
                            a quiver on his back with a bow and the end of at least one arrow
                            visible. His mouth may be open. He extends both arms horizontally, palms
                            facing up, and may hold or touch an object (perhaps another garland or
                            leaves) visible near his left hand and just above the sleeping figure's
                            head. He may be throwing the leaves downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>arrow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quiver</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lowest figure in the upper part of the image representing
                            The Vision of Queen Katharine wears a quiver on his back that appears to
                            hold at least one arrow, visible behind his right shoulder. The ends of
                            his bow are visible behind his right shoulder and below his left
                            hip.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>garland</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and behind the Queen Katharine's head and just below the
                            extended left arm of the lowest visionary figure, an indeterminate
                            object composed of several small circles appears to hover. This object
                            may represent another garland or branch such as those mentioned in the
                            play's text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Blue sky is visible along the upper edge of the image with
                            colorful clouds(?) and beams of light below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but247.1.penandink.01.01" justify="left" indent="49">WB<note>This pen and
                            ink inscription is probably not by Blake. It was partly cut off at the
                            bottom when the edge of the paper was trimmed.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
