<bad id="but218r.1" type="penc"
    work="Sketches for ‘The Book of Thel’: Thel and the Clod of Clay, and Thel Fleeing From the House of Clay"
    copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="218r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title
                    reg="Sketches for ‘The Book of Thel’: Thel and the Clod of Clay, and Thel Fleeing From the House of Clay">
                    <main>Sketches for "The Book of Thel": Thel and the Clod of Clay, and Thel
                        Fleeing From the House of Clay</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work copyright © 2018 British Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>October 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Sketches for "The Book of Thel": Thel and the Clod of Clay, and Thel
                        Fleeing From the House of Clay</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author. Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription,
                        lower right.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1789">c. 1789<note>The date is based on the relationship between
                        this preliminary drawing and *The Book of Thel*, dated 1789 on its title
                        page.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>22.4 x 31.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22.4 x 31.7 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and
                        ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>top portion only of a fleur-de-lis watermark</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1982</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>approximately &#163;3000</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by
                    Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer
                    Bernard Quaritch, offered in his Nov. 1882 catalogue, item 346 with 39 other
                    works (&#163;36), catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, item 13843, same group and
                    price, *Catalogue of Works on the Fine Arts* of Oct. 1883, item 13843, same
                    group and price, and catalogue of *William Blake's Original Drawings* of May
                    1885, no item number, same group and price; sold by Quaritch on 30 June 1886 to
                    W. Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949,
                    lot 63 with four other works by Blake (&#163;42 to the dealer Maggs Bros. Ltd.);
                    offered by Maggs, 1949 catalogue 117 of Sept. 1949, item 498 (&#163;35); the
                    dealer Ernest Seligmann; sold 1960 to W. A. Caro; his daughter, Ann Caro,
                    probably by gift or inheritance; sold by Ann Caro to the British Museum in late
                    1982 for approximately &#163;3000 and accessioned by the Museum in 1983. </note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings:
                    prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1983,0305.1</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but218r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT218.1.1r.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Sketches for "The Book of Thel": Thel and the Clod of
                    Clay, and Thel Fleeing From the House of Clay</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 218 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This pencil sketch is a preliminary for two plates in Blake's *The Book of
                        Thel* of 1789. The mock-up of the plate on the left includes the design used
                        on Bentley plate 7, but in this sketch it appears as a headpiece above the
                        roman numeral indicating the beginning of chapter III, which begins on
                        Bentley plate 6 in the poem. The mock-up on the right would thus presumably
                        be for the next plate, Bentley plate 7. The design, apparently showing Thel
                        standing in front of the "house" of the "matron Clay" (Erdman page 6), was
                        not used in *The Book of Thel*. This rejected design lends support to the
                        supposition that Blake originally intended a different ending for his
                        illuminated book than the one present in all extant copies. The design,
                        however, might illustrate the present ending of the poem when Thel flees the
                        house of Clay (the grave) to return to "the vales of Har" (Erdman page 6).
                        See also the sketch on the verso of this leaf, a preliminary drawing for the
                        design on Bentley plate 6 of *The Book of Thel*.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>22.4 x 31.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This pencil sketch is a preliminary for two plates in Blake's *The
                        Book of Thel* of 1789. The mock-up of the plate on the left includes the
                        design used on Bentley plate 7, but in this sketch it appears as a headpiece
                        above the roman numeral indicating the beginning of chapter III, which
                        begins on Bentley plate 6 in the poem. The mock-up on the right would thus
                        presumably be for the next plate, Bentley plate 7. The design, apparently
                        showing Thel standing in front of the "house" of the "matron Clay" (Erdman
                        page 6), was not used in *The Book of Thel*. In the design at left, a
                        vignette (or headpiece) of Thel, a seated gowned woman in a contracted
                        position with legs drawn up and arms crossed over her knees, occupies the
                        top register above horizontal lines, indicating the position of a text, in
                        the lower half. The larger figure below her is the "matron Clay"; the
                        smaller figure to the left is the infant "Worm" (Erdman page 6). The
                        composition at right contains similar horizontal lines indicating text in
                        the upper register while the vignette (or tailpiece) below depicts Thel with
                        outstretched arms in front of the house of Clay as three figures fly or
                        hover above. These last figures may be Thel's "moans" which "flew o'er my
                        [the Clay's] roof" (Erdman page 6).</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms folded</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Thel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The top half of the rectangular sketch at left depicts a
                            vignette of Thel, a seated gowned woman in a contracted position with
                            legs drawn up and arms crossed over her knees. Bending forward, she
                            turns her head down; her long hair may be pulled back in a bun. She may
                            look down at the two smaller figures on the ground in front of
                            her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Worm</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two smaller figures sit or recline on the ground in front of
                            the seated female figure in the composition at left. The figure at left,
                            who may lean against the larger figure's gown, is the infant "Worm"
                            (*The Book of Thel*, Erdman page 6), facing forward and right with legs
                            extended forward, toward the viewer. This figure has curly hair and is
                            nude. Its slightly bent arms are visible by its sides, and it may look
                            toward the second figure at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying on side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Clod</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two smaller figures sit or recline on the ground in front of
                            the seated female figure in the composition at left. The figure at right
                            is the "matron Clay" (*The Book of Thel*, Erdman page 6), a nude female
                            figure who reclines on her side facing forward with head at left turned
                            to look toward her companion at left. The matron Clay is also referred
                            to in the poem as the "Clod of Clay" (Erdman page 5). She appears to
                            have short hair. Her left arm is extended and braced on the ground while
                            her right is raised horizontally to reach or lean forward and touch the
                            shoulder of the infant. Her legs are extended with the left crossed over
                            the right near the knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Various types of vegetation surround the three figures
                            depicted in the top half of the sketch at left. There appear to be vines
                            or perhaps the stems of flowers (perhaps with blossoms?) at right and
                            additional, albeit indeterminate, vegetation at left. There may be a
                            tall lily visible at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower half of the rectangular composition at left,
                            horizontal lines act as stand-ins for the lines of text that appear in
                            later versions of plate 6 in *The Book of Thel* Above these lines is the
                            chapter number, "III" (see the Textual Transcription).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Thel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vignette in the bottom half of the sketch at right depicts
                            Thel, a figure standing before a structure, as three figures fly or
                            hover above. Thel, who may be gowned, stands or walks facing forward and
                            to the left with one leg extended backward and arms raised between the
                            horizontal and 135 degrees. This figure may have its hair arranged in a
                            bun(?). Thel may be fleeing the house, much as she "Fled back unhinderd
                            ... into the vales of Har" at the end of *The Book of Thel* (Erdman page
                            6). The design may be an alternative version for the tailpiece on
                            Bentley plate 7 of *The Book of Thel*. The design published in that
                            position is the one depicted upper left in this drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vignette in the bottom half of the sketch at right depicts
                            Thel, a figure standing before a structure, as three figures fly or
                            hover above. The building appears to be a one-story structure with a
                            slanted roof and vertical posts lining both of the visible exterior
                            walls. The figure appears to stand in an open doorway (though the door
                            inside is not clearly depicted). The structure is probably the "house"
                            of the "matron Clay" (Erdman page 6).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vignette in the bottom half of the sketch at right depicts
                            Thel standing before a structure as three figures fly or hover above.
                            These flying figures may be Thel's "moans" which "flew o'er my [the
                            Clay's] roof" (Erdman page 6). The highest of these figures is
                            positioned horizontally with head at left, facing left with head up and
                            mouth open(?). Its arms are raised at 135 degrees with fingers spread.
                            Both legs are extended with one raised diagonally upward. This figure
                            appears to wear clothing of some sort (perhaps a shirt and pants?)
                            though the details of these are indistinct.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vignette in the bottom half of the sketch at right depicts
                            a figure entering or exiting a structure as three figures fly or hover
                            above. These flying figures may be Thel's "moans" which "flew o'er my
                            [the Clay's] roof" (Erdman page 6). The middle figure is positioned
                            horizontally with head at left, facing forward, and appears to wear a
                            gown. Its arms are bent upward and legs extended together. The figure
                            may look down toward the standing figure of Thel below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms reaching downward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vignette in the bottom half of the sketch at right depicts
                            a figure entering or exiting a structure as three figures fly or hover
                            above. These flying figures may be Thel's "moans" which "flew o'er my
                            [the Clay's] roof" (Erdman page 6). The lowest of these figures is also
                            the smallest and may be a child or infant. This figure is positioned
                            diagonally downward with head at right, facing right perhaps to look at
                            the standing figure of Thel below. Both arms appears to be raised
                            horizontally and may reach toward the standing figure. It may extend one
                            leg backward and bend one leg at the knee, though these details are
                            indistinct.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Along the left edge of the vignette in the composition at
                            right, a large tree is visible. Its thick trunk, which may be wrapped
                            with vines near the base, grows up the left margin. Several short
                            branches, perhaps with leaves, are visible at left while, at right, one
                            sizeable branch appears to grow rightward along the upper margin of the
                            scene, above the three flying figures. This branch produces several
                            smaller branches that may have leaves that grow downward near the right
                            side of the design and hang over the roof of the structure below.
                            Alternatively, the lines upper right in this vignette may be clouds
                            and/or background hills.</illusobjdesc>
                        <component type="object" location="D">
                            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                            <illusobjdesc>In the vignette lower right, the lines upper right may be
                                part of the large tree growing left of the house, but might be
                                independent motifs such as clouds or background
                                hills.</illusobjdesc>
                        </component>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the top half of the rectangular composition at right,
                            horizontal lines act as stand-ins for the lines of text; however, this
                            plate design was replaced in the final version of *The Book of
                            Thel*.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but218r.1.penink.01.01" justify="left">III<note>This roman numeral,
                            written in pencil by Blake, is a chapter number for *The Book of Thel*.
                            In that book, chapter III begins on Bentley plate 6.</note></l>
                    <l n="but218r.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="44">By William
                            Blake<note>This pen and ink inscription, lines 2-4, is by Frederick
                            Tatham.</note></l>
                    <l n="but218r.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="44">attested by</l>
                    <l n="but218r.1.penink.01.04" justify="left" indent="46">
                        <hi rend="underscore">Frederick Tatham</hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
