<bad id="but207r.1" type="penc" work="Ugolino in Prison" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="vanda"
    catalog="butlin" catid="207r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Ugolino in Prison">
                    <main>Ugolino in Prison</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work copyright © 2018 Victoria and Albert Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
                        <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>May 2003</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Amy Havlan, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Ugolino in Prison</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author. The pen and ink inscription below the
                        design has been attributed to Frederick Tatham.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>17.5 x 22.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>27.3 x 31.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The inscription below the design is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name>
                <date>1881</date>
                <dealer>E. Parsons</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by
                    Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold Sotheby's,
                    29 April 1862, possibly lot 200 or 201 with 33 other works (2s. or 3s. to the
                    dealer Francis Harvey) or lot 160 with four other works (9s. to George A.
                    Smith); Smith by 1876, sold Christie's, 10 July 1880, in lot 121 or 122 (each
                    lot bought by the dealer E. Parsons for 3s.); sold by Parsons to the Victoria
                    and Albert Museum in 1881.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Victoria and Albert Museum</institution>
                <addressline>South Kensington</addressline>
                <addressline>Cromwell Road</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW7 2RL</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7942 2000</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images Agency: +44 (0)20 7942 2479</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images Agency: +44 (0)20 7942 2482</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Images Agency: vaimages@vam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.vam.ac.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Finding and Buying Images:
                    http://www.vam.ac.uk/resources/buying/index.html</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">8763.B</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but207r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT207.1.1r.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Ugolino in Prison</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 207 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The pen and ink inscription below the design is attributed to Frederick
                        Tatham in Butlin 207. The inscription lower right, "8763.B," is the Victoria
                        and Albert Museum accession number written by a curator, probably c. 1881.
                        See also the verso of this leaf, *Head of a Man and Small Head of Ugolino*,
                        Butlin 207 verso. This recto pencil sketch is closely related to a
                        monochrome wash drawing of approximately the same date, *Ugolino: "Does Thy
                        God, O Priest, Take Such Vengeance as This?"*, Butlin 208. Blake executed
                        several similar designs based on the subject of Ugolino in prison with his
                        sons and grandsons, including a pencil sketch in his Notebook, Butlin
                        201.59; *For Children: The Gates of Paradise*, Bentley plate 14; *For the
                        Sexes: The Gates of Paradise*, Bentley plate 14; *The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell*, Bentley plate 16; *Ugolino and His Sons in Prison* among the Dante
                        water colors, Butlin 812.68; and the tempera painting, *Count Ugolino and
                        His Sons in Prison*, Butlin 805. The present sketch is not a direct
                        preliminary drawing for any of these later works.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>17.5 x 22.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In a rectangular composition positioned against the right margin
                        of the leaf, five figures sit in what appears to be the dark interior space
                        of a prison. The central figure is Ugolino, a gowned male with curly hair
                        standing on end and a beard. He sits cross-legged facing forward. His arms
                        are at his sides. His facial expression suggests fear, despair, or madness.
                        The other figures are his sons and grandsons. The rightmost figure, a nude
                        male with long hair, sits or leans against a wall facing left with left arm
                        by his side, hand clenched in a fist. His extended legs touch those of his
                        companion at far left; his left ankle may be shackled. He turns his head up
                        in a gesture that suggests despair. The second figure from the right sits
                        with legs drawn up facing forward against the rear wall. He has long hair
                        and may wear a gown. With arms by his sides, he turns his head up and to the
                        left, perhaps to look toward the central figure. The second figure from the
                        left, a nude(?) male with long hair, sits with legs drawn up facing forward
                        and looking right, likely toward the central figure. His right arm is by his
                        side with hand braced on the ground. The fifth and leftmost figure sits or
                        leans against a wall facing right with head turned down and eye closed. He
                        may wear a gown. His right arm is visible by his side with open palm braced
                        on the ground, and his extended legs touch those of his companion at far
                        right. Behind the central figure, several horizontal lines suggest a heavy,
                        barred door in this prison. The diagonal shading of the interior walls
                        indicates the darkness of the space.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ugolino</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ugolino</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In a rectangular composition positioned against the right
                            margin of the leaf, five figures sit in what appears to be the dark
                            interior space of a prison. The central figure is Ugolino, a gowned male
                            with curly hair standing on end and a beard. He sits cross-legged facing
                            forward. His arms are at his sides. His facial expression suggests fear,
                            despair, or madness.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure, a nude male with long hair, sits or
                            leans against a wall facing left with left arm by his side, hand
                            clenched in a fist on the ground. His extended, slightly bent legs touch
                            those of his companion at far left; his left ankle may be shackled. He
                            turns his head up in a gesture that suggests despair. He is one of the
                            sons or grandsons of Ugolino who is imprisoned with his
                            family.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure may wear a shackle around his left
                            ankle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the right sits with legs drawn up
                            facing forward against the rear wall. He has long hair and appears to
                            wear a gown. With arms by his sides, he turns his head up and to the
                            left, perhaps to look toward the central figure. He is one of the sons
                            or grandsons of Ugolino who is imprisoned with his
                            family.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the left, a nude(?) male with long
                            hair, sits with legs drawn up facing forward and looking right, likely
                            toward the central figure. His right arm is by his side with hand braced
                            on the ground. He is one of the sons or grandsons of Ugolino who is
                            imprisoned with his family.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The fifth and leftmost figure sits or leans against a wall
                            facing right with head turned down and eye closed. He may wear a gown.
                            His right arm is visible by his side with open palm on the ground, and
                            his extended legs touch those of his companion at far right. His posture
                            suggests despair. He is one of the sons or grandsons of Ugolino who is
                            imprisoned with his family.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prison</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dungeon</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the central figure, several horizontal lines suggest a
                            heavy, barred door. The diagonal shading of the interior walls indicates
                            the darkness of the space. The identification of these figures as
                            Ugolino and his sons and grandsons indicates the space is a prison
                            cell.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but207r.1.penink.01.01" justify="left">Original sketch for the
                            Ugolino.<note>This pen and ink inscription is attributed to Frederick
                            Tatham in Butlin 207. The inscription lower right, "8763.B," is the
                            Victoria and Albert Museum accession number written by a curator,
                            probably c. 1881.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
