<bad id="but370.1" type="penink" work="A Garden Path, Eartham" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="370" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Garden Path, Eartham">
                    <main>A Garden Path, Eartham</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2015 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>A Garden Path, Eartham</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author, </role>
                    <role>delineator.  Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription, lower right.</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1801">1801<note>Blake executed this drawing while living in Felpham, Sussex, Sept. 1800 to Sept. 1803.  Like Felpham, Eartham is a village in the district of Chichester.  A similar drawing, Butlin 369, shows the former house of Blake's patron, William Hayley, in Eartham.  This related drawing can be dated to 1801 because Hayley and Blake visited the house in Nov. 1801 (see Bentley, *Records*, page 113).  The present drawing very probably dates from about the same time.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>27.4 x 41.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>27.4 x 41.7 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1967</date>
                <dealer>Colnaghi</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; Frederick Tatham at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his catalogue of Nov. 1882, item 346 with forty-four other works as listed in Butlin 79 (£36), the same group, catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, item 13,843 (same price), the same group, catalogue of Oct. 1883, item 13,843 (same price), and the same group, May 1885 catalogue of *William Blake's Original Drawings*, pages 1-2, no item number (same price); sold 30 June 1886 to W. Graham Robertson; sold from his collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 80 with three other works as listed in Butlin 370 (£73.10s. to the dealer Thomas Agnew &amp; Sons); L. G. Duke; sold 1952 to the dealer Colnaghi; Lord Eccles; returned to the dealer Colnaghi; sold to the British Museum in 1967.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1967,0617.10</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but370.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT370.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Garden Path, Eartham</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 370)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>27.4 x 41.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A landscape scene, the drawing illustrates a field with twelve distinct trees, most arranged along diagonal lines, in the foreground and additional fields, trees, and other vegetation in the background.  Most of the foregrounded trees have slender trunks with few branches near the base though they are very leafy at the tops.  There may be one willow tree near the center of the composition and perhaps and an oak at far left.  The long shadows cast by the trunks suggest the time is early morning near sunrise or late afternoon near sunset.  A path or road extends from the center of the lower margin diagonally to the right, where it seems to disappear over a hill.  Shading in an area near the middle of the left margin may suggest reflections on a body of water, perhaps a lake.  Several clouds are visible in the sky in the upper left corner of the scene.  The drawing may be a representation of the garden at Eartham, William Hayley's home until 1800.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>willow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The drawing illustrates twelve distinct trees in the foreground.  Ten of these trees have slender trunks with few branches near the base though they are very leafy at the tops.  The eighth tree from the right in the center of the composition appears to be a willow tree.  The leftmost tree in the foreground has a thicker base and denser foliage, suggesting it too is a specific species (perhaps an oak?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hedge</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In addition to the twelve trees in the foreground, additional fields, trees, plants, and other vegetation are visible in the background.  What appears to be a denser area of vegetation slightly left of center may be a hedge.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The long shadows cast by the trunks suggest the time is early morning near sunrise or late afternoon near sunset.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>path</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>road</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A path or road extends from the center of the lower margin diagonally to the right, where it seems to disappear over a low hill.  Small circles and semi-circles along the edges of the path suggest it is lined, perhaps with stones or tufts of grass.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shading in an area near the middle of the left margin may suggest reflections on a body of water, perhaps a lake.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several clouds are visible in the sky in the upper left corner of the scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but370.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="44">Landscape Drawn by</l>
                    <l n="but370.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="52">William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but370.1.penink.01.03" justify="left" indent="58">Frederick Tatham.<note>This inscription was penned by Frederick Tatham.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>