<bad id="but396.1" type="paint" work="St. Matthew" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="private" catalog="butlin" catid="396" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="St. Matthew"><main>St. Matthew</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 21KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 600KB to 1400KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
         
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and color correction, BAD creation, illustration markup, final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2013-March 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle ,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*St. Matthew*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1799">c. 1799</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>37.2 x 25.7 cm.</objsize><medium>water-based tempera with a glue and/or gum binder and with pen and ink outlining</medium><support>canvas</support><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>private collection</name><date>1971 or later</date><dealer>Galleria Galatea</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Acquired, and probably commissioned, from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1799; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; William Michael Rossetti by 1863; William Bell Scott by 1876, sold from his collection Sotheby's, 14 July 1892, lot 238 (£27 to the dealer Bernard Quaritch); offered by Quaritch, *Rough List* no. 127 of August 1892, item 916 (£36), and *Miscellaneous Catalogue* no. 62 of 1893, no item no. (£36); sold 9 May 1893 to E. H. van Ingen acting for Mrs. William Emerson and sold from her collection Sotheby's, 19 May 1958, lot 12 (£1300 to the dealer Thomas Agnew &amp; Sons acting for Gwen, Lady Melchett); sold from Melchett's collection, Christie's, 9 Nov. 1971, lot 71 (£5250 to Piccadilly Gallery); sold by Piccadilly Gallery to the Galleria Galatea, Turin, Italy, by whom sold to a private collector, Milan, Italy.  On the market through Nicholas Lott of Larkhall Fine Art, Bath, in Nov. 2013; present whereabouts unknown but possibly still in the private collection in Milan.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Private Collection</institution></repository></source><desc id="but396.1.pt.01" dbi="BUT396.1.1.PT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">St. Matthew</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="U1">(Butlin 396)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The Hebrew letters on the scroll held by the angel are now worn and difficult to interpret.  They would seem to represent the idea of a Hebrew inscription without actually being an intelligible text.</p></objnote><objsize>37.2 x 25.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="780" height="600"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The figures of St. Matthew and the angel fill this design.  St. Matthew stands in front of but is shorter than his companion; the angel's head and shoulders are visible above Matthew's head.  The angel stands facing forward, but turns his head slightly left and tilts it down.  His enormous wings are folded but spread to either side of his body.  He extends his slightly bent right arm down to the left at 45 degrees, and grasps one end of a scroll with his raised right hand.  His left hand holds the other side of the scroll, and is visible just below Matthew's raised hands.  The angel seems to be nude, and has short curly hair.  Light surrounds his head and upper body, forming a halo or kind of mandorla.  The angel holds the scroll open in front of Matthew, who bends his head to read the lines of Hebrew text visible on the scroll's surface.  St. Matthew stands in a semi-crouched position facing left.  His shoulders are slightly hunched.  His left arm is by his side, drawn forward slightly and bent across his torso at the elbow.  His raised left hand is open, with the fingers spread and the vertical palm facing away.  His right hand is also raised in front of his chest, and mirrors the left in position.  These hand gestures and his open mouth suggest surprise.  His bent left leg is forward.  The shape of his garments suggests that his right leg is also bent and extended backwards.  He wears a long gown, belted at a high waistline.  His left foot emerges from beneath its folds.  He has a beard and short curly hair.  Its color suggests his age.  To either side of Matthew's lower body, but especially on the left, the angel's light reveals the bricks in a wall, or possibly an altar, behind the figures.  Dark shadow surrounds Matthew and the angel, stretching to the edges of the design on the bottom and the left and right sides.  The design is not based on any specific passage in the gospel of Matthew.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>mandorla</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures of St. Matthew and the angel fill this design.  St. Matthew stands in front of but is shorter than his companion; the angel's head and shoulders are visible above Matthew's head.  The angel stands facing forward, but turns his head slightly left and tilts it down.  His enormous wings are folded but spread to either side of his body.  He extends his slightly bent right arm down to the left at 45 degrees, and grasps one end of a scroll with his raised right hand.  His left hand holds the other side of the scroll, and is visible just below Matthew's raised hands.  The angel seems to be nude, and has short curly hair.  Light surrounds his head and upper body, forming a halo or kind of mandorla.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures of St. Matthew and the angel fill this design.  St. Matthew stands in front of but is shorter than his companion; the angel's head and shoulders are visible above Matthew's head.  The angel holds open a scroll in front of Matthew, who bends his head to read the lines of Hebrew text visible on the scroll's surface.  The now worn and distorted Hebrew letters are difficult to interpret; they do not appear to form an intelligible text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Matthew</characteristic><characteristic>saint</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures of St. Matthew and the angel fill this design. St. Matthew stands in front of but is shorter than his companion; the angel's head and shoulders are visible above Matthew's head.  St. Matthew stands in a semi-crouched position facing left.  His shoulders are slightly hunched and his head is tilted down; he seems to be reading the open scroll that the angel holds before him.  His left arm is by his side, drawn forward slightly and bent across his torso at the elbow.  His raised left hand is open, with the fingers spread and the vertical palm facing away.  His right hand is also raised in front of his chest, and mirrors the left in position.  These hand gestures and his open mouth suggest surprise.  His bent left leg is forward.  The shape of his garment suggests that his right leg is also bent and extended backwards.  He wears a long gown, belted at a high waistline.  His left foot emerges from beneath its folds.  He has a beard and short curly hair.  Its color suggests his age.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>brick</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><characteristic>altar</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures of St. Matthew and the angel fill this design.  Light surrounds the angel's head and upper body, forming a halo or kind of mandorla.  To either side of Matthew's lower body, but especially on the left, the angel's light reveals the bricks in a wall, or possibly an altar, behind the figures. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figures of St. Matthew and the angel fill this design.  Dark shadow surrounds them, stretching to the edges of the design on the bottom and the left and right sides.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>