<bad id="but313.1" type="cprint" work="Pity" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="313" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Pity"><main>Pity</main>
                    : electronic edition
                </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                    Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the Library of Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software grants from Sun Microsystems
                </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
                10918)
                files ranging in size from 99KB to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH<date>November 2004</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright ©  <date>2004</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
            and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
            shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
            Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
            express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
            publisher.
            Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
            granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
            This image copyright © 2004 British Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>February 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration description</change><date>Spring 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Michelle Langston</name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Sarah Tolf </name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Republication using virtual group DTD 2008</change><date>2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Tolf </name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Pity*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>printer, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1795.A">1795</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1795.A">c. 1795<note>The smaller size of this impression indicates that it was printed from a different matrix than the other versions of *Pity* (Butlin 310-12).  This impression was probably a preliminary attempt, printed before the other versions and possibly in 1794.</note></printdate><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>19.7 x 27.5 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>27.7 x 36.2 cm.</leafsize><medium>color printed from a metal plate etched very slightly in relief and with water color and pen and ink additions to the impression</medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><support>paper, probably wove</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>loose</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1874</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis, who gave the print to the British Museum in 1874.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 44-2076-361555</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><collection>British Museum</collection><repositoryid label="Accession number">1874.12.12.380</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but313.1.cprint.01" dbi="BUT313.1.1.CPD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Pity</title>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="U313">(Butlin 313)</objcode><objcode code="B1"/></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This impression of "Pity" is considerably smaller than 
                    all the other color printed drawings; the coloring of the human figures and the horse is clearly unfinished.  The print was probably a trial effort at planographic color printing and may have preceded all the other color printed drawings (or at least all those printed planographically) in date of composition and printing.</p><p>"Pity" illustrates lines from Shakespeare's *Macbeth*, Act 1, Scene 7: "And Pity, like a naked new-born babe,/ Striding the blast, or heav'n's cherubin hors'd/ Upon the sightless couriers of the air...."  The closed eye of the horse suggests that Blake has transposed sightlessness from the observer (one who cannot see the wind) to the observed (blind horses).  The design would seem to be a positive image of compassion, but some of Blake's writings of the 1790s indicate that it is only the useless product of a fallen condition.  As he writes in "The Human Abstract" in "Songs of Experience," "Pity would be no more,/ If we did not make somebody Poor" (Erdman page 27).</p><p>The coloring on the human figures and on the horse is clearly unfinished.</p></objnote><objsize>19.7 x 27.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="550"/></physdesc><related objectid="but310.1.cprint.01"/><related objectid="but311.1.cprint.01"/><related objectid="but312.1.cprint.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Two figures, one of whom holds a baby, ride back-to-back on a horse and soar above a supine woman below.  The horse extends at least one front leg, and both hind legs, horizontally in a posture suggestive of leaping, striding, or flying.  The horse's mouth is open; a rein extends from it toward the horse's neck.  Its mane flies forward and its tail streams backward and up.  The front-most figure, one of Shakespeare's "cherubin" (angels), wears a gown that covers her lower body, sits on the horse with her right leg drawn up, but turns her upper body to face the viewer.  With both of her arms, she reaches down to hold the child, who stands with his right foot on the fingertips of her left hand.  With her right hand she supports the child.  Her flame-like hair stands on end, angled to the left.  She may be looking down toward the woman lying below, or perhaps toward the child.  The child faces away from the viewer, but bends its head and body backwards to look up towards the female who holds him.  The child’s right leg is extended down and back; its left leg is not pictured.  Its arms are raised horizontally (or between the horizontal and 135 degrees).  Behind the front-most female figure, and facing away from the viewer, is another figure of uncertain gender (more likely male than female?) with semi-long hair.  This figure’s upper body is nude, but the drapery streaming out behind him suggests that a gown covers his lower body.  His arms are extended horizontally with the left palm probably down.  Beneath the horse and the figures above lies a supine, gowned female with long hair.  Her arms are bent at the elbows and her hands clasped on her breast with fingers interlinked in an attitude of prayer.  Her head is bent back in a limp posture.  Her eyes are open, pupils raised; her mouth is open and we can see her teeth.  The horse flies over clouds.  The woman lies on the ground, which may be covered with low-growing vegetation (grass, moss, or lichens).  Long grass or reeds bend to the right over her upper legs.  The background is dark; this is certainly a stormy scene, and may be a night scene.  Two other impressions of this color print picture two horses, but there is no clear representation of a second horse in this impression.  Uncolored areas to the right and left of the figure with arms extended horizontally may have been reserved for picturing a second horse, particularly its tail and head.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>straddling</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The front-most female figure in the upper part of the design, whose lower body is draped with a gown, rides a horse.  She is probably one of the "cherubin" (that is, angels) in the text illustrated (Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>).  Her right leg is drawn up, her lower body faces to the right, and she turns her upper body to face the viewer.  With both of her arms, she reaches down to hold the child, who stands on one foot on the fingertips of her left hand; she supports the child with her right hand.  Her long, flame-like hair stands on end, angled to the left.  She may be looking down toward the woman lying below, or perhaps toward the child.  She sits on a blanket draped over the horse’s back.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horziontally</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>crucified</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>pity</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male child or infant with short, curly hair stands (or hovers) with his right foot on tiptoe on the fingers of the central female figure.  The child faces away from the viewer, but bends its head and body backwards to look up towards the female who holds him.  The child’s right leg is extended down and back; his left leg is not pictured.  His arms are raised horizontally (or between the horizontal and 135 degrees) in a cruciform posture.  The child probably personifies pity in the passage illustrated from Shakepseare's <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>partially nude</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the front-most female figure, and facing away from the viewer, another figure is pictured, apparently riding on or hovering behind the horse.  This figure's gender is uncertain, but is more likely male than female.  His hair is short but bushy.  He is probably one of the "cherubin" (that is, angels) in the text illustrated (Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>).  This figure's upper body appears to be nude, but the drapery streaming out behind him suggests that a gown covers his (unpictured) lower body.  His arms are extended horizontally with the palm of his left hand apparently down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="E"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>rein</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>blind</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>leaping</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A horse soars above the supine female figure.  The horse has at least the right front leg and both hind legs extended horizontally.  The horse may have its right eye closed (no pupil is pictured), or perhaps it is blind in accord with Blake's response to the text illustrated ("sightless couriers").  The horse's mouth is open; a rein extends from its mouth toward its neck.  The horse's mane flies forward, and its tail streams backwards and up.  The horse has a blanket draped over its back, visible to the left of its rider.  Two other impressions of this color print picture two horses, but there is no clear evidence of a second horse in this impression.  Uncolored areas to the right and left of the figure with arms extended horizontally may have been reserved for picturing a second horse, particularly its tail and head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the horse and the figures above lies a supine female with long, slightly curly hair whose head is bent back limply.  She may be the mother of the new-born child above.  Her arms and shoulders are bare, but a gown covers the rest of her body and wraps around her feet, almost like a shroud (although she is probably not dead).  Her arms are bent at the elbows and her hands clasped on her breast with fingers interlinked in an attitude of prayer.  Her eyes are open, with pupils raised, and her mouth is slightly open, with teeth visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The horse flies above (and probably in front of) clouds.  A wind apparently blows from left to right, as indicated by the forward angle of the horse's mane and the angle of the long grasses or reeds covering the supine woman's upper legs.  The background of this stormy scene is dark; it may be night.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>moss</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>reed</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The supine woman may be lying on low-growing vegetation, such as grass, moss, or lichens.  Long grasses or reeds arch over her lower legs.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>