
<bad id="but343.1" type="paint" work="Eighteen Heads of Poets: Chaucer" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="manchester" catalog="butlin" catid="343.5" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt><title reg="Eighteen Heads of Poets: Chaucer"><main>Eighteen Heads of Poets: Chaucer</main>
                : electronic edition
            </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                    Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt/>
                <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
                10918) files ranging in size from 500KB to 1800KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2021</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2023</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
            and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
            shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
            Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
            express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
            publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
            granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
            This image copyright © 2023 Manchester Art Gallery</userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created and publication in preview mode</change>
                <date>April 2023</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester; 
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and 
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf, </name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Natasha Bharucha, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer, </name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian, </name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green, </name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Rob Rich, </name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose, </name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
                    <name>Iftekhar Uddin, </name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired</change>
                <date>July 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester; 
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and 
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William S. Shaw</name>        
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>*Eighteen Heads of Poets: Chaucer*</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1800.A">c.1800-1803</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>42.5 x 63.7 cm.</objsize>
                <medium>water-based tempera with a glue and/or gum binder and with some pen and ink outlining</medium>
                <support>canvas</support>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1"><name>Manchester Art Gallery</name>
                <date>1885</date>
                <dealer>Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>The group of eighteen paintings commissioned by William Hayley c. 1800; his cousin, Captain Godfrey, by inheritance in 1820; the group sold c. 1840 and dispersed (C. J. Toovey had at least five of the paintings); reunited by William Russell by 1863; sold Christies, 5 Dec. 1884, lots 109-26 (&#163;124.19s. to the dealer Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons); sold by Agnew in 1885 to the Manchester City Art Gallery (now the Manchester Art Gallery).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository><institution>Manchester Art Gallery</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1885.4</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        
        <desc id="but343.5.1.pt.01" dbi="BUT343.5.1.PT">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">Eighteen Heads of Poets: Chaucer</title>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U5">(Butlin 343.5)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote><p>This painting is one of the eighteen Heads of Poets Blake designed and executed for William Hayley's Library.  Chaucer's features and dress are probably based on an engraving by George Vertue published in John Urry's 1721 *Works of Geoffrey Chaucer*.  A copy of the book was in Hayley's Library.  One detail, however, suggests that Blake may have consulted other Chaucer portraits engraved by Vertue, one issued in 1730 among his series of "Twelve Celebrated English Poets" and another published in 1737 and 1740 editions of *The Canterbury Tales*.  These two, like Blake's version, show three buttons on Chaucer's gown rather than the two buttons in the plate published with Urry's text.  In most of the eighteen paintings in the group, Blake included characters from the poet's work right and left of The central portrait.  For Chaucer, Blake pictures the Merchant on the left and the Wife of Bath on the right, both from *The Canterbury Tales*.  These are closely based on engraved headpieces, unsigned but attributable to Vertue, on pages 66 and 76 of Urry's edition of Chaucer's *Works*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>42.5 x 63.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="780" height="600"/>

</physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, the bust of a male figure, Geoffrey Chaucer, is encircled by a vegetative wreath of intertwined stems and flame-like leaves, probably a fruiting laurel wreath. The  laurel originates in the center of the lower margin and forms a circular shape which surrounds the bust entirely. Two indistinct, decorative objects, which may be palm fronds or feathers, extend upward from the middle of the left and right margins to the top corners. Situated inside the wreath, Chaucer faces left and looks downward, perhaps toward the small figure to his left. His mouth is closed but he may be smiling. He has a bare forehead, with some hair visible above his right ear, thin eyebrows, and well-defined eye lashes. His tunic or shirt has a high collar and at least three top buttons. In the lower two corners of the image, pictured outside the laurel wreath, are two figures on horseback.  These are the Merchant on the left and the Wife of Bath on the right, both from Chaucer's <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>. The Merchant faces right. He appears to wear a hat or helmet. His right leg extends forward to rest in a stirrup, and his right hand grasps a bridle. The horse faces right and is likely trotting or walking. Also on horseback, the Wife of Bath rides side-saddle and faces forward and left. She wears a hat and a veil or drapery, perhaps a wimple, that covers her shoulder and neck. The rider's horse faces left with its front left leg raised off the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Chaucer,Geoffrey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>poet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>turban</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>button</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, the bust of a male figure, Geoffrey Chaucer, is depicted. Situated inside the wreath, Chaucer faces left and looks downward, perhaps toward the small figure to his left. His mouth is closed but he may be smiling. He has a bare forehead, with some hair visible above his right ear, thin eyebrows, and well-defined eye lashes. His tunic or shirt has a high collar and at least three top buttons. His head is mostly covered by a turban-like cloth or drapery which folds across his forehead and hangs to the right side of his face, draping behind his neck and back. His beard is short, and encircles his mouth and covers his chin. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E"> 
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wreath</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, the bust of a male figure, Geoffrey Chaucer, is encircled by a vegetative wreath of intertwined stems and flame-like leaves. It is probably a fruiting laurel wreath. The circular shape of this wreath appears to be formed by two separate branches or stems of laurel which overlap in the lower margin of the image. These two branches curve outwards and up, encircling Chaucer's bust. Flame-like leaves grow from each branch. Buds or fruits appear along each branch. As they curve inward, the laurel branches bifurcate so that the stems intertwine as they reach the top margin of the image.</illusobjdesc>  
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB"> 
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two indistinct, decorate objects, which may be palm fronds or feathers, extend from the middle of the left and right margins to the top corners.</illusobjdesc>  
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Merchant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>riding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ruff</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures riding horses are depicted outside of the laurel wreath, one in each lower corner of the image. The figure on the left is the Merchant from Chaucer's <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>. He faces right. He appears to wear a hat or helmet and may have a beard. His visible right eye looks forward and may look up. Around his neck, there may be cloth or drapery that extends from his headpiece, or it may be a scarf, ruff, or armor. His upper body appears to be encased in a breastplate or dressed in a tunic or shirt. He sits or straddles the horse, and his right leg extends forward to rest in a stirrup. His right arm bends at the elbow to hold the reins with a clenched fist.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hoof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>saddle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blanket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the left corner of the image rides a horse as it walks or trots forward, facing right with its head facing down. Its left front leg is raised and bent with its left hoof above the ground. Its right front leg is extended with its hoof planted on the ground. The horse's right back leg is bent, with its right hoof above the ground. Its left back leg is extended and its hoof appears to be touching the ground. There is a blanket under the horse's saddle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Wife of Bath</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>riding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wimple</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures riding horses are depicted outside of the laurel wreath, one in each lower corner of the image. The Figure on the right is the Wife of Bath from Chaucer's <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>. She faces forward and to the left. She wears a pointed hat or helmet and, beneath it, drapery or a veil which may be a wimple that covers her neck and shoulders. She wears a robe and rides side-saddle, and bends her left arm to hold the reins with at least one hand. Her right leg appears to be bent at the knee, so that her legs are spread slightly as she sits.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mane</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hoof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>saddle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hoof</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the right corner of the image rides a horse as it walks or trots forward, facing left with its head down. The horse's left side is visible. The horse faces left with its head down, showing a curling mane. Its right front leg is raised and bent with its left hoof above the ground. Its left front leg is extended with its hoof on the ground. The horse's right back leg is bent, with its right hoof on the ground. Its left back leg is extended and its hoof appears to be touching the ground. It appears to be saddled and bridled.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>