<bad id="but475.1" type="wc" work="The Baptism of Christ" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ashmolean" catalog="butlin" catid="475" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Baptism of Christ"><main>The Baptism of Christ</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 104KB to 1600KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2011 Ashmolean Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>April 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning, metadata collection and color correction</change><date>September 2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">The Baptism of Christ</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1803">c. 1803</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>31.3 x 34.4 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>31.3 x 34.4 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Ashmolean Museum</name><date>1962</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>bequest</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1803; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; offered at Sotheby's, 26 June 1852, lot 167 (5s. to "Butts," thus indicating that the lot was bought-in if Butts was the vendor); sold from the Butts collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 113 (19s. to John Clark Strange); possibly sold to, or on consignment with, the dealer Francis Harvey and possibly the work offered in his catalogue of c. 1865; Samuel Prince, sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 11 Dec. 1865, lot 274 (£5.5s. to "Bright," probably H. A. Bright); H. S. Drummond; sold Sotheby's, 29 Jan. 1912, lot 100 (£52 to "Dunthorne," probably a dealer); Greville Macdonald by 1914; A. B. Clifton of Carfax &amp; Co., sold in 1921 to Francis Falconer Madan; bequeathed by Madan in 1962 to the Ashmolean Museum.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Ashmolean Museum</institution><addressline>Beaumont Street</addressline><addressline>Oxford OX1 2PH</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)1865 278000</addressline><addressline>Fax: +44 (0)1865 278018</addressline><addressline>Email: publications@ashmus.ox.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.ashmolean.org</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">WA1962.17.57</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but475.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT475.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Baptism of Christ</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 475)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower left with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  Inscribed on the mount, not by Blake, "This is my beloved son, in whom I am well pleased" and "Matt:<hi rend="superscript">W</hi> ch: 3:<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> v. 16:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>" and with text below.</p></objnote><objsize>31.3 x 34.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="750" height="750"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design is based on Matthew 3:16. In the center of the design stands Jesus, facing away but turned slightly right. He is mostly nude, though he has a loincloth around his waist. His left leg is bent and extended backward slightly as his left foot is on tiptoe. He has long, curly hair and a beard and bends his arms upward with his palms together as if in prayer or supplication. He may have a halo-like aura of light around his head. To the right of Jesus, and baptizing him, stands John the Baptist, facing left in profile and slightly forward, but looking up with his mouth open. He may be praying, speaking, or blessing. He has long, curly hair and a beard and wears a furry animal skin like a toga. His left arm is bent at his side with his index and middle fingers on his left hand raised as though pointing. His right arm is raised at 135 degrees and from it he pours water onto Jesus's head. His right leg is bent and extended backward as his right foot is on tiptoe. To the right of John the Baptist kneel two female figures facing left, both probably gowned with long hair. The leftmost female has her arms bent upward and her hands together as if in prayer or supplication, though she looks down. Her mouth may be open. She may be praying. Only the head and back of the rightmost female is visible. She may have her eyes closed. 
  To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. Only the top of the head of the leftmost figure is visible, with long hair, though a gown may be partly visible along the lower left margin of the design. The second figure from the left in this group of kneeling figures is that of a gowned female with long hair pulled up into a bun. She wears a gold band in her hair. The third figure from the left is a gowned female with long, slightly curly hair. She bends her right arm upward and holds it to her chest. Her head faces slightly forward. The fourth figure from the left in this group is an old man with long hair and a beard. He looks down but bends his arms upward with his palms together as though in prayer or supplication. The fifth figure from the left in this group is gowned but of indeterminable gender. The sixth figure from the left is a nude or mostly nude male, who may have a strip of cloth covering his genitals. He has long hair and bends one leg underneath him, drawing the right knee up. He bends his right arm upward around his head and faces slightly forward. His facial expression suggests pain or despair.
  On the left of the group of kneeling figures stands a gowned female, facing left and away, but looking up and to the right. Her left arm is at her side and her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe, perhaps to suggest that she is walking. She has long, slightly curly hair that spirals to the right. Jesus, John the Baptist, and nine other figures stand or kneel in the Jordan River. On either side of the river in the background rise small mountains or large hills, dotted with indeterminate leafy vegetation. The riverbanks are sandy. The sky in the background is slightly cloudy. 
  In the top center of the design is the dove of the Holy Ghost, seen from behind and facing down, perhaps flying downward. Its wings are spread and it has an aura of light and beams of light emanating from it. To the right and left of the dove hover gowned and winged angels, most likely all male. There are at least ten angels to the left and seven to the right. They may all be looking at Jesus. The angels on the left of the design face right and slightly forward, as well as down. The first and fourth angels from the left have long hair, while the second and third from the left have short, curly hair. Their mouths may be open. They may be speaking, singing and/or praying. The second and fourth angels from the left hold (and presumably play) tambourines; the third angel from the left hands and plays a lyre. The angels on the right of the design face left and slightly forward as well as down. The rearmost angel as well as the first and second from the right have long hair, while the second and third from the left have short, curly hair. The third angel from the left may have his mouth open, while the middle angel may be smiling. The fourth angel from the left holds and plays a lyre; the second angel from the right holds and probably plays a tambourine. Beams of light as well as clouds surround the angels.  
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design stands Jesus, facing away but turned slightly right. He is mostly nude, though he has a loincloth around his waist. His left leg is bent and extended backward slightly as his left foot is on tiptoe. He has long, curly hair and a beard and bends his arms upward with his palms together as if in prayer or supplication. He has a halo-like aura of light around his head. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>John the Baptist</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>skin</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>blessing</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>giving</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>blessing</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus, and baptizing him, stands John the Baptist, facing left and slightly forward, but looking up with his mouth open. He may be praying, speaking, or blessing. He has long, curly hair and a beard and wears a furry animal skin like a toga. His left arm is bent with the index and middle fingers of the left hand raised as though pointing. His right arm is raised at 135 degrees and from it he pours water onto Jesus's head. His right leg is bent and extended backward as his right foot is on tiptoe. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design kneel two female figures facing left and down, both probably gowned with long hair. The leftmost female one has her arms bent upward and her hands together as if in prayer or supplication, though she looks down. Her mouth may be open. She may be praying.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right of the design kneel two female figures facing left and down, both probably gowned with long hair. The rightmost female may have her eyes closed. Only part of the left side of her face, head and part of the back are visible. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. Only the top of the head of the leftmost figure is visible, with long hair, though a gown may be partly visible along the lower left margin of the design. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>band</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. The second figure to the left of this group is a gowned female with long hair pulled up into a bun. She wears a gold band in her hair. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. The third figure from the left is a gowned female with long, slightly curly hair. She bends her right arm upward and holds it to her chest. She turns her head to face slightly forward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. The fourth figure from the left is an old man with long hair and a beard. He looks down but bends his arms upward with his palms together as though in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. The fifth figure from the left is gowned but of indeterminable gender. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>pain</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus kneels a group of six figures, facing right. The sixth figure from the left is a nude or mostly nude male, who may have a strip of cloth covering his genitals. He has long hair and bends one leg underneath him, drawing the right knee up. He bends his right arm upward around his head and faces slightly forward. His facial expression suggests pain or despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left of the design stands a gowned female figure, facing left and away, but looking up and to the right. Her left arm is at her side and her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe, perhaps to suggest that she is walking. She has long, slightly curly hair twisted into a spiral extending to the right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>Jordan River</characteristic><characteristic>stream</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus, John the Baptist, and nine other figures stand or kneel in the Jordan River. There are small waves in the river.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>bank</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On either side of the river in the background rise small mountains or large hills, dotted with indeterminate leafy vegetation. The riverbanks are sandy. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky in the background is slightly cloudy. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>dove</characteristic><characteristic>Holy Ghost</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top center of the design is the dove of the Holy Ghost, seen from behind and facing down, perhaps flying downward. Its wings are spread and it has an aura with beams of light emanating from it.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>singing</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>tambourine</characteristic><characteristic>lyre</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right and left of the dove hover gowned and winged angels, most likely all male. There are at least ten angels on the left and seven on the right. They may all be looking at Jesus. The angels on the left face right and slightly forward, as well as down. The first and fourth angels from the left have long hair, while the second and third from the left have short, curly hair. Their mouths may be open. They may be speaking, singing, and/or praying. The second and fourth angels from the left hold (and presumably play) tambourines; the third angel from the left holds and plays a lyre.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>singing</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>tambourine</characteristic><characteristic>lyre</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right and left of the dove hover gowned and winged angels, most likely all male. There are at least ten angels on the left and seven on the right. The angels on the right of the design face left and slightly forward as well as down. The leftmost angel as well as the first and second from the right have long hair, while the second and third from the left have short, curly hair. The third angel from the left may have his mouth open; he may be speaking, singing and/or praying, while the middle angel may be smiling. The fourth angel from the left holds and plays a lyre; the second angel from the right holds and probably plays a tambourine.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beams of light as well as clouds surround the angels.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but475.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">inv</l><l n="but475.1.wc.01.02" justify="left">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>