<bad id="but457.1" type="wc" work="Goliath Cursing David" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="boston" catalog="butlin" catid="457" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Goliath Cursing David"><main>Goliath Cursing David</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 153KB to 1800KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages illustrated.  They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings.  The present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and 1805.  These designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine.  In works such as <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive.  In other designs, including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction.
            <lb/><lb/>
            This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible.  In coming months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series executed for Butts.  Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> of c. 1824.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This work copyright © 2010 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>March 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Natalie Moix,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Lily Todorinova,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>April 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Goliath Cursing David</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1803">c. 1803-05</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>34.9 x 36.8 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>45.5 x 37.1 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name><date>1890</date><dealer>Bernard Quaritch</dealer><price>$5,000 for the group of 32 works by Blake (see the note on provenance below)</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1803-05; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 123 (17s. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); John Clark Strange by 1863; the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, in item 13,842 with 31 other works by Blake in three volumes (£1,200), in the same group at the same price in Quaritch's advertising flyer of *William Blake's Original Drawings* of May 1885 and Nov. 1886, and in Quaritch's *General Catalogue of Books* of 1887, item 13,842, in the same group (£1,200); one of the "Nine large Drawings to illustrate the Bible" offered with the same group of three volumes of works by Blake in Quaritch's 1890 *Hand-List of a Peerless Collection of Books and Manuscripts Exhibited to the Bibliophiles of America*, item 156 ($5,000); the entire group in three volumes sold by Quaritch in 1890 to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution><addressline>Avenue of the Arts</addressline><addressline>465 Huntington Avenue</addressline><addressline>Boston, Massachusetts 02115-5597</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-617-267-9300</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.mfa.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Images: 1-617-369-4339</addressline><addressline>Fax, Image: 1-617-437-7471</addressline><addressline>Email, Images: mfaimages@mfa.org</addressline><department>Prints, Drawings, and Photographs</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">90.109</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but457.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT457.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Goliath Cursing David</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 457)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower left with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>34.9 x 36.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="730" height="720"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc> The design illustrates 1 Samuel 17:4-7, 41-43. Dominating the left side of the design is the giant figure Goliath. He stands, facing forward and to the right. He wears a full suit of armor, including a crested helmet, and his dark skin is almost indistinguishable from the armor. The armor has scales in places on his abdomen. His right leg is bent slightly and his left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe; he may be striding forward. His arms are raised horizontally, though his right arm is also bent upward. His left hand's fingers are spread, and he holds a large spear with his right hand. His mouth is open (he may be speaking) and he appears to be looking to the right at David. To the right of Goliath is a male figure in armor, facing forward and slightly left. He may be Goliath's assistant or squire. He has a beard and his left leg is extended backward. His right arm is at his side. In his right hand he holds a giant sword and in his left he holds a giant shield. On the shield, which is presumably Goliath's, is an intricate design, perhaps of a sea deity or merman. A human male's face with a beard is attached to a fish or eel-like body, which is covered in scales. His right arm is raised vertically and his left is wrapped around his waist. He has a tail and bat-like wings or fins. Backing this figure on the shield are what appear to be flames or waves. To the right of the shield stands the youthful David, facing left and presumably looking at Goliath. His right leg is bent and on tiptoe and his left arm is bent and held across his body. He holds a shepherd's crook to his right. David has short, curly hair and wears a gown. To the right of David, three male figures in armor, crested helmets, and capes are visible. The leftmost figure stands, facing forward and slightly left. He has a beard and his right foot is on tiptoe. He may be looking at David. The middle figure of this group faces forward and slightly right, but turns his head to look left, perhaps at Goliath. His arms are bent, with his right palm vertical and his left hand holding a spear across his shoulder. His right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. He has a curly beard. The rightmost figure faces forward, though with his head turned to face left. He may be looking at David or Goliath. Behind this group and extending to the left are at least 25 spears, indicating an army. To the left of and between Goliath's legs, a number of spears and at least four tents are visible, indicating the presence of his army. The earth in the foreground is slightly grassy, though David and his army may stand on a road, path, or patch of bare earth with small plants below David's feet. Distant mountains are visible in the background on the left. The sky backing this scene is partly cloudy.    
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>giant</characteristic><characteristic>Goliath</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>spear</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dominating the left side of the design is Goliath. He stands, facing forward and to the right. He wears a full suit of armor, including a crested helmet, and his dark skin is almost indistinguishable from the armor. The armor has scales in places on his abdomen. His right leg is bent slightly and his left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. His arms are raised horizontally, though his right arm is also bent upward. His left hand's fingers are spread, and he holds a large spear with his right hand. His mouth is open (he may be speaking) and he appears to be looking to the right at David.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>carrying</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>shield</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>servant</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Goliath is a male figure in armor, facing forward and slightly left. He may be Goliath's assistant or squire. He has a beard and his left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe; he may be striding forward. His right arm is at his side. In his right hand he holds a giant sword and in his left he holds a giant shield. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>merman</characteristic><characteristic>picture</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>eel</characteristic><characteristic>fish</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>fin</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>wave</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the shield, which is presumably Goliath's, is an intricate design, perhaps of a sea deity or a merman. A human male's face with a beard is attached to a fish or eel-like body, which is covered in scales. His right arm is raised vertically and his left is wrapped around his waist. He has a tail and bat-like wings or fins. Backing this figure on the shield are what appear to be flames or waves.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>David</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the shield stands David, facing left and presumably looking at Goliath. His right leg is bent and on tiptoe and his left arm is bent and held across his body. He holds a shepherd's crook to his right. David has short, curly hair and wears a gown.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of David, three male figures in armor, crested helmet, and capes are visible. The leftmost figure stands, facing forward and slightly left. He has a beard and his right foot is on tiptoe. He may be looking at David.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>spear</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of David, three male figures in armor, crested helmets, and capes are visible. The middle figure of this group faces forward and slightly right, but turns his head to look left, perhaps at Goliath. His arms are bent, with his right palm vertical and his left hand holding a spear across his shoulder. His right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. He has a curly beard. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>armor</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of David, three male figures in armor, crested helmet, and capes are visible. The rightmost figure faces forward, though with his head turned to face left. He may be looking at David or Goliath.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>spear</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the three figures on the right and extending to the left are at least 25 spears, indicating an army.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>spear</characteristic><characteristic>tent</characteristic><characteristic>soldier</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of and between Goliath's legs, a number of spears and at least four tents are visible, indicating the presence of his army.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The earth in the foreground is slightly grassy, though David and his army may stand on a road, path, or patch of bare earth. Small plants grow below David's feet.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc> Distant mountains are visible in the background lower left. They may be dotted with some trees or indeterminate vegetation just right of Goliath's left foot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky backing this scene is partly cloudy.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but457.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">inv</l><l n="but457.1.wc.01.02" justify="left">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>