<bad id="but470.1" type="wc" work="The Presentation in the Temple: 'Simeon Was Not to See Death Before He Had Seen the Christ'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fogg" catalog="butlin" catid="470" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Presentation in the Temple: 'Simeon Was Not to See Death Before He Had Seen the Christ'"><main>The Presentation in the Temple: "Simeon Was Not to See Death Before He Had Seen the Christ"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 124KB to 3600KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2011 Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>April 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>April 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">The Presentation in the Temple: "Simeon Was Not to See Death Before He Had Seen the Christ"</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1803">c. 1803-05</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>34.3 x 32.4 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>34.3 x 32.4 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>Fragments of a single framing line in ink appear along the bottom margin on the left, top margin on the right, the upper left margin, and the right margin.</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Fogg Art Museum</name><date>1890</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>bequest</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1803-05; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 129 (14s. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); William Bell Scott by 1876; sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 14 July 1892, lot 180, titled "Nunc Dimittis" (£16.5s. to the dealer Bernard Quaritch); offered by Quaritch in his "Rough List" 127, Aug. 1892, item 913 (£25), catalogue 62 of 1893, catalogue 9 of 1893, and catalogue 11 of 1894; acquired by E. H. van Ingen; sold Anderson Galleries, New York auction, 25 Nov. 1927, lot 11 ($6100); possibly acquired by Philip Hofer; acquired by the dealer Gabriel Wells and sold by him April 1932 to Grenville Lindall Winthrop; bequeathed by Winthrop to the Fogg Art Museum in 1943.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Fogg Art Museum</institution><addressline>Harvard University Art Museums</addressline><addressline>32 Quincy Street</addressline><addressline>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-617-495-9400</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Digital Imaging and Visual Resources: 1-617-495-2389</addressline><addressline>Email: divr@fas.harvard.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.artmuseums.harvard.edu/fogg/</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.403</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but470.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT470.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Presentation in the Temple: "Simeon Was Not to See Death Before He Had Seen the Christ"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 470)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower left with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>34.3 x 32.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="800" height="800"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates Luke 2:22-38. The scene takes place in the temple. In the center of the design stands Simeon, portrayed as an old man with long hair and a beard. He wears a gown and faces forward, but looks slightly up. His arms are bent and crossed slightly so that he can support the infant Jesus. In Simeon's arms sits the infant Jesus, nude and facing forward. His legs are bent and his arms are crossed. He has a halo around his head. In the foreground to the left of Simeon's feet, two doves sit or stand on the floor, facing left and slightly forward. Their wings are raised and they appear to be bowing, while looking at Simeon and Jesus. To the left of the doves stands an old woman, Anna, described in Luke 2:36 as a "prophetess."  She faces right. Most of her hair is covered by a veil and she wears a gown, perhaps with a belt at the waist. She has a sandal on her visible right foot, and her right leg is slightly bent. Her arms are bent upward with her palms together as if in prayer or supplication. She is bent forward slightly as she bows and perhaps looks at Jesus. To the right of Simeon in the foreground kneel Joseph and Mary. Joseph has short, curly hair and a beard and kneels, facing left and down. He is slightly hunched forward. His arms are bent and held to his chest. Mary kneels, slightly hunched forward and facing left and down. Her hair is pulled up into a bun that is covered by a veil. She wears a gown and has her arms bent upward and held to her chest. Three male figures stand in the background to the left of Simeon. The leftmost figure has long hair and a beard and wears a gown. He faces right and may look at the figure to his right. The middle figure of this group faces left and slightly forward and may look at the figure to his left. He may wear a gown and has long hair and a beard. The rightmost figure of this group faces forward and has long hair and a beard. He wears a gown. To the right of Simeon in the background stands a group of five male figures, all wearing gowns. The leftmost figure of this group has long hair and a beard and faces forward. The second-to-left figure has short, curly hair and a beard and faces left and slightly forward, looking at Simeon. The middle figure of this group faces left and slightly forward, looking at Simeon and Jesus. He bends his arms to hold his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. The second-to-right figure of this group has long hair and beard and faces left and slightly forward, looking at Simeon. He bends his arms to hold his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. The rightmost figure of this group has short, curly hair and a beard and faces forward and slightly left, and looks down toward Jesus. He bends his arms and holds his hands, palms down and out, fingers spread. Hi gesture and facial expression suggest surprise. 
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>chamber</characteristic><characteristic>temple</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a room of the temple. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Simeon</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design stands Simeon, portrayed as an old man with long hair and a beard. He wears a gown and faces forward, but looks slightly up. His arms are bent and crossed slightly so that he can support the infant Jesus. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In Simeon's arms sits the infant Jesus, nude and facing forward. His legs are bent and his arms are crossed. He has a halo around his head and he has short, curly hair. His mouth may be slightly open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>dove</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground to the left of Simeon's feet, two doves sit or stand on the floor, facing left and slightly forward. Their wings are raised and they appear to be bowing, while looking at Simeon and Jesus. The one visible eye of the front-most dove is slightly raised.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>Anna</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>prophet</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>sandal</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the doves stands an old woman, Anna, described in Luke 2:36 as a "prophetess." She faces right. Most of her hair is covered by a veil and she wears a gown, possibly with a belt at the waist. She has a sandal on her visible right foot, and her right leg is slightly bent. Her arms are bent upward with her palms together as if in prayer or supplication. She is bent forward slightly as she bows and perhaps looks at Jesus. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Joseph</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the foreground kneel Joseph and Mary. Joseph has short, curly hair and a beard and kneels, facing left. He looks down and is slightly hunched forward. His arms are bent and held to his chest. An aura seems to emanate from him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the foreground kneel Joseph and Mary. Mary kneels, slightly hunched forward and facing left and down. Her hair is pulled up into a bun that is covered by a veil. She wears a gown and has her arms bent upward and held to her chest. An aura seems to emanate from her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in the background to the left of Simeon. The leftmost figure has long hair and a beard and wears a gown. He faces right and may look at the figure to his right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in the background to the left of Simeon. The middle figure of this group faces left and slightly forward and may look at the figure to his left. He may wear a gown and has long hair and a beard. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in the background to the left of Simeon. The rightmost figure of this group faces forward and has long hair and a beard. He wears a gown. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the background stands a group of five male figures, all wearing gowns. The leftmost figure of this group has long hair and a beard and faces forward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the background stands a group of five male figures, all wearing gowns. The second-to-left figure has short, curly hair and a beard and faces left and slightly forward, looking at Simeon. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the background stands a group of five male figures, all wearing gowns. The middle figure of this group faces left and slightly forward, looking at Simeon and Jesus. He bends his arms to hold his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the background stands a group of five male figures, all wearing gowns. The second-to-right figure of this group has long hair and beard and faces left and slightly forward, looking at Simeon. He bends his arms to hold his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Simeon in the background stands a group of five male figures, all wearing gowns. The rightmost figure of this group has short, curly hair and a beard and faces forward and slightly left, and looks down toward Jesus. He bends his arms and holds his hands, palms down and out, fingers spread. His gesture and facial expression suggest surprise.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but470.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">inv</l><l n="but470.1.wc.01.02" justify="left">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>