<bad id="but498.1" type="wc" work="The Entombment" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="498" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Entombment"><main>The Entombment</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 10KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 68KB to 829KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2011 Tate Collection</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>July 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition and metadata collection</change><date>March 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">The Entombment</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>41.7 x 31.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>41.7 x 31.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Tate Collection</name><date>1949</date><dealer>none recorded</dealer><price>£1,102.10s.</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1805; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; offered from the Butts collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 124, entitled "Christ in the Sepulchre" and with Blake's water color, <hi rend="i">The Crucifixion</hi>" (not sold; bought-in at £1.10s.), and at Foster and Son, 8 March 1854, lot 14, with two other works by Blake (not sold; bought-in at 10s.); by inheritance in 1862 to Captain Frederick J. Butts; offered Sotheby's, 24 June 1903, lot 15 (£305 to "Fowler," but apparently not sold); the widow of F. J. Butts; sold April 1906 through Carfax &amp; Co. to W. Graham Robertson; sold from his collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 35 (£1,102.10s. to the executors of Robertson's estate for presentation through the National Art Collections Fund to the Tate Gallery, now Tate Collection).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Tate Collection</institution><addressline>Millbank</addressline><addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7887 8888</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Images: +44 (0)20 7887 8871</addressline><addressline>Fax, Images: +44 (0)20 7887 8805</addressline><addressline>Email, Images: picture.library@tate.org.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">N 05896 / B 498</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but498.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT498.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Entombment</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 498)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower right with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  Inscribed on the mount, not by Blake, "Joseph Burying Jesus" and "Luke ch:23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> v. 53<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>," with a quotation from the biblical passage below the title.</p></objnote><objsize>41.7 x 31.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="700"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is based on Luke 23:53, the entombment of Jesus's body, and Luke 23:55, the arrival of the three Marys at the tomb. At the bottom center of the design lies Jesus, supine, in a shroud that covers all but his face. His beard is visible, and his eyes are closed. His arms are at his side. Jesus lies on a pillow and a mattress or slab of stone. To the left of Jesus's body kneel two figures. The frontmost figure is that of a gowned old man with long hair and a beard. He, or the bearded figure above, may be Joseph of Arimathea (see Luke 23:50-51). He faces right and down, looking at Jesus's body. His legs are bent under him and his arms are raised horizontally and bent slightly. He may be arranging Jesus's body or its coverings. The rear figure also faces right and down, hunching over slightly, and appears to have long hair and be gowned. In the middle ground in the center of the design sit three containers, perhaps a covered bowl in the middle with a vial or glass on either side. On the left side of the middle ground stand three gowned figures. The leftmost figure faces left and down and is only visible as the top of a head. The middle figure is that of a man with long hair and a beard. He, or the bearded figure below, may be Joseph of Arimathea (see Luke 23:50-51). He faces right and down, looking at Jesus's body. His arms are bent with his hands together as though in prayer or supplication. The rightmost figure stands, facing forward and down slightly. Its gender is indeterminable. It is hooded, and covers its face with its upward bent arm. On the right in the middle ground stand at least five figures, facing left and down. The leftmost figure is that of a young woman with long, wavy hair. She is gowned and faces forward slightly, looking at Jesus. We see only the hair of the next figure to the right. The frontmost figure is gowned and hooded, and of indeterminable gender. Its face is not visible and its arms may be crossed. The figure just above may be that of a male with short, curly hair, but is only visible as the top of a head facing slightly forward. The rightmost figure is that of a gowned and mostly bald male, who may have his eyes closed. In the center background, three gowned female figures stand in a doorward, facing forward and looking down. The leftmost woman has long, curly hair over which she wears a veil. She faces left slightly and may cross her arms upward across her chest. The middle figure has long, curly hair and bends her left arm upward, with her hand on her face. This is probably the Virgin Mary. She may be crying. Her right arm is at her side but bent slightly. Her left foot protrudes from beneath the hem of her gown, which may indicate that she is walking. In her right hand she holds a large lit candle. The rightmost figure has a veil over her hair and faces right slightly. Her arms are crossed. The left and right women are probably Mary Magdalene and Mary, the wife of Cleophas. The scene takes place in a shadowy tomb with an open arched doorway, from which two steps lead downward. Through the arch in the background, dark trees and clouds are visible against the night sky.
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates the entombment of Jesus's body. At the bottom center of the design lies Jesus, supine, in a shroud that covers all of him but his face. His beard is visible, and his eyes are closed. His arms are at his side. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>mat</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus lies on a pillow and a mattress or slab of stone. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>Joseph of Arimathea</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's body kneel two figures. The frontmost figure is that of a gowned old man with long hair and a beard. He, or the bearded figure above, may be Joseph of Arimathea (see Luke 23:50-51). He faces right and down, looking at Jesus's body. His legs are bent under him and his arms are raised horizontally and bent slightly. He may be arranging Jesus's body or its coverings. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's body kneel two figures. The rear figure also faces right and down, hunching over slightly, and appears to have long hair and be gowned. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>bowl</characteristic><characteristic>lid</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>vial</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the middle ground in the center of the design sit three containers, perhaps a covered bowl in the middle and a glass vial on either side. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left side of the middle ground stand three gowned figures. The leftmost figure faces left and down and is only visible as the top of a head. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Joseph of Arimathea</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left side of the middle ground stand three gowned figures. The middle figure is that of a man with long hair and a beard. He faces right and down, looking at Jesus's body. His arms are bent with his hands together as though in prayer or supplication. He, or the bearded figure below, may be Joseph of Arimathea (see Luke 23:50-51).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left side of the middle ground stand three gowned figures. The rightmost figure stands, facing forward and down slightly. Its gender is indeterminable. It is hooded, and covers its face with its upward bent arm. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right in the middle ground stand at least five figures, facing left and down. The leftmost figure is that of a young woman with long, wavy hair. She is gowned and faces forward slightly, looking at Jesus. </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right in the middle ground stand at least five figures.  We see only the hair of the second figure from the left.</illusobjdesc></component></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right in the middle ground stand at least five figures, facing left and down. The frontmost figure is gowned and hooded, and of indeterminable gender. Its face is not visible and its arms may be crossed. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right in the middle ground stand at least five figures, facing left and down. The second-to-right figure may be that of a male with short, curly hair, but is only visible as the top of a head facing slightly forward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right in the middle ground stand at least five figures, facing left and down. The rightmost figure is that of a gowned and mostly bald male, who may have his eyes closed. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>Mary Magdalene</characteristic><characteristic>Mary, wife of Cleophas</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center background, three gowned female figures stand in a doorward, facing forward and looking down. The leftmost woman has long, curly hair that she wears a veil over. She faces left slightly and may cross her arms upward across her chest. This or the woman on the right is probably either Mary Magdalene or Mary, the wife of Cleophas.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>candle</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center background, three gowned female figures stand in a doorward, facing forward and looking down. The middle figure has long, curly hair and bends her left arm upward, with her hand on her face. This is probably the Virgin Mary. She may be crying. Her right arm is at her side but bent slightly. Her left foot protrudes from beneath the hem of her gown, which may indicate that she is walking. In her right hand she holds a large lit candle. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>Mary Magdalene</characteristic><characteristic>Mary, wife of Cleophas</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the background, three gowned female figures stand in a doorward, facing forward and looking down. The rightmost figure has a veil over her hair and faces right slightly. Her arms are crossed. This or the woman on the left is probably either Mary Magdalene or Mary, the wife of Cleophas.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>chamber</characteristic><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in a shadowy tomb with an open arched doorway, from which two steps lead downward. The structures are probably made of stone.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Through the arch in the background, dark trees and clouds are visible against the night sky.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="15"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but498.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="21">inv</l><l n="but498.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="20">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>