<bad id="but467.1" type="wc" work="The King of Babylon in Hell: 'Hell From Beneath is Moved For Thee'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="boston" catalog="butlin" catid="467" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The King of Babylon in Hell: 'Hell From Beneath is Moved For Thee'"><main>The King of Babylon in Hell: "Hell From Beneath is Moved For Thee"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 158KB to 1900KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages illustrated.  They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings.  The present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and 1805.  These designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine.  In works such as <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive.  In other designs, including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction.
            <lb/><lb/>
            This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible.  In coming months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series executed for Butts.  Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> of c. 1824.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2010 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>April 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Natalie Moix,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Lily Todorinova,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>April 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The King of Babylon in Hell: "Hell From Beneath is Moved For Thee"*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>36.2 x 31.7 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>36.5 x 31.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, black chalk, and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name><date>1890</date><dealer>Bernard Quaritch</dealer><price>$5,000 for the group of 32 works by Blake (see the note on provenance below)</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1805; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 122 (£1 to John Clark Strange); the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, in item 13,842 with 31 other works by Blake in three volumes (£1,200), in the same group at the same price in Quaritch's advertising flyer of *William Blake's Original Drawings* of May 1885 and Nov. 1886, and in Quaritch's *General Catalogue of Books* of 1887, item 13,842, in the same group (£1,200); one of the "Nine large Drawings to illustrate the Bible" offered with the same group of three volumes of works by Blake in Quaritch's 1890 *Hand-List of a Peerless Collection of Books and Manuscripts Exhibited to the Bibliophiles of America*, item 156 ($5,000); the entire group in three volumes sold by Quaritch in 1890 to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution><addressline>Avenue of the Arts</addressline><addressline>465 Huntington Avenue</addressline><addressline>Boston, Massachusetts 02115-5597</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-617-267-9300</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.mfa.org/</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Digital Image Resources: 1-617-369-4339</addressline><addressline>Fax, Digital Image Resources: 1-617-437-7471</addressline><addressline>Email, Digital Image Resources: mfaimages@mfa.org</addressline><department>Prints, Drawings, and Photographs</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">90.103</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but467.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT467.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The King of Babylon in Hell: "Hell From Beneath is Moved For Thee"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 467)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower right with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>36.2 x 31.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="800"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates Isaiah 14:9-12. The king of Babylon stands on the right side of the design, facing left and forward but with his head turned to look right. His left leg is bent, as are his arms, which cross at the wrist. He wears a gown and a three-tiered, spiky crown suggestive of a papal crown. The king has a curly beard but appears to be bald. His wrists are shackled and the chain connected to them is held by a figure to the left. The figure to the left of the king of Babylon is that of a nude male with scales covering his shoulders, upper chest, and genitals. This is probably the Devil or Satan, referred to as Lucifer in Isaiah 14:12. He has short, curly hair and hovers in mid-air, with his right leg extended backward. He faces forward and slightly left, but looks to the right at the king. His left arm is at his side and in that hand he holds the king's chain. His right arm is raised horizontally and he points right with his index finger. To the right of the king of Babylon, a nude male figure is suspended in mid-air, upside down. His knees are bent and his arms are behind his back. His open mouth is visible as he faces forward, though his head is bent back. He may be howling in pain. Wrapped around the waist and knees of this suspended figure is what appears to be a large, scaly serpent. To the left of the king of Babylon's feet is what appears to be a pit of fire with large rocks and seven figures in it, three crowned and four helmeted. The five pictured faces suggest fear. The three crowned figures are those of old men with long hair and beards. The leftmost king has a spiky crown and faces right, looking up at the king of Babylon. His head is bent back and his right arm is bent upward to hold on to a rock(?) to his right. His mouth may be slightly open. The middle king has a two-tiered crown and faces forward and right. He may be looking at the king of Babylon. His mouth may be partly open. The rightmost king hunches over slightly, with his body facing forward and left, but his head facing forward and right to look at the king of Babylon. He also wears a spiky crown. The four helmeted figures are lower in the pit of fire than the kings. We see only the head and face in right profile of the figure on the far left. Is one pictured eye is raised. The next figure to the right looks up at the king of Babylon. He looks forward and slightly right up at the king of Babylon. His brow is furrowed and his mouth may be partly open. Only the head of the next figure to the right is visible; his eyes are raised. The rightmost figure is only visible from the nose up. The scene takes place in hell, which resembles a dark and shadowy cave. 
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Babylonian</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>Pope</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The king of Babylon stands on the right side of the design, facing left and forward but with his head turned to look right. His left leg is bent, as are his arms, which cross at the wrist. He wears a gown and a three-tiered, spiky crown suggestive of a papal crown. The king has a curly beard but appears to be bald. His wrists are shackled and the chain connected to them is held by a figure to the left.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Devil</characteristic><characteristic>Satan</characteristic><characteristic>Lucifer</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure to the left of the king of Babylon is that of a nude male with scales covering his shoulders, upper chest, and genitals. This is probably the Devil or Satan, referred to as Lucifer in Isaiah 14:12. He has short, curly hair and hovers in mid-air, with his right leg extended backward. He faces forward and slightly left, but looks to the right at the king. His left arm is at his side and in that hand he holds the king's chain. His right arm is raised horizontally and he points right with his index finger. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>pain</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>serpent-coiled</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the king of Babylon, a nude male figure is suspended in mid-air, upside down. His knees are bent and his arms are behind his back. His open mouth is visible as he faces forward, though his head is bent back. He may be howling in pain. Wrapped around the waist and knees of this suspended figure is what appears to be a large, scaly serpent. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the king of Babylon's feet is what appears to be a pit of fire with large rocks and seven figures in it. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the king of Babylon's feet is what appears to be a pit of fire with large rocks and seven figures in it, three crowned and four helmeted. The five pictured faces suggest fear. The three crowned figures are those of old men with long hair and beards. The leftmost king has a spiky crown and faces right, looking up at the king of Babylon. His head is bent back and his right arm is bent upward to hold on to a rock to his right. His mouth may be slightly open. The middle king has a two-tiered crown and faces forward and right. He may be looking at the king of Babylon. His mouth may be partly open. The rightmost king hunches over slightly, with his body facing forward and left, but his head facing forward and right to look at the king of Babylon. He also wears a spiky crown. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>helmet</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>drowning</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the king of Babylon's feet is what appears to be a pit of fire with large rocks and seven figures in it, three crowned and four helmeted. The five pictured faces suggest fear. The four helmeted figures are lower in the pit of fire than the kings. We see only the head of the figure far left, pictured in right profile with eye raised. The next figure to the right looks up at the king of Babylon. He looks forward and slightly right up at the king of Babylon. His brow is furrowed and his mouth may be partly open. Only the next figure to the right is visible; his eyes are raised. Only the head of the rightmost figure is visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>hell</characteristic><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in hell, which resembles a dark and shadowy cave.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but467.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="46">inv</l><l n="but467.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="45">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>