<bad catalog="butlin" catid="494" copy="1" copyid="1" hidden="false" id="but494.1" institution="fogg" type="wc" work="Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves">
          <main>Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves</main>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
          , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>1 XML file approx. 10KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 125KB to 2500KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
        <date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are 
        <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi>
        of 1809 and 
        <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>
        in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>
        , datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>
        . 
                    
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2011</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This image copyright © 2011 Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University</userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>November 2012</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Illustration markup</change>
        <date>Summer 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>March 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Joseph Vogel,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>BAD creation</change>
        <date>April 2010</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
          <name>Robin Curry, </name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Lamperez,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Image scanning, metadata collection and color correction</change>
        <date>April 2005</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
          <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
          <name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>
            *Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves*
          </title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>delineator, </role>
          <role>colorist</role></origination>
        <origination>Anonymous
          <role>delineator.  The pencil inscription below the design, &quot;W. Blake,&quot; and the inscribed lines beginning &quot;And he Said,&quot; also below the design, are not by Blake.  These are available under Related Works in the Archive.</role></origination>
        <compdate value="1800">c. 1800-03</compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <numberobj>1</numberobj>
        <objsize>40.4 x 33.4 cm.</objsize>
        <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>46.2 x 37.1 cm.</leafsize>
        <medium>pen and ink and water color
          <note>In the inscriptions below the water color, &quot;W. Blake&quot; is in pencil, all others are in pen and ink.</note></medium>
        <support>wove paper</support>
        <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
        <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
        <framelines>3
          <note>One ink framing line is contiguous with the edges of the water color; the other is approximately 1.2 cm. from the edges of the water color.  A fine pencil framing line is outside the other two and extends below all inscriptions.</note></framelines>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University</name>
        <date>1943</date>
        <dealer>none</dealer>
        <price>bequest</price>
        <note>Acquired, and probably commissioned, from Blake by Thomas Butts c. 1800-03; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 26 March 1852, lot 151 (£1 to Charles Wentworth Dilke); Dilke's son, probably by inheritance in 1864; sold from his collection, Christie's, 10 April 1911, lot 126 (£28.7s. to the dealer E. Parsons); offered by Parsons in Oct. 1911 for £60; A. Betts, who sold the work in May 1923 to the dealer Thomas Agnew &amp; Sons; sold August 1923 to the dealer Scott and Fowles; sold May 1924 to Grenville L. Winthrop; bequeathed by Winthrop in 1943 to the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University.</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>Fogg Art Museum</institution>
        <addressline>Harvard University Art Museums</addressline>
        <addressline>32 Quincy Street</addressline>
        <addressline>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 617-495-9400</addressline>
        <addressline>URL: http://www.artmuseums.harvard.edu/fogg/</addressline>
        <addressline>Department: Digital Imaging and Visual Resources</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 617-495-2389</addressline>
        <addressline>Fax: 617-495-2990</addressline>
        <addressline>Email: divr@fas.harvard.edu</addressline>
        <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.400</repositoryid>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="BUT494.1.1.WC" id="but494.1.wc.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 494)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>A few marks on the hat or headband of the figure, facing forward and standing left of the central cross, are probably meant to indicate Hebrew letters, but they do not constitute actual letter forms.  Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram, and inscribed a reference to the biblical passage illustrated below the design on the right.  See the textual transcription.  The other inscriptions below the design are not by Blake; these are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>40.4 x 33.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="880" width="750"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="inscbut494.1.rm.01" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut494.1.rm.02" ovp="noindex"/>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The design is based on Luke 23:33-43., the crucifixion of Christ on the hill of Calvary. In the center hangs a crucified Jesus, wearing only a loincloth and a crown of thorns. He faces forward and looks down and to the left. He has long, curly hair and a beard. A halo surrounds his head. His arms are raised horizontally and his feet are crossed. There is a nail in each hand and through his feet. To the left of Jesus hangs a nearly nude male with short, curly hair who wears only a loincloth. This is one of the thieves. He faces forward and right and looks up at Jesus, mouth open. He may be howling or screaming in pain or despair. His arms are raised at 135 degrees and his feet are crossed. A nail is in each hand and through his feet. To the right of Jesus hangs a nearly nude male with short hair standing on end, who wears only a loincloth. This is one of the thieves. He faces forward and to the left and looks slightly up, mouth open. He may be howling or screaming in pain or despair. His arms are raised at 135 degrees and his feet are crossed. A nail is in each hand and through his feet. Jesus hangs on a wooden cross in the center of the design inscribed with the letters &quot;INRI.&quot; Each thief, referred to in the passage illustrated only as &quot;malefactors&quot; (Luke 23:32), hangs on a wooden T-shaped cross. The sky in the background is dark and cloudy, with a red wash that suggests sunrise or sunset. To the left and below the leftmost thief stand two old male figures with long hair and beards. The top figure faces forward and slightly up and looks to the right with his mouth open. The bottom figure faces right and slightly up, with his head bent back. He wears a gown. Between the leftmost thief and Jesus stand three or four figures.  We see only the two raised (left?) arms of the figures in the back of the group, although the arm second from the left might belong to the figure closest to Jesus's cross. Both arm are clothed. The hands on these arms each have one finger pointing up. The front-most figure in this group has a curly beard and wears a hat on his head. A few lines on the hat, or on a separate head band or cloth, bears a few lines that suggest a Hebrew inscription.  He may be a priest. His body faces slightly right, but his head is turned to face forward, as though looking at the viewer. His mouth is open; he may be speaking. He raises his right arm at 45 degrees and bends it upward, pointing with his right hand. He raises his left arm vertically, palm out. The rightmost figure of this group has a curly beard. He faces right and looks up, with his head bent back slightly. Between Jesus and the thief to the right stand four figures, all gowned and presumably male. The leftmost figure is that of an old male with long hair and a beard. He faces left and up, with his head bent back and his mouth slightly open; he may be speaking. He raises his right arm vertically and points with his right hand. The next figure to the right also appears to be that of an old male, but his hair is not visible. He faces left and up, with his head bent slightly back. He raises his right arm vertically and points upward with his right index and middle fingers. The front-most figure is a male with a beard and long hair, or perhaps a long cloth draped over his head. He faces left and away and looks up, with his head bent slightly back and his mouth open; he may be speaking. His left arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent upward and his right arm is raised vertically. He points with both hands. The rightmost figure of this group is only visible as a vertical right arm, facing left and pointing. To the right of the rightmost thief stand two male figures, facing left. The front figure is that of an old, gowned male with a long beard. The top of his head appears to be bald, however. We see only the top of the head of the figure behind.  
                    </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
            <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
            <characteristic>aura</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>thorn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hanging</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feet touching</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design hangs a crucified Jesus, wearing only a loincloth and a crown of thorns. He faces forward and looks down and to the left. He has long, curly hair and a beard. A halo surrounds his head. His arms are raised horizontally, fingers slightly spread, and his feet are crossed. There is a nail in each hand and through his feet.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>thief</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feet touching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hanging</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>screaming</characteristic>
            <characteristic>howling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus left hangs a nearly nude male with short, curly hair who wears only a loincloth. This is one of the thieves. He faces forward and right and looks up at Jesus, mouth open. He may be howling or screaming in pain or despair. His arms are raised at 135 degrees and his feet are crossed. A nail is in each hand and through his feet. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>thief</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hanging</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feet together</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>screaming</characteristic>
            <characteristic>howling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus hangs a nearly nude male with short hair standing on end, who wears only a loincloth. This is one of the thieves. He faces forward and to the left and looks slightly up, mouth open. He may be howling or crying out in pain or despair. His arms are raised at 135 degrees and his feet are crossed. A nail is in each hand and through his feet. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Calvary</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Jesus hangs on a wooden cross in the center of the design inscribed with the letters &quot;INRI.&quot; Each thief hangs on a wooden T-shaped cross. The scene takes place on the hill of Calvary.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The sky in the background is dark and cloudy, with a red wash that suggests sunrise or sunset. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the leftmost thief stand two old male figures with long hair and beards. The top figure faces forward and slightly up and looks to the right with his mouth open. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the leftmost thief stand two old male figures with long hair and beards. The bottom figure faces right and slightly up, with his head bent back. He wears a gown. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between the leftmost thief and Jesus stand three or four figures.  We see only the two raised (left?) arms of the figures in the back of the group, although the arm second from the left might belong to the figure closest to Jesus's cross. The hands on these arms each have one finger pointing up. All three arms are clothed.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>priest</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>band</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The front-most figure in the group between the thief on the left and Jesus has a curly beard and wears a hat on his head. A few lines on the hat, or on a separate head band or cloth, bears a few lines that suggest a Hebrew inscription.  He may be a priest. His body faces slightly right, but his head is turned to face forward, as though looking at the viewer. His mouth is open; he may be speaking. He raises his right arm at 45 degrees and bends it upward, pointing with his right hand. He raises his left arm vertically, palm out. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between the leftmost thief and Jesus stand three or four gowned and presumably all male figures. The rightmost figure of this group has a curly beard. He faces right and looks up, with his head bent back slightly. His mouth is slightly open; he may be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the thief to the right stand four figures, all gowned and presumably male. The leftmost figure is that of an old male with long hair and a beard. He faces left and up, with his head bent back and his mouth slightly open; he may be speaking. He raises his right arm vertically and points with his right hand. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the thief to the right stand four figures, all gowned and presumably male. The figure second from the left also appears to be that of an old male, but his hair is not visible. He faces left and up, with his head bent slightly back. He raises his right arm vertically and points upward with his right index and middle fingers. The fingers are spread apart.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the thief to his right stand four figures, all gowned and presumably male. The font-most figure is a male with a beard and long hair, or perhaps a long cloth draped over his head. He faces left and away and looks up, with his head bent slightly back and his mouth open; he may be speaking. His left arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent upward and his right arm is raised vertically. He points with both hands. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the thief to his right stand four figures, all gowned and presumably male. The rightmost figure of this group is only visible as a vertical right arm, facing left and pointing. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the rightmost thief stand two male figures. The front figure is that of an old, gowned male with a long beard. The top of his head appears to be bald, however. He faces left and up.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the rightmost thief stand two male figures, facing left and up. We see on the top of the head of the figure in back.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="but494.1.wc.01.01">I N R I
            <note>This inscription appears on the cross above Christ's head.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="10"/>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="6" justify="left" n="but494.1.wc.01.02">inv</l>
          <l indent="b" justify="left" n="but494.1.wc.01.03">WB</l>
        </lg>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="45" justify="left" n="but494.1.wc.01.04">Luke XXIIIc 42 v</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="BUT494.1.1-full.RM" id="inscbut494.1.rm.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">full view including inscriptions </Objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>A few marks on the hat or headband of the figure, facing foward and standing left of the central cross, are probably meant to indicate Hebrew letters, but they do not constitute actual letter forms.  Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram, and inscribed a reference to the biblical passage illustrated below the design on the right.  The pencil inscription, &quot;W. Blake,&quot; and the lines inscribed below the image, beginning &quot;And he said...,&quot; are not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>46.2 x 37.1 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="875" width="700"/>
      </physdesc>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT494.1.1-insc-b.RM" id="inscbut494.1.rm.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Christ Crucified Between the Two Thieves</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">bottom inscriptions </Objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The pencil inscription below the design, &quot;W. Blake,&quot; and the lines inscribed below the image, beginning &quot;And he said...,&quot; are not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>4.2 x 32.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="850"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="45" justify="left" n="inscbut494.1.rm.01.04">Luke XXIIIc 42 v</l>
          <l indent="18" justify="left" n="inscbut494.1.rm.01.05">W. Blake</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="inscbut494.1.rm.01.06">And he said unto Jesus, &quot;Lord remember me when thou comest</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="inscbut494.1.rm.01.07">into thy Kingdom.&quot;—</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>