<bad id="but496.1" type="wc" work="Christ Nailed to the Cross: The Third Hour" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="morgan" catalog="butlin" catid="496" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Christ Nailed to the Cross: The Third Hour"><main>Christ Nailed to the Cross: The Third Hour</main>

: electronic edition

</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>

            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918)

files ranging in size from 164KB to 3600KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>

This work copyright © 2011 Morgan Library and Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>October 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition and metadata collection</change><date>May 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Eric Forster,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Christ Nailed to the Cross: The Third Hour</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1803">c. 1803<note>In a letter of 30 Jan. 1803 to his brother James, Blake states that he is "now learning my Hebrew" (Erdman page 727).  The Hebrew inscriptions in this water color suggest that it was not executed until after that date.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>33.2 x 34.6 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>33.2 x 34.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium><support>paper, probably wove</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Morgan Library and Museum</name><date>2005</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts c. 1803; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster &amp; Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 138, titled "The Crucifixion" (13s. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); possibly Col. Gould Weston; Alexander Anderdon Weston by 1876, probably by inheritance; his widow by inheritance in 1901; sold Christie's, 28 June 1904, lot 6 (£18.18s. to the dealer E. Parsons, probably acting for W. Graham Robertson); sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 32 (£294 to Francis Neate acting for Lord Glentanar); Lord Glentanar's daughter, Mrs. Jean Bruce, probably by inheritance in 1971; sold Christie's, 4 June 1974, lot 134 (£14,700 to the dealer Lew David Feldman for his firm, the House of El Dieff, New York); the dealer Justin G. Schiller, New York, probably in association with House of El Dieff; the dealer Barry Friedman, New York, probably in association with House of El Dieff and Schiller; sold May 1980 through the Fine Art Society to M. Koike, Tokyo, possibly on behalf of Professor Kimiyoshi Yura, Tokyo; sold from Yura's collection, Sotheby's, 8 July 1982, lot 79 (£28,600); Eugene V. Thaw, probably acquired at (or shortly after) the 1982 auction; given by Thaw to the Morgan Library and Museum by 2005.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Morgan Library and Museum</institution><addressline>225 Madison Avenue</addressline><addressline>New York, New York 10016</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1 212 685 0008</addressline><addressline>Fax: 1 212 481 3484</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Photography: 1 212 590 0386</addressline><addressline>Email, Photography: photoservices@themorgan.org</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">Thaw repository no. EVT9</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but496.1.wc.01" dbi="but496.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Christ Nailed to the Cross: The Third Hour</title>,

<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 496)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower right with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  According to W. Graham Robertson's manuscript catalogue of his collection, the water color is inscribed on the back, "And it was the Third Hour, and they crucified Him" (from Mark 15:25).  This inscription, very probably not by Blake, is now obscured by the backing mat.  We are grateful to Sheila Spector for assistance with the Hebrew inscriptions.</p></objnote><objsize>44.0 x 33.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="825" height="850"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is based on Mark 15:25-26. In the center lies Christ, nearly nude except for a loincloth and crown of thorns. He faces forward and slightly up, with his head turned to look left. His arms are raised horizontally, palms up, and his legs dangle. He has long, curly hair and a beard, and a halo-like aura surrounds his head. Jesus lies on a wooden cross that leans against a large boulder or hillside. Three nails or spikes lie on the rock near the cross, two below his right arm and one below and to the right of his left hand. To the left of Jesus's legs kneels a group of five figures. The leftmost figure appears to be that of a female with long, curly hair and a veil covering part of her hair. She faces forward and slightly left, looking up with her mouth open. She may be crying. The second-to-left figure is that of a male with short, curly hair. He wears a gown and faces forward and to the right, looking up at Jesus. His mouth is partly open. His arms are bent with his palms held vertical, fingers slightly spread. The middle figure of this group faces right, slightly away, and bending down, as though bowing. This figure is of indeterminable gender, but wears a gown. The second-to-right figure is also of indeterminable gender and faces right, slightly away, and bowing down, wearing a gown. The rightmost figure is that of a female with long hair and a gown, facing right and down. Her arms are bent upward with her hands presumably on her face. Her legs are bent underneath her. She too is bowing, possibly praying or lamenting. To the right of Jesus's legs is a group of five gowned figures. The leftmost figure kneels, facing left and down. This figure is of indeterminable gender, but has slightly curly hair. The figure's legs are bent underneath it and its arms are bent upward, with its hands to its face. The figure may be praying or lamenting. The second-to-left figure faces left and down. This figure is of indeterminable gender, and covers its head with a hood or veil. The middle figure of this group is of indeterminable gender, and faces left and down. It may be kneeling. It covers its head with a hood or veil. The second-to-right figure may be a female, facing right and slightly down and forward. She covers her hair with a hood or veil and bends her arms up so her hands are on her face, covering her eyes. She may be crying. The rightmost figure may be that of a male with short, curly hair, facing right and down. He wears a hood or veil over part of his hair. To the left of Jesus's head sits, squats, or kneels a male figure facing forward, with his right knee slightly drawn up. He wears a shirt and pants or tights and holds a wooden hammer in his right hand. His right arm is bent and his left arm is raised horizontally, pointing to the right. His mouth is open; he may be speaking. Above Jesus's head sits an old man with a long, curly beard. He wears a gown and a hat. His hat, or a separate head band, and the hem of his garment where, are inscribed with Hebrew letters (see the textual transcription). He is very probably a priest. He faces forward and looks to the left, and may be smiling. His arms are bent, and in his hands he holds a scroll with the letters "INRI" written on it (see the textual transcription). To the right of Jesus's head sits, kneels, or squats a man with short, curly hair and a beard. He wears a gown and holds a wooden hammer in his right hand. His right arm is bent and his left arm appears to be at his side. His left leg is drawn up slightly. He faces forward, but looks to the left. The cross and the priest above it are backed with a large stone or hill, possibly the hill of Calvary. The sky backing this scene is partly cloudy, with a red wash that suggests sunrise or sunset.   
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>thorn</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>legs dangling</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><characteristic>crucified</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design lies Christ, nearly nude except for a loincloth and crown of thorns. He faces forward and slightly up, with his head turned to look left. His arms are raised horizontally, palms up, and his legs dangle. He has long, curly hair and a beard, and a halolike aura surrounds his head. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cross</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>nail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus lies on a wooden cross that leans against a large boulder or hillside. Three nails or spikes lie on the rock near the cross, two below his right arm and one below and to the right of his left hand. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's legs kneels a group of five figures. The leftmost figure appears to be that of a female with long, curly hair and a veil covering part of her hair. She faces forward and slightly left, looking up with her mouth open. She may be crying or moaning. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's legs kneels a group of five figures. The second-to-left figure is that of a male with short, curly hair. He wears a gown and faces forward and to the right, looking up at Jesus. His mouth is partly open. His arms are bent with his palms held vertical, fingers slightly spread. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's legs kneels a group of five figures. The middle figure of this group faces right, slightly away, and bows down. This figure is of indeterminable gender, but wears a gown. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's legs kneels a group of five figures. The second-to-right figure is of indeterminable gender and faces right, slightly away, and bows down, wearing a gown. The figure's feet are prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's legs kneels a group of five figures. The rightmost figure is that of a female with long hair and a gown, facing right and bowing down. Her arms are bent upward with her hands presumably on her face. Her legs are bent underneath her. She may be praying or lamenting.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus's legs is a group of five gowned figures. The leftmost figure kneels, facing left and down. This figure is of indeterminable gender, but has slightly curly hair. The figure's legs are bent underneath it and its arms are bent upward, with its hands to its face. He or she may be praying or lamenting.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus's legs is a group of five gowned figures. The second-to-left figure faces left and down. This figure is of indeterminable gender, and covers her or his head with a hood or veil. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus's legs is a group of five gowned figures. The middle figure of this group is of indeterminable gender, and faces left and down. He or she may be kneeling. It covers its head with a hood or veil. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus's legs is a group of five gowned figures. The second-to-right figure may be a female, facing right and slightly down and forward. She covers her hair with a hood or veil and bends her arms up so her hands are on her face, covering her eyes. She may be crying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus's legs is a group of five gowned figures. The rightmost figure may be that of a male with short, curly hair, facing right and down. He wears a hood or veil over part of his hair. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>hammer</characteristic><characteristic>murderer</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus's head sits, kneels, or squats a male figure facing forward, with his right knee slightly drawn up. He wears a shirt and pants or tights and holds a wooden hammer in his right hand. His right arm is bent and his left arm is raised horizontally, pointing to the right. His mouth is open; he may be speaking. He might be considered an executioner, and thus one of the murderers of Jesus.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>priest</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>band</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above Jesus's head sits an old man with a long, curly beard. He wears a gown and a hat.  His hat, or a separate head band, and the hem of his garment where it falls over his left wrist bear inscriptions in Hebrew.  He is very probably a priest. He faces forward and looks to the left, and may be smiling. His arms are bent, and in his hands he holds a scroll inscribed with INRI. See the textual transcription.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>hammer</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>murderer</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus's head sits, squats, or kneels a man with short, curly hair and a beard. He wears a gown and holds a wooden hammer in his right hand. His right arm is bent and his left arm appears to be at his side. His left leg is drawn up slightly. He faces forward, but looks to the left. He might be considered an executioner, and thus a murderer of Jesus.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>Calvary</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The cross and the priest above it are backed with a large stone or hill, possibly the hill of Calvary. The sky backing this scene is partly cloudy, with a red wash that suggests sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but496.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="20">הוהאג<note>These Hebrew letters are written on the priest's head band or phylactery.  Our transcription is tentative.  If we assume an initial י at the right end of the inscription but mostly hidden by the priest's hair, and if we assume that Blake meant the final letter on the left to be ל (lamed), then the inscription could mean "Jehovah Elohim," a name for god in Genesis chapter 2 of the Hebrew Old Testament, translated as "Lord God" in the King James Bible.</note></l><l n="but496.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="20">INRI<space extent="3"/>יה ידכך צוד יונ<note>The letters, "INRI," on the scroll held by the priest above Christ's head are an abbreviation for the Latin inscription "Iesus Nazarenus Rex Iudæorum" (Jesus of Nazareth King of the Jews).  According to John 19:19, "Jesus of Nazareth the King of the Jews" was written by Pilate and placed "on the cross" on which Christ was crucified (see also Matthew 27:37, Mark 15:26, and Luke 23:38 for slightly different versions).  The Hebrew letters are written vertically, bottom to top, on the priest's cloak where it falls below his left arm, possibly as an unconventional substitute for the phylactery conventionally worn on the left arm.  Our transcription is tentative; some of the letters are poorly formed and they seem to constitute little more than fragments of words.  It is very difficult to distinguish among several letters in Blake's Hebrew writing, particularly ד (dalet), ו (vav), ך (final kaf), and ר (resh).  The first word, יה (right end of the inscription), is probably "Yah," a name for God.</note></l></lg><vspace extent="8"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but496.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="50">inv</l><l n="but496.1.wc.01.04" justify="left" indent="49">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>