<bad id="but469.1" type="wc" work="Satan in His Original Glory: 'Thou Wast Perfect Till Iniquity Was Found in Thee'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="469" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Satan in His Original Glory: 'Thou Wast Perfect Till Iniquity Was Found in Thee'"><main>Satan in His Original Glory: "Thou Wast Perfect Till Iniquity Was Found in
                        Thee"</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 107KB
                to 1200KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an
                electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These
                designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages
                illustrated. They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the
                features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed
                descriptions of Blake’s images). <lb/><lb/> The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.
                Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings. The
                present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of
                similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and c. 1806. These
                designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine. In works such as
                    <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many
                    Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive. In other designs,
                including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the
                relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction. <lb/><lb/> This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a
                large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible. In coming
                months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series
                executed for Butts. Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and
                    Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical
                water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>
                of c. 1824. <lb/><lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library
                of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums
                that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections
                in the Archive. </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © 2010 Tate Collection</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>May 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>Spring-Summer 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Satan in His Original Glory: "Thou Wast Perfect Till Iniquity
                            Was Found in Thee"</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>42.9 x 33.9 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>42.9 x 33.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Tate Collection</name><date>1949</date><dealer>none recorded</dealer><price>£1260</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1805; by inheritance
                    in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; offered at Sotheby's, 26 June 1852, lot 157,
                    titled "Thou wast perfect till iniquity was found in thee" (10s. to "Butts,"
                    thus indicating that the lot was bought-in if Butts was the vendor); offered
                    from the Butts collection, Foster &amp; Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot
                    103 (not sold; bought-in at 11s.), and at Foster &amp; Son, 8 March 1854, lot
                    14, with two other works by Blake (not sold; bought-in at 10s.); by inheritance
                    to Captain Frederick J. Butts; his widow; sold April 1906 through Carfax &amp;
                    Co. to W. Graham Robertson; sold from his collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949,
                    lot 23 (£1260 to the executors of Robertson's estate for presentation through
                    the National Art-Collections Fund to the Tate Gallery, now Tate
                    Collection).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Tate Collection</institution><addressline>Millbank</addressline><addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7887 8888</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Images: +44 (0)20 7887 8871</addressline><addressline>Fax, Images: +44 (0)20 7887 8805</addressline><addressline>Email, Images: picture.library@tate.org.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">N 05892 / B 469</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but469.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT469.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Satan in His Original Glory: "Thou Wast Perfect Till
                Iniquity Was Found in Thee"</title><objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 469)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower right with his monogram; see the textual
                        transcription. Inscribed, not by Blake, on a prior and damaged mat, "Thou
                        wast perfect...", part of the text from Ezekiel 27, and "Ezekiel ch. 28.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> v. 13.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>...."</p></objnote><objsize>42.9 x 33.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="800"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design is based in part on Ezekiel 28:14-15. Dominating this
                        design is the figure of an angelic, not-yet-fallen Satan or Lucifer. He
                        stands or hovers, facing forward. He is nude, but has multiple sets of
                        wings, one of which covers his genitals. His hair is short and curly and
                        topped by a flame-like crown with vegetative forms topped with a star or
                        blossom. A strap, as if for a quiver or a sash of honor, runs diagonally
                        across his chest. His left leg is bent backward and on tiptoe. His arms are
                        raised at 45 degrees. In his right hand he holds an orb topped with a cross.
                        In his left hand he holds a scepter topped with a fleur-de-lis. Satan
                        appears to be suspended in space, perhaps with clouds surrounding him. He
                        may also emanate an aura around his head and with beams of light angling
                        downward lower right and left. By his feet are at least 45 stars, 16 planets
                        (including Saturn with its rings), and one crescent moon. A variety of small
                        figures surround Satan. Near his right hand are eight hovering or flying
                        figures. The top right figure appears to be that of a gowned male with short
                        hair. His legs are extended behind him and his arms are crossed as he faces
                        left and down slightly. To the left of the cross on the orb is a figure of
                        indeterminable gender, facing right and slightly up. Its right arm is raised
                        horizontally and its legs are spread. It may be nude. To the left of the orb
                        held in Satan's right hand is a figure sitting, hunched forward. It is of
                        indeterminable gender and wears a gown as it faces forward and down. Its
                        legs are bent to support a book on its lap, from which it apparently reads.
                        Beneath the reading figure, and perhaps supporting it, is another figure of
                        indeterminable gender, facing forward and right. Its arms are raised at 135
                        degrees and bent as though supporting the book on the other figure's lap. It
                        may be gowned and have short hair. To the left of the reading figure is
                        another flying figure of indeterminable gender, which may wear a gown and
                        have short hair. It faces left and away, with its body twisted to face up.
                        Its legs are together and its arms are raised vertically. To the left of
                        this flying figure are two small figures, perhaps cherubs or children. The
                        leftmost figure's body is horizontal as it flies left and slightly down. Its
                        legs are spread slightly and its arm is raised horizontally. Its gender is
                        indeterminable, but it may be gowned. The rightmost figure of this pair
                        faces forward and may look up and to the right. Its gender is also
                        indeterminable. Beneath Satan's right hand is the figure of a male, facing
                        forward. He may wear breeches or pants, but his upper body is nude. He has
                        short hair and bends his legs behind him. His arms are at his side and hold
                        an indeterminable object, perhaps a stone pillar. Beneath this figure are
                        three flames. To the left of Satan's right leg hover thirteen small figures.
                        Two figures hold and perhaps play large tambourines. Both figures may be
                        gowned and have short hair, though their gender is indeterminable. The
                        leftmost figure faces left and up, with its right arm raised vertically. The
                        rightmost figure faces left and up. To the left of the tambourine players
                        are two figures playing trumpets or horns. The leftmost figure is bald and
                        faces forward and down with his(?) arms bent to hold the horn to his mouth.
                        His lower body seems to be made of or perhaps shrouded in cloud. The
                        rightmost figure has long hair and faces right and down, with her(?) arms
                        bent upward to hold a horn to her mouth. To the left of these trumpeters are
                        two more figures, seated on a cloud. The leftmost figure of the pair appears
                        to be a female, partly clothed by a skirt or cloth secured around her waist.
                        She has long hair pulled up into a bun and sits, hunched over, with her legs
                        bent, facing left and down. The rightmost figure is of indeterminable
                        gender, but faces forward and right. It may be wrapped in a cloth or
                        drapery. To the left of Satan's right foot is a pair of figures embracing.
                        The leftmost figure is nude and faces right and down, looking away at the
                        figure to the right. His right arm is raised vertically (relative to his
                        body) and points. The rightmost figure faces right and up and may be gowned.
                        Her left arm is bent upward, almost vertically, and points. To the left of
                        these embracing figures are a set of three trumpeters or horn players, all
                        gowned and with curly hair. The leftmost trumpeter faces down and left and
                        extends his(?) left arm horizontally, with his right arm bent upward,
                        holding the horn to his mouth. The middle figure faces down and slightly
                        forward, with his body facing left and with both arms raised horizontally to
                        hold the trumpet to his mouth. The rightmost figure faces down and forward,
                        with his body facing left, and both arms raised horizontally to hold the
                        trumpet to his mouth. Above these trumpeters are a pair of gowned figures
                        with curly hair, but of indeterminable gender. The leftmost figure faces
                        forward and down, with its left leg extended out behind it. Its right arm is
                        bent upward and it points with its right hand. It may be looking at the
                        trumpeters. The rightmost figure faces forward and right, with its left arm
                        raised horizontally and perhaps pointing and its right arm bent upward to
                        hold a large book. To the right of Satan's left leg is a group of six
                        figures. The uppermost pair of figures sits on a cloud. The leftmost figure
                        faces forward and right and is of indeterminable gender. It may look at the
                        figure to its right. The rightmost figure of the pair appears to be that of
                        a male with a beard and wearing a gown. His body is twisted so that the
                        lower half faces up and left while the upper half faces forward and right.
                        His knees are bent and he reclines on a book. His right arm points down and
                        he may hold a pen or quill in his right hand. His right arm is bent and his
                        hand rests on the book. To the right of Satan's foot is a set of three
                        trumpeters, perhaps all male and gowned with long hair. All of their eyes
                        may be closed. The leftmost trumpeter faces right and down, though his lower
                        body is twisted to face up and left. His right arm is raised horizontally to
                        hold the horn to his mouth. The middle trumpeter faces right, with his left
                        arm raised horizontally to hold the trumpet to his mouth. The rightmost
                        trumpeter may have curly hair, and faces right and down, with his right arm
                        raised horizontally to hold the trumpet to his mouth. Below the trumpeter
                        descends a male(?) nude holding a book in his bent left arm and pointing
                        down with his right. His legs are bent above him. Surrounding the scepter
                        held in Satan's left hand is a group of six figures. The uppermost two sit
                        on a cloud and are of indeterminable gender. The leftmost of the pair wears
                        a gown and faces left and forward, though with its head turned to face right
                        and down, perhaps looking at the figure to its right. Its arms may be
                        crossed and it is standing or walking on the cloud. The rightmost figure of
                        this pair sits, facing right and forward, and looking down at a book or
                        tablet that it holds on its lap. Its left leg is bent and drawn up to
                        support the book, and its arms are bent to hold the book. Three figures
                        cling to the scepter. The leftmost figure is nude and appears to be a male
                        cherub or child with short hair, seen from behind, though also facing right
                        slightly. Its legs are bent behind it and its arms are bent upward. The
                        middle figure may be a female with long hair pulled up into a bun. She faces
                        right and down, though with her head turned to look left, perhaps at the
                        cherub to her left. She may wear a gown. The rightmost clinging figure faces
                        left and up, with her legs extended behind her. She has long hair and wears
                        a gown, and is seen from behind. Her arms are raised horizontally. Beneath
                        the group clinging to the scepter is the figure of a gowned female (perhaps
                        only clothed by a skirt or cloth secured around her waist). She sits on a
                        cloud, facing left and down slightly. She hunches or bends forward, with her
                        arms extended horizontally, to hold onto a long scroll. Below the scroll and
                        scepter is a group of five figures. The uppermost figure appears to be that
                        of a gowned male with short hair, sitting on a cloud and facing forward and
                        slightly left. He is hunched or bent forward and looks down at an open book
                        that he holds on his drawn-up knees. Holding on to the end of the scroll
                        with her(?) right hand is a gowned figure (perhaps only clothed from the
                        waist down) with short hair. She faces left and slightly forward, with her
                        arms raised at 135 degrees. She may look up. Below the figure holding on to
                        the scroll is a nude or partly nude female(?) figure with long hair. Her
                        body faces right and down, though her head faces left. Her right arm is
                        raised horizontally to hold onto an upside down cross or small sword,
                        wrapped around with cloth. Beneath the cross or sword are two gowned male(?)
                        figures with short hair. The uppermost one faces right and down, though his
                        body is twisted to face left. He holds a tube, pillar, or rolled scroll. The
                        lowermost figure also holds a tube, pillar, or rolled scroll and is facing
                        down and away, with his(?) left arm bent upward around the tube. The
                        background sky is dark. The scene may take place in heaven since Lucifer is
                        not yet fallen. The blue strip at the bottom of the design was formerly
                        covered by a mat; hence, this area did not fade.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Satan</characteristic><characteristic>Lucifer</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>band</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dominating this design is the figure of an angelic,
                            not-yet-fallen Satan or Lucifer. He stands or hovers, facing forward. He
                            is nude, but has multiple sets of wings, one of which covers his
                            genitals. His hair is short and curly and topped by a flame-like crown
                            with vegetative forms topped by a star or blossom. A strap, as if for a
                            quiver or a sash of honor, runs diagonally across his chest. His left
                            leg is bent backward and on tiptoe. His arms are raised at 45 degrees.
                            In his right hand he holds a orb topped with a cross. In his left hand
                            he holds a scepter topped with a fleur-de-lis. Lucifer may emanate an
                            aura of light around his head and with beams of light angling downward
                            lower right and left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>orb</characteristic><characteristic>cross</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In his right hand Satan holds an orb topped with a cross. In
                            his left hand he holds a scepter topped with a
                            fleur-de-lis.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>crescent</characteristic><characteristic>planet</characteristic><characteristic>Saturn</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Satan appears to be suspended in space, perhaps with clouds
                            surrounding him. He may also emanate an aura. By his feet are at least
                            45 stars, 16 planets (including Saturn with its rings), and one very
                            small crescent moon. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A variety of small figures surround Satan. Near his right hand
                            are eight hovering or flying figures. The top right figure appears to be
                            that of a gowned male with short hair. His legs are extended behind him
                            and his arms are crossed as he faces left and down slightly. To the left
                            of the cross on the orb is a figure of indeterminable gender, facing
                            right and slightly up. Its right arm is raised horizontally and its legs
                            are spread. It may be nude. To the left of the orb held in Satan's right
                            hand is a figure sitting, hunched forward. It is of indeterminable
                            gender and wears a gown as it faces forward and down. Its legs are bent
                            to support a book on its lap, from which it probably reads. Beneath the
                            reading figure, and perhaps supporting it, is another figure of
                            indeterminable gender, facing forward and right. Its arms are raised at
                            135 degrees and bent as though supporting the book on the other figure's
                            lap. It may be gowned and have short hair. To the left of the reading
                            figure is another flying figure of indeterminable gender, which may wear
                            a gown and have short hair. It faces left and away, with its body
                            twisted to face up. Its legs are together and its arms are raised
                            vertically. To the left of this flying figure are two small figures,
                            perhaps cherubs or children. The leftmost figure's body is horizontal as
                            it flies left and slightly down. Its legs are spread slightly and its
                            arm is raised horizontally. Its gender is indeterminable, but it may be
                            gowned. The rightmost figure of this pair faces forward and may look up
                            and to the right. Its gender is also indeterminable. Beneath Satan's
                            right hand is the figure of a male, facing forward. He may wear breeches
                            or pants, but his upper body is nude. He has short hair and bends his
                            legs behind him. His arms are at his side and hold an indeterminable
                            object, perhaps a stone pillar. Beneath this figure are three flames.
                        </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>tambourine</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A variety of small figures surround Satan. To the left of
                            Satan's right leg hover thirteen small figures. Two figures hold and
                            perhaps play large tambourines. Both figures may be gowned and have
                            short hair, though their gender is indeterminable. The leftmost figure
                            faces left and up, with its right arm raised vertically. The rightmost
                            figure faces left and up. To the left of the tambourine players are two
                            figures playing trumpets or horns. The leftmost figure is bald and faces
                            forward and down with his(?) arms bent to hold the horn to his mouth.
                            His lower body seems to be made of or perhaps shrouded in cloud. The
                            rightmost figure has long hair and faces right and down, with his arms
                            bent upward to hold a horn to his mouth. To the left of these trumpeters
                            are two more figures, seated on a cloud. The leftmost figure of the pair
                            appears to be a female, partly clothed by a skirt or cloth secured
                            around her waist. She has long hair pulled up into a bun and sits,
                            hunched over, with her legs bent, facing left and down. The rightmost
                            figure is of indeterminable gender, but faces forward and right. It may
                            be wrapped in a cloth or drapery with at least one arm wrapped around
                            its body. To the left of Satan's left foot are a pair of figures
                            embracing. The leftmost figure is nude and faces right and down, looking
                            away at the figure to the right. His right arm is raised vertically
                            (relative to his body) and points. The rightmost figure faces right and
                            up and may be gowned. Her left arm is bent upward, almost vertically,
                            and points. To the left of these embracing figures are a set of three
                            trumpeters or horn players, all gowned and with curly hair. The leftmost
                            trumpeter faces down and left and extends his(?) left arm horizontally,
                            with his right arm bent upward, holding the horn to his mouth. The
                            middle figure faces down and slightly forward, with his body facing left
                            and with both arms raised horizontally to hold the trumpet to his mouth.
                            The rightmost figure faces down and forward, with his body facing left,
                            and both arms raised horizontally to hold the trumpet to his mouth.
                            Above these trumpeters are a pair of gowned figures with curly hair, but
                            of indeterminable gender. The leftmost figure faces forward and down,
                            with its left leg extended out behind it. Its right arm is bent upward
                            and it points with its right hand. It may be looking at the trumpeters.
                            The rightmost figure faces forward and right, with its left arm raised
                            horizontally and perhaps pointing and its right arm bent upward to hold
                            a large book. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>pen</characteristic><characteristic>quill</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A variety of small figures surround Satan. To the right of
                            Satan's left leg is a group of six figures. The uppermost pair of
                            figures sits on a cloud. The leftmost figure faces forward and right and
                            is of indeterminable gender. It may look at the figure to its right. The
                            rightmost figure of the pair appears to be that of a male with a beard
                            and wearing a gown. His body is twisted so that the lower half faces up
                            and left while the upper half faces forward and right. His mouth may be
                            open. His knees are bent and he reclines on an open book. His right arm
                            points down and he may hold a pen or quill in his right hand. His right
                            arm is bent and his hand rests on the book. To the right of Satan's foot
                            is a set of three trumpeters, perhaps all male and gowned with long
                            hair. All of their eyes may be closed. The leftmost trumpeter faces
                            right and down, though his lower body is twisted to face up and left.
                            His right arm is raised horizontally to hold the horn to his mouth. The
                            middle trumpeter faces right, with his left arm raised horizontally to
                            hold the trumpet to his mouth. The rightmost trumpeter may have curly
                            hair, and faces right and down, with his right arm raised horizontally
                            to hold the trumpet to his mouth. Below the trumpeter is a descending
                            nude male(?) holding a book in his raised left arm and pointing down
                            with his right. His legs are bent upward behind him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>tablet</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A variety of small figures surround Satan. Surrounding the
                            scepter held in Satan's left hand is a group of six figures. The
                            uppermost two sit on a cloud and are of indeterminable gender. The
                            leftmost of the pair wears a gown and faces left and forward, though
                            with its head turned to face right and down, perhaps looking at the
                            figure to its right. Its arms may be crossed and it is standing or
                            walking on the cloud. The rightmost figure of this pair sits, facing
                            right and forward, and looking down at a book or tablet that it holds on
                            its lap. Its left leg is bent and drawn up to support the book, and its
                            arms are bent to hold the book. Three figures cling to the scepter. The
                            leftmost figure is nude and appears to be a male cherub or child with
                            short hair, seen from behind, though also facing right slightly. Its
                            legs are bent behind it and its arms are bent upward. The middle figure
                            may be a female with long hair pulled up into a bun. She faces right and
                            down, though with her head turned to look left, perhaps at the cherub to
                            her left. She may wear a gown. The rightmost clinging figure faces left
                            and up, with her legs extended behind her. She has long hair and wears a
                            gown, and is seen from behind. Her arms are raised horizontally. Beneath
                            the group clinging to the scepter is the figure of a gowned female
                            (perhaps only clothed by a skirt or cloth secured around her waist). She
                            sits on a cloud, facing left and down slightly. She hunches or bends
                            forward, with her arms extended horizontally, to hold onto a long
                            scroll. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>cross</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A variety of small figures surround Satan. Below the scroll
                            and scepter is a group of five figures. The uppermost figure appears to
                            be that of a gowned male with short hair, sitting on a cloud and facing
                            forward and slightly left. He is hunched or bent forward and looks down
                            at, and probably reads, an open book that he holds on his drawn-up
                            knees. Holding on to the end of the scroll with his right hand is a
                            gowned figure (perhaps only clothed from the waist down) with short
                            hair. He faces left and slightly forward, with his arms raised at 135
                            degrees. He may look up. To the right of the figure holding on to the
                            scroll is a nude or partly nude female(?) figure with long hair. Her
                            body faces right and down, though her head faces left. Her right arm is
                            raised horizontally to hold onto an upside down cross or small sword,
                            wrapped around with cloth. Beneath the cross or sword are two gowned
                            male(?) figures with short hair. The uppermost one faces right and down,
                            though his body is twisted to face left. He holds a tube, pillar, or
                            rolled scroll. The lowermost figure also holds a tube, pillar, or rolled
                            scroll and is facing down and away, with his(?) left arm bent upward
                            around the tube.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The background sky is dark. The scene may take place in heaven
                            since Lucifer is not yet fallen.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but469.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="41">inv</l><l n="but469.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="40">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>