<bad catalog="butlin" catid="499" copy="1" copyid="1" hidden="false" id="but499.1" institution="ycba" type="wc" work="Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch">
          <main>Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch</main>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
          , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 160KB to 2600KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
        <date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
        
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are 
        <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi>
        of 1809 and 
        <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>
        in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
          
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>
        , datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>
        . 
          
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2011</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This work courtesy Yale Center for British Art</userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>November 2012</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Illustration markup</change>
        <date>Summer 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>March 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
        
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
        
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
        
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Joseph Vogel,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>BAD created</change>
        <date>July 2010</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
        
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
        
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
        
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Lamperez,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Images received, catalogued and color corrected</change>
        <date>May 2004</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
        
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
        
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
        
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name>
          <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>
            *Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch*
          </title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>delineator, </role>
          <role>colorist</role></origination>
        <origination>Anonymous
          <role>delineator.  The pencil inscription above the design (&quot;IX&quot;) and the pencil title inscription below the design (&quot;Sealing the Stone &amp; setting a Watch&quot;) are not by Blake.  These anonymous inscriptions are available under Supplemental Views.</role></origination>
        <compdate value="1803">c. 1803
          <note>In a letter of 30 Jan. 1803 to his brother James, Blake states that he is &quot;now learning my Hebrew&quot; (Erdman page 727).  The Hebrew inscriptions in this water color suggest that it was not executed until after that date.</note></compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <numberobj>1</numberobj>
        <objsize>40.1 x 33.3 cm.</objsize>
        <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>51.0 x 43.1 cm.</leafsize>
        <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color
          <note>The inscription above the design and the title inscription below the design are in pencil.  These anonymous inscriptions are available under Supplemental Views.</note></medium>
        <support>wove paper</support>
        <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
        <pennednumbers>none
          <note>The number &quot;IX&quot; is inscribed in pencil above the design.  This anonymous inscription is available under Supplemental Views.</note></pennednumbers>
        <framelines>4
          <note>The innermost framing line is contiguous with the edge of the image.  The space between the two outer framing lines is tinted with pale gray wash.  Blake may have drawn these framing lines.</note></framelines>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>Yale Center for British Art</name>
        <date>1977</date>
        <dealer>C. A. Stonehill
          <note>See the Note on provenance, below, for the sale of this work to the Yale University Art Gallery and later transfer to the Yale Center for British Art.</note></dealer>
        <price>not recorded</price>
        <note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts c. 1803; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; by inheritance to Frederick J. Butts in 1862; offered Sotheby's, 24 June 1903, lot 16 (bought-in by &quot;Knowles&quot; for £105); the widow of Frederick J. Butts by inheritance in 1905; sold by her in April 1906 through Carfax &amp; Co. to W. Graham Robertson; sold Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 36 (£504 to the dealer Meatyard); offered by Meatyard in catalogues of Feb. 1950, item 546, and 1954, item 812 (£750); sold to the dealer C. A. Stonehill; acquired 1956 by the Yale University Art Gallery; transferred in 1979 to the Yale Center for British Art.</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>Yale Center for British Art</institution>
        <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
        <addressline>1080 Chapel Street, Box 208280</addressline>
        <addressline>New Haven, Connecticut 06520-8280</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 203-432-2800</addressline>
        <addressline>Fax: 203-432-6780</addressline>
        <addressline>Email: ycba.photorights@yale.edu</addressline>
        <addressline>URL (general): http://ycba.yale.edu</addressline>
        <addressline>URL (Rights and Reproductions): http://ycba.yale.edu/departments/depart-ser-rights.html</addressline>
        <repositoryid label="Accession number">B1979.12.703</repositoryid>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="BUT499.1.1.WC" id="but499.1.wc.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 499)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>Blake signed the work, lower right, with his monogram, and inscribed a reference to the passage illustrated lower right below the design.  See the textual transcription.  The inscribed number above the design and the title below the design are not by Blake.  These are available under Related Works in the Archive.  We are grateful to Sheila Spector for assistance with the Hebrew inscriptions.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>40.1 x 33.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="800" width="700"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="inscbut499.1.rm.01" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut499.1.rm.02" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut499.1.rm.03" ovp="noindex"/>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The design is based on Matthew 27:66, the sealing of Christ's tomb. Toward the top center stands a partly nude male on a ladder. He wears pants and sandals, but has no shirt on. He has short, curly hair and holds a trowel in his right hand and a piece of wood with mortar on it with his left hand. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees but bent upward and his left arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent slightly. He faces away and looks to the right. His left leg is bent as he climbs or balances on the ladder. A wooden ladder scales the center of the design. To the left of the ladder stand five male figures. The leftmost figure is that of a guardian soldier with a beard. He wears a plumed helmet and a cloak, and faces left and down. The second-to-left figure is that of a guardian soldier, facing forward and to the right. He wears a plumed helmet and armor with a cloak over it. His right arm is bent upward and with that hand he holds a halberd (a battle ax with a long handle). The middle figure of this group is another soldier with a plumed helmet. He is only visible as a head, facing away and to the left. The second-to-right figure is gowned and faces away. Hebrew letters adorn the hem of his gown (see the textual transcription). He has long hair and bends his right arm upward to point. The rightmost figure of this group is an old man with a long beard, facing forward and to the left. He wears a gown as well as a hat that is adorned with Hebrew letters; see the textual transcription.  He is probably a priest. His mouth is open (he is probably speaking) and he bends his right arm upward to point. His left arm is at his side, palm down. To the right of the ladder stand three male figures. The leftmost figure has short, curly hair and wears a gown. He faces away, with his left arm bent and his right arm raised vertically, pointing with his right hand. His right leg is bent and on tiptoe. He may be looking at the work of the mason. The middle figure is a guardian soldier wearing a plumed helmet and a cloak. His left arm is bent upward, and his right arm is bent so that he can hold a halberd with his right hand. His right leg is bent and crossed over the left, and on tiptoe. He faces forward and to the left, looking up. The rightmost figure is that of a guardian soldier wearing a plumed helmet and a cloak. He may hold the long spear that rises above him. He has a beard and faces forward and looks up to the left. This scene takes place in front of the stone wall of Christ's tomb, the arched doorway of which is being sealed.
          </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trowel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mortar</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Toward the top center of the design stands a partly nude male on a ladder. He wears pants and sandals, but has no shirt on. He has short, curly hair and holds a trowel in his right hand and a piece of wood with mortar on it with his left hand. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees but bent upward and his left arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent slightly. He faces away and looks to the right. His left leg is bent as he climbs or balances on the ladder. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>ladder</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A wooden ladder scales the center of the design. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the ladder stand five male figures. The leftmost figure is that of a guardian soldier with a curly beard. He wears a plumed helmet and a cloak, and faces left and down. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the ladder stand five male figures. The second-to-left figure is that of a guardian soldier, facing forward and to the right. He wears a plumed helmet and armor with a cloak over it. His right arm is bent upward and with that hand he holds a halberd (a battle ax with a long handle). He has a curly beard and may be looking at the second-to-right figure of the group. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
            <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the ladder stand five male figures. The middle figure of this group is another guardian soldier with a plumed helmet. He is only visible as a head, facing away and to the left. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the ladder stand five male figures. The second-to-right figure is gowned and faces away. Hebrew letters adorn the hem of his gown (see the textual transcription). He has long hair and bends his right arm upward to point. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>priest</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the ladder stand five male figures. The rightmost figure of this group is an old man with a long beard, facing forward and to the left. He wears a gown as well as a hat that is adorned with Hebrew letters; see the textual transcription. He is probably a priest a priest. His mouth is open (he is probably speaking) and he bends his right arm upward to point. His left arm is at his side, palm down. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the ladder stand three male figures. The leftmost figure has short, curly hair and wears a gown. He faces away, with his left arm bent and his right arm raised vertically, pointing with his right hand. His right leg is bent and on tiptoe. He may be looking at the work of the mason. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ax</characteristic>
            <characteristic>handle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoe</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the ladder stand three male figures. The middle figure is a guardian soldier wearing a plumed helmet and a cloak. His left arm is bent upward, and his right arm is bent so that he can hold a halberd (a battle ax with a long wooden handle) with his right hand. His right leg is bent and crossed over the left, and on tiptoe. He probably wears shoes. He faces forward and to the left, looking up. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of the ladder stand three male figures. The rightmost figure is that of a guardian soldier wearing a plumed helmet and a cloak. He may hold the long spear that rises above him. He has a beard and faces forward and looks up to the left. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tomb</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>This scene takes place in front of the stone wall of Christ's tomb, the arched doorway of which is being sealed. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="object">
            <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ax</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In addition to the halberd (a battle ax with a long wooden handle) held by the soldier facing forward in the group on the left, there is also a spear and another halberd rising above the group.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <vspace extent="5"/>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="10" justify="left" n="but499.1.wc.01.01">וטח את בית
            <note>These Hebrew letters are written on the headband or phylactery of the bearded man standing immediately to the left of the ladder.  The inscription, reading right to left, can be translated as &quot;and he sealed up the place.&quot;  The third (final) word, &quot;תיב,&quot; can be transliterated as &quot;bayit&quot; and means &quot;house&quot; in normative Hebrew.  In this context, it would appear to take on a more general meaning of &quot;place&quot; or even the &quot;sepulchre&quot; of the passage illustrated, Matthew 27:66 in the King James Bible.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="5"/>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="but499.1.wc.01.02">יהיו במוץ ינפל רוח רבאלאה
            <note>These Hebrew letters are written on the hem of the gown worn by the figure seen from behind and standing left of the ladder.  The first four words, reading right to left, can be translated as &quot;they are in the chaff scattered by the wind.&quot;  The phrase is similar to several passages in the King James Bible; see particularly Job 21:18, Psalms 1:4 and 35:5, and Isaiah 17:13.  The first letter of the second word might be a kaph (כ), in which case the meaning would be &quot;they are like the chaff&quot; rather than &quot;they are in the chaff.&quot;  The third letter in the fourth word looks like a tav (ת), but that would not spell a word.  We are uncertain about the letters of the fifth (final) word; one or more letters may be within the fold in the man's garment between the second and third letters.  The first letter might be a daleth (ד) or a vav (ו).  The second letter is unclear; our selection of a bet (ב) is highly speculative.  None of these possible combinations of letters spells a word.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="50" justify="left" n="but499.1.wc.01.03">inv</l>
          <l indent="49" justify="left" n="but499.1.wc.01.04">WB</l>
          <l indent="35" justify="left" n="but499.1.wc.01.05">Matthew XXVII c 66 v</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="BUT499.1.1-full.RM" id="inscbut499.1.rm.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">full view including all inscriptions </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The inscribed number above the design and the title below the design are not by Blake.  We are grateful to Sheila Spector for assistance with the Hebrew inscriptions.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>51.0 x 43.1 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="900" width="700"/>
      </physdesc>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT499.1.1-insc-t.RM" id="inscbut499.1.rm.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">top inscription </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The inscribed number above the design is not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>6.5 x 9.1 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="500"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="inscbut499.1.rm.02.01">IX</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT499.1.1-insc-b.RM" id="inscbut499.1.rm.03">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">bottom title inscription </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The title inscription below the design is not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>6.5 x 41.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="800"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="10" justify="left" n="inscbut499.1.rm.03.01">Sealing the Stone &amp; setting a Watch</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>