<bad id="but440.1" type="wc" work="Finding of Moses" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="vanda" catalog="butlin" catid="440" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Finding of Moses: The Compassion of Pharaoh's Daughter"><main>The Finding of Moses: The Compassion of Pharaoh's Daughter</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 146KB to 1900KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages illustrated.  They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings.  The present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and 1805.  These designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine.  In works such as <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive.  In other designs, including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction.
            <lb/><lb/>
            This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible.  In coming months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series executed for Butts.  Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> of c. 1824.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2010 Victoria and Albert Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup created</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>September 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>October 2003</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke,</name><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image scanning and metadata</change><date>September 2003</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke,</name><name>Gerald Miller,</name><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The Finding of Moses: The Compassion of Pharaoh's Daughter*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>32.3 x 32.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>32.3 x 32.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color over pencil</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name><date>1949</date><dealer>Thomas Agnew &amp; Sons</dealer><price>£2152.10s.</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; offered in two auctions by Foster &amp; Son, London, 29 June 1853, lot 126 (bought-in at 19s.), and 8 March 1854, in lot 15 (bought-in at 18s.); by inheritance to Capt. F. J. Butts; by inheritance to his widow, who sold the work through Carfax &amp; Co. to W. Graham Robertson in April 1906; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 6 (£2152.10s. to Thomas Agnew &amp; Sons, apparently acting for the Victoria and Albert Museum).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Victoria and Albert Museum</institution><addressline>Cromwell Road</addressline><addressline>South Kensington, London SW7 2RL</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 20-7942-2479</addressline><addressline>Fax: 20-7942-2482</addressline><addressline>Email: vanda.images@vam.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.vam.ac.uk/</addressline><department/><repositoryid label="Accession number">P.25-1949</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but440.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT440.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Finding of Moses: The Compassion of Pharaoh's Daughter</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="U1">(Butlin 440)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>32.3 x 32.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="780" height="780"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This water color illustrates Exodus 2:5-9, the discovery of Moses by Pharaoh's daughter. Pharaoh's daughter occupies the center of the design, facing left and slightly forward. She bends forward and looks down at the baby Moses. She wears a gown and has long, curly hair. Her arms are at her side, though bent slightly and with her palms down. Her legs are also bent slightly. She wears a crown on her head and her mouth may be slightly open. To either side of Pharaoh's daughter stand two children, both apparently female with long hair. The child to the left faces left and slightly forward, and bends down to look at Moses. She may be gowned. Her right arm is bent upward, with her palm out. She may be smiling. The child to the right is nude and faces left and down slightly to look at Moses. Her left arm is at her side and her left leg is bent and on tiptoe. To the right of Pharaoh's daughter stand two gowned women, perhaps servants, with long, curly hair. The figure to the left stands, facing forward and slightly left. She bends her head down slightly to look at Moses. Her left arm is at her side. In her left hand she holds a jar or a large vial. Her right arm is bent upward, and she seems to be touching or holding her hair with her right hand. She may be smiling. The figure to the right stands in profile, facing left and looking down at Moses. Her left arm is bent over her chest. To the left of Pharaoh's daughter is Moses. He lies in a wicker basket containing a pillow and blanket. Moses is an infant, nude with short, curly hair. His legs are spread, with his right leg bent under him and his left leg extended forward. His genitals are pictured. His arms are raised at 135 degrees and he faces forward, looking at the woman to his left. To the left of Moses are two gowned female figures. The figure to the far left may be a child, with long hair, who stands facing right. She bends forward at the waist with her arms at her side to look at Moses. The figure to the right is an adult, whose hair is partly covered with a veil or cloth of some sort. She kneels, bending forward, to look at Moses. Her mouth may be slightly open. Her left arm is bent and raised at 45 degrees; with it, she lifts Moses out of his basket. Her right arm is at her side, but bent; her right hand holds her exposed breast. 
       On the lower right corner of the design, a heron or stork stands facing right and bending forward. In its beak it holds a fish, which it is feeding to its chicks, of which there are at least five with upturned beaks, facing left, right, and away. An inlet of the river Nile is in the foreground. The river contains flowering lily pads, reeds with catkins, and long grass. The ground under the figures' feet appears to be grassy and has indeterminate and, at points, flowering vegetation. Three palm trees with rough trunks are in the middle distance, one behind Pharaoh's daughter, one between the rightmost servants, and one on the right margin. Clusters of dates are visible toward the tops of the trunks. In the background, two large pyramids are visible. The ground in the background appears to be sandy.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Pharaoh's daughter</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Pharaoh's daughter stands in the center of the design, facing left and slightly forward. She bends forward and looks down at the baby Moses. She wears a gown and has long, curly hair. Her arms are at her side, though bent slightly and with her palms down. Her legs are bent slightly as well. She wears a crown on her head and her mouth may be slightly open.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To either side of Pharaoh's daughter stand two children, both apparently female with long hair. The child to the left faces left and slightly forward, and bends down to look at Moses. She may be gowned. Her right arm is bent upward, with her palm out. She may be smiling.   </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To either side of Pharaoh's daughter stand two children, both apparently female with long hair. The child to the right is nude and faces left and down slightly to look at Moses. Her left arm is at her side and her left leg is bent and on tiptoe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>vial</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Pharaoh's daughter stand two gowned women with long, possibly curly hair. These figures are perhaps servants. The figure to the left stands, facing forward and slightly left. She bends her head down slightly to look at Moses. Her left arm is at her side, and in her left hand she holds a jar or a large vial. Her right arm is bent upward, and she seems to be touching or holding her hair with her right hand. She may be smiling.   </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Pharaoh's daughter stand two gowned women with long, possibly curly hair. These figures are perhaps servants. The figure to the right stands, facing left and looking down at Moses. Her left arm is bent over her chest.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>Moses</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Pharaoh's daughter lies Moses. Moses is an infant, nude with short, curly hair. His legs are spread, with his right leg bent under him and his left leg extended forward. His arms are raised at 135 degrees and he faces forward, looking at the woman to his left. His genitals are pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Moses are two gowned female figures. The figure to the far left is a child, with long hair, who stands in profile facing right. She bends forward with her arms at her side to look at Moses.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>lifting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Moses are two gowned female figures. The figure to the right is an adult, whose hair is partly covered with a veil or cloth of some sort. She kneels, bending forward, to look at Moses. Her mouth may be slightly open. Her left arm is bent and raised at 45 degrees; with it, she lifts. Her right arm is at her side, but bent; her right hand holds her exposed breast.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>stork</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>giving</characteristic><characteristic>eating</characteristic><characteristic>fish</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the lower right corner of the design, a heron or stork stands facing right and bending forward. In its beak it holds a fish, which it is feeding to its chicks, of which there are at least five with upturned beaks, facing left, right, and away.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Moses lies in a wicker basket containing a pillow and blanket.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>river</characteristic><characteristic>stream</characteristic><characteristic>Nile</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An inlet of the river Nile is in the foreground.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>lily</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>reed</characteristic><characteristic>catkin</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the river are flowering lily pads, reeds with catkins, and long grass. The ground under the figures' feet appears to be grassy and has indeterminate and, at points, flowering vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>palm</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>date</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three palm trees with rough trunks are in the middle distance, one behind Pharaoh's daughter, one between the right-most servants, and one on the right edge of the design. Clusters of dates are visible toward the tops of the trunks.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>pyramid</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the background, two large pyramids are visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground in the background appears to be sandy.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but440.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="2">inv</l><l n="but440.1.wc.01.02" justify="left">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>