<bad id="but424.1" type="paint" work="The Last Supper: 'Verily I Say Unto You that One of You Shall Betray Me'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="424" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Last Supper: 'Verily I Say Unto You that One of You Shall Betray Me'"><main>The Last Supper: "Verily I Say Unto You that One of You Shall Betray Me"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 500KB to 1800KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>December 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
         
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2010 The National Gallery of Art</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup creation</change><date>May 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation, final proofing and publication</change><date>November-December 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and color correction</change><date>September 2003</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Gerald Miller,</name><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The Last Supper: "Verily I say unto You that One of You Shall Betray Me"*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1799">1799<note>The work was exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1799.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>33.0 x 50.0 cm.</objsize><medium>water-based tempera with a glue and/or gum binder and with pen and ink outlining</medium><support>canvas</support><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>National Gallery of Art, Washington</name><date>1951</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Acquired, and probably commissioned, from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1799; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 87 (with lots 85 and 86, *Christ Giving Sight to Bartimaeus*, Butlin 420, and *Job and His Daughters*, Butlin 394, for 11s. to John Clark Strange); possibly an anonymous collector or collectors; the dealer B. F. Stevens and Brown; sold anonymously, Christie's, 22 July 1949 (£819 to the William Blake Trust); sold to Lessing J. Rosenwald in 1951 for presentation to the National Gallery of Art, Washington.</note></provenance><repository><institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution><addressline>Constitution Avenue NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline><addressline>Washington, DC 20565</addressline><addressline>Mailing Address: 2000B South Club Drive, Landover, Maryland 20785</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-202-737-4215</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Print Study Rooms: 1-202-842-6380</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 1-202-842-6126</addressline><addressline>URL, Visual Services: http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">1355</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but424.1.pt.01" dbi="BUT424.1.1.PT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Last Supper: "Verily I Say Unto You That One of You Shall Betray Me"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 424)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work with his monogram, lower left; see the textual transcription.  An enhanced image of the monogram has been provided below.  He exhibited the work at the Royal Academy in 1799.  The painting was restored by John Hell in 1949-51.</p><illus filename="but424.1.1.sg.300.jpg"/></objnote><objsize>33.0 x 50.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="780" height="600"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates the Last Supper (Matthew 26:20-34). Jesus and his twelve apostles sit in a darkened, shadowy room on carpets that are rolled to provide cushions. In the center of the group are (left to right) a goblet, a pitcher with a loaf of bread below it, another goblet, a plate with three loaves of bread and an empty plate above it, and a third goblet. Jesus sits at the head of the group, facing forward and leaning on a roll of carpet with his left arm. He wears a gown, and has long hair, a beard, and a halo composed of beams of light. His legs are stretched out to the left. His arms are bent upward, with his palms out and his fingers outspread. To the left of Jesus sit four apostles. The leftmost apostle sits, facing away but with his head turned to the right, perhaps to look at Jesus. He wears a gown like a toga, and has curly hair and a beard. His legs are bent under him so that he sits on them. His arms are bent upward, with his palms out and his fingers spread, as if in imitation of Jesus's gesture. The second apostle from the left in this group sits facing forward, but looking up and to his right. He appears to be an old man with long hair and a beard. He also wears a gown and has his arms raised, with his hands together as if in prayer. The apostle second from the right has long hair and sits, facing forward but looking to the right and down, with his left arm leaning on a carpet roll. His arms are raised, with his hands clasped together, as if in prayer. He wears a gown. The rightmost apostle in this group sits, facing forward, but looking to the right. He wears a gown and has curly hair and a beard. His arms are bent with his hands together, as if in prayer. To the right of Jesus sit four apostles. The leftmost apostle, though presumably a male, is very feminine looking. This may be John, the youngest of the Evangelists. He has long, curly hair, wears a gown, and sits facing forward and looking to the left, presumably at Jesus. Like Jesus, his legs are extended out, though this apostle's are to the right. His arms are crossed with his hands on his chest, finger's slightly spread. The next apostle to the right sits, facing left, and presumably looking at Jesus. His right arm is raised, with his hand at his face, palm vertical, perhaps in a gesture of surprise or an attempt to shield his face. He has curly hair and a beard. The next apostle to the right in this group sits, facing forward but looking to the left. He has curly hair and wears a gown. He leans with his right arm on a carpet roll with his right hand on his breast. His left arm is bent with the palm out and fingers spread. This gesture suggests that the man is indicating that he is not the one who will betray Christ. The rightmost apostle in this group sits, or perhaps kneels, facing left. He has a beard and his shoulders are hunched, as his head faces down. His arms are raised, with his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. In the foreground is a third group of four apostles. The leftmost apostle appears to be lying, facing away and to the right. He wears a gown and his body is slightly twisted. He has slightly curly hair and a beard, and his arms are bent with his hands together, as if in prayer or supplication. The next apostle to the right sits, facing away, with his legs extended to the left. He is partly clothed by a cloth or drapery around his waist. He faces right to look at the apostle to his right, and has his mouth open. He may be speaking. He also leans with his right arm on a carpet roll. The apostle second from the right in this group sits, facing away but looking to the apostle on the left. He has long curly hair and wears a gown like a toga. His left arm is raised, with the palm vertical and fingers spread. His legs are outstretched to the right. His mouth is slightly open; he may be speaking. The rightmost apostle of this group sits, facing forward, with his legs outstretched to the right. He leans with his right arm on a carpet roll. His left arm is bent, with the palm up and fingers spread to hold coins. He seems to point to his left palm with his right index finger to count the coins. There may be a purse dangling from his right wrist.  This is Judas, Christ's betrayer (although in the Bible he will not receive payment until after the betrayal). He has long hair and a beard and is probably looking at the coins.   
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>chamber</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus and his twelve apostles sit in a darkened, shadowy room.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>carpet</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>pitcher</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus and his twelve apostles sit on carpets that are rolled to provide cushions. In the center of the group are (left to right) a goblet, a pitcher with a loaf of bread below it, another goblet, a plate with three loaves of bread and an empty plate above it, and a third goblet. These all appear to be on the floor of the room.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jesus sits at the head of the group, facing forward and leaning on a roll of carpet with his left arm. He wears a gown, and has long hair, a beard, and a halo composed of beams of light. His legs are stretched out to the left. His arms are bent upward, with his palms out and his fingers outspread. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus sit four apostles. The leftmost apostle sits, facing away but with his head turned to the right, perhaps to look at Jesus. He wears a gown like a toga, and has curly hair and a beard. His legs are bent under him so that he sits on them. His arms are bent upward, with his palms out and his fingers spread, as if in imitation of Jesus's gesture. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus sit four apostles. The apostle second from the left sits facing forward, but looking up and to his right. He appears to be an old man with long hair and a beard. He also wears a gown and has his arms raised, with his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus sit four apostles. The apostle second from the right in this group has long hair and sits, facing forward but looking to the right and down, with his left arm leaning on a carpet roll. His arms are raised, with his hands clasped together, as if in prayer or supplication. He wears a gown. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus sit four apostles. The rightmost apostle in this group sits, facing forward, but looking to the right. He wears a gown and has curly hair and a beard. His arms are bent and his hands together, as if in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>John</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus sit four apostles. The leftmost apostle, though presumably a male, is very feminine looking. He may be John, the youngest of the Evangelists. He has long, curly hair, wears a gown, and sits facing forward and looking to the left, presumably at Jesus. Like Jesus, his legs are extended out, though this apostle's are to the right. His arms are crossed with his hands on his chest, fingers slightly spread. He leans with his right arm on a carpet roll.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus sit four apostles. The apostle second from the left sits, facing left, and presumably looking at Jesus. His arm is raised, with his hand at his face, palm vertical and fingers slightly spread, perhaps in a gesture of surprise or an attempt to shield his face. He has curly hair and a beard. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breast</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus sit four apostles. The apostle second from the right in this group sits, facing forward but looking to the left. He has curly hair and wears a gown. He leans with his right arm on a carpet roll. His right arm is bent over his chest with his right hand, fingers slightly spread, on his breast. His left arm is bent with the palm vertical and fingers spread. These gestures suggest that he is indicating that he is not the apostle who will betray Christ.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To he right of Jesus sit four apostles. The rightmost apostle in this group sits, or perhaps kneels, facing left. He has a beard and his shoulders are hunched, as his head faces down. His arms are raised, with his hands together as if in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground is a third group of four apostles. The leftmost apostle appears to be lying, facing away and to the right. He wears a gown and his body is slightly twisted. He has slightly curly hair and a beard, and his arms are bent with his hands together, as if in prayer or supplication. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground is a third group of four apostles. The apostle second from the left sits, facing away, with his legs extended to the left. He is partly clothed by a cloth or drapery around his waist. He faces right at the apostle to his right, and has his mouth open. He may be speaking. He also leans with his right arm on a carpet roll. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground is a third group of four apostles. The apostle second from the right sits, facing away but looking to the apostle on his left. He has long curly hair and wears a gown like a toga. His left arm is raised, with the palm vertical and fingers spread. His mouth is slightly open; he may be speaking. His legs are outstretched to the right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Judas</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>counting</characteristic><characteristic>coin</characteristic><characteristic>purse</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the foreground is a third group of four apostles. The rightmost apostle in this group sits, facing forward, with his legs outstretched to the right. He leans with his right arm on a carpet roll. His left arm is bent, with the palm up and fingers spread to hold coins. He seems to point to his left palm with his right index finger to count the coins. There may be a purse dangling from his right wrist. This is Judas, Christ's betrayer (although in the Bible he will not receive payment until after the betrayal). He has long hair and a beard and may be looking at the coins.   </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but424.1.pt.01.01" justify="left">inv<note>The upper parts of the letters are obscured, possibly by paint added during restoration.</note></l><l n="but424.1.pt.01.02" justify="left" indent="1">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>