<bad id="but480.1" type="wc" work="The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ycba" catalog="butlin" catid="480" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins"><main>The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 9KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 176KB to 3700KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This work copyright © 2011 Yale Center for British Art</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>May 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image rescanning, new metadata collection and color correction</change><date>August-September 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Gwen Kern,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and metadata collection</change><date>November 1998</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Jessica Kem,</name><name>Greg Murray</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1825">c. 1825</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>42.2 x 35.3 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>42.2 x 35.3 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Yale Center for British Art</name><date>1977</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>William Haines, probably acquired directly from Blake or his wife Catherine c. 1825; Haines' granddaughter, Miss Haines, probably by inheritance in 1848; J. Edwards, offered from his collection, Sotheby's, 20 Dec. 1938, lot 456 (not sold; bought-in at £28); sold to the dealers A. C. Stonehill and P. &amp; D. Colnaghi &amp; Co.; sold for £600 to the dealer Gabriel Wells, possibly acting for A. Edward Newton; sold from Newton's collection, Parke-Bernet, New York, 16 April 1941, lot 117 ($3,100 to the dealer Thomas J. Gannon, possibly acting for Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon, who acquired the work in 1941); given by Paul Mellon to the Yale Center for British Art in 1977.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Yale Center for British Art</institution><addressline>1080 Chapel Street</addressline><addressline>Box 208280</addressline><addressline>New Haven, Connecticut 06520-8280</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-203-432-2840</addressline><addressline>Fax: 1-203-432-7314</addressline><addressline>Email: pdbac@pantheon.yale.edu</addressline><addressline>Email, Rights and Reproductions: ycba.photorights@yale.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: http://ycba.yale.edu/collections/coll_p-d-index.html</addressline><addressline>URL, Rights and Reproductions: http://ycba.yale.edu/departments/depart-ser-rights.html</addressline><department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">B1977.14.6102</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but480.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT480.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 480)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower right in gold; see the textual transcription.  The backing sheet, 45.0 x 36.0 cm. and framing the work on all four sides but largest at the bottom, appears to have been tinted to match the dominant tones of the water color.  The work was in very poor condition when sold at auction in 1938.  It was restored between 1938 and 1941, probably before its sale to Gabriel Wells.</p></objnote><objsize>42.2 x 35.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="700" height="725"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The subject is taken from Matthew 25:1-13. To the left of the design stand the five wise virgins, each one wearing a gown with a head veil over her long, curly hair and holding a lit oil lamp on a chain. The leftmost figure faces left. She holds her lamp in her left hand, with her left arm at her side. The second-to-left figure stands, facing forward and perhaps looking to her right. She holds her lamp in her left hand, and her left arm is at her side. Her right arm is bent with her right palm held vertically. The middle figure faces forward but turns her head to face left. Her left arm is at her side and she holds her lamp in her left hand. The second-to-right figure has her body twisted so that the lower half faces left while the upper half faces forward. She looks up and to the right and has her mouth partly open. Her left arm is bent upward, with her left palm vertical. Her right arm is at her side and she holds her lamp in that hand. The rightmost figure stands in contrapposto so that her body faces forward and the lower half faces slightly left. She looks to the right and holds her left arm horizontally, pointing with her left hand. Her right arm is at her side and she holds her lamp in her right hand. Her mouth may be slightly open. On the right side of the design are the five foolish virgins, each wearing a gown as well as a head veil over her long, curly hair. The leftmost figure kneels with her left leg extended backward. She faces forward and to the left, looking up at the rightmost wise virgin. Her right arm is raised at 135 degrees, reaching for the figure to her left, while her left arm is raised at 45 degrees. Around her left wrist is the chain to an unlit oil lamp. Her mouth is partly open. The second-to-left figure of this group faces away, but looks up and to the left. She may be walking or standing. Her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her left arm, though bent, is raised horizontally. Her right arm, though bent, is raised vertically and in her right hand she holds her veil. Her mouth is open. The middle figure of this group faces right and down and may be standing or walking. She bends forward and bends her arms upward to hold her hands to her face. The second-to-right figure kneels, facing forward and slightly right, though looking up and to the left. Her arms are bent with her hands to the sides of her face, perhaps in fists or perhaps clutching her face. Her mouth is open. The rightmost figure kneels—or may be in the process of standing up—facing forward and slightly right, though looking up and to the left. Her right knee is bent and her arms are raised nearly vertically and bent upward. Her left hand holds the chain of her extinguished lamp. Her mouth is partly open. The scene takes place at night and thus is dark. The virgins stand on a patch of grassy earth. In the left background are low hills and in the right background, a city with at least six buildings is visible, including three spires and a tower. On the right side of the design is a wooden(?) house or hut with a roof and open doorway. The night sky appears to be cloudy. Along the top of the design flies or hovers a spectral male figure, possibly an angel. His body is horizontal and he wears a gown and appears to have long, slightly curly hair. His left arm is extended horizontally and in his left hand he holds a horn or trumpet to his lips, which he presumably blows. The slight indication of his right arm also extends horizontally, with the palm of his right hand facing out toward the viewer. 
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the design stand the five wise virgins, each one wearing a gown with a head veil over her long, curly hair and holding a lit oil lamp. The leftmost figure faces left, though with her body turned to face slightly forward. She holds her lamp on a chain in her left hand, with her left arm at her side. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the design stand the five wise virgins, each one wearing a gown with a head veil over her long, curly hair and holding a lit oil lamp. The second-to-left figure stands, facing forward and perhaps looking up. She holds her lamp on a chain in her left hand with her left arm at her side, and her right arm is bent with the palm vertical. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the design stand the five wise virgins, each one wearing a gown with a head veil over her long, curly hair and holding a lit oil lamp. The middle figure faces forward but turns her head to face left. Her left arm is at her side, though slightly bent, and she holds her lamp on a chain in her left hand. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the design stand the five wise virgins, each one wearing a gown with a head veil over her long, curly hair and holding a lit oil lamp. The second-to-right figure has her body twisted so that the lower half faces left while the upper half faces forward. She looks up and to the right and has her mouth partly open. Her left arm is bent upward, with the left palm vertical. Her right arm is at her side and she holds her lamp on a chain in that hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the design stand the five wise virgins, each one wearing a gown with a head veil over her long,curly hair and holding a lit oil lamp. The rightmost figure stands in contrapposto so that her body faces forward and the lower half faces slightly left. She looks to the right and holds her left arm horizontally, pointing with her left hand. Her right arm is at her side and she holds her lamp on a chain in her right hand. Her left foot may be on tiptoe and her mouth may be slightly open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right side of the design are the five foolish virgins, each wearing a gown as well as a head veil over her long, curly hair. The leftmost figure kneels with her left leg and foot extended backward. She faces forward and to the left, looking up at the rightmost wise virgin. Her right arm is raised at 135 degrees, reaching for the figure to her left, while her left arm is raised at 45 degrees. Around her left wrist is the chain of an unlit oil lamp. Her mouth is partly open. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right side of the design are the five foolish virgins, each wearing a gown as well as a head veil over her long, curly hair. The second-to-left figure of this group faces away, but looks up and to the left. She may be walking or standing. Her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her left arm, though bent, is raised horizontally. Her right arm, though bent, is raised vertically and in her right hand she holds her veil. Her mouth is open. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right side of the design are the five foolish virgins, each wearing a gown as well as a head veil over her long, curly hair. The middle figure of this group faces right and down and may be standing or walking. She bends forward and bends her arms upward to hold her hands to her face. She may be crying. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>fist</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hands on face</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right side of the design are the five foolish virgins, each wearing a gown as well as a head veil over her long, curly hair. The second-to-right figure kneels or crouches, facing forward and slightly right, though looking up and to the left. Her arms are bent with her hands to the sides of her face, perhaps in fists or perhaps clutching her face. Her mouth is open. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right side of the design are the five foolish virgins, each wearing a gown as well as a head veil over her long, curly hair. The rightmost figure kneels—or may be in the process of standing up—facing forward and slightly right, though with her body twisted so she looks up and to the left. Her right knee is bent and her arms are raised nearly vertically and bent upward. Her left hand holds the chain of her extinguished lamp. Her mouth is partly open. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>spectre</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Along the top of the design flies or hovers a spectral male figure, perhaps an angel. His body is horizontal and he wears a gown and appears to have long, slightly curly hair. His left arm is extended horizontally and in his left hand he holds a horn or trumpet to his lips, which he presumably blows. He faces left and slightly forward. His right arm is also extended horizontally with the palm of his right hand facing out toward the viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The virgins stand on a patch of grassy earth. In the left background are low hills.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>city</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right background, a city with at least six buildings is visible, including three spires and a tower.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="BD"><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>nail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the right side of the design is a wooden(?) house or hut with a roof and open doorway. The heads of three nails are pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place at night and thus is dark. The night sky appears to be cloudy. A glow on the horizon near the city suggests that it may be near sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but480.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="45">WBlake inv</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>