<bad id="but448.1" type="wc" work="God Writing Upon the Tables of the Covenant" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngs" catalog="butlin" catid="448"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="God Writing Upon the Tables of the Covenant"><main>God Writing Upon the Tables of the Covenant</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of
                    Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 99KB
                to 997KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                Archives<date>November 2012</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2012</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © 2012 National Gallery of Scotland</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation, copyheader and illustration description</change><date>Summer 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition and color correction</change><date>May 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*God Writing Upon the Tables of the Covenant*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>41.9 x 34.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>42.5 x 34.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>National Gallery of Scotland</name><date>1881</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>bequest</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts no later than c. 1805; by
                    inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; possibly the work offered at
                    Sotheby's, 26 June 1852, lot 182x, not titled (11s. to "Butts," probably
                    indicating that the work did not sell and was returned to the vendor, Thomas
                    Butts, Jr.); Foster &amp; Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 116, titled
                    "The Ten Commandments" (£1.10s. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); acquired at
                    an unknown time by William Findlay Watson; bequeathed by Watson in 1881 to the
                    National Gallery of Scotland.</note></provenance><repository><institution>National Gallery of Scotland</institution><addressline>The Mound</addressline><addressline>Edinburgh EH2 2EL</addressline><addressline>Scotland</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 44 (0)131 624 6200</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.nationalgalleries.org</addressline><addressline>Email: enquiries@nationalgalleries.org</addressline><addressline>Email, Curatorial Staff: nginfo@nationalgalleries.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Curatorial Staff: 44 (0)131 624 6512</addressline><addressline>Email, Registrar: registrars@nationalgalleries.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Registrar: 44 (0)131 624 6317</addressline><addressline>Email, Prints and Drawings:
                    printsanddrawings@nationalgalleries.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Prints and Drawings: 44 (0)131 624 6593</addressline><addressline>URL, Picture Library:
                    http://www.nationalgalleries.org/shop/commercial-and-non-commercial-reproduction</addressline><addressline>Email, Picture Library:
                    picture.library@nationalgalleries.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Picture Library: 44 (0)131 624 6258</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Picture Library: 44 (0)131 624 6260</addressline><department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Inventory number">D 2281</repositoryid><lb/><lb/></repository></source><desc id="but448.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT448.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">God Writing Upon the Tables of the Covenant</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="U1">(Butlin 448)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work, lower right, with his monogram; see the textual
                        transcription. The verso is inscribed, lower right, "D 2281," not by
                        Blake.</p></objnote><objsize>41.9 x 34.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="650" height="760"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The subject of this design, God writing on the tablets of the Ten
                        Commandments, is briefly described in both Exodus 31:18 and Deuteronomy
                        9:10. In the center of the design stands God, facing away. He wears a
                        transparent gown, through which His muscular physique is clearly visible. He
                        has long, white hair that appears to be blowing to the left, as though by a
                        wind. His left leg is bent backward slightly and on tiptoe. His arms are
                        raised between the vertical and 135 degrees, with His left palm vertical and
                        His right hand pointing upward. He has just begun to write on the tablets,
                        as the single letter near the top of the right tablet indicates. Below God,
                        a figure kneels and bends forward in a bow. This is most likely Moses. He
                        wears a gown and his left foot is visible beneath the hem of his gown. He
                        faces away. Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                        right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                        wings. The bottom right group of figures contains at least five figures. The
                        leftmost figure is a male with flame-like hair. He appears to wear a gown
                        and faces to the right and slightly forward. The figure second from the
                        right appears to be a male with cloth draped around his waist. He faces
                        away, with his body twisted slightly so he looks right and down. His right
                        foot is visible. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and he holds a long
                        horn in his right hand, which he presumably blows into. The central figure
                        appears to be a nude female with her hair in a bun. She faces away and is
                        visible from the shoulders up. Her right arm is raised vertically and bent
                        over her head. The figure second from the right appears to be a female(?)
                        and may be gowned. She faces right and looks down. The rightmost figure is a
                        male(?) with short, curly hair. He faces forward and down, as well as to the
                        right slightly. He may be partly clothed in a draping cloth. His right arm
                        is raised horizontally (relative to his body) and he holds a long horn in
                        his right hand. The horn is to his mouth and he presumably blows into it.
                        The central group of figures on the right side of the design consists of
                        five figures. The leftmost figure is a nude, muscular male with short, curly
                        hair. He faces right and down, as though his body is horizontal or he is
                        bending forward. His right arm is raised horizontally and his left arm is
                        bent upward over his head, as though he is supporting the bottom right
                        corner of the tablets that God is writing on. The figure above and second
                        from the left is of indeterminable gender, but faces right and may be
                        gowned. The central and lowest figure may be male and nude. He faces away,
                        with his long hair blowing (by a wind?) to the right, and looks slightly
                        left. The figure second from the right appears to be a female with long
                        hair. She may wear a gown. She faces forward and to the right and is bending
                        forward slightly. The figure above and to the right has short, curly hair
                        and may be nude. It faces away and is of indeterminable gender. The topmost
                        group of figures on the right side of the design appears to be a pair. The
                        leftmost figure is only visible from the neck upward and is of
                        indeterminable gender. It faces to the right and down and has curly hair.
                        The rightmost figure is gowned, but of indeterminable gender. It faces down
                        and to the right, but turns its head to face away. The topmost group of
                        figures on the left side of the design appears to be a pair, both gowned and
                        facing left and up. Both figures may have long hair, though their gender is
                        indeterminable. The central group of figures on the left side of the design
                        consists of four figures. The top figure is a male with short, curly hair.
                        He may wear a gown. He faces right and up. The figure second from the top
                        may be a female with her hair pulled back. She may wear a cloth draped over
                        one shoulder. She faces away and to the left. Her left arm is bent upward
                        over her head. The bottommost figure in the group is a male with curly hair.
                        He faces to the left and his body is horizontal. He may have a strap of
                        cloth over his right shoulder. The rightmost figure of this group is a nude
                        male with short, curly hair. His body is horizontal and he faces left. His
                        left arm is bent upward over his head and he holds onto the left tablet with
                        his left hand. He may be supporting the weight of the tablet on his back.
                        The bottom left group of figures in the design contains five figures. The
                        topmost figure may be a male with short, curly hair; he looks to the right.
                        The figure second from the top may be a male with curly hair. He faces left
                        and down, with a horn to his lips. His left arm is raised horizontally and
                        his left hand holds the long horn. The central figure may be a gowned
                        female(?) with curly hair that is short or pulled back; she faces left and
                        down. The figure second from the bottom may be a partly gowned male(?) with
                        long hair. He faces left and bends forward to look down. His right arm is
                        raised horizontally (relative to his body) and he holds a long horn to his
                        lips with his right hand. The bottommost figure may be a female with curly
                        hair and a headband. She may be gowned, though her shoulders are bare. She
                        faces down and to the left, with both arms raised horizontally (relative to
                        her body) and both hands holding a long horn to her lips. God stands in
                        front of a pair of stone tablets, onto which He has just begun to write the
                        commandments. On the top center of the right tablet is a Hebrew letter. God
                        stands on a stone that may represent the top of Mount Sinai. Flames and
                        smoke radiate outward from the center of the design. A fiery sky may be
                        visible in a break in the smoke and flames at the top center of the
                        design.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>God</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>writing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design stands God, facing away. He wears
                            a transparent gown, through which His muscular physique is clearly
                            visible. He has long, white hair that appears to be blowing to the left,
                            as though by a wind. His left leg is bent backward slightly and on
                            tiptoe. His arms are raised between the vertical and 135 degrees, with
                            His left palm vertical and His right hand pointing upward. He has just
                            begun to write on the tablets, as indicated by the single letter at the
                            top of the tablet on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Moses</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below God, a figure kneels and bends forward in a bow. This is
                            most likely Moses. He wears a gown and his left foot is visible beneath
                            the hem of his gown. He faces away. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                            right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                            wings. The bottom right group of figures contains at least five figures.
                            The leftmost figure is a male with flame-like hair. He appears to wear a
                            gown and faces to the right and slightly forward. The figure second from
                            the right appears to be a male with cloth draped around his waist. He
                            faces away, with his body twisted slightly so he looks right and down.
                            His right foot is visible. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and he
                            holds a long horn in his right hand, which he presumably blows into. The
                            central figure appears to be a nude female(?) with her hair in a bun.
                            She faces away and is visible from the shoulders up. Her right arm is
                            raised vertically and bent over her head. The figure second from the
                            right appears to be a female(?) and may be gowned. She faces right and
                            looks down. The rightmost figure is a male with short, curly hair. He
                            faces forward and down, as well as to the right slightly. He may be
                            partly clothed in a draping cloth. His right arm is raised horizontally
                            (relative to his body) and he holds a long horn in his right hand. The
                            horn is to his mouth and he presumably blows into it. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                            right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                            wings. The central group of figures on the right side of the design
                            consists of five figures. The leftmost figure is a nude, muscular male
                            with short, curly hair. He faces right and down, as though his body is
                            horizontal or he is bending forward. His right arm is raised
                            horizontally and his left arm is bent upward over his head, as though he
                            is supporting the bottom right corner of the tablets that God is writing
                            on. The figure above and second from the left is of indeterminable
                            gender, but faces right and may be gowned. The central and lowest figure
                            may be male and nude. He faces away, with his long hair blowing (by a
                            wind?) to the right, and looks slightly left. The figure second from the
                            right appears to be a female with long hair. She may wear a gown. She
                            faces forward and to the right and is bending forward slightly. The
                            figure above and furthest to the right has short, curly hair and may be
                            nude. It faces away and is of indeterminable gender. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                            right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                            wings. The topmost group of figures on the right side of the design
                            appears to be a pair. The leftmost figure is only visible from the neck
                            upward and is of indeterminable gender. It faces to the right and down
                            and has curly hair. The rightmost figure is gowned, but of
                            indeterminable gender. It faces down and to the right, but turns its
                            head to face away. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                            right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                            wings. The topmost group of figures on the left side of the design
                            appears to be a pair, both gowned and facing left and up. Both figures
                            may have long hair, though their gender is indeterminable.
                        </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                            right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                            wings. The central group of figures on the left side of the design
                            consists of four figures. The top figure is a male with short, curly
                            hair. He may wear a gown. He faces right and up. The figure second from
                            the top may be a female with her hair pulled back. She may wear a cloth
                            draped over one shoulder. She faces away and to the left. Her left arm
                            is bent upward over her head. The bottommost figure in the group is a
                            male with curly hair. He faces to the left and his body is horizontal.
                            He may have a strap of cloth over his right shoulder. The rightmost
                            figure of this group is a nude male with short, curly hair. His body is
                            horizontal and he faces left. His left arm is bent upward over his head
                            and he holds onto the left tablet with his left hand. He may be
                            supporting the weight of the tablet on his back. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>band</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Twenty-three figures hover in the flames around the left and
                            right sides of the design. These may be angels, even though they have no
                            wings. The bottom left group of figures on the design contains five
                            figures. The topmost figure may be a male with short, curly hair; he
                            looks to the right. The figure second from the top may be a male(?) with
                            curly hair. He faces left and down, with a horn to his lips. His left
                            arm is raised horizontally and his left hand holds the long horn. The
                            central figure may be a gowned female(?) with curly hair that is short
                            or pulled back; she faces left and down. The figure second from the
                            bottom may be a partly gowned male with long hair. He faces left and
                            bends forward to look down. His right arm is raised horizontally
                            (relative to his body) and he holds a long horn to his lips with his
                            right hand. The bottommost figure may be a female with curly hair and a
                            headband. She may be gowned, though her shoulders are bare. She faces
                            down and to the left, with both arms raised horizontally (relative to
                            her body) and both hands holding a long horn to her lips.
                        </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>tablet</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>decalogue</characteristic><illusobjdesc>God stands in front of a pair of stone tablets, onto which He
                            is just beginning to write the commandments. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic><characteristic>Old Testament</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the top center of the right tablet is the Hebrew letter
                            ל (lamed).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>Mount Sinai</characteristic><illusobjdesc>God stands on a stone that may represent the top of Mount
                            Sinai.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Flames and smoke radiate outward from the center of the
                            design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A fiery sky may be visible in a break in the smoke and flames
                            at the top center of the design. It may indicate sunrise or sunset.
                        </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but448.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="40">ל<note>This Hebrew
                            letter (lamed) is inscribed at the top of the stone tablet on the right.
                            This is the first letter (reading right to left) in the sixth
                            commandment, "thou shalt not kill." This commandment usually appears at
                            the top of the left tablet in representations of the
                        decalogue.</note></l></lg><vspace extent="8"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but448.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="61">inv</l><l n="but448.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="60">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>