<bad id="but438.1" type="wc" work="Jacob's Dream" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="438" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Jacob's Dream"><main>Jacob's Dream</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 8KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 106KB to 2400KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages illustrated.  They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings.  The present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and 1805.  These designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine.  In works such as <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive.  In other designs, including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction.
            <lb/><lb/>
            This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible.  In coming months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series executed for Butts.  Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> of c. 1824.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2010 British Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>September 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>July 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image scanning and metadata</change><date>September 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Gwen Kern, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Jacob's Dream*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>37.0 x 29.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>39.8 x 30.6 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1949</date><dealer>none recorded</dealer><price>£5460</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; R. Monckton Milnes, 1st Lord Houghton, by 1863; by inheritance in 1885 to his son, 1st Marquess of Crewe; sold in 1904 to W. Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 4 (£5460 to the executors of Robertson's estate for presentation through the National Arts Collection Fund to the British Museum).</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 020-7323-8408</addressline><addressline>Fax: 020-7323-8999</addressline><addressline>Email: printsphoto@thebritishmuseum.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">1949.11.12.2</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but438.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT438.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Jacob's Dream</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 438)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram.  The inscription lower right is also in Blake's hand.  See the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>37.0 x 29.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="780"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This water color illustrates Genesis 28:12, Jacob's dream of a ladder to heaven. At the bottom center of the design lies Jacob, supine and facing forward and up. He wears a toga-like gown and has short curly hair. His eyes are closed, indicating that he is sleeping. His arms are raised horizontally and his right leg is stretched out to the right; his left leg is not visible. Jacob appears to be lying on a rock or hilltop, which may be mossy or grassy. In the background is the night sky, with at least twenty-four stars visible. The sky is lit at the top of the design by a shining orb with rays extending from it—this may be the sun. Beginning to the left of Jacob and ascending to the top of the design is a spiral staircase with a number of figures on it. The first group of four figures on the staircase stands to the left of Jacob. The leftmost figure is a female angel, facing left and slightly forward. Her head is in profile. She is gowned and has wings as well as long hair pulled up in a bun. Her left leg is bent and on tiptoe, suggesting that she is walking—specifically, that she is descending the staircase. Her arms are raised horizontally and bent upward to hold a basket that she balances on her head. The contents of the basket are unclear, but it might contain loaves of bread and/or fruit. The middle figure stands, facing left, but turning her head forward and to the right. She may be looking at the figure to the right. She wears a gown and has curly hair, though it is unclear whether her hair is short or just not visible. In her left hand, she holds a basket or purse. Her right arm, raised vertically, balances a pitcher on her head. She is also descending the stairs. The rightmost adult figure in this group is a female, seen from behind. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her right leg is extended behind her to indicate that she is ascending the stairs. She may be looking at the figure to the left. Her right arm is raised at 135 degrees and between her hands she steadies a small child or infant. The last figure of this group is an infant or small child of indeterminate gender, seen from behind and facing left. It has short hair and is nude. Its right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe and its right arm is raised horizontally to hold the hand of the woman on whose shoulder it balances. It may look at the figure to the left. 
          The second group of figures comprises two gowned and winged angels who are descending the staircase. The figure to the left is male and has short, curly hair. He faces forward and to the left but turns his head to look at the angel to the right. His right leg is bent and on tiptoe. His arms are raised at 45 degrees and in his hands he holds a scroll. The angel to the right is female, and has long hair pulled up in a bun. She faces left and forward and her left leg is bent and on tiptoe. Her arms are at her side, with her right palm out and her left hand holding a book or folio. The next group of figures on the stairs comprise two gowned individuals. The figure to the left, likely a female with long hair, faces away. Her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her right arm is raised at 45 degrees and her left arm is raised at 135 degrees. Between her hands, she holds a scroll. She is ascending the stairs. The figure to the right is male and has short, perhaps curly, hair. He faces forward and right, but turns to look left at the figure or her scroll. His arms are at his side but bent slightly. In his left hand he holds compasses or dividers. In his right hand, he holds an object that may be another instrument such as a plumb bob and string. He is descending the staircase. 
          The next group of figures contains seven individuals, all ascending the staircase. The leftmost figure of this group is a gowned female, seen from behind but turned to look to the right. Her left leg is bent at the knee and her right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her right arm is raised at 45 degres and may hold the hand of the figure to the right. Her left arm is raised horizontally, palm up and fingers spread, and may be pointing to the left. The second-to-left figure appears to be that of a child, though its gender is indeterminable. It wears a gown and stands, facing away, with its arms raised at 135 degrees. It may have short hair. The third-to-left figure is that of an adult female, facing left and slightly forward, though with her head turned to look to the right. She wears a gown and has long hair pulled up into a bun. Her left arm is at her side and she may be holding the hand of the figure to the right. The middle figure of this group appears to be that of a female child, facing left. She is gowned and may be looking at the figure to the left. Her left leg is bent and on tiptoe. The third figure from the right is that of an adult female, seen from behind and standing in contrapposto. Her right leg is extended back and on tiptoe and her arms are at her side, though her right arm is bent so that she can hold the hand of the figure to the right. The second-to-right figure of this group is that of a male(?) angel, nude but with wings. He faces left and away slightly. His right leg is bent and his left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. He has short hair and raises his left arm at 135 degrees to hold the hand of the figure to the left. The rightmost figure of this group may be a female, facing left. She wears a gown and her hair is in a bun. Her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her left arm is at her side, though bent to play the lyre that she presumably holds in her right hand. She raises her head slightly to look upward. 
           The next group on the staircase consists of eight figures. The leftmost figure is that of a female child, who faces right and looks up at the figure to the right. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her right leg is extended backward as she ascends the staircase. Her right arm is at her side but bent, while her left arm is raised at 135 degrees to hold the hand of the figure to the right. The second-to-left figure is that of an adult female, facing right and forward. She looks at the child to the left. Her hair may be short or pulled up into a bun. She wears a gown and has her right arm at her side. She may hold the hand of the child to the left. Her left leg is extended backward as she ascends the staircase. The third-to-left figure is that of an adult female, facing left and slightly forward. Her long hair is pulled up into a bun and she wears a gown. Her left leg is bent as she ascends the staircase. Her arms are crossed around a nude infant that she holds. This infant may face away and has its arms raised at 135 degrees, palms up. The fourth figure from the right may be that of a female(?), facing right as she ascends the stairs. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her right arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent upward to embrace the figure to the right. The third-to-right figure may be a male, facing left. He wears a gown. His right leg is extended backward as he descends the staircase. His left arm is raised horizontally and bent to embrace the figure to the left. The second-to-left figure appears to be that of a child of indeterminable gender. It faces right and extends its right leg backward and on tiptoe as it ascends the staircase. Its right arm is raised at 45 degrees, perhaps to embrace the figure to its right. The rightmost figure of this group stands on the staircase, facing left. This figure may be that of a female child, with her hair pulled back into a ponytail. She is gowned and looks at the figure to the left. She raises her left arm at 45 degrees, perhaps to embrace or hold the figure to the left. 
            The next group of figures on the staircase contains five individuals, all gowned. The leftmost three figures, all of indeterminable gender, all face away and slightly to the left, with their left legs extended backward as they ascend the staircase. The figure second from the right is of indeterminate gender and stands, facing right. Its left leg is extended backward as it descends the stairs. Its arms are raised at 45 degrees to hold the hands of the figure to the right, at which it is looking. The rightmost figure of this group appears to be that of a female, facing left and away. Her long hair is partly pulled into a bun. Her left arm is raised at 45 degrees to hold the hand of the figure to the left, at which she is looking. The next group of figures contains at least nine individuals of indeterminable gender, and all perhaps gowned. The three leftmost and fifth-to-left figures face right and ascend the staircase; the fourth-to-left and four rightmost figures face left and descend the staircase. The leftmost, third-to-left, and fourth-to-left figures are those of children. The leftmost figure has its arms raised at 45 degrees and the fifth-to-left figure has its arms raised horizontally to hold the shoulders of the figure to the right, at which it may be looking. The next group of figures contains at least five figures of indeterminable gender, all gowned, ascending the staircase, and facing away and to the left. All but the second-to-right figure have their left legs extended backward. The middle figure may have its left arm raised at 135 degrees. On the top three loops of the staircase are a number of difficult to discern figures, at least eighteen in total. They all appear to be gowned and to be ascending the staircase. Those on the third-to-top loop face right.          
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the bottom center of the design lies Jacob, supine and facing forward and up. He wears a toga-like gown and has short curly hair. His eyes are closed, indicating that he is sleeping. His arms are raised horizontally and his right leg is stretched out in front of him; his left leg is not visible. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>moss</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Jacob appears to be lying on a rock or hilltop, which may be mossy or grassy. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the background is the night sky, with at least twenty-four stars visible. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>orb</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky is lit at the top of the design by a shining orb with rays extending from it. This may be the sun as image of heaven. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>steps</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beginning to the left of Jacob and ascending to the top of the design is a spiral staircase with a number of figures on it. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>fruit</characteristic><characteristic>purse</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>pitcher</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The first group of four figures on the staircase stands to the left of Jacob. The leftmost figure is a female angel, facing left and slightly forward. She is gowned and has wings as well as long hair pulled up in a bun. Her left leg is bent and on tiptoe, suggesting that she is walking—specifically, that she is descending the staircase. Her arms are raised horizontally and bent upward to hold a wicker basket that she balances on her head. The contents of the basket are unclear, but it might contain loaves of bread and/or fruit. The middle figure stands, facing left, but turning her head forward and to the right. She may be looking at the figure to the right. She wears a gown and has curly hair, though it is unclear whether her hair is short or just not visible. On her left arm, which is at her side, she holds a basket. Her right arm, raised vertically, balances a pitcher on her head. She is also descending the stairs. The rightmost adult figure is that of a female, seen from behind. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her right leg is extended behind her to indicate that she is ascending the stairs. She may be looking at the figure to the left. Her right arm is raised at 135 degrees and between her hands she steadies a small child or infant. The last figure of this group is an infant or small child of indeterminate gender, seen from behind and facing left. It has short hair and is nude. Its right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe and its right arm is raised horizontally to hold the hand of the woman on whose shoulder it balances. It may look at the figure to the left. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The second group of figures is that of two gowned and winged angels who are descending the staircase. The figure to the left is male and has short, curly hair. He faces forward and to the left but turns his head to look at the figure to the right. His right leg is bent and on tiptoe. His arms are raised at 45 degrees and in his hands he holds a scroll. The figure to the right is female, and has long hair pulled up in a bun. She faces left and forward and her left leg is bent and on tiptoe. Her arms are at her side, with her right palm out and her left hand holding a book or folio. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>compasses</characteristic><characteristic>dividers</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The third group of figures on the staircase contains two gowned individuals. The figure to the left, likely a female with long hair, faces away and is ascending the staircase. Her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her right arm is raised at 45 degrees and her left arm is raised at 135 degrees. Between her hands, she holds a scroll. She is ascending the stairs. The figure to the right is male and has short—perhaps curly—hair. He faces forward and right, but turns to look left at the figure or her scroll. His arms are at his side but bent slightly. In his left hand he holds a large pair of compasses or dividers. In his right hand, he holds an object that is difficult to distinguish, but which may be an instrument such as a plumb and string. He is descending the staircase. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>lyre</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The fourth group of figures contains seven individuals, all ascending the staircase. The leftmost figure of this group is a gowned female, seen from behind but turned to look to the right. Her left leg is bent at the knee and her right leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her right arm is raised at 45 degres and may hold the hand of the figure to the right. Her left arm is raised horizontally, palm up and fingers spread, and may be pointing to the left. The second-to-left figure appears to be that of a child, though its gender is indeterminable. It wears a gown and stands, facing away, with its arms raised at 135 degrees. It may have short hair. The third-to-left figure is that of an adult female, facing left and slightly forward, though with her head turned to look to the right. She wears a gown and has her long hair pulled up into a bun. Her left arm is at her side and she may be holding the hand of the figure to the right. The middle figure of this group appears to be that of a female child, facing left. She is gowned and may be looking at the figure to the left. Her left leg is bent and on tiptoe. The figure third from the right is that of an adult female, seen from behind and standing in contrapposto. Her right leg is extended back and on tiptoe and her arms are at her side, though her right arm is bent so that she can hold the hand of the figure to the right. The second-to-right figure of this group is that of a male(?) angel, nude but with wings. He faces left and away slightly. His right leg is bent and his left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. He has short hair and raises his left arm at 135 degrees to hold the hand of the figure to the left. The rightmost figure of this group may be a female, facing left. She wears her hair in a bun and wears a gown. Her left leg is extended backward and on tiptoe. Her left arm is at her side, though bent to play the lyre that she presumably holds in her right hand. She raises her head slightly to look upward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The fifth group on the staircase consists of eight figures. The leftmost figure is that of a female child, who faces right and looks up at the figure to the right. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her right leg is extended backward as she ascends the staircase. Her right arm is at her side but bent, while her left arm is raised at 135 degrees to hold the hand of the figure to the right. The second-to-left figure is that of an adult female, facing right and forward. She looks at the child to the left. Her hair may be short or pulled up into a bun. She wears a gown and has her right arm at her side. She may hold the hand of the child to the left. Her left leg is extended backward as she ascends the staircase. The third-to-left figure is that of an adult female, facing left and slightly forward. Her long hair is pulled up into a bun and she wears a gown. Her left leg is bent as she ascends the staircase. Her arms are crossed around a nude infant that she holds. This infant may face away and has its arms raised at 135 degrees, palms up. The figure fourth from the right may be that of a female(?), facing right as she ascends the stairs. She wears a gown and has long hair. Her right arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent upward to embrace the figure to the right. The third-to-right figure may be a male, facing left. He wears a gown. His right leg is extended backward as he descends the staircase. His left arm is raised horizontally and bent to embrace the figure to the left. The second-to-left figure appears to be that of a child of indeterminable gender. It faces right and extends its right leg backward and on tiptoe as it ascends the staircase. Its right arm is raised at 45 degrees, perhaps to embrace the figure to the right. The rightmost figure of this group stands on the staircase, facing left. This figure may be that of a female child, with her hair pulled back. She is gowned and looks at the figure to the left. She raises her left arm at 45 degrees, perhaps to embrace or hold the figure to the left. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sixth group of figures on the staircase contains five individuals, all gowned. The leftmost three figures—all of indeterminable gender—all face away and slightly to the left, with their left legs extended backward as they ascend the staircase. The second-to-right figure is of indeterminate gender and stands, facing right and slightly forward. Its left leg is extended backward as it descends the stairs. Its arms are raised at 45 degrees to hold the hands of the figure to the right, at which it is looking. The rightmost figure of this group appears to be that of a female, facing left and away. Her long hair is partly pulled up into a bun. Her left arm is raised at 45 degrees to hold the hand of the figure to the left, at which she is looking. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The seventh group of figures contains at least nine individuals of indeterminable gender, and all perhaps gowned. The three leftmost and fifth-to-left figures face right and ascend the staircase; the fourth-to-left and four rightmost figures face left and descend the staircase. The leftmost, third-to-left, and fourth-to-left figures are those of children. The leftmost figure has its arms raised at 45 degrees and the fifth-to-left figure has its arms raised horizontally to hold the shoulders of the figure to its right, at which it may be looking. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The eighth group of figures contains at least five figures of indeterminable gender, all gowned, ascending the staircase, and facing away and to the left. All but the second-to-right figure have their left legs extended backward. The middle figure may have its left arm raised at 135 degrees. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the top three loops of the staircase are a number of difficult to discern figures, at least eighteen in total. They all appear to be gowned and to be ascending the staircase. Those on the third-to-top loop face right.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but438.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">inv</l><l n="but438.1.wc.01.02" justify="left">WB</l><l n="but438.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="48">Genesis XXVIII c. 12 v</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>