<bad id="but416.1" type="paint" work="The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="416" mode="preview" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes"><main>The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of
                    Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 500KB
                to 1800KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>December 2010</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2010</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © Robert N. Essick</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup creation</change><date>May 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation, final proofing and publication</change><date>November-December 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and color correction</change><date>September 2003</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Gerald Miller,</name><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1800">c. 1800</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>32.7 x 49.4 cm.</objsize><medium>water-based tempera with a glue and/or gum binder and with pen and ink
                    outlining</medium><support>copper</support><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1980</date><dealer>Raphael Valls Gallery</dealer><price>$12,000</price><note>Acquired, and probably commissioned, from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1800; by
                    inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold from his collection, Foster and
                    Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 140, with *The
                        Circumcision*, Butlin 403 (16s. to "C. Martin," probably a dealer);
                    anonymous owner or owners between 1853 and the 1960s; "bought c. 1960 at a
                    London sale room (not Christie's or Sotheby's) in a mixed lot as 'and another
                    [item]'" (Butlin 416); sold Sotheby's, 23 Nov. 1966, lot 82 (£1000 to A. J.
                    Mathers acting for Kerrison Preston); sold from Preston's estate, Sotheby's, 20 March 1974, lot 28
                    (£2000 to the dealer Herner Wengraf Ltd.); "passed by amalgamation" (Butlin 416)
                    to the dealer P. and D. Colnaghi; passed to the dealer Rafael Valls Gallery; offered Christie's, 23 June 1978, lot 145 (not sold);
                    acquired April 1980 from Rafael Valls Gallery by Robert N. Essick.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick, Altadena, California</institution></repository></source><desc id="but416.1.pt.01" dbi="BUT416.1.1.PT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 416)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake exhibited this work at the Royal Academy in 1800. The painting has been
                        restored at least twice. The faces of the three Apostles left of Christ have
                        been overpainted in ways uncharacteristic of Blake's work.</p></objnote><objsize>32.7 x 49.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="780" height="600"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design represents Christ's miracle of the loaves and fishes as
                        described in Matthew 14:15-21. In the center stands Jesus, with long hair, a
                        beard, and a halo (the halo no much decayed). He faces forward and wears a
                        gown. His arms are bent at the elbow with his right palm facing out, as
                        though blessing, and his left arm is holding what appears to be two loaves
                        of bread. Three of the Evangelists, probably Matthew, Mark, and Luke, stand
                        on the left. The leftmost of this group faces left and is bending down
                        slightly to look at the man to whom he hands bread. He has short, curly hair
                        and a beard, and wears a gown. In his left arm, which is bent, he holds what
                        appear to be three loaves of bread. His right arm is at his side, and he
                        uses that hand to give out another loaf. The middle of the apostles to the
                        left of Jesus faces forward. He has curly hair and a beard and wears a gown.
                        His eyes appear to be closed or cast sharply down. In his arms, which are
                        crossed, he appears to hold two loaves of bread and a fish. The rightmost of
                        the apostles to the left of Jesus faces right and slightly forward. He has a
                        beard and wears a gown, and appears to be looking at Jesus. At least his
                        left hand is raised, palm out. The largest figure right of Jesus and just
                        within the right margin is probably John, the youngest Evangelist. He faces
                        right, though with his head turned slightly forward. He bends forward to
                        hand food to someone past the edge of the image. He wears a gown and has
                        long, possibly curly hair. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent
                        slightly. He holds with is left hand a cloth, or a part of his gown, which
                        may contain a loaf of bread visible just left of his right upper arm. The
                        suggestion of the multitudes gathered to hear Jesus preach and to be fed by
                        him is made by a number of groups of figures, most of which are indistinct.
                        There are two groups of huddled figures to the left of the leftmost
                        disciple, one in the background and one in the foreground. The group in the
                        background is particularly indistinct and could contain any numbers of
                        bodies, but there is the suggestion of the back of at least one figure,
                        sitting and facing right. In the group in the foreground, two figures are
                        distinguishable, male(?) child facing forward and an old man with a beard.
                        The old man is seated, probably gowned, ans with his left arm bent upward to
                        receive a loaf of bread from the apostle to the right. Between Jesus and the
                        apostle to his right are two groups of huddled figures, one in the
                        background and one in the middle ground. There may be ten or more figures in
                        the group in the background. Two figures of indeterminate gender are
                        somewhat distinguishable in the center of this group. The figure to the left
                        sits, facing left, with its legs extended in front of it. Its left arm may
                        be resting on its left thigh, and bent upward. The figure to the right lies,
                        propped up on its right arm, which is bent at the elbow. It faces right and
                        extends its legs in front of it. In the group in the middle ground, three
                        heads are visible on the left side of the group. Their gender is
                        indeterminable and they face right and forward. Directly below them is
                        visible the head of what may be an old man in a gown, with long hair and a
                        beard, facing right. On the right side of this group, two figures are
                        distinguishable. The figure to the left may be a woman in a gown, facing
                        left. The figure to the right is an old man in a gown, with long hair and a
                        beard, facing left. His visible left arm is bent toward his chest, as though
                        his arms are crossed. His right leg is extended backward, and both his legs
                        are bent as though he is walking to the left. Given the similarity of his
                        pose to that of the disciples in the foreground, he may be a disciple
                        handing out food. In the foreground right of Christ, a nude young male with
                        short, curly hair is seen from behind. He looks up to his left at Jesus. His
                        left leg is extended backward and is on tiptoe. His arms are bent with the
                        palms held vertically and out and the fingers spread. His size suggests that
                        he is a child. In the crook of his right arm he holds a wicker basket. Above
                        John, the Evangelist far right, are two groups of huddled figures, one atop
                        a hill in the background and one midway down the hill. There may be seven or
                        more figures in the group atop the hill. The only one clearly
                        distinguishable sits, facing left, with its legs extended in front and bent
                        slightly. There may be four or more figures in the group midway up the hill.
                        The face of the leftmost figure is visible, facing right and slightly
                        forward. There may be a group of huddled figures just above John's right
                        lower arm. Three figures are distinguishable below and to the right of John.
                        The leftmost figure is that of a nude child with short hair. This child
                        faces right and slightly forward, and has its right arm bent upward to hold
                        what appears to be a loaf of bread. Its left leg is extended backward and is
                        on tiptoe, and both legs are bent to suggest that he(?) is walking to the
                        right. The middle figure is that of a nude infant with short hair, being
                        suckled. It faces right, with its head turned forward and its right arm bent
                        upward to hold its mother's breast. The rightmost figure is that of a woman,
                        with long, curly hair pulled up into a bun. Her breasts are exposed, but she
                        may wear a skirt or have some other kind of cloth secured around her waist.
                        She is sitting, facing left and forward, with her legs bent and drawn up
                        slightly. Her arms are bent so that she can support with both hands the
                        infant she is feeding. She may be looking at the child to the left who is
                        carrying a loaf of bread. The foreground beneath Jesus and the apostles is
                        grassy, as is the top of a hill in the background, far upper right. The sky
                        appears to be cloudy. </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>blessing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center stands Jesus, with long hair, a beard, and a
                            halo (the halo no much decayed). He faces forward and wears a gown. His
                            arms are bent at the elbow with his right palm facing out, as though
                            blessing, and his left arm is holding what appears to be two loaves of
                            bread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>Matthew</characteristic><characteristic>Mark</characteristic><characteristic>Luke</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>fish</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>giving</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three of the Evangelists, probably Matthew, Mark, and Luke,
                            stand on the left. The leftmost of this group faces left and is bending
                            down slightly to look at the man to whom he hands bread. He has short,
                            curly hair and a beard, and wears a gown. In his left arm, which is
                            bent, he holds what appear to be three loaves of bread. His right arm is
                            at his side, and he uses that hand to give out another loaf. The middle
                            of the apostles to the left of Jesus faces forward. He has curly hair
                            and a beard and wears a gown. His eyes appear to be closed or cast
                            sharply down. In his arms, which are crossed, he appears to hold two
                            loaves of bread and a fish, the latter identifiable by its tail. The
                            rightmost of the apostles to the left of Jesus faces right and slightly
                            forward. He has a beard and wears a gown, and appears to be looking at
                            Jesus. At least his left hand is raised, palm out.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>John</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>giving</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The largest figure right of Jesus and just within the right
                            margin is probably John, the youngest Evangelist. He faces right, though
                            with his head turned slightly forward. He bends forward to hand food to
                            someone past the edge of the image. He wears a gown and has long,
                            possibly curly hair. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent
                            slightly. He holds with is left hand a cloth, or a part of his gown,
                            which may contain a loaf of bread visible just left of his right upper
                            arm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There are two groups of figures to the left of the leftmost
                            disciple, one in the background and one in the foreground. The group in
                            the background is particularly indistinct and could contain any numbers
                            of bodies, but there is the suggestion of the back of at least one
                            figure, sitting and facing right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The suggestion of the multitudes gathered to hear Jesus preach
                            and to be fed by him is made by a number of groups of figures, most of
                            which are indistinct. There are two groups to the left of the leftmost
                            disciple, one in the background and one in the foreground. The group in
                            the background is particularly indistinct and could contain any numbers
                            of bodies, but there is the suggestion of the back of at least one
                            figure, sitting and facing right. In the group in the foreground, two
                            figures are distinguishable, male(?) child facing forward and an old man
                            with a beard. The old man is seated, probably gowned, ans with his left
                            arm bent upward to receive a loaf of bread from the apostle to the
                            right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>resting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the apostle to the right are two groups of
                            huddled figures, one in the background and one in the middle ground.
                            There may be ten or more figures in the group in the background. Two
                            figures of indeterminate gender are somewhat distinguishable in the
                            center of this group. The figure to the left sits, facing left, with its
                            legs extended in front of it. Its left arm may be resting on its left
                            thigh, and bent upward. The figure to the right lies, propped up on its
                            right arm, which is bent at the elbow. It faces right and extends its
                            legs in front of it.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>disciple</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the apostle to his right are two groups of
                            huddled figures, one in the background and one in the middle ground. In
                            the group in the middle ground, three heads are visible to the left side
                            of the group. Their gender is indeterminable and they face right and
                            forward. Directly below them is visible the head of what may be an old
                            man in a gown, with long hair and a beard, facing right. On the right
                            side of this group, two figures are distinguishable. The figure to the
                            left may be a woman in a gown, facing left. The figure to the right is
                            an old man in a gown, with long hair and a beard, facing left. His
                            visible left arm is bent toward his chest, as though his arms are
                            crossed. His right leg is extended backward, and both his legs are bent
                            as though he is walking to the left. Given the similarity of his pose to
                            that of the disciples in the foreground, he may be a disciple handing
                            out food.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>basket</characteristic><characteristic>wicker</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between Jesus and the apostle to the right is a nude male with
                            short, curly hair is seen from behind. He looks up to his left at Jesus.
                            His left leg is extended backward and is on tiptoe. His arms are bent
                            with the palms held vertically and out and the fingers spread. His size
                            suggests that he is a child. In the crook of his right arm, he holds a
                            wicker basket.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above John, the apostle on the right, are two groups of
                            huddled figures, one atop a hill in the background and one midway down
                            the hill. There may be seven or more figures in the group atop the hill.
                            The only one clearly distinguishable sits, facing left, with its legs
                            extended in front and bent slightly. There may be four or more figures
                            in the group midway up the hill. The face of the leftmost figure is
                            visible, facing right and slightly forward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There may be a group of huddled figures just above John's
                            right lower arm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>eating</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below and to the right of John (the Evangelist on the right)
                            are a group of three figures. The leftmost figure is that of a nude
                            child with short hair. This child faces right and slightly forward, and
                            has its right arm bent upward to hold what appears to be a loaf of
                            bread. Its left leg is extended backward and is on tiptoe, and both legs
                            are bent to suggest that he(?) is walking to the right. The middle
                            figure is that of a nude infant with short hair being suckled. It faces
                            right, with its head turned forward and its right arm bent upward to
                            hold its mother's breast. The rightmost figure is that of a woman, with
                            long, curly hair pulled up into a bun. Her breasts are uncovered, but
                            may wear a skirt or have some other kind of cloth secured around her
                            waist. She is sitting, facing left and forward, with her legs bent and
                            drawn up slightly. Her arms are bent so that she can support the infant
                            she is breast feeding with both hands. She may be looking at the child
                            to the left who is carrying a loaf of bread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The foreground beneath Jesus and the apostles is
                            grassy.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>There may be grass atop the hill far upper
                            right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A hill with a steep cliff on its left side rises far upper
                            right. To the left is another hill or distant mountain.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky appears to be cloudy.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>