<bad id="but51.1" type="wc" work="The Landing of Brutus in England" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="princeton" catalog="butlin" catid="51">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Landing of Brutus in England">
                    <main>
                        The Landing of Brutus in England</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 33KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Princeton University Library

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Landing of Brutus in England*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1779.A">c. 1779<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations and the relationship between this work and Blake's other water colors illustrating English history.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>13.5 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.5 x 18.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Princeton University Library</name>
                <date>1985</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, lot 172 with eight other works by Blake (19s.); Colonel Gould Weston; by inheritance to Nora Hunter; sold anonymously from the "properties of the late Colonel Gould Weston," Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 26 (&#163;68 to the dealer Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons); Mrs. A. B. Clifton; sold 1966 through Agnew's to Robert H. Taylor; deposited by Taylor in the Princeton University Library in 1972; given by bequest at Taylor's death in 1985 to Princeton University Library.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Princeton University Library</institution>
                <collection>Robert H. Taylor Collection</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">RTC01, HSVTaylor, drawer 11</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but51.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT51.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Landing of Brutus in England</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 51)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This work is part of a series of water colors Blake executed c. 1779 illustrating major events in the history of England.  Eight of these works are extant.  These designs may be related to "The History of England, a small book of Engravings" Blake listed in his advertisement "To the Public" of 10 Oct. 1793 (Erdman page 693).  No copy of that "book" has ever been recorded.  See also the list of subjects from the history of England Blake wrote in his Notebook c. 1793 (Erdman page 672).</p></objnote>
                <objsize>13.5 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design represents the legendary arrival of Brutus, great-grandson of Aeneas, from Greece with a troupe of rebel Trojans to conquer Albion. It shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. In the center of the design, near its lower edge, Brutus kneels and kisses the ground. He is beardless and wears a helmet on his head. His upper body is covered in armor, and a long flowing cape covers his lower body, gathering into folds near the water behind him. A spear rests on the ground below Brutus's left hand and points to the left. The other six figures who are fully visible all have curly hair and beards. They are as follows, from left to right: a man wearing a helmet and breastplate who lunges forward and raises both hands upward; an old man kneeling behind Brutus with his head raised and his hands in a prayerful posture; above the old man and Brutus, a man in a long gown and a cape who holds his left hand downward and his right hand forward with his palm facing out; another gowned man with a cape who strides forward and points with his right hand but looks backward toward the boats and his companions; a gowned and robed man who also looks backward with his right arm raised in front and his left hand resting on his bent left leg; and an armored, robed man who grasps the figure in front of him with his left hand, holds his right arm across his chest, and looks behind him. Above this last man's head, a hand appears, presumably from a figure outside of the design's edge. Another hand appears between the right shoulder of the rightmost figure and the face of the man in front of him. In the lower righthand corner, the bows of two open boats protrude from the design's right edge. Both bear decorations on their visible port sides, and they float on a small area of water near the design's lower edge. The shore contains what appear to be shells in the lower lefthand corner. The hilly English landscape behind the figures is vaguely populated with vegetation and animals. Mountain tops form the background at upper left.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sailor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Arms and hands near the right edge of the design suggest additional figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Brutus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. In the center of design, near its lower edge, Brutus kneels and kisses the ground. Facing left, his body bends forward in a contracted posture with his bent legs pulled under him as his haunches rest on flexed feet. His head is down, his eyes closed, and his mouth open as his lips touch the ground. Brutus's left arm is bent, and his palm is braced on the ground in front of his left knee. His right arm extends outward along the ground beside his head. The fingers of his right hand are spread and his palm faces forward. Unlike the other men, the Brutus figure is beardless. He wears a helmet on his head. His upper body is covered in armor to the wrists, but his hands are bare. A long, flowing cloak or cape covers his lower body, gathering into folds near the water behind him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A spear rests on the ground below Brutus's left hand. Its tip points to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Brutus's men all have curly hair and beards. The figure farthest left strides or lunges out in front of his companions, including Brutus, with his right leg forward and his left bent behind him. Alternatively, he may kneel with his left knee resting on the ground. He faces left and raises both hands above his head with spread fingers, suggesting a posture of worship, gratitude, or elation. He appears to gaze up and left, and his mouth may be open. A long cloak coveres bulky pants (or part of a gown) and a slight suggestion of a breastplate or other armor. The man's arms are bare except for his shoulders, which are covered by the cloak or drapery. On his head is a helmet that resembles Brutus's but with a large plume on top.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sailor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Brutus's men all have curly hair and beards. Second from left in this group is an old man in a gown who kneels behind Brutus in a similarly contracted posture. He faces left with his shoulders hunched forward, but his head is raised; his eyes and mouth appear to be closed. He holds his hands out in front in a prayerful posture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sailor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Brutus's men all have curly hair and beards. Above the old man and Brutus is a man in a long gown, a belt, and a cloak or other drapery that covers his right shoulder and crosses in front of his body toward his left hip. His legs are hidden by the figures in front of him, but he appears to stride leftward. He faces left, perhaps with eyes raised and mouth open. His right arm is bent at the elbow, his forearm extends horizontally leftward, and his hand is raised at a ninety-degree angle with his palm facing to the left. His fingers may be spread slightly. He holds his left hand downward at his side, palm facing forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sailor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Brutus's men all have curly hair and beards. Fourth from left among these men, just in front of the leftmost boat, a man appears to walk toward the left. He wears a sleeveless gown and a short cloak or cape with a decorative border extends behind him. His raised right arm extends horizontally and is mostly hidden behind the man who walks in front of him. With the index finger of his right hand, which appears to the left of this other man, he points leftward. Most of his left arm is hidden behind the figure at left, but the angle of his shoulder suggests that this arm is also raised, though slightly lower than his right arm. The young man turns his head to look backward at his companions who are still in the boats. He gazes right and slightly downward with his mouth open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sailor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chest</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Brutus's men all have curly hair and beards. Standing on the leftmost boat is a man whose chest is partly covered by a short-sleeved gown or shirt and a long, draping cloak or other drapery with a scalloped edge. His torso is turned to face the viewer, but his lower body is turned toward the left; his head turns to the right, back toward his companion in the boat. The sailor's right arm, partially covered by his cloak, is raised horizontally toward the man in front of him with a slight bend in the elbow. He holds his hand upward with fingers spread, and his palm faces the viewer. His left arm extends downward and bends slightly so that his left hand rests on his bent left knee. The bend in his left leg forms a right angle, and his foot rests on the edge of the boat. The figure turns his head to face the man behind him, casting his eyes slightly downward at this companion or at the boats below. His mouth may be open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sailor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows at least seven male figures arriving in two boats and climbing onto the English shore. Brutus's men all have curly hair and beards. The last figure in this procession, pictured at the right edge of the design, is a man standing erect in one of the boats. He wears armor that covers his torso and part of his left arm. A long cloak or other cloth covers his right shoulder and crosses in front of his body to wrap around his left hip. His left arm is bent at the elbow, his forearm extending to the left to touch or grasp the waist of the man in front of him. His right arm appears to be crossed in front of his chest. While the man's body faces left, his head faces right as he turns to look backward at (presumably) more sailors outside the design's frame. His eyes, like his companion's, are cast slightly downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trojan</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the rightmost man's head, a raised arm and hand appear, presumably from a figure outside of the design's border. Another hand appears between the rightmost man's right shoulder and the face of the man in front of him at left. This hand is clenched into a fist.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner, the bows of two open boats protrude from the design's right edge. Both bear decorations on their visible port sides.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two boats sit on a small area of water near the design's lower right edge.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Britain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The shoreline of Britain extending along the bottom of the design contains what appear to be shells in the lower lefthand corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Britain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The English landscape behind the figures is composed of rolling hills. Mountains rise at left along the design's upper edge.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rolling hills of the English landscape behind the figures is vaguely populated with vegetation, likely trees and bushes.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="A">
                        <characteristic>deer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the background landscape, between the heads of two leftmost standing figures, are two deer running or leaping to the left among the hills and trees. The deer on the left has antlers, suggesting that he may be a stag. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
