<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2005-07-07T15:01:49-04:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><!-- Step 2 Conversion to BAD DTD 2004 using modblake.pl Mon Jun 27 14:35:47 2005 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="but528.1" type="wc" work="Illustrations to Milton's Comus" set="The Butts Set" copyid="1" institution="boston" catalog="butlin" catid="528"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Illustrations to Milton's &#34;Comus&#34;"><main>Illustrations to Milton's "Comus"</main><set>The Butts Set</set>: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, and</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt><sponsor>The
               Library of Congress and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 
               with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software grants from Sun Microsystems
               
            </sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file; 16 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 170KB to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; CDL<date>November 2007</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of Blake's illustrations to John Milton's <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>. This group of eight water colors was acquired, and probably commissioned, by Thomas Butts in about 1815. These designs, now in the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (our image annotation program).<lb/><lb/>
            Blake had produced a suite of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> water colors for the Rev. Joseph Thomas in 1801. This earlier group, previously published in the Archive, pictures the same eight subjects as the set presented here. There are, however, many differences between the two suites in motifs and in the portrayals of characters from the poem. The Thomas designs show strong outlines and relatively subdued colors; in contrast, the Butts designs include more interior modeling and an emphasis on complex surfaces created with small brush strokes.<lb/><lb/>
            In his <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs, as is usual in his work as an illustrator of other poets' writings, Blake paid close attention to the text, but this disciplined approach did not preclude his own interpretations. For example, Milton ends his masque with joyous dance and song, but Blake ends his illustrations on a more serious note, as indicated by the facial expressions of all six figures. His selection of poetic passages to illustrate reveals, in itself, Blake's emphasis on unusual states of consciousness, including trances and visions.<lb/><lb/>
            With this publication, the Archive contains five of Blake's nine series of water colors illustrating Milton's poetry: both sets of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs, the Thomas set of illustrations to "On the Morning of Christ's Nativity," the illustrations to "L'Allegro" and "Il Penseroso," and the <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> designs. It is our intention to publish in the near future the remaining four series: three sets illustrating <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and the Butts set of designs for "On the Morning of Christ's Nativity."<lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2007</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2007 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>September 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee, </name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration description creation</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Michelle Langston, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Illustrations to Milton's "Comus"*, The Butts Set</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake
               <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1815.A">c. 1815</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>8</numberobj><objorder>1-8</objorder><objsize>each approximately 15.4 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>8</numberleaves><leafsize>approximately 15.4 x 12.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and water color</medium><support>paper, probably wove</support><watermark>none visible because the designs are pasted to backing mats</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name><date>1890</date><dealer>Bernard Quaritch</dealer><price>not recorded, but probably near $5000 with 18 other works by Blake</price><note>Acquired directly from Blake, and probably commissioned, by Thomas Butts, c. 1815; possibly inherited in 1845 by Thomas Butts, Jr., or sold to Edward Vernon Utterson; offered anonymously (but possibly from Utterson's collection or from the Butts collection), Sotheby's, 5 July 1852, lot 253 (£4.6s. to Thomas Butts, Jr., indicating that the lot was bought-in if Butts was the vendor); sold from the Butts collection, Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 98 (£6.6s. to J. C. Strange); acquired at an unrecorded time (probably shortly before August 1883) by the dealer Bernard Quaritch; offered in Quaritch's catalogue 350 of August 1883, item 13842, with a large group of other works by Blake (£1200); the same group offered in Quaritch's catalogues of *William Blake's Original Drawings*, May 1885 and November 1886, page 1, no item number (£1200); the same group offered in Quaritch's 1887 *General Catalogue of Books*, vol. 2, item 13842 (£1200); offered in Quaritch's 1890 *Hand-List of a Peerless Collection of Books and Manuscripts Exhibited to the Bibliophiles of America*, item 156, with 9 water colors from the Butts set of Blake's *Paradise Lost* illustrations (Butlin 536) and a group of 9 of Blake's drawings illustrating the Bible ($5000); this last group acquired in 1890 by the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, the gift of Mrs. John L. Gardner and George N. Black.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution><addressline>Avenue of the Arts</addressline><addressline>465 Huntington Avenue</addressline><addressline>Boston, Massachusetts 02115-5597</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 617-267-9300</addressline><addressline>Fax: 626-859-4972</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.mfa.org/</addressline><department>Prints, Drawings, and Photographs</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">90.119-126</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but528.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT528.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Comus with His Revellers</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 528.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.4 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Five revelers, representing Comus and four of his enchanted followers,
                  gambol across the design from mid-upper right to lower left, in a woodland setting.
                  Comus, the male in human form at the right, prances forward with right leg
                  extended, carrying a magician's wand or staff in one of his upraised hands and a
                  cup or goblet in his other hand.  
                  Three of his followers are depicted at full-length, with the head and part of the upper body
                  of a fourth pictured just to the left of the tree trunk on the right.
                  The four followers have each been turned into brutes and have animal heads atop
                  (mostly) human bodies (from left to right, a hog, a dog, an ox or cow, and a bird).  
                  They each bear a torch or large candle.
                  A young woman sits on a rock or bank at the bottom right corner;
                  she turns right and holds her arms bent upward from the elbows, palms out. With her head
                  up and back, she looks up and to the right.
                  She is Milton's "Lady," threatened by Comus.  
                  A tree with prominent roots grows above and to the right of the Lady and leans
                  rightward out of the design, while other trees fill in the background to the left and right
                  of the human-beasts.  The dark sky with stars indicates
                  that this is a night scene.
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Comus</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>carrying</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     Comus, the male in human form at the right, prances forward with right leg
                     extended and left leg bent backward.  Legs apart, he strides forward and to 
                     the left but turns his head to look right.  He holds both arms upward, bent
                     at the elbows, and carries a magician's wand or staff in his upraised right
                     hand and a goblet or cup in his left.  He is wearing semi-transparent tights
                     and has shoes or slippers on both feet.  His hair is curly and he appears to
                     be smiling slightly, eyes raised.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>arm</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>hog</characteristic><characteristic>ox</characteristic><characteristic>cow</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>fingers</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><illusobjdesc> Five revelers, representing Comus and four of his enchanted followers,
                     gambol across the design from mid-upper right to lower left, in a woodland setting.  
                     Three of his followers are depicted at full-length, while the head and upper body
                     of a fourth extends just to the left of the tree trunk on the right.  The followers
                     have each been turned into brutes and have animal heads atop (mostly) human bodies 
                     (from left to right, a hog, a dog, an ox or cow, and a bird).  The leftmost figure, a woman
                     wearing a transparent gown, has the head of a hog.  This figure strides forward or 
                     stands on her left foot, right foot extended behind her on tiptoe, and twists
                     her upper body rightward, lifting both arms over her head.  She carries a candle in 
                     her right hand.  Two tusks are visible in her mouth.  The dog-man to the right of her
                     lunges left, with right leg bent forward and bent left leg extended behind him.  He
                     twists away and to the right, as if to look behind him, and lifts both arms vertically;
                     his right palm is held vertically, and his left hand holds a candle.  He is wearing a
                     collar around his neck, and ribbons or bands of cloth attached to the loop on the collar
                     (depicted above his right shoulder) wind around his body, which is otherwise nude.  His
                     open mouth shows at least one sharp tooth.  The third fully-pictured follower is just
                     to the left of Comus.  With upper body facing the viewer, this sexually-ambiguous figure
                     holds both arms bent upward; the right hand holds a candle, and the left is held with
                     palm horizontal above his or her head.  His or her ox's (or cow's) head, complete with horns, is
                     bent slightly to the right.  Bands of fur or cloth extend from the figure's neck in
                     waving folds, covering the torso and hips.  He or she strides leftward with the left
                     leg, right leg extended backward on tiptoe.  The head and part of the upper body of
                     the fourth follower appears to the right of Comus.  This figure appears to lean leftward
                     into the design.  His or her vertically raised right arm holds a candle overhead.
                     The figure's bird head looks left.  Feathers form a spiky crest near the crown of the bird's 
                     head.  The left arm and lower body are not pictured.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>fingers</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc> A young woman sits on a bank at the bottom right corner; although
                     her lower body faces left, her upper body twists to face forward and to the right. She
                     holds her head up, bent slightly back and turned rightward, and she gazes up and to the 
                     right.  Her arms are bent at the elbows, and her palms are held vertically, facing right.
                     She wears a long, high-waisted gown and has long curly hair.  Her feet, visible beneath 
                     the hem of her gown, are clad in shoes or slippers.  She is Milton's "Lady," threatened
                     by Comus.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>root</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large tree trunk grows from prominent roots that spread above and 
                     to the right of the Lady and grasp part of the bank on which she sits.  The
                     trunk leans rightward, out of the frame of the design.  Other trees with canopies of
                     leaves line the low horizon on the left, with three trunks visible: two to the left of
                     the dog-man and at least one more to the left of the hog-woman.  The line of tree
                     canopies continues rightward, pictured to the left and right of the ox-figure and Comus.
                     Sketchy lines and marks along the ground to the right and left and below the feet of the
                     hog-woman, and what seems to be a tuft visible against the bottom of the Lady's gown,
                     suggest grass.  The coloring of the bank and a few lines suggesting vegetation suggest that it may be covered
                     with grass as well.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>bank</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady, lower right, sits on a section of rock or earth jutting
                     out slightly from a large bank.  Comus and his revelers dance across
                     the top of this bank, above her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>staff</characteristic><characteristic>rod</characteristic><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>candle</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Comus, the male in human form at right with both arms held high,
                     brandishes a magician's wand or staff in his upraised right hand, and a glass
                     or goblet in his left.  Each of his four followers, including the one at far
                     right shown only from the torso up, carries a lighted candle.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The background color is dark blue and studded with stars, perhaps thirteen in all, indicating
                     a nighttime sky.  A dark shadow extends over the ground, lower left, from the left edge of the bank.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="65">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.02" dbi="BUT528.1.2.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Comus, Disguised as a Rustic, Addresses the Lady in the Wood</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="U2">(Butlin 528.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.4 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.02"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc> In a dark scene dominated by several large tree trunks, an old man
                  wearing a long cloak approaches the Lady from the previous design.  This is Comus, now
                  disguised as a country villager.  With hat in hand, and magician's wand—now appearing
                  to be a gnarled
                  walking stick—held hidden from the Lady behind his back, the long-haired, hunched old man 
                  steps 
                  toward the Lady.  The Lady stands facing forward, with hands raised and palms facing out from her body,
                  and turns her head to look toward the old man. 
                  The two figures stand 
                  before four large trees, the foliage of which meets over their heads.  
                  The angelic form of the attendant Spirit
                  hovers at the right of the design.  Other trees are visible in the background.
                  
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Comus</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     In a dark scene dominated by two tree trunks, an old man
                     wearing a long cloak or gown and shoes approaches the Lady.  This is Comus, now
                     disguised as an old country villager with long hair and hunched shoulders.  Walking to the right 
                     toward the Lady, right foot on tiptoe, the old man carries his
                     hat in his right hand, with his arm at his side, and his magician's wand—now appearing to be a gnarled walking
                     stick—in his left, hidden from the Lady's sight behind his back.  With chin jutted forward due to his posture,
                     the old man looks towards the Lady.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady stands 
                     facing forward, with hands raised and palms facing out from her body,
                     and turns her head to look at the old man.  
                     Her hand gesture suggests surprise.  She wears
                     a long, high-waisted gown; her long, curly hair spills over her shoulders.  The fingers of her left hand are slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The angelic form of the attendant Spirit hovers to the right of the figures
                     of Comus and the Lady, at the right side of the plate.  The Spirit's lower body faces right,
                     but his upper body twists leftward and his head is turned left to look towards the other figures.
                     His arms are at his side and bent upward at the elbows, with palms held up and facing out
                     from his body.  His wings appear to be partly folded behind his back.  His hair is long and his
                     head is encircled by a halo.  The fingers of his left hand are slightly spread.  He is wearing semi-transparent, colored tights that end at the wrist 
                     and mid-calf.
                     A transparent gown drapes over this outfit, extending below his feet.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>staff</characteristic><characteristic>rod</characteristic><characteristic>stick</characteristic><characteristic>walking stick</characteristic><illusobjdesc> Comus, now disguised as a country villager, carries a hat in one hand
                     and his magician's wand or staff (disguised as a walking stick) held behind his back.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The overall darkness of the scene suggests that the time is night.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>root</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dark scene is dominated by several large and leafy trees, the branches of which 
                     reach over the heads of the old man and the Lady to form several arch-like structures.  One tree
                     stands just to the left of Comus, a second between Comus and the Lady; and two more trees, one
                     slightly behind and to the right of the other, stand to the right of the Lady.  Foliage and branches
                     from each of these trees are pictured above the figures' heads.  The tree just to the right of the
                     Lady has more prominent roots than the others.  Other, more distant trees are visible between the
                     foremost trees.  One particularly well-depicted tree trunk stands just to the right of the Spirit.
                     Sketchy marks and coloring along the ground across the design suggest grass.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.02.01" justify="left" indent="18">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.03" dbi="BUT528.1.3.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Brothers Seen by Comus Plucking Grapes</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="U3">(Butlin 528.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.4 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.03"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc> Comus, disguised as an old villager,
                     carries a hat and his magician's wand, which is camouflaged as a walking stick.
                     Head bowed and torso turned slightly rightward, he stands or steps toward the viewer with his left
                     foot forward.  The Lady's brothers pick grapes from the grapevines at the right side of the design.
                     The brother on the left stands facing away from the viewer, left leg bent and foot resting on a
                     rock, as he stretches overhead to receive a cluster of grapes from his brother.  The other,
                     wearing shoes, is positioned higher up in the vines, facing forward with right leg drawn up toward his
                     body.  With his right arm he hands a cluster of grapes down to his brother, and with the other
                     reaches over his head to grasp the vine or rocks.  Both brothers turn their heads to gaze at one another.
                     In the middle distance a farmer and two oxen in yokes are visible between the old man and the
                     hill or cliff.  Trees line the horizon in the background; at the base of one sits the small,
                     distant figure of the Lady.  Above the Lady, and above the trees, the attendant Spirit hovers
                     in angelic form.  Beams of light irradiate the sky, emanating from the area around the Spirit,
                     while several small white spots left and right of the Spirit may be intended to represent stars.
                     
                  </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Comus</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>stick</characteristic><characteristic>rod</characteristic><characteristic>walking stick</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                        Comus, disguised as an old, cloaked villager, appears on the left.
                        With head bowed and torso turned slightly rightward, his body faces the viewer as he stands or 
                        steps toward the viewer with 
                        his left foot forward.  Arms at his side, he carries a hat and a magician's wand or staff, 
                        which is camouflaged
                        here as a walking stick.  He wears a long cloak and shoes.
                     </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bending left</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>giving</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady's brothers pick grapes from the grapevines at the right side
                        of the design.  The brother on the left faces away from the viewer, with his left leg
                        drawn up and his foot resting on a section of the rock, and his right leg extended
                        to stand on the ground below.  Both of his feet are on tiptoe.  With his right arm he
                        reaches overhead to receive a cluster of grapes in his open palm from his brother.  His
                        left arm extends downward, elbow resting against his left knee, and his hand touches another
                        cluster of grapes that rests on the rock to the left of his left foot.  The other brother is
                        situated higher up in the vines, facing forward with right leg drawn up toward his body, foot
                        resting on tiptoe on a vine.  His left leg is extended to stand on a vine below.  With his
                        bent right arm, he hands a cluster of grapes down to his brother.  Although he is bent
                        forward and leftward towards his brother, his left arm stretches above his head to grasp
                        a section of rock and/or vine.  Both brothers turn their heads to gaze at one another, a move
                        that requires the brother on the left to tilt his head sharply back.  Both brothers wear tights,
                        and the wide waistline of the left brother's clothing suggests a belt.  The neckline of the 
                        right brother's clothing features a wide collar, a characteristic that the small section of 
                        collar visible at the back of the left brother's neck suggests may be part of his outfit as well.
                        While the left brother's feet are bare, the right brother seems to be wearing slipper-like shoes.
                        Both brothers have curly hair (short on the right brother, longer on the left).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><illusobjdesc> Above the Lady and the trees where she sits, the attendant Spirit hovers
                        in angelic form.  The gowned figure faces forward with wings upraised and arms at his side.
                        His left leg and foot appear to be held forward.  The radiance emanating from the figure forms a halo-like oval around him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Leafy trees line the horizon in the background; at the base of one sits the small, distant
                        figure of the Lady.  The gowned figure faces left, with her visible left
                        arm resting on her lap.  Her long hair falls down her back.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>rope</characteristic><characteristic>harness</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the middle distance a farmer and two oxen wearing a yoke are visible between the old 
                        man and the hill.  The farmer has long hair and wears a hat; he faces left and down.  
                        We see only his head and upper body; he appears to be wearing a gown, shirt, or coat.
                        He may have a section of harness or rope over his left shoulder.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>ox</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>yoke</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the middle distance a farmer and two horned oxen in yokes are visible between the old 
                        man and the hill.  The oxen face left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>grape</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady's brothers pick grapes from the grapevines (there would appear to be at least two) at the right side of the design.
                        The vines are rooted partway up the rock or cliff on the right.  Two main trunks are visible,
                        sending up intertwining branches that reach up the side of the design to the upper right corner.
                        A third and perhaps fourth trunk are depicted rooted between the two main trunks and the right side
                        of the design.  Large, distinct leaves grow on many of the branches.  Three grape clusters are shown:
                        one below the left brother's left hand, one being passed from right brother to left brother, and
                        a third still on the vine below the right brother's left arm.  Leafy trees line the horizon between
                        the left side of the design and the hill or cliff.  Green coloring and sketchy marks throughout the
                        middle-ground between the left side of the design and the cliff suggest grass or small plants.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady's brothers pick grapes from the grapevine rooted in a cliff or hill at the right
                        side of the design.  This rocky-looking hill or cliff begin near the base of the design and stretches
                        up apparently as if continuing beyond the upper right corner.  Comus, in the guise of an old man,
                        steps forward on the left side; his feet are on a path or road that meets the lower left corner of the
                        design and may continue rightward across the bottom of the design. This path or road curves gently
                        to the right as it recedes, until it is hidden by the hill, suggesting that perhaps the ox and farmer
                        are walking on the same path or road.  Another section of path or road curves below and to the right
                        of the seated Lady.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the Lady, and above the trees, the attendant Spirit hovers in angelic 
                        form.  Beams of light irradiate the sky, emanating from the area around the Spirit, while
                        several small white spots left and right of the Spirit may be intended to represent stars.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.03.01" justify="left" indent="60">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.04" dbi="BUT528.1.4.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Brothers Meet the Attendant Spirit in the Wood</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="U4">(Butlin 528.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.3 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.04"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The attendant Spirit stands between the Lady's brothers and is now disguised
                  as Thyrsis, their father's shepherd.  The brothers, loosely holding their swords, look
                  towards the Spirit as if in conversation with him, as he holds up a small flower.  The
                  three figures are framed by four large trees whose foliage meets overhead.  Other vegetation
                  fills in the background behind the figures.  Above the trees, as if coiling across their
                  foliage, two serpents carry a figure rightwards.  
                  This figure
                  may represent the moon goddess Hecate, or Hecate synthesized with Cotytto.  The dark sky and 
                  the moon itself, depicted just to the right of the figure's head, indicate a night scene.
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Thyrsis</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>buckle</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     The attendant Spirit stands between the Lady's brothers and is now disguised as
                     Thyrsis, their father's shepherd.  His body faces forward and slightly to the left,
                     with his left leg positioned slightly forward and bent at the knee.  With right arm
                     bent upward at the elbow, he holds up a small flower with his right hand, fingers slightly spread.  His left
                     arm is at his side, his hand holding the shepherd's crook that forms part of his
                     disguise.  He wears a hat, shoes with buckles or ties, and tights or breeches and
                     a shirt with buttons down the front and at either side of a panel below his waist;
                     his hair is long.  He appears to be looking at the flower or the brother on the left.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The brothers stand on either side of the Spirit and look towards him, as if
                     in conversation with him.  They may be looking at the flower held by the Spirit.  Both hold
                     their swords loosely with the points resting on the ground.  The brother on the left faces
                     forward with his weight on his right leg and his left leg bent, his sword in his extended
                     right arm; he holds his free left arm and hand across his chest, palm held roughly vertical
                     and facing left.  His hair is long.  The brother on the right faces away and stands
                     with his weight on his left leg, right leg bent, sword in his extended right arm.  His left
                     arm is also extended and down at his side, but the palm is held out and facing down.  His 
                     hair is short and curly.  Both brothers incline their heads towards the Spirit.  They
                     both wear slipper-like shoes and knee-length tights that
                     subtly cinch at the waist.
                     The left brother's clothing has a wide v-shaped neckline, while the right brother,
                     seen from behind, has a wide collar at the back of his neck.  The left brother's left foot, and the right brother's right foot, are on tiptoe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three figures—the brothers and the attendant Spirit, disguised as Thyrsis—
                     are framed by four large trees whose foliage meets overhead, creating three roughly arched
                     spaces, one around and above each figure.  The foliage combines so that an unbroken canopy
                     of leaves appears to stretch horizontally from one side of the design to the other.  Additional
                     vegetation fills in the background behind the figures.  The coloring of the ground on which the
                     figures stand suggests grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>haemony</characteristic><illusobjdesc> The attendant Spirit, disguised as 
                     Thyrsis, holds a small star-like flower in his right hand; 
                     this probably represents the magical root haemony.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>carrying</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the trees, as if coiling across their foliage,
                     two serpents carry a figure rightwards.  Both
                     serpents' mouths are open, with tongues extended.  Their bodies
                     are slightly marked with large scales, especially where they curve upward
                     to lift their upraised heads.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Hecate</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>Cotytto</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the trees, as if coiling acoss their foliage, two serpents carry a figure rightwards.  This figure
                     may represent the moon goddess Hecate, or Hecate synthesized with Cotytto.  Apparently gowned and trailing a curl of drapery, she bends forward sharply, at least one arm
                     extended and bent slightly at the elbow.  Her hand holds reins that lead to the necks
                     of the serpents.  Her long hair streams backward over her shoulders.  She may be riding the backs of the serpents or on a chariot of some sort, although no such vehicle is represented.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>chariot</characteristic><characteristic>rein</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the trees, as if coiling across their foliage,
                     two serpents draw a dark figure rightwards.  She may be riding on the backs of the serpents or on some sort of chariot, although no vehicle is clearly represented.  Two reins, lightly sketched,
                     extend from the figure's right hand to the necks of the serpents.  The dark
                     sky and moon, as well as the presence of a moon goddess, indicate a night scene.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.04.01" justify="left" indent="43">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.05" dbi="BUT528.1.5.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Magic Banquet with the Lady Spell-Bound</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="U5">(Butlin 528.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.3 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.05"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Five figures are seated at a table in a palace.  The four figures seated
                  behind the table, away from the viewer, are some of Comus' enchanted followers; they have
                  the heads of animals (from left to right, an elephant, a lion, a hog just visible to the
                  right of Comus' cloak, and a bird).  Two other followers stand slightly behind them and to 
                  the left, each bearing a pitcher or jar.  The one on the right is a cat.  The
                  one on the left is a wrinkled, bald old man.  The Lady sits before the table at the left 
                  side of the design, in a sturdy chair decorated with the images of grain shafts.  She sits
                  rigidly with her arms resting on her bent legs, palms facing down.  Comus, now shown in
                  his own physically-imposing form, towers above the Lady from his position standing before
                  the table at the right of the design.  With body facing the viewer, Comus holds a goblet
                  in his left hand and extends his right towards the Lady to hold his magiciam's wand or
                  staff over her head.  His position suggests that he is conjuring up the semitransparent snake 
                  rising out of the jar
                  held by the wrinkled old man standing behild the Lady.  The table is set with at least
                  a platter and a large cup or vase.  Overhead hang three large lamps.  A series of arches
                  and columns in the background suggest the classical grandeur of the palace.  The outline
                  of a cloud appears above the heads of the followers on the left.
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Comus</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>staff</characteristic><characteristic>rod</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at the knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     Comus, now shown in his own physically-imposing form, towers above the Lady from
                     his position standing before the table at the right of the design.  With body facing
                     the viewer, Comus stands with his weight on his left leg, his right leg bent at the knee
                     and his right foot on tiptoe.  He holds a goblet in his left hand and extends his right
                     towards the Lady to hold his magician's wand or staff over her head.  Comus turns his head
                     to the left to look toward the Lady.  He wears a long blue cloak or cape and rose-purple
                     semi-transparent tights; his short, curly hair is reddish.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms on lap</characteristic><characteristic>arms resting</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>rigid</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>prisoner</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady sits in a chair facing right before the table at the left side of the design.
                     She sits with her bent arms at her side, forearms resting in her lap.  Her hands, palms down, lie on her knees.
                     Her stiff, rigid posture suggests her bondage to Comus.  Her right foot is visible beneath the hem of her long
                     gown and seems to be clad in a slipper-like shoe.  Her hair is long and curly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The lady sits in a sturdy, decorated chair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>grain</characteristic><characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic><characteristic>grain stem</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The side of the back of the chair in which the Lady sits is decorated with
                     what appears to be a carving of shafts of grain.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>elephant</characteristic><characteristic>lion</characteristic><characteristic>hog</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>tusk</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>mane</characteristic><characteristic>fingers</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>paw</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four of Comus' enchanted crew are seated behind the table, away from the viewer.  All
                     have the heads, and most have the upper bodies, of animals.  The figure farthest right has a bird's
                     head with a long, pointed beak extending downward from its face and a crest on the top
                     of its head.  Its round eyes stare forward.  This figure has the most human-like hands, with 
                     fingers that grasp either side of a cup or vase on the table in front of it.  Though the figure's elbows
                     and arms seem to be resting on the table, it is difficult to tell how or in what they are clothed.  To
                     the left of this bird-figure, just visible to the right of Comus' cloak, is the snout, eye, and perhaps
                     the left shoulder of a hog-figure.  Facing right, the hog's snout is open, revealing an extended tongue
                     and perhaps a tusk.  Just to the left of Comus sits a lion-figure, facing forward and resting at least 
                     one paw on the table.  This figure has a long curly mane extending downward to cover its chest.  Its
                     mouth is open, showing two canine teeth, and its eyes are round and staring.  To the left of this 
                     lion-figure is an elephant-figure, who is the leftmost of the followers seated at the table.  The
                     elephant looks rightward from its position at the far left corner of the table.  Its trunk extends
                     downward over the table and its mouth is open beneath two curling tusks.  Its right arm is resting
                     on the table, with forearm and hand or paw lying on a platter that sits on the table.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>carrying</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>robe</characteristic><characteristic>grain</characteristic><characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic><characteristic>grain stem</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>whiskers</characteristic><characteristic>cat</characteristic><characteristic>vase</characteristic><characteristic>pitcher</characteristic><characteristic>jar</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two of Comus' followers stand to the left of the table, one on each side of the Lady's
                     chair.  The follower to the right of the Lady has the head of a cat, with small ears, large whiskers,
                     and round, staring eyes that are rather like the lion's and the bird's.  This cat-figure is dressed in
                     a long gown or robe, which has embroidery or similar decoration along the collar area and down the front.  The decoration may be grain stems, like those on the Lady's chair.
                     With visible right arm bent and held at its side, it holds a pitcher or jar resting on a platter in front of its
                     chest; the left hand may be visible beneath the right.  It looks rightward and forward towards Comus and the Lady.
                     Behind and to the left of the Lady's chair stands an old man, who also carries a jar or vase held with
                     both hands before him, his visible wrist positioned to suggest that his arm is bent and held at his side.
                     The old man is bald and his face, neck, and right hand are wrinkled.  His bare feet are visible beneath
                     his robe or gown, which has a seam running from its v-shaped neckline to its hem.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AC"><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A semitransparent snake rises, facing up and to the right, over the Lady's head.  Its mouth is open with forked tongue extended; it may have a crest on its head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>table</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least four figures are seated at a table covered with a cloth.  
                     Overhead hang three large (oil?) lamps, suspended on chains, 
                     each with a tall flame.  The outline of a cloud (of smoke?) rises above the heads of the figures on the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>vase</characteristic><characteristic>pitcher</characteristic><characteristic>jar</characteristic><characteristic>plate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A goblet or vase rests on the table at the right, near the edge of the design.
                     The bird-figure grips it with his hands.  A plate or platter sits
                     on the left end of the table; the elephant-figure rests his hand on it. There might also be a plate or platter below the lion's right paw.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>room</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>classical art</characteristic><characteristic>prison</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A series of (stone?) arches, columns or pillars with capitals, in the background suggests
                     the classical grandeur of a palace.  This room, however, serves as a prison for those under Comus' spell.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.05.01" justify="left" indent="65">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.06" dbi="BUT528.1.6.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Brothers Driving Out Comus</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="U6">(Butlin 528.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.4 x 12.1 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>In this design, the Lady's brothers have interrupted Comus' banquet and scattered his 
                  revelers.  The brothers are shown driving Comus leftward.  Nothing of the palace is visible,
                  having been replaced by a forest scene with trees, grass, and sky.  Even the Lady's
                  chair where she is still stiffly seated seems different, now missing a back and any visible
                  coherent design.  Clouds of gray smoke nearly fill the left side of the design, billowing
                  from behind the Lady's chair and from flames
                  rising along the ground near Comus' feet; more flames appear between the
                  brothers' striding legs.  Comus' undulating blue cloak seems to merge with the billows of smoke,
                  which nearly surround him.  Four heads that may belong to Comus' followers seem to float in the smoke
                  clouds above the fleeing Comus.  Comus, both arms raised, is still carrying his staff or rod
                  in his right hand, but one of the brothers has seized the goblet and bears it aloft.  Both brothers
                  hold their swords high in nearly-parallel positions and stride to the left with mirror-image
                  strides.  The Lady, still seated in the chair, remains facing rightward with her arms resting along
                  her lap.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Comus</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>leaping</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     Comus is shown fleeing leftward away from the pursuing brothers.  He still carries
                     his rod in his right hand, with both arms raised above his head, but one of the 
                     brothers has seized the goblet.  Comus' raised left hand is open, palm facing down
                     and to the right, and fingers spread towards the brothers.  He strides leftward with
                     bent right leg, left leg extended to the right and left foot on tiptoe.  His body
                     faces forward and his head is bent to the right; his mouth may be slightly open.  He may be looking at the brothers.
                     Comus is clothed in transparent tights that end at his wrists and just below his
                     knees, and his blue cloak billows behind him, merging with the clouds of smoke.  He
                     wears slipper-like shoes.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>pursuing</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady's brothers are shown driving Comus leftward towards the edge of
                     the design.
                     Comus is still carrying his rod, but one of the brothers—the one closest
                     to the viewer—has seized the goblet and bears it aloft in his left hand.  
                     He looks left toward Comus.  The brother furthest from
                     the viewer holds his left arm raised at 135 degrees, his palm vertical and facing
                     out from his body.  This brother turns his head to look forward, his mouth open.
                     Both brothers hold their swords in their right hands, with right arms behind them
                     and raised high in nearly-parallel positions.  They step to the left with mirror-image
                     strides, each with a leg extended behind, trailing foot on tiptoe.  Both wear semi-transparent tights that
                     end at their wrist and ankles.  The nearest brother is wearing slipper-like shoes
                     and a belt (or his tights cinch at the waist); the other may be wearing similar shoes,
                     but they are harder to distinguish.  Both brothers have curly (and fairly short?) hair.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>face</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four heads seem to float in or just above the smoke cloud, above and to the right
                     of the fleeing Comus.  At top right of this cluster is a woman's (?) head wearing a shawl or scarf 
                     that covers much of her hair.  She looks downward, facing to the left.  A few strands of hair
                     escape from her scarf at her left temple, and additional strands, or folds of her scarf, cascade
                     over her shoulder and hang below her face.  A smaller, bald head rests on her shoulder, enveloped
                     in her hair or folds of cloth, as if it belongs to a baby that the woman is holding.  But the features
                     and expression on the face of this head, which looks outward, suggest those of a disgruntled old man.
                     Below the woman hovers another smaller head, also facing forward and to the right.  Its mouth appears to be open.  A 
                     pair of bat-like wings stretch leftward from this head.  To the left of the wings, and somewhat between
                     them, is the head of what appears to be a bald old man, perhaps with a mustache and possibly a beard.
                     This head looks upward and to the right, and is roughly the same size as the second two heads.  Another
                     bat-wing structure appears to the right of the woman's shoulder.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms on lap</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>rigid</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady is seated stiffly just to the right of Comus, facing right.  Her arms are bent
                     and her forearms rest on her lap.  Her hands, palms down, lie on her knees.  She is gowned; her hair
                     is long and slightly curly.  Her right foot (wearing a slipper-like shoe?) is visible beneath the folds of her gown.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>goblet</characteristic><characteristic>glass</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>staff</characteristic><characteristic>rod</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Comus is still carrying his rod or staff in his raised right hand, but 
                     one of the brothers has seized Comus's goblet
                     and holds it aloft.  A thin line below the rim of the goblet suggests that it might contain a liquid, perhaps a magic potion. Both brothers hold 
                     their swords in their right hands, with right arms behind them and
                     raised high in nearly-parallel positions.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>seat</characteristic><characteristic>stool</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady sits stiffly just to the right of Comus.  If what she is sitting on is the
                     ornamented chair from the previous design, then both its back and legs are not 
                     visible in this design.  Perhaps the chair has been replaced by a stool or even a large stone in this outdoor setting.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Trees fill in the background of the design.  At least three trunks, with
                     their combined crowns, are visible at the right side of the design.  Foliage continues
                     leftward, filling in the space between the brothers and the smoke, and around the rising 
                     smoke clouds.  Grass covers the ground across the bottom of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The blue coloring above the trees indicates daytime sky.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A cloud of smoke dominates the background behind the figures leftward
                     of the brothers.  It seems to rise partially from around the Lady's seat.  Flames
                     sweep upward from the ground around Comus' feet to meet the smoke; more
                     flames rising between the brothers' legs.  Comus' blue cloak billows behind him and 
                     seems to merge with the smoke clouds.
                  </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.06.01" justify="left">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.07" dbi="BUT528.1.7.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sabrina Disenchanting the Lady</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="U7">(Butlin 528.7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.3 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.07"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Sabrina, goddess of the River Severn, appears in this design to free the Lady from her
                  enchantment.  Sabrina hovers, partly kneeling, to the right of the Lady and extends her open right hand
                  towards the Lady at shoulder-height.  In her left hand the river goddess holds a large scallop shell
                  at waist level.  The brothers stand next to each other on the other side of the Lady and bend 
                  over her.  The brother farthest from the viewer clasps his hands under his chin, while the closer
                  brother's visible right arm is at his side.  At the center of attention in this scene sits the Lady,
                  now much less rigidly than in previous designs.  Though her legs lie facing right, she turns her 
                  upper body to face forward and holds her raised hands out from her body with the palms up.  Her head
                  up, she looks slightly leftward toward her brothers.  The attendant Spirit stands in his shepherd's guise at the far left
                  of the design, gesturing upward with his right hand and looking rightward towards the Lady.  Two of
                  Sabrina's nymphs kneel or hover near her at the right side of the design.  A pool or stream of water, 
                  which perhaps represents the Severn, extends from their gowns to the bottom of the design on the right.
                  A rainbow arches from the right side of the design over Sabrina's head, to fade just right of the Lady's head.
                  The Lady herself is seated on what appears to be a rock or large stone.  Vegetation in the background fills in 
                  the spaces around the figures.  At least two large hills or mountains appear above the trees.  Rays
                  of light shoot over the horizon above the valley between the mountains, further lighting a blue sky.
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>Sabrina</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>fingers</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Sabrina, goddess of the River Severn, appears in this design to free the Lady from her
                     enchantment.  Sabrina hovers, partly kneeling, to the right of the seated Lady and looks at her with 
                     head bent and eyes raised, as she extends her open right hand, palm up, towards the Lady.  Her left arm is at
                     her side, bent at the elbow; in her left hand she holds a large scallop shell.  Although no neckline
                     or cuffs are visible, Sabrina seems to be wearing a long, semi-transparent gown that trails into
                     the water behind or below her.  Her long, curly hair falls over her shoulders.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     At the center of attention in this scene is the Lady, now much less rigid than in previous
                     designs.  Though her legs lie facing right, she turns her upper body to face forward and holds
                     her raised hands out from her body with the palms facing up and out and the fingers of her left hand slightly spread.  Her arms are at her side,
                     but bent upward at the elbows. Her head up, she looks slightly leftward toward her brothers.  Her right foot, perhaps
                     wearing a slipper or shoe of some sort, is visible below the hem of her gown.  Just above the right foot may be he upper part of the left foot.  Her hair is long
                     and curly; her mouth is slightly open, as though she is speaking.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The brothers stand next to each other to the left of the Lady.  Both brothers stand with their weight
                     on their right feet, with left legs bent, and lean over the Lady.  The brother on the left, who 
                     stands just in front of the other brother, holds his extended right arm at his side with the palm 
                     facing down and the fingers spread.  His left foot is on tiptoe.  The other brother's arms are at his side and bent upward at the
                     elbows, his hands held together under his chin as if in prayer.  With the front-most brother's bent head faces directly
                     towards the Lady, the rear brother looks slightly forward and down toward the Lady.  They are both wearing shoes
                     and tights that end at the wrist and just below the knee.  Both brothers have long curly hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>fingers</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><illusobjdesc>  The attendant
                     Spirit is positioned at the far left of the design, still appearing in the guise of a shepherd.  He
                     faces forward, standing on his right leg and holding his left leg slightly bent; his left foot is hidden
                     behind one of the brother's left foot.  His head is turned to the right and he appears to be gazing at the 
                     Lady.  With right arm lifted high over his head, he points upward with his right index finger.  His left
                     arm is hidden behind the brothers.  He wears a hat over his long hair, and tights with a belt or waistband 
                     and buttons.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>nymph</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>carrying</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two of Sabrina's child-sized nymphs partly kneel or hover near her at the right side of the design.
                     The nymph behind and to the right of Sabrina faces left, though her head turns slightly forward.  Only
                     her left arm is visible, at her side and bent at the elbow; she appears to be holding a shell (perhaps a
                     conch or whelk) in front of her chest.  Her long hair may be braided or adorned with pearls or beads across the
                     crown of her head.  She seems to be looking at Sabrina or the Lady.  The nymph to the left of Sabrina's is
                     seen partly from behind, but since her head looks towards the Lady, the viewer can see a partial left
                     profile of her face.  Her left arm is visible at her side, bent upward at the elbow.  With her left
                     hand, she holds a large whelk shell in front of her chest.  Braids or jewels decorate her hair across
                     the top of her head, and her long hair appears to be gathered at the nape of her neck.  Her legs extend
                     behind her and her left foot is visible below or through her semi-transparent gown.  Both nymphs wear
                     semi-transparent gowns that trail behind them into the water.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>shell</characteristic><characteristic>beads</characteristic><characteristic>pearl</characteristic><characteristic>jewelry</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Both of Sabrina's nymphs have long hair adorned with braids or possibly jewels that crown
                     their heads like tiaras.  The nymph to the left of Sabrina holds a whelk.  Only the top of the shell
                     in the hands of the nymph to Sabrina's right is visible, but it seems to be a conch or whelk.
                     Sabrina holds a scallop shell.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Indeterminate vegetation—perhaps trees, although no trunks are visible, or hedges—
                     in the middle background across the design fills in the spaces around the figures.  Sketchy marks across
                     the mountains or hills above hint at more vegetation, perhaps bushes or grass.  The ground at the
                     bottom of the design is colored green, suggesting grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>chair</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>seat</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the trees are at least two large hills or mountains.  A stone or rock
                     outcropping forms a chair-like seat on which the Lady sits at the water's edge.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wave</characteristic><characteristic>river</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Water, with small waves, is pictured below Sabrina, lower right.  
                     This probably represents the River Severn.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>rainbow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>
                     Beams of light shoot over the mountainous horizon, indicating that the sun is just
                     rising (more probably than setting) over the valley, in a blue sky.  A rainbow arches from the right side of the design
                     over Sabrina's head and fades just to the left of the Lady.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.07.01" justify="left">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but528.1.wc.08" dbi="BUT528.1.8.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Lady Restored to Her Parents</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="U8">(Butlin 528.8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.4 x 12.1 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="635" width="510"/></physdesc><related objectid="but527.1.wc.08"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The Lady is returned to the arms of her aged parents, who stand at the right side
                  of the design in front of the door to their simple dwelling.  They welcome
                  the Lady, who walks rightward towards her old home.  The Lady's brothers have also returned, and are
                  standing just to the left of the Lady.  They look upward and to the left, gesturing with surprise
                  at the revelation of the attendant Spirit, who has dropped the guise of a shepherd and hovers in
                  full glory in the upper left quadrant of the design.  With wings and arms outstretched, the Spirit
                  twists gracefully to watch the human tableau below.  The rising sun breaks over the hill on the 
                  horizon in the background.  Trees form a line across the middle ground, as if representing the
                  edge of a forest, and their foliage fills in the spaces around the figures.
               </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>tights</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady's brothers have also returned to the home of their aged parents, and are shown
                     just to the left of the Lady, looking with surprise at the new (to them) appearance of the attendant Spirit.
                     The brother on the right is standing facing forward with his weight on his left leg and his right leg bent slightly
                     at the knee.  With arms bent, he is holding his hands together in front of his chest in a praying position.  He looks
                     up and to the left at the attendant Spirit.  His curly hair is long and he is wearing shoes.  His semi-transparent
                     tights have a wide v-shaped neckline.  The brother on the left, who is standing slightly in front of the other, is
                     seen from behind.  He is standing with his weight on his right foot, left leg bent, and craning his neck backward
                     to look up and to the left at the attendant Spirit.  His face is shown in partial left profile.  His arms
                     are at his side with the hands held out from his body, palms down and fingers slightly spread apart.  His curly hair is short; a line below his ankle
                     on his right foot suggests a shoe.
                     The collar at the back of his neck suggests that his own semi-transparent tights have the same v-shaped neckline
                     as his brother's.  Both brothers' tights have belts, or more likely, well-defined waistbands.  The left brother's left foot, and the righ brother's right foot, are on tiptoe.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at the knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The attendant Spirit has dropped the guise of a shepherd and hovers in full glory at the left
                     side of the design.  Seen from behind, the Spirit twists gracefully away from the viewer and to the right to
                     gaze at the human tableau below.  With arching wings and lifted arms stretching above his head, he holds his
                     palms towards the sun rising above the Lady and her parents.  The fingers are spread slightly on each hand.
                     His bent legs extend behind him, as if out towards the viewer, and the bottoms of both bare feet are visible beneath
                     the hem of his gown.  His hair is long and slightly curly.  His long gown has a belt or defined waistline.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>Lady</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>virgin</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady is returned to the arms of her parents, who stand at the right side of the design
                     in front of the door to their humble dwelling.  The Lady looks at her parents and walks to the right 
                     (or stands with right foot on tiptoe)
                     with her bent arms held out towards her parents.  Her palms are open and held vertically, facing one another; 
                     the fingers
                     on each hand are slightly spread.  Her eyes are raised, perhaps towards her parents, and she is arching her back slightly.  
                     Her hair is long
                     and curly.  Her feet, visible beneath the hem of her gown, seem to be clad in slipper-like shoes.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady is returned to the arms of her parents, who stand at the right side of the design
                     in front of the door to their humble dwelling.  They both face leftward towards the Lady to welcome her
                     as she walks rightward towards her old home.  The aged father, who stands slightly to the right and in
                     front of his wife, holds his arms at his side, bent at the elbows, with his left hand out towards the Lady,
                     palm up.  His right hand is not visible.  The Lady's hands are positioned between the father's right arm and
                     left hand.  The father's head is bent and his shoulders stooped; wrinkles line his face, and his hair and beard
                     are long and white.  The mother holds her one visible hand, her right, up before her chest with the palm open, and fingers spread,
                     and facing out towards the viewer.  Her head is bent slightly down and to the left, and she wears a hood or scarf, which hides 
                     most of her white hair.  Both unsmiling parents wear gowns that reach to the ground, where one foot belonging
                     to each parent is visible beneath the hems of their garments.  The father's foot is clad in a shoe; the mother may also
                     be wearing a slipper-like shoe.
                  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="B"><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>post</characteristic><characteristic>lintel</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Lady's parents stand at the right side of the design in front of the door to their
                     humble dwelling.  The tall door fills the partially-shown side of this house, which is surmounted
                     by a pitched roof.  The doorway, its posts and lintel, may be constructed of wood.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground is tinted green and depicted with sketchy lines, suggesting grass.  Trees
                     form a line across the middle ground, as if representing the edge of a forest, and their foliage
                     fills in the spaces around the figures.  Three trunks are depicted in a line to the left of the leftmost
                     brother's knees, and at least one more trunk is visible between the Lady and her mother.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A shadow extends below and to the left of the feet of the Lady's parents (the two figures on the right).  The feet of the Lady also cast small shadows.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The rising (more probably than setting) sun breaks over a distant hill or mountain on the horizon in the background,
                     just to the left of the house.  It sends out beams of light that begin to brighten the
                     dawn sky, which is colored faintly rose near the sun itself.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but528.1.wc.08.01" justify="left">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>