<bad catalog="butlin" catid="502" copy="1" copyid="1" hidden="false" id="but502.1" institution="fogg" type="wc" work="The Resurrection">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="The Resurrection">
          <main>The Resurrection</main>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
          , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>2 XML files approx. 9KB; 8 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 88KB to 1700KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
        <date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are 
        <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi>
        of 1809 and 
        <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>
        in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>
        , datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>
        . 
                    
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2011</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This image copyright © 2011 Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University</userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>November 2012</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Illustration markup</change>
        <date>Summer 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>March 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Joseph Vogel,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>BAD created</change>
        <date>July 2010</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Lamperez,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Images received, catalogued and color corrected</change>
        <date>April 2005</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
          <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
          <name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>
            *The Resurrection*
          </title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>delineator, </role>
          <role>colorist</role></origination>
        <origination>Anonymous
          <role>delineator.  The inscriptions on the mount, available under Supplemental Views, are not by Blake.  They could not have been written before 1846, the earliest known date for the production of the paper on which the inscriptions are written.  The identity of the calligrapher who wrote the inscriptions is not known.</role></origination>
        <compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <numberobj>1</numberobj>
        <objsize>42.0 x 30.3 cm.</objsize>
        <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>42.0 x 30.3 cm.</leafsize>
        <medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium>
        <support>paper, probably wove</support>
        <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
        <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
        <framelines>none</framelines>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>Fogg Art Museum</name>
        <date>1943</date>
        <dealer>none</dealer>
        <price>bequest</price>
        <note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts c. 1805; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 26 March 1852, lot 160 (£1.2s. to the dealer &quot;Evans,&quot; probably Edward Evans or R. H. Evans); Samuel Prince; sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 11 Dec. 1865, lot 275 (£4.10s. to the dealer Halstead); H. R. Hogg; sold Christie's, 23 June 1916, lot 52 (£84 to the dealer Carfax &amp; Co.); the dealer Scott and Fowles, sold Nov. 1922 to Grenville L. Winthrop; bequeathed by Winthrop in 1943 to the Fogg Art Museum.</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University Museums</institution>
        <addressline>32 Quincy Street</addressline>
        <addressline>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 617-495-9400</addressline>
        <addressline>URL: http://www.artmuseums.harvard.edu/fogg</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone, Images: 617-495-2389</addressline>
        <addressline>Fax, Images: 617-495-2990</addressline>
        <addressline>Email, Images: divr@fas.harvard.edu</addressline>
        <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.405</repositoryid>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="BUT502.1.1.WC" id="but502.1.wc.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Resurrection</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 502)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  The inscriptions on the mount above and below the design are not by Blake.  These are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>42.0 x 30.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="775" width="650"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="inscbut502.1.rm.01" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut502.1.rm.02" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut502.1.rm.03" ovp="noindex"/>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The design is based in part on 1 Corinthians 15:4, as the inscription on the mount indicates, but some motifs are based on the description of Christ's resurrection in Matthew 28 and 1 Corinthians 15:44. Dominating the center of the design is the hovering figure of Jesus, nude except for a cloth wrapped around his waist and genitals. This is the &quot;spiritual body&quot; of Christ (1 Corinthians 15:44). He has long, curly hair and a beard. His hair is flame-like and stands on end. Jesus emanates an aura or halo with beams of light. His right leg is bent slightly and his arms are raised horizontally, palms vertical and his fingers pointing upward. He faces forward but looks slightly left. To the left of Jesus in the lower foreground are three figures, probably male. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. The leftmost figure faces forward and up to the right. He may have long hair and have his eyes closed. He may wear a gown and be crouching, with his body facing left. The middle figure faces up, with his body facing forward and to the right. He may have long hair and his mouth may be slightly open. His eyes are closed and he may be fainting. He leans on his bent right arm. The rightmost figure is visible only has a head with its mouth open. He faces right, up, and forward, and may have long hair. In the center of the foreground is a male figure with short, curly hair. This is the &quot;natural body&quot; of Christ (1 Corinthians 15:44) he leaves behind at the resurrection. He may be nude, or partly clothed with a cloth (perhaps Christ's shroud) draped over his back. He faces down, prone, with his arms raised horizontally. To the right of Jesus are three more guards at Christ's tomb. The leftmost is male with short, curly hair. His mouth is open and he looks up to the left, while his body faces down and right. His arm is raised horizontally and he holds what may be a shield or a stone tablet with writing (perhaps suggesting Hebrew letters) on it. If the latter, this may be a tablet of the Ten Commandments, the old law that Christ's dispensation replaces. He may be lying on the ground. The middle figure is that of an old man with long hair and a beard. He wears a gown and faces down, right, and forward. His mouth is open. He may be kneeling or falling forward. Only the gowned shoulders and neck of the rightmost figure, facing right and down, are visible, above and slightly to the right of the bearded old man. The scene is dark and appears to appears to take place at night. A stone wall of Christ's tomb with an open arched doorway is visible in the background.   
                    </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
            <characteristic>aura</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Dominating the center of the design is the hovering figure of Jesus, nude except for a cloth wrapped around his waist and genitals. He has long, curly hair and a beard. His hair is flame-like and stands on end. Jesus emanates an aura or halo with beams of light. His right leg is bent slightly and his arms are raised horizontally, palms vertical and his fingers pointing upward. He faces forward but looks slightly left. This is the &quot;spiritual body&quot; of Christ (1 Corinthians 15:44).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus in the foreground are three figures, probably male. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. The leftmost figure faces forward and up to the right. He may have long hair and have his eyes closed. He may wear a gown and be crouching, with his body facing left. Alternatively, the curved object to the right of this figure's face may be a shield rather than part of his garment.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fainting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus in the foreground are three figures, probably male. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. The middle figure faces up, with his body facing forward and to the right. He may have long hair and his mouth may be slightly open. His eyes are closed and he may be fainting. He leans on his bent right arm. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of Jesus in the foreground are three figures, probably male. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. The rightmost figure is visible only has a head with its mouth open. It faces right, up, and forward, and may have long hair. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shroud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands on ground</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the center of the foreground is a male figure with short, curly hair. This is the &quot;natural body&quot; of Christ (1 Corinthians 15:44) he leaves behind at the resurrection. He may be nude, or partly clothed with a cloth (perhaps Christ's shroud) draped over his back. He faces down, prone, with his arms raised horizontally, right palm facing down. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>text</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
            <characteristic>decalogue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus are three figures. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. The leftmost is a gowned male with short, curly hair. His mouth is open and he looks up to the left, while his body faces down and right. His expression suggests fear and/or surprise. His right arm is raised horizontally and he holds what may be a shield or stone tablet with writing (possibly Hebrew letters) on it. If the latter, this may be a tablet of the Ten Commandments, the old law that Christ's dispensation replaces. He may be lying on the ground. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>priest</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus are three figures. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. The middle figure is that of an old man with long hair and a beard. He wears a gown and faces down, right, and forward. His mouth is open. He may be kneeling or falling forward. He may be a priest (see Matthew 27:62).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>guard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of Jesus are three figures. These are the guards at Christ's tomb. Only the gowned shoulders and neck of the rightmost figure, facing right and down, are visible, above and slightly to the right of the bearded old man. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The scene is dark and appears to appears to take place at night.  </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>tomb</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A stone wall of Christ's tomb with an open arched doorway is visible in the background. Christ's natural body lies on the tomb's floor.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="4" justify="left" n="but502.1.wc.01.01">inv</l>
          <l indent="4" justify="left" n="but502.1.wc.01.02">WB</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="BUT502.1.1-full.RM" id="inscbut502.1.rm.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Resurrection</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">full view including mount inscriptions </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>Blake signed the work, lower left, with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  The inscriptions on the mount (the backing mat) above and below the design are not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>51.3 x 31.5 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="850" width="600"/>
      </physdesc>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT502.1.1-insc-t.RM" id="inscbut502.1.rm.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Resurrection</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">top mount inscription </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The inscription on the mount above the design is not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>3.9 x 31.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="800"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="22" justify="left" n="inscbut502.1.rm.02.01">The Resurrection.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT502.1.1-insc-b.RM" id="inscbut502.1.rm.03">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Resurrection</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">bottom mount inscriptions </objnumber>
          <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 502)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The inscriptions on the mount below the design are not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>5.8 x 31.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="800"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="32" justify="left" n="inscbut502.1.rm.03.01">1:
            <hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
            Corinth: ch 15:
            <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
            v. 4
            <hi rend="superscript">th</hi></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l justify="left" n="inscbut502.1.rm.03.02">Christ died &amp; was buried, &amp; arose again according to the</l>
          <l indent="25" justify="left" n="inscbut502.1.rm.03.03">Scriptures.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>