<bad id="but5.1" type="wc" work="Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin" catid="5">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb">
                    <main>
                        Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 21KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Society of Antiquaries, London.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1775.A">c. 1775<note>This monument was uncovered in the presbytery of Westminster Abbey in the summer of 1775 and was covered again in 1778.  Blake probably drew this design shortly after the monument was revealed.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>25.1 x 21.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>27.0 x 23.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>3</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its engraving for Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, first published by the Society of Antiquaries in 1780.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries, London</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 25</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but5.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT5.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 5)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The collection stamp of the Society of Antiquaries appears lower left just inside the framing lines.  A water color replica (Butlin 14) of this water color is in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.  An engraving of this design was published in Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, Plate 3 (1780), and in *Vetusta Monumenta*, volume 2 of c. 1789, Plate 31.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>27.0 x 23.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Neatly spaced and surrounded by a fine, triple border are drawings of three details from the Countess Aveline's tomb. All three represent decorations to the tomb's canopy, and they are labeled "A," "B," and "C." Drawing "A" represents the vaulting under one side of the tomb's canopy. Three decorative capitals form the foundation of the vault. A vertical fluted pillar rises from the leftmost capital; two similar fluted pillars extend upward from the middle and rightmost capitals and meet in an arch at the design's top center. A decorative topper joins the arching pillars, and a smaller arch is visible within this larger one. The top and right sides of the design are enclosed by a border line, and the spaces between the two arches and on either side of the main arch are filled with curling vines that bear ivy leaves and possibly fruit or berries. Drawing "B" shows a detail of a trefoil on the tomb canopy. The trefoil is missing part of its top third and has three lines, perhaps suggesting cracks, emanating from the center. It has a decorative stone(?) border around an image of two female figures, perhaps angels(?). The figures kneel or sit and lean toward one another. A fire appears above and between their heads, and two fleur de lis appear at right. Drawing "C" depicts a gold acanthus bloom with a brown center and some orange coloring on its irregular petals. A pencil inscription below the designs explains their location on the Countess's tomb.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="structure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Aveline</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tomb canopy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Right of the penciled letter "A." is a drawing of the vaulting under one side of the canopy on the Countess of Aveline's tomb in Westminster Abbey. From three decorative capitals extend upward three large and two small pieces of vaulting. The left two capitals touch in the lower left corner of the design, and the third anchors the other side of the arch at right. Straight upward from the leftmost base extends a fluted pillar. Similar fluted pillars rise from the other two capitals and meet in a vaulted arch at the top of the design, culminating in a round topper whose decorative design somewhat resembles the design of the capitals. Also extending from the right two capitals, inside the arching pillars, are two shorter pillars that form a smaller, lower arch.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The top and right sides of the tomb canopy design are enclosed by a border line.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ivy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>berry</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>From the apex of the smaller arch in the tomb canopy design, a curling vine extends upward and fills the space within the larger arch. The vine bears leaves, possible of ivy, and may bear some sort of berries or fruit. Similar leaved, possibly fruited vines fill the spaces between the arch and the far-left pillar on one side, and between the arch and the border at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>tomb canopy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trefoil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crack</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Right of the penciled letter "B." is a detail of a trefoil on the tomb canopy. Three lines, perhaps suggesting cracks, radiate from the center and divide the image into thirds. A substantial portion of the top section is missing. A decorative stone(?) border outlines the trefoil. The thicker outer portion of this border displays a segmented, rectangular pattern, which is repeated on the thinner interior portion of the border.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design inside the trefoil shows two nearly identical female figures, perhaps angels(?), who sit or kneel and lean toward one another in the center of the trefoil. Both have short, curly hair and appear to look at each other. They are gowned or perhaps wear skirts and shirts. The figure on the left, who leans and faces right, may have a wing extending left from her right shoulder. Her arms may be bent upward(?) and she may smile.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design inside the trefoil shows two nearly identical female figures, perhaps angels, who sit or kneel and lean toward one another in the center of the trefoil. Both have short, curly hair and appear to look at each other. They are gowned or perhaps wear skirts and shirts. The figure at right, who is slightly smaller and without wings, leans and faces forward and left. Her arms are bent upward and she appears to clasp her hands together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the trefoil design above the two figures (between their heads) is an area of red that suggests flames. Toward the outside of each lower section of the trefoil is a dark area of shadow behind each figure. In the lower half of the shadowy area at right are two fleur-de-lis.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>acanthus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>petal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Right of the penciled letter "C." is a drawing of an gold acanthus bloom that appears on the front of the tomb's canopy. Petals of varying length radiate from the flower's darker, brownish center. A ring of orange colors the petals about halfway between the center and their tips. At lower left is one darkened petal, or perhaps a leaf.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="5"/>
                <lg>
                    <l n="but5.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">A.  <space extent="30"/>B.<note>This inscription and line 2 are in pencil. They are probably not by Blake.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="7"/>
                <lg><l n="but5.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="36">C.<note>See the note to line 1.</note></l></lg>
                <vspace extent="15"/>
                <lg><l n="but5.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="60">B del.<note>"B" (with a loop over the left side and top of the letter) is the surname initial of Blake's engraving master, James Basire.  This inscription was probably not written by Blake.</note></l></lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg><l n="but5.1.wc.01.04" justify="left" indent="1">Ornaments from the Tomb of Aveline Countess of Lancaster on the N. Side of the Altar. Vet. Mon. Vol. II pl. 31<note>This pen and ink inscription is probably not by Blake.  "Vet. Mon. Vol. II. pl. 31" is a reference to volume 2 of *Vetusta Monumenta*, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.  An engraving that included this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published as plate 31 in that volume.</note></l>
                </lg>            
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
