<bad id="but52.1" type="wc" work="" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="princeton" catalog="butlin" catid="52">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Landing in Britain">
                    <main>
                        A Landing in Britain</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 44KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Princeton University Library

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *A Landing in Britain*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1779.B">c. 1779<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations and the relationship between this work and Blake's other water colors illustrating English history.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>13.5 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.5 x 18.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Princeton University Library</name>
                <date>1985</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, lot 172 with eight other works by Blake (19s.); Colonel Gould Weston; by inheritance to Nora Hunter; sold anonymously from the "properties of the late Colonel Gould Weston," Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 25 (&#163;115.10s. to the dealer Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons); Mrs. A. B. Clifton; sold 1966 through Agnew's to Robert H. Taylor; deposited by Taylor in the Princeton University Library in 1972; given by bequest at Taylor's death in 1985 to Princeton University Library.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Princeton University Library</institution>
                <collection>Robert H. Taylor Collection</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">RTC01, HSVTaylor, drawer 11</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but52.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT52.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Landing in Britain</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(BUT52)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This work is part of a series of water colors Blake executed c. 1779 illustrating major events in the history of England.  Eight of these works are extant.  These designs may be related to "The History of England, a small book of Engravings" Blake listed in his advertisement "To the Public" of 10 Oct. 1793 (Erdman page 693).  No copy of that "book" has ever been recorded.  See also the list of subjects from the history of England Blake wrote in his Notebook c. 1793 (Erdman page 672).</p></objnote>
                <objsize>13.5 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design continues the composition of "The Landing of Brutus in England" with groups of figures-including men, women, and children-arriving on Albion's shore in boats. The lower half of the design contains a long, open boat that sits on choppy water and is propelled by two men who are nude from the waist up and have short, curly hair. One man at lower left crouches in the water facing away from the viewer; he pulls the boat with muscular arms as he strides leftward in a low lunge. The other man stands atop the boat's prow and leans or strides toward the right with his left leg. He bends toward the right with his left arm raised and his right arm lowered to push off with a long pole. Inside the boat are ten figures, from left to right: a man in a long-sleeved gown who extends his left arm forward but looks to the right, back toward his male companion; a bearded, curly-haired man in similar posture standing directly behind the leftmost man and reaching forward to place his hand on his arm; a mostly-hidden figure who faces away from the viewer and wears a hat; a woman in a long-sleeved gown who faces the viewer but looks downward at the infant in her arms; an infant wearing a hat and reaching upward toward the shoulder of its mother; below the mother and infant, a short-haired child of ambiguous gender who faces away from the viewer and reaches upward toward the infant; behind the mother stands a bearded man who faces toward the viewer with his left arm raised and his right arm lowered to hold the hand of a young girl; a girl, wearing a long-sleeved gown and facing leftward, who holds the man's hand with her right hand and the garment of the child in front of her with her left; a gowned woman with her left arm down at her side and her right possibly crossed across her chest; and a bearded man who sits near the back of the boat, facing leftward with his right elbow on his knee and his head propped on his right hand in a contemplative posture. Another group of figures-possibly in a second boat or already on the shore- appears in the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the man with the pole. They are, as follows, from left to right: a gowned woman who faces the viewer, crosses her arms in front of her chest, and looks rightward toward her male companion; a bearded man who faces left toward the woman, looks at her, and places his left hand on her hip; a bearded man who faces the viewer, raises his right arm vertically, and may look toward the man at his left; and a bearded man who faces left toward the man with the raised arm. Lines and coloring behind these figures suggest the possible presence of more figures, though no individuals are discernable. There may also be a suggestion of trees or a cloudy sky above the heads of this second group. In the upper right corner is another, much larger boat or ship. Two figures appear to be climbing into or out of the ship. Only the legs and one foot are visible of the figure at left. The figure at right faces left and reaches upward with his left arm to hold onto the ship. His left knee may be raised, or this shape may represent the head of an eleventh figure in the smaller boat. A rope and an anchor are visible hanging over the side of the ship at the left of these climbing figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knees bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lunging</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower half of the design contains a long, open boat that sits on choppy water and is propelled by two men who are nude from the waist up and have short, curly hair. The man at lower left is muscular and wears short tights or breeches. He crouches in the water, facing away from the viewer as he pulls the boat to shore. He may turn his head to face left. His left knee is bent forward and his right leg extended backward as he strides to the left in a low lunge. Only his right arm is visible. It extends behind him at right, grasping the edge of the boat to pull it along.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pole</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>oar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pushing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower half of the design contains a long, open boat that sits on choppy water and is propelled by two men who are nude from the waist up and have short, curly hair. Above the man in the water, another man-in a loincloth or skirt of some sort-stands atop the boat's prow and leans or strides toward the right with his left leg, which is bent at the knee. His right leg is extended backward toward the front of the boat at left. He leans toward the right with his left arm raised and his right arm lowered, holding a long pole or oar. He may use this pole to push the boat toward the shore. His head is lowered.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower half of the design contains a long, open boat that sits on choppy water. We do not see the prow or stern of the boat because it extends beyond the design's frame on both sides. Along the edge of the visible port side are zig-zagging decorative lines.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Britain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The boat in the lower half of the design sits on water that covers the entire lower border. Lines throughout this watery area suggest it may be rough or choppy.  The boat is landing on the shore of Britain.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat that appears in the design's lower are ten figures, including men, women, children, and one infant. Most wear gowns and some sort of robe or cloak.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Farthest left stands a man(?) in a long-sleeved gown and a cloak or other garment with open sides. He appears to have short, curly hair and may have a short beard.  His torso faces away from the viewer, but his head turns to the right to look backward toward the male figure at right. His visible left arm bends at a right angle, and he holds his forearm horizontally with the palm of his hand facing away and his fingers spread.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Second from left, a bearded, curly-haired man stands, facing left, directly behind the man in the front of the boat. He appears to look at the leftmost figure. The man wears a long cloak or other garment that covers most of his body and hangs over his left arm. Underneath this cloak, he appears to be wearing pants and a long-sleeved shirt. Alternatively, he may wear a gown that has wrapped around his visible left leg, which bends at the knee and extends backward slightly, suggesting that he may be walking. His left arm bends at the elbow, and he holds his forearm horizontally as he reaches forward to place his hand on the arm of the man in front of him. His fingers are spread as he touches his arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Third from left stands a figure of uncertain gender who is mostly obscured by the surrounding figures. This hidden figure faces away from the viewer and appears to wear a gown and a hat.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>woman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Fourth from left, a woman in a long-sleeved gown stands facing the viewer. Her curly hair is gathered into a bun. Her head turns to the right, and she looks downward at the infant she holds in her arms. Her left arm is bent horizontally across her chest. She may be a mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. An infant of uncertain gender lies horizontally in the arms of its mother, the fourth figure from the left. The infant raises its left arm at 45 degrees from its body, reaching toward the right shoulder of its mother. The infant faces left and looks upward toward the woman. The child appears to be wearing a hat.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                    	<characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Below the mother and infant, a child of ambiguous gender with short, curly hair wears a gown and coat. The child faces away from the viewer with its left arm bent at the elbow and its right arm raised vertically. The figure appears to reach upward toward the infant or  may tug at the sleeve of its mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Behind the mother and child at right stands a bearded man who faces toward the viewer but looks slightly downward and to the left, perhaps at the infant or at the child standing below. His mouth may be open. He wears a gown that is obscured slightly by a cloth that covers his left shoulder, extends across his body, and gathers at his right hip. His left arm is bent upward with his palm facing the viewer and his fingers spread. His right arm dangles across the front of his body, and he holds the hand of the child below and to the right. He may be the child's father.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. Below and to the right of the bearded man, a young child stands facing left and wears a long-sleeved gown and a cloak or other covering garment. The child's curly hair appears to be short. Its right arm is bent and raised upward to hold the hand of the man beside him or her, perhaps the father. With lowered left arm, the child reaches to grasp the coattail of the child standing at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside the boat are ten figures. The ninth from left, standing behind the man and child, is a gowned woman who faces left. She appears to have short hair, or she may have longer hair gathered into a bun. She holds her bent left arm down at her side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Inside this boat are ten figures. Farthest right, near the back of the boat, sits a bearded man. He faces leftward and hunches his shoulders slightly to rest his right elbow on his knee. His right forearm rises vertically, and he props his head on his right hand in a contemplative posture. His left arm is bent and rests on his lap, suggesting that his left hand may rest on his left knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another group of four figures-possibly in a second boat or already on the shore-appears in the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the man with the pole. Lines and coloring behind this group suggest the possible presence of more figures, though no individuals are discernable.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>talking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another group of figures-possibly in a second boat or already on the shore-appears in the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the man with the pole. Farthest left stands a gowned woman who faces the viewer and crosses her arms in front of her chest to rest each hand on the opposite forearm. Her hair is short or may be gathered into a bun. She turns her head to the right looks toward the man behind her. Her mouth appears to be open slightly, suggesting that she may be talking with the man.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another group of figures-possibly in a second boat or already on the shore-appears in the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the man with the pole. Second from left, a man with short, curly hair and a beard stands with body and head facing left toward the woman in front of him. He tilts his head down slightly and looks at her, and reaches around her to place his left hand on her left hip. The man wears a long-sleeved gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another group of figures-possibly in a second boat or already on the shore-appears in the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the man with the pole. Third from left stands a bearded man with short hair and a mustache. He wears a long-sleeved shirt or gown (his lower body is not visible). The man's torso faces the viewer, but his head turns toward the right to face the man next to him. His visible right arm bends upward behind the head of the man in front of him; the palm of his hand faces toward the viewer, and his fingers are spread.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Another group of figures-possibly in a second boat or already on the shore-appears in the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the man with the pole. Last in this group is a short-haired, bearded man shown in profile to the right of the man with the raised hand. He also wears a shirt or gown, but neither of his arms is visible. He stands facing and perhaps looking toward the man at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ship</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>anchor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the second group of figures, a second, much larger boat or ship rises from the water and occupies the upper right corner of the design. A rope and an anchor are visible hanging over the visible port side of the ship at the left of two figures who appear to be climbing into or out of the ship.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the upper edge of the ship, near the upper righthand corner of the design, two figures climb into or out of the ship. Only the lower body of the figure at left is visible, but the tights covering the figure's right leg suggest that he is male. His left leg is bent at the knee, and his foot extends out away from the boat to the right with the sole of his foot facing the viewer. His muscular right leg dangles along the side of the ship.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the upper edge of the ship, near the upper righthand corner of the design, two figures climb into or out of the ship. The figure at right, probably male given his short hair and apparel (a shirt and tights), reaches upward with his left arm and holds onto the ship with his left hand. His left leg may be bent with his knee drawn up to help him climb.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper lefthand corner of the design, behind the group of four figures and to the left of the ship's prow, there is the suggestion of a grove of trees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Alternatively, in the upper lefthand corner of the design, a cloudy sky may be suggested above the group of standing figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
