<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2005-07-07T15:01:49-04:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><!-- Step 2 Conversion to BAD DTD 2004 using modblake.pl Mon Jun 27 14:35:47 2005 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="but542.1" type="wc" work="Illustrations to Milton's On the Morning of Christ's Nativity" set="The Butts Set" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="butlin" catid="542"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Illustrations to Milton's &#34;On the Morning of Christ's Nativity&#34;"><main>Illustrations to Milton's "On the Morning of Christ's Nativity"</main><set> The Butts Set</set>: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>

            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 13KB; 12 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 105KB to 635KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives</publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce  the publication of electronic editions of Blake’s illustrations to John Milton’s "On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity" and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. The six "Nativity Ode" water colors were acquired, and probably commissioned, by Thomas Butts in about 1815. This series is now in the Huntington Library and Art Gallery. The group of three <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> water colors was acquired, and almost certainly commissioned, by John Linnell in 1822. The first two designs are now in the National Gallery of Victoria; the third is in the Fitzwilliam Museum. Both sets are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (our image annotation program). With this publication, the Archive now contains all nine of Blake's series of water colors illustrating Milton's poetry.<lb/><lb/>
            Blake had created six "Nativity Ode" illustrations for the Rev. Joseph Thomas in 1809. Blake repeated the same basic designs, with many minor but intriguing variations, in the Butts set presented here. When sold at auction in 1852, the water colors were accompanied by the poem, or possibly only the passages illustrated, in manuscript. This text, possibly in Blake's hand, is now untraced. In comparison to the earlier series, the Butts water colors are more highly finished and show careful attention to interior modeling and detailed coloring.<lb/><lb/>
            Blake produced twelve <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> water colors for Thomas in 1807 and a similar set of twelve for Butts in 1808. It may have been Blake's intention to execute another set of twelve illustrations for Linnell, but only the three extant designs are known. They are based on the fourth, eighth, and eleventh illustrations in the Butts series. In comparison to these models, the Linnell water colors show an increased emphasis on dramatic lighting, particularly evident in the radiance surrounding Christ in the third design, "Michael Foretells the Crucifixion." The Job engravings, commissioned by Linnell in 1823, show a similarly masterful use of intense illumination.<lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2008</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This work courtesy Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>September 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee, </name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup creation</change><date>April-May 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>July 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Jones, </name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name><name>Michelle Langston, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>June 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Jones, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image cataloguing and color correction</change><date>Spring 2006</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin van Kleeck</name><resp>Technical Editor:</resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Illustrations to Milton's "On the Morning of Christ's Nativity"*, The Butts Set</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake
               <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1815.B">c. 1815<note>The approximate date of composition is established by stylistic considerations.  The coloristic effects and delicate surfaces built with small brush strokes in the "Nativity Ode" designs associate them with Blake's illustrations to Milton's *Paradise Regained*, "L'Allegro," and "Il Penseroso," all of which include designs on paper with an 1816 watermark.  The lapidary surfaces of these works, dated to c. 1816-20 in Butlin, are more highly wrought than in the "Nativity Ode" water colors, and thus a date of c. 1815 seems likely.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>6</numberobj><objorder>1-6</objorder><objsize>each approximately 16.0 x 12.5 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>6</numberleaves><leafsize>approximately 16.0 x 12.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>IVY MILL<note>The watermark appears on all 6 objects.</note></watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name><date>1916</date><dealer>Rosenbach Company (A. S. W. Rosenbach)</dealer><price>$10,000, with Blake's *Satan, Sin, and Death* (Butlin 536.2), according to Rosenbach's receipt in the Huntington archives.</price><note>Acquired directly from Blake, and probably commissioned, by Thomas Butts; by inheritance in 1845 to his son, Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 26 March 1852, lot 147, "with the poem in MS." (£6.12s.6d. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); B. G. Windus; probably by inheritance or gift  to his daughter, Mrs. J. K. de Putron, by 1863; sold anonymously, Christie's, 16 March 1912, lot 6 (£336 to the dealer Frank T. Sabin); offered by the Rosenbach Company, December 1912 catalogue, item 11 (not priced) and in Rosenbach's November 1913 catalogue 17, item 61 ($9500); sold October 1916, with Blake's *Satan, Sin, and Death* (Butlin 536.2), to Henry E. Huntington ($10,000, according to Rosenbach's receipt in the Huntington archives).  The manuscript copy of the poem sold with the water colors in 1852 may have included only the passages illustrated, not the entire poem.  Butlin 542 claims, without providing any evidence, that this manuscript contained "Milton's verses in Blake's hand," apparently like those Blake wrote in pen and ink on separate sheets that accompany his illustrations to Milton's "L'Allegro" and "Il Penseroso" (Butlin 543).  This manuscript may have been lost or discarded prior to the 1912 auction, the catalogue of which makes no mention of such texts.  Until 1993, the "Nativity Ode" water colors were pasted to backing mats, probably made for Rosenbach, with passages from the poem written below each design in fine italic script.  The relationship, if any, between these mat inscriptions and the earlier manuscript is not known.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution><addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline><addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2191</addressline><addressline>Fax: 626-405-0225</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org/</addressline><department>Art Division</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">000.14-19</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but542.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT542.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Descent of Peace</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 542.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.9 x 12.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="750" width="707"/></physdesc><related objectid="but538.1.wc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The Spirit of Peace descends over the Nativity scene to awaken the slumbering Nature below.  The Spirit of Peace is 
               presented as a personified bird or angel and flies upside down on outstretched wings.  Circles of light or radiance behind the Spirit 
               of Peace may represent the star of Bethlehem.  A stable stands below the Spirit of Peace.  The roof may be thatched straw, and we view 
               the Nativity scene through a large Gothic arch.  In the center of the stable, the infant Christ flies or hovers surrounded by a halo of 
               light.  He faces forward with his arms raised at 135 degrees and his legs crossed.  To the right, the Virgin Mary kneels facing left.  
               Her head, surrounded by a halo, is bent back and she leans or rests against Joseph in a posture suggesting exhaustion.  Joseph stands to the 
               right of Mary and faces left.  He bends forward at the waist and holds Mary's head with his left arm.  His head is surrounded by a halo 
               of light.  To the left of the infant Christ, Elizabeth kneels with the young John the Baptist seated on her lap, both with hands raised toward the hovering Christ child.  Above and to the left of Elizabeth we see the head and right shoulder of Zacharias.  Above and to the left of the infant Christ are the heads of two horned cows or oxen.  Below the stable, 
               the Spirit of Nature lies on her side partially buried in the earth.  Her head is turned up and she looks toward the 
               Spirit of Peace.  The ground may be covered with snow.  Stalks of grain (or possibly vines on poles) grow left and right 
               of the stable; these are also covered with frost or snow..  Wash in the sky right and left of the stable's roof indicate clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Spirit of Peace</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Spirit of Peace is presented as a personified bird or angel, and flies or hovers upside down above the stable.  
                   She is gowned and shows slight traces of long hair left of her head.  Her head is bent 
                   back and she faces down and to the right.  Her arms are raised at 135 degrees, relative to her body, and she holds a stick or staff in her right hand.  Her 
                   legs are together and are bent to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>stick</characteristic><characteristic>staff</characteristic><characteristic>grain stem</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Spirit of Peace holds a stick or staff in her right hand.  Markings at the end of the object may suggest a grain stem or vines.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>star of Bethlehem</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Light or radiance appears as three concentric circles behind the Spirit of Peace, possibly emanating from the Star 
                  of Bethlehem.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>stable</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A stable stands below the Spirit of Peace.  The roof may be thatched straw, and we view the Nativity scene through a 
                  large Gothic arch.  A small square window is pictured in the top center of the archway, above the figures in 
                  the Nativity scene.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the stable, the infant Christ flies or hovers surrounded by a halo of light.  He faces forward with his 
                  arms raised at 135 degrees and his palms facing up.  His right leg is crossed behind his left.  He is nude and may have short, curly hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>exhausted</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the infant Christ, the Virgin Mary kneels on the floor of the stable facing left.  She is gowned and has 
                  long hair.  A halo of light surrounds her head.  Her left arm is pictured at her side and her legs are crossed at the ankles.  Her head 
                  is bent back and she leans or rests against Joseph.  Her posture suggests limp exhaustion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>Joseph</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Joseph stands just to the right of the Virgin Mary, facing left with his head turned partly forward.  He is gowned with short, curly hair and traces of a beard.  
                  He bends forward with his head down and seems to look at Mary.  His arms are down and he supports Mary against his arms and left leg.  His 
                  left foot is visible beneath the hem of his gown.  His head is surrounded by a halo of light.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>Elizabeth</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure kneels to the left of the infant Christ.  She faces right in profile and wears a gown and a cloth scarf 
                  or veil.  Her arms are bent up towards Christ with her fingers spread.  She is likely Elizabeth, the 
                  mother of John the Baptist.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>John the Baptist</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned child—likely John the Baptist—sits in Elizabeth's lap facing right.  He has curly hair.  His arms 
                  are bent upward towards Christ.  His fingers (at least on his left hand) are spread apart.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>Zacharias</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above and to the left of Elizabeth is the head and right shoulder of a male figure, probably her husband Zacharias.  He is bearded and appears to have long hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>cow</characteristic><characteristic>ox</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>eating</characteristic><characteristic>manger</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above and to the left of Christ are the heads of two horned cows or oxen.  They may be eating from a manger.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Spirit of Nature</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>buried</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the bottom of the design, the Spirit of Nature wakes and looks up towards the Spirit of Peace.  She lays on her side 
                  and is seen from behind.  She faces right with her left arm bent and resting on the ground with her palm down.  She is nude, but is 
                  partially buried in the earth.  her mouth may be slightly open; her left foot is prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>snow</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>pole</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>grain stem</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground may be covered with snow.  Grain stems, or possibly vines on poles, may grow left and right of the stable.  This vegetation seems to be covered with frost or snow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Wash in the sky right and left of the stable's roof indicate clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but542.1.wc.01.01" justify="left">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but542.1.wc.02" dbi="BUT542.1.2.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Annunciation to the Shepherds</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="U2">(Butlin 542.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.8 x 12.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="750" width="681"/></physdesc><related objectid="but538.1.wc.02"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A group of eight shepherds (seven adults and one child) sit or kneel below a host of angels.   The host of angels consists of 
               five winged males (presumably Cherubim) in the center with nine or more females (Seraphim?) in a circle around them.  The central angels are 
               nude and stand with their arms raised at 135 degrees.  The second and fourth angels from 
               the left are partially obscured by the arms of the other angels.  The circle of angels appear to be gowned females, several of whom hold 
               and play instruments.  The pair of angels at the base of the circle are winged and play horns, possibly trumpets.  The angels towards the top of the circle 
               are indistinct and appear as little more than outlines of heads and shoulders.  The host of angels is surrounded by a halo with beams of 
               light radiating outward.  Below, the group of shepherds consists of three females, three males, the outline of a human (?) head of indeterminate gender, and one child of indeterminate gender seated 
               on the leftmost figure's lap.  All of the figures are gowned; the female figures also wear cloth scarves or veils.  Several of the figures 
               hold their hands together in prayer and most look up toward the angels.  The central shepherd (sixth from the left) sits on a stone with his 
               right leg bent backward.  He is seen from behind with his arms bent and his palms facing away from the viewer.  A dog is seen from behind 
               between the second and third figures from the right.  A flock of sheep lies behind the group of shepherds, extending left and right.  Most 
               appear as indistinct shapes.  In the foreground, left and right, is a dog (left) possibly with a collar and a ram with curled horn.  They may be 
               sleeping.  Above and to the right of the shepherds are two tents.  A distant view of the stable is pictured between the 
               shepherds and the angels.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Five nude angels stand in a row in the top half of the design.  They may wear hats or helmets, possibly decorated with feathers.  They are winged and hover or 
                  fly with their arms raised at 135 degrees.  The second and fourth angels from the left are partially obscured by the arms of the other 
                  angels.  The central angel's palms are raised and face out with the fingers spread.  A few lines suggest that the central angel has long hair.  The other angels' palms appear to be turned up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>ascending</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>harp</characteristic><characteristic>lyre</characteristic><characteristic>tambourine</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A group of nine or more female(?) angels fly or hover in a circle around the five male angels.  The lowest six angels are clearly defined and are gowned with long hair.  The two lowest angels are also winged and hold horns, possibly trumpets, with a single extended arm.  Several 
                  angels are seen from behind and face away from the viewer.  The angel third up from the bottom right bends her right arm and may hold and 
                  play an indistinct instrument, possibly a harp, lyre, or tambourine.  The angel third up from the bottom left may be holding a tambourine in her extended hands.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beams of light or radiance emanates from the host of angels.  Darker coloring on the outer edges of the beams of light 
                  suggest darkness or a night scene.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="CD"><characteristic>stable</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A distant view of the stable is pictured between the shepherds and the angels.  A few sketchy lines vaguely suggest a human figure within.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>facing away</illusobjdesc><illusobjdesc>Eight figures sit or kneel in a row below the host of angels.  The figure far left is a female shepherd seated on a rock, facing 
                  right in profile.  She is gowned and wears a cloth scarf or veil and looks up toward the angels.  Her right arm is bent and rests on 
                  her lap.  She may hold the small child sitting on her lap.  The child has long hair and is seem from behind, facing away from the viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight figures appear in a row beneath the host of angels.  A female shepherd sits or kneels third from the left.  She is 
                  gowned and has long hair.  Her head is bent back as she looks up toward the angels.  Her mouth may be slightly open.  Her expression suggests surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight figures sit or kneel in a row beneath the host of angels.  Fourth from the left, a gowned male shepherd kneels with his back to 
                  the viewer.  His body faces to the right with his head facing away.  His right arm is bent.  His hands are together with the palms held 
                  vertically as if in prayer.  Just to the right and above this shepherd's hands is the outline of a human (?) head, presumably that of another shepherd, facing forward and to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight figures sit or kneel in a row beneath the host of angels.  Third from the right, a male shepherd sits on a stone with 
                  his right leg bent back.  He has long hair, and his gown has a hood which is not drawn up.  He is seen from behind with his head bent back; 
                  he looks toward the angels above.  His arms are bent with his hands raised palms out (away from the viewer).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight figures sit or kneel in a row beneath the host of angels.  Second from the right, a female shepherd sits on a 
                  stone and is seen from behind.  She is gowned and wears a cloth scarf or veil.  Her left arm is bent with the fingers on her left 
                  hand spread.  She looks up toward the angels.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>fur</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Eight figures sit of kneel in a row beneath the host of angels.  Far right, a male shepherd sits facing left.  
                  He is gowned and wears a fur (?) hat.  His left arm is bent upward.  His hands are together with the palms held vertically as if in prayer.  His eyes may be turned upward to look at the angels.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dog sits(?) between the second and third figures from the right.  He is seen from behind and faces left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>flock</characteristic><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>collar</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A flock of sheep lies behind the group of shepherds, extending left and right.  Most appear as indistinct shapes.  In the foreground on the left is a dog, possibly wearing a collar.  On the right is a horned ram.  Both have their eyes closed and are probably sleeping.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least four of the shepherds sit on stones.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="D"><characteristic>tent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two tents rise above the two shepherds on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the shepherds is covered in grass.  The ground above the shepherds (below the stable) is with bushes or small trees.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but542.1.wc.02.01" justify="left" indent="55">WBlake<note>The final letter of the signature was very lightly written and is partly obscured by pen and ink drawing in the design.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but542.1.wc.03" dbi="BUT542.1.3.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Old Dragon</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="U3">(Butlin 542.3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.8 x 12.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="750" width="723"/></physdesc><related objectid="but538.1.wc.03"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The top third of the design depicts the Nativity scene.  A stable is shown with a large Gothic archway.  
               Two indistinct figures stand in the center of the arch.  They probably represent the Virgin Mary (holding the infant Christ?) and Joseph.  Three robed or cloaked figures, possibly the three wise men, kneel below the arch, facing away from the viewer.  A trail of thirteen stars appears 
               above the stable.  The lower half of the design depicts the "old Dragon" of Milton's poem and five other figures in an underground cave.  
               The dragon (possibly Typhon) sits on a stone with his legs bent and crossed.  He holds a sword in his left hand and a scepter (with a pomegranate finial) in his right.   
               Typhon has seven heads, most of which are bent back and look towards the Nativity scene above.  All of the heads appear to have one or two small 
               horns.  The largest head (fifth from the left) is bearded and may wear a crown.  A long serpent tail coils around the figure and extends 
               upward to the left of the stable.  A smaller serpent winds around the figure's feet and ankles.  A third serpent appears to the left of Typhon's right 
               arm, with its head at his elbow.  A disembodied bearded head hovers to the right of Typhon.  Below this head, a muscular nude male is seen 
               from behind.  His arms are raised vertically and he points upward with both hands.  His head is bent back and turned to the left; he appears 
               to look at Typhon.  Below and to the left of Typhon, a nude male kneels with his right leg bent beneath him.  The figure has the head of a 
               lizard or fish, webbed fingers, and patches of scales.  To the left, a nude male sits on a rock with his left leg drawn up.  His right arm is 
               bent upward and his left arm is raised vertically.  The figure has his head bent back, facing right, and he looks up toward the Nativity.  To the left of 
               Typhon, a female figure sits with legs drawn up in a small cave or alcove.  She appears to wear a cloth scarf or 
               veil.  Flames appear in the lower right corner of the design, possibly indicating hell.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="AB"><characteristic>stable</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the design, a stable is shown with a large Gothic arch.  The building extends in wings to the left and right of the archway.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>Joseph</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two indistinct figures stand in the center of the archway of the stable.  They are robably the Virgin Mary (holding the infant Christ?) and Joseph.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>robe</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three robed or cloaked figures, possibly the three wise men, kneel below the arch, facing away from the viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A trail of thirteen stars appears in the night sky above the stable.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>Typhon</characteristic><characteristic>dragon</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>heads, multiple</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>pomegranate</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The central figure in the lower portion of the design is the "old Dragon" of Milton's poem, possibly represented here as Typhon.  
                  Typhon sits on a stone with his legs bent and crossed.  His left arm is at his side and he holds 
                  a sword in his left hand.  His right arm is bent and his elbow rests on a rock to the left.  In his right hand he holds a scepter with a finial in the shape of a pomegranate.  
                  Typhon has seven heads.  The heads furthest right and left may be female and have long hair.  All of the heads have horns; the second, third and fourth heads from the left have a single pointed horn while 
                  the others have two rounded horns each.  The largest head (fifth from the left) faces forward.  He is bearded with long hair and may wear 
                  a crown.  The leftmost head faces left.  The remaining heads are bent back and appear to look up toward the Nativity.  The head fourth 
                  from the left may have its mouth open.  A long and scaly serpent tail coils around the figure and extends upward to the left of the stable.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>winding</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A serpent or snake is wound around Typhon's ankles.  Another snake appears left of Typhon's right arm with its head at his 
                  elbow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A disembodied, ghostly and bearded male head floats or hovers right of Typhon.  The figure faces forward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male stands or hovers to the right of Typhon.  The figure is seen from behind with his legs bent and his arms 
                  raised vertically.  He points upward towards the Nativity with both hands.  His head is bent back and faces right; he appears to look 
                  at Typhon.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>lizard</characteristic><characteristic>fish</characteristic><characteristic>web</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>fin</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>Dagon</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male kneels with his right leg bent beneath him.  The figure has the head of a serpent, lizard or fish.  He has 
                  a ridged and spiky spine, like the dorsal fin on a fish, and is covered in patches of scales at his shoulders, thigh and calf.  his fingers are webbed.  His legs face to the right with his torso twisted 
                  to face away from the viewer.  His arms are bent with the palms facing away from the viewer and his fingers spread.  His left elbow rests on a rock to the left.  His head appears to be bent back.  He may be Dagon, mentioned in the poem as "that twice-batter'd god of Palestine" and described elsewhere by Milton as half man, half fish.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a rock with his left leg drawn up.  His right arm is bent upward and his left arm is raised vertically.  
                  Both palms are held vertically.  The figure has his head bent back, facing right, and he may look up toward the Nativity.  The figure 
                  has short and possibly curly hair.  The fingers on both hands may be slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>pain</characteristic><characteristic>Astarte</characteristic><characteristic>Ashtaroth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of Typhon, a female figure sits with her legs drawn up.  She may sit in a small cave or alcove.  She wears a cloth scarf or veil.  Her expression suggests fear or pain.  She may be Astarte, referred to in the poem as the Phoenician moon goddess "Ashtaroth."</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>hell</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The lower half of the design is set in a dark underground cave.  Several of the figures sit or rest against stones.  Fire 
                  in the lower right corner suggests that this may be Hell.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but542.1.wc.03.01" justify="left">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but542.1.wc.04" dbi="BUT542.1.4.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Overthrow of Apollo and the Pagan Gods</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="U4">(Butlin 542.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.7 x 12.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="750" width="712"/></physdesc><related objectid="but538.1.wc.04"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, the spirit of Apollo flees from its statue at Christ's birth.  The nude 
               statue stands facing forward on a pillar, plinth, or altar.  His left arm is raised horizontally and he holds a bow in his left hand.  He wears a quiver 
               of arrows on his back (the arrows are visible over his right shoulder) and a cape or other drapery rests over his left arm.  To the left of Apollo, a serpent is 
               coiled around a pillar.  The spirit of Apollo emanates from the statue in a tongue of light or fire.  The figure is seen from behind and bends 
               to the left while upside down.  His arms are raised vertically (relative to his body).  Below the spirit 
               of Apollo, a small (gowned?) figure hovers or flies above a seascape.  A fire with smoke burns on the altar below the statue.  A colonnade 
               supported by two pillars extends to the left of the statue.  Below the statue, four gowned priests or priestesses kneel with their heads down.  
               The figures on the left face right with their arms bent and their forearms resting on the ground in prayer or supplication.  The figure closest 
               to the viewer has long hair.  The figures on the right face left.  Their arms are bent upward with the palms held together as if in prayer.  
               To the right of the statue, a partially nude priestess sits in a cave.  Her breasts are exposed and a skirt or other drapery hangs over her 
               legs.  Her body is slightly twisted with her arms bent upward and braced against the wall of the cave.  Three trees with arching branches 
               appear left and right of the statue of Apollo.  To the right of the statue, a similar scene of departure takes place on a cliff.  
               Three spirits (two with outstretched, bat-like wings) arise from an indistinct altar or statue.  A pillar and horizontal beam, probably part of a colonnade, appear behind this second altar.  Wash in the sky suggests dark clouds, possibly at night.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>Apollo</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>quiver</characteristic><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>cape</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, a statue of Apollo stands on a pillar, plinth, or altar.  The figure is nude and appears to have short, possibly 
                  curly hair.  A few lines above his left shoulder, however, may be strands of long hair.  His left leg is slightly bent and his left foot is on tiptoe.  His right arm is at his side and his left arm is raised horizontally.  In his left hand he 
                  holds a bow.  He wears a quiver of arrows on his back (visible over his right shoulder) and a cape or other drapery rests over his left 
                  arm.  To the left of Apollo, a statue of a serpent is coiled around a pillar.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="CD"><characteristic>altar</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The statue of Apollo stands on a (stone?) pillar, plinth or column.  A fire with smoke burns beneath the statue, suggesting an altar.  Two 
                  smaller columns support a beam, probably part of a  (stone?) colonnade, to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>Apollo</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>bending left</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The spirit of Apollo emanates from the statue in a tongue of light or fire.  The figure is seen from behind and bends or 
                  twists to the left while upside down.  His arms are raised vertically (in relation to his body) and he may be fleeing the statue.  The 
                  figure's skin has a dark appearance.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below the spirit of Apollo, a small (gowned?) figure hovers or flies to the left above a seascape.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A sea with waves is pictured below the small hovering spirit in the left half of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>priest</characteristic><characteristic>priestess</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms resting</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below the statue, four gowned figures kneel with their heads down.  The figures on the left face right with their arms 
                  bent and their forearms resting on the ground in prayer or supplication.  The figure closest to the viewer has long hair.  The figures 
                  on the right face left in contracted postures.  Their arms are bent upward with the palms held together as if in prayer.  The figures are likely priests or 
                  priestesses.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>priestess</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms braced</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Apollo's statue, a partially nude priestess sits in a cave with her left leg drawn up slightly.  Her breasts 
                  are exposed and a skirt or other drapery hangs over her legs.  Her body is twisted with her head bent back and her arms bent upward and braced against 
                  the wall of the cave.  She has very long, slightly flame-like, hair.  Her mouth is open and she may be howling, speaking, or crying out.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The priestess sits in a small cave or alcove.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaves</characteristic><illusobjdesc>arching</illusobjdesc><illusobjdesc>Three trees with arching branches appear left and right of the statue of Apollo.  The tree right of the statue, and possibly closest to the statue on the left, bear leaves.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>altar</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>beam</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An indistinct shape, possibly a second statue, pillar, or altar, is seen right of Apollo's statue.  Red coloring at the base of 
                  the pillar suggests fire.  A pillar supporting a horizontal beam, probably part of a colonnade, stands behind of the statue or pillar.  These are probably made of stone.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least three spirits (two with outstretched, bat-like wings) arise from the indistinct altar, pillar,, or statue.  The figure without wings 
                  raises at least one arm vertically.  They are likely fleeing.  An indistinct shape to the left may be the head of a fourth spirit.  Red 
                  coloring around the figures suggests fire.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The indistinct statue or altar stands on a cliff that faces the sea left of the statue of Apollo.  A low hill appears behind the colonnade lower left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Green coloring suggests grass above the kneeling priests, on top of the cliff to the right of the statue of Apollo, and on the hill behind the colonnade lower left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dark wash in the top half of the design suggests a night sky.  Dark shapes above and to the left of the spirit of Apollo 
                  may be clouds or possibly indistinct spirits descending as a continuation of the rising spirit right of Apollo.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but542.1.wc.04.01" justify="left">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but542.1.wc.05" dbi="BUT542.1.5.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Flight of Moloch</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="U5">(Butlin 542.5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.7 x 12.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="750" width="686"/></physdesc><related objectid="but538.1.wc.05"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>At the top of the design, the spirit of Moloch is seen fleeing from his statue below.  The figure is seen from behind 
               and flies on outstretched arms from which extend bat-like wings.  The figure has both legs bent and the soles 
               of his feet turned out towards the viewer.  His left arm is raised horizontally while his right is raised at 135 degrees.  Both palms are 
               turned downward.  Below is an altar to Moloch composed of a large furnace and a statue of Moloch with three infants.  Fire erupts from the three openings in 
               the furnace (right, left, and forward) and also rise to the left and right of the statue.  Smoke rises from the fire and fills the sky to the right 
               of the fleeing spirit.  The statue wears a crown and holds a scepter in his right hand.  His right arm is bent and rests on a stone to the left.  
               His left arm is at his side, and he holds the limp, upside-down body of a child or infant in his left hand.  
               Two other infants stand or kneel below and to the left of Moloch.  They face right and reach towards Moloch with their arms 
               raised vertically.  Below the furnace, a nude male 
               infant stands surrounded by flames.  His arms are raised vertically, fingers spread.  The infant may be a victim sacrificed to Moloch or may possibly 
               represent the infant Christ.  A male and gowned female kneel to the right and left of the infant respectively; they 
               may be his parents.  The female figure twists to the left.  Her right arm is bent up toward her face with the fingers on her right hand spread.  Her left arm 
               is raised horizontally and extended towards the child with the palm held vertically.  Her mouth is open and she may be howling or shrieking; 
               her expression suggests grief or anguish.  The male figure twists to the right and is seen from behind.  His right arm is bent and his right 
               hand covers his face.  His left arm is raised horizontally and extended towards the child with the palm held vertically.  His posture 
               suggests grief.  Left of the furnace, two bearded, gowned males stand with their arms raised vertically. Both hold a pair of cymbals.  Their 
               mouths are open and they may be singing.  Right of the furnace, three gowned female figures stand with their arms raised vertically holding 
               cymbals.  The figures are seen from behind; the rightmost figure twists to the right at the waist to face the viewer.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Moloch</characteristic><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>bending right</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms down</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the design, the spirit of Moloch flees from his altar below.  He is seen from behind and his body bends or 
                  stretches to the right as he flies on outstretched, spiky, bat-like wings.  The figure is nude and bald.  Both legs are bent backward with the right drawn up more than the left.  His 
                  left arm is raised horizontally while his right is raised at 135 degrees.  Both palms are turned downward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>Moloch</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>altar</characteristic><characteristic>furnace</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A statue of Moloch as a king sits or crouches atop a large furnace used as a sacrificial altar.  The statue is nude and 
                  wears a crown.  His right arm is bent and rests on a stone to the left.  He holds a scepter in his right hand.  His left arm is at his 
                  side, and he holds a nude, limp, upside-down and probably dead child or infant in his left hand.  Two other 
                  infants, apparently alive or part of the statue, stand or kneel below and to the left of Moloch.  They face right and reach towards Moloch with their 
                  arms raised vertically.  The furnace below the statue spews fire from three openings (right, left, and forward); a thick column of smoke rises to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>victim</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below the furnace, a nude male infant stands or strides forward, surrounded by flames.  His arms are raised vertically with the palms turned 
                  out toward the viewer and the fingers spread.  He has short curly hair.  His mouth appears to be open and he may be speaking.  The infant 
                  may be a victim sacrificed to Moloch or may possibly represent the infant Christ, unharmed by the flames.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female with long hair kneels to the left of the infant.  She may be his mother.  The figure's lower body faces 
                  right, but she twists left towards the viewer as she leans backward.  Her right arm is bent with her hand held palm up beside her head.  Her fingers may be 
                  spread.  Her left arm is raised horizontally and extended towards the child with the palm held vertically.  Her mouth is open and she 
                  may be howling or crying out; her expression suggests grief or despair.  Her bare feet are prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>grief</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned male figure kneels to the right of the infant.  He may be his father.  The figure's lower body faces left, but he 
                  twists to the right and is seen from behind.  He has short, curly hair and his head is down; he appears to be wearing shoes or slippers.  His right arm is bent and his right hand 
                  covers or clutches his face.  His left arm is raised horizontally and extended towards the child with the palm held vertically.  His 
                  posture suggests grief or despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>cymbal</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>singing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Left of the furnace, two bearded, gowned males stand or stride forward with their arms raised vertically.  They may be 
                  dancing.  Both hold and play a pair of cymbals.  Their mouths are open and they may be singing.  The left foot of the front-most figure is prominent.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>cymbal</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>singing</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Right of the furnace, three gowned female figures stand or stride away from the viewer.  They may be dancing.  The figures 
                  have long hair; the second figure from the right may have her hair drawn back into a coiled braid.  All three figures have their arms raised 
                  vertically; they hold and play cymbals.  The rightmost figure twists to the right to face the viewer; her feet are prominent.  Her mouth is open and she may be 
                  singing.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but542.1.wc.05.01" justify="left" indent="60">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="but542.1.wc.06" dbi="BUT542.1.6.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Night of Peace</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="U6">(Butlin 542.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.7 x 12.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="750" width="686"/></physdesc><related objectid="but538.1.wc.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A stable stands in the center of the design with a large Gothic archway.  The Virgin Mary kneels on the floor 
               of the stable.  She is gowned with her arms down at her sides and her left foot visible.  A halo of light surrounds her head, which rests 
               against the figure of Christ to the left.  The infant Christ lies or reclines on a bed of straw, perhaps supported by a manger, to the left of Mary.  He is gowned.  A 
               halow of light surrounds his entire body.  He leans to the right and rests his head against that of Mary.  Joseph stands to the right of 
               Mary and bends left over her.  He is gowned and may wear a cloth scarf over his head.  His left arm is bent and he may rest his head on his 
               left arm or hand.  All three figures have their eyes closed and may be sleeping.  Two pairs of angels appear as mirror images left and 
               right of the stable.  One pair stands with their wings extended along the roof of the stable.  Each may wear a cloth scarf or hood, although the headgear of the standing angel on the left may be a helmet.  
               Each bends a single visible arm upward and may hold a spear.  A total of six spears are pictured, three to either side of the stable; this arrangement hints at the presence of four more angels behind those that are pictured standing in front of the spears.  A 
               pair of winged angels sit or crouch below.  Both are gowned and wear hats or helmets decorated with feathers.  The figure to the left bends his left arm across his 
               chest and holds a sword with the blade's tip resting on the ground.  The figure to the right bends his right arm across his chest and also 
               holds a sword.  The ground below appears to be made of clouds or possibly drifts of snow.  Above the stable, two gowned angels hover or fly on outstretched wings.  
               Both hold and play harps.  The figure to the left is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer.  The figure to the right faces right 
               with his or her head turned toward the viewer.  Between these angels, a gowned female (the personification of the star of Bethlehem) sits 
               in a chariot holding a lit oil lamp in her left hand.  To the left of the chariot, two horses lie facing left.  The chariot 
               and horses rest on a cloud.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>stable</characteristic><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A stable stands in the center of the design with a large Gothic arch.  Its roof slopes steeply to either 
                  side of the arch.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Virgin Mary kneels on the floor of the stable.  Her long hair falls behind her shoulders.  She is gowned and faces 
                  forward with her arms at her sides.  Her left foot is visible below the hem of her gown.  Her upper body leans slightly left and her 
                  head rests against that of the infant Christ to the left.  Her body posture is limp; her eyes are closed and she is probably sleeping.  
                  Her head is surrounded by a halo of light.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The infant Christ lies or reclines on a bed of straw left of the Virgin Mary.  His body posture is limp; his arms are 
                  at his sides and his head rests against that of Mary.  His eyes are closed and he is probably sleeping.  His body is surrounded by a 
                  bright halo of light.  His hair is short and curly.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>manger</characteristic><characteristic>bed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The Virgin Mary and the infant Christ both rest on beds of straw.  Christ may lay on a manger.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>Joseph</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>bending left</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Joseph stands to the right of Mary and bends or leans over her to the left.  He is gowned and may wear a cloth scarf or 
                  hood over his head.  His left arm is bent, and his head may rest on his left hand.  A halo of light surrounds his head.  His eyes are 
                  closed and he is probably sleeping.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged angel stands left of the stable, facing left.  The figure may wear a cloth scarf, hood, or helmet on his head.  His 
                  left arm is bent and he probably holds the leftmost spear pictured above.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>hood</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged angel stands right of the stable, facing right.  The figure may wear a cloth scarf or hood on his head.  His 
                  right arm is bent and he may hold the rightmost spear pictured above.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>spear</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A total of six spears are pictured left and right of the stable's roof, three on each side.  This number suggests that there are four more guardian angels in addition to the two pictured standing in front of the spears.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged angel sits to the left of the stable.  The figure is gowned and wears a hat or helmet decorated with feathers.  
                  The angel sits facing forward and twists his upper body to the left.  His left arm is bent upward across his chest and he holds the hilt 
                  of a sword with his left hand.  His right arm may also be bent upward with his right hand also holding or touching the sword.  A curving line descending over the blade may be a belt.  The figure's right foot is visible below the hem of his gown.  His head is turned to the right with his 
                  eyes raised.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged angel sits to the right of the stable.  The figure is gowned and wears a hat or helmet decorated with feathers.  
                  The angel sits facing forward and twists his upper body to the right.  His right arm is bent upward across his chest and he holds the hilt 
                  of a sword with his right hand.  His head is turned to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>snow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the stable appears to be made of clouds or possibly drifts of snow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>harp</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged angel hovers or flies to the left above the stable.  The figure is seen from behind and faces away from the viewer.  The 
                  angel is gowned with long hair.  The figure's left arm is bent and he or she plays a harp with his or her left hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>harp</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>singing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A winged angel hovers or flies to the right above the stable.  The angel is gowned with curly hair.  The figure's right arm is bent 
                  and he or she plays a harp with his or her right hand.  The figure's mouth may be open and he or she may be singing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>star of Bethlehem</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the design, a gowned female (the personification of the star of Bethlehem) sits in a chariot.  Her long hair 
                  may be drawn back in a bun.  Her left arm is pictured at her side.  Her right arm is bent and she holds an oil lamp with a flame or 
                  star above it.  Her head is turned and faces slightly to the left; she may be looking at the lamp.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>lamp</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>star of Bethlehem</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The female figure in the chariot holds an oil lamp in her right hand with a flame or star (probably the star of Bethlehem) above it.  
                  Beams of light emanate from the flame or star.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>chariot</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The female figure holding a lamp sits in a chariot.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two horses lie resting on a cloud to the left of the chariot.  Their front legs are bent and folded beneath them.  The 
                  leftmost horse is partly obscured by its companion.  The rightmost horse has a luxuriant mane and tail, the latter extending to the right.  The horses eyes are 
                  closed and they may be sleeping.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dark wash suggests a night sky.  The horses and chariot rest on a single cloud.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="but542.1.wc.06.01" justify="left" indent="55">WBlake</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>