<bad catalog="butlin" catid="521" copy="1" copyid="1" hidden="false" id="but521.1" institution="ngadc" type="wc" work="The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: 'And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations'">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: 'And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations'">
          <main>The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: &quot;And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations&quot;</main>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
          , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>2 XML files approx. 11KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 132KB to 855KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
        <date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are 
        <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi>
        of 1809 and 
        <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>
        in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>
        , datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as 
        <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>
        . 
                    
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2011</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This image copyright © 2011 National Gallery of Art, Washington</userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>November 2012</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Illustration markup</change>
        <date>Summer 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>March 2011</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Joseph Vogel,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>BAD created</change>
        <date>July 2010</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Lamperez,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Image color corrected</change>
        <date>July 2009</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
          <name>Michelle Langston, </name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Image scanned and catalogued</change>
        <date>September 2002</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
          <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
          <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>
            *The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: &quot;And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations&quot;*
          </title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>delineator, </role>
          <role>colorist</role></origination>
        <origination>Anonymous
          <role>delineator.  The inscriptions on the mount, available under Related Works in the Archive, are not by Blake.  They could not have been written before 1846, the earliest known date for the production of the paper on which the inscriptions are written.  The identity of the calligrapher who wrote the inscriptions is not known.</role></origination>
        <compdate value="1803">c. 1803-05</compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <numberobj>1</numberobj>
        <objsize>40.1 x 35.6 cm.
          <note>The mount (the backing mat) measures 50.6 x 41.5 cm.</note></objsize>
        <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>40.1 x 35.6 cm.
          <note>The mount (the backing mat) measures 50.6 x 41.5 cm.</note></leafsize>
        <medium>pen and ink and water color
          <note>The inscriptions on the mount (the backing mat) are in pencil.</note></medium>
        <support>paper, probably wove
          <note>The mount (the backing mat) is a card-like paper.  It bears a blind embossment, &quot;Turnbull's Crayon Board,&quot; arranged around an oval, palette-like shape in the top left corner.</note></support>
        <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
        <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
        <framelines>none</framelines>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington</name>
        <date>1945</date>
        <dealer>none</dealer>
        <price>gift</price>
        <note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts c. 1803-05; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold Sotheby's, 26 June 1852, lot 164 (£1.1s. to &quot;Fuller,&quot; probably a dealer); H. A. J. Munro; sold Christie's, 24 April 1868, lot 497 (£2.8s. to &quot;Kibble,&quot; probably a dealer); Marsden J. Perry by 1905; sold in 1908 to W. A. White; sold in 1929 to Lessing J. Rosenwald through the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach; given by Rosenwald to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, in 1945.</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
        <addressline>Constitution Ave. NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline>
        <addressline>Washington, D. C. 20565</addressline>
        <addressline>mailing address: 2000B South Club Drive</addressline>
        <addressline>Landover, Maryland 20785</addressline>
        <addressline>United States</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 202-737-4215</addressline>
        <addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov/</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone, Print Study Room: 202-842-6380</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 202-842-6126</addressline>
        <addressline>URL, Visual Services: http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline>
        <department>Drawings and Prints</department>
        <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art, Washington</collection>
        <repositoryid label="Accession number">B-11062</repositoryid>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="BUT521.1.1.WC" id="but521.1.wc.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: &quot;And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations&quot;</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 521)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>Blake signed the work, lower right, with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  The inscriptions on the mount above and below the design are not by Blake.  These are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>40.1 x 35.6 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="800" width="700"/>
      </physdesc>
      <related objectid="inscbut521.1.rm.01" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut521.1.rm.02" ovp="noindex"/>
      <related objectid="inscbut521.1.rm.03" ovp="noindex"/>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The design takes its subject from Revelation 13:1-2. Dominating the design is the figure of a muscular nude male standing, facing forward with legs spread and bending his legs slightly to crouch. His right leg is on tiptoe and fins are visible along both legs. His arms are at his side, palms down. He has bat-like wings decorated with stars, at least 24 on his right wing and 16 on his left wing. This demon, devil, or dragon has seven heads. The leftmost head is that of a bald male wearing a crown and with a looped horn like a ram's; it faces left and down. The second-to-left head faces left and has a horn like a unicorn's. The third-to-left head is that of a female with long, curly hair that wears a crown or band of gold and has two looped horns; it looks left and down, but faces slightly forward. The middle head has two looped horns like a ram's and is male, facing forward and down with its eyes closed; it wears a spiky crown. The third-to-right head is that of a female with long, curly hair that looks down and to the right but faces slightly forward; it has two looped horns and wears a crown. The second-to-right head faces right and has short hair and a horn like a unicorn's. The rightmost head is that of a bald male wearing a spiky crown; it has one looped horn and looks right and down. This figure also has a tail the extends below the chest of the figure below. The sky backing the scene is dark, perhaps indicating that it takes place at night. At the bottom of the design are dark waves of the sea. Rising from the sea, with only its upper body exposed is a nude figure of another demon, devil, or dragon, facing forward. There are slight indications of hair or fur on its chest. Its arms are raised at 135 degrees and are lined with fins. In its left hand it holds a scepter topped with a fleur-de-lis, surrounded by flames just above the demon's hands. In its right hand it holds a sword, wrapped around with flames. The figure may be male, but its seven heads are animal-like. The leftmost head faces left and up and has its mouth slightly open with its teeth showing; it may have a mustache and has a large and a small horn like a unicorn that may each have a small, spiky crown surrounding its base. The second-to-left head faces forward and up with its mouth open. The third-to-left head faces forward and slightly up and has its mouth open; it has two horns. The middle (highest) head faces forward and looks up with its mouth open and teeth visible; it has two looped horns like a ram's and each horn may have a crown surrounding its base. The third-to-left head faces forward and to the right, looking up with its mouth partly open; it has two looped horns like a ram's. The second-to-right head faces up, forward, and slightly left with its mouth open; its eyes may be closed. The rightmost head faces right and up and has a large and a small horn resembling a unicorn's, perhaps with a small, spiky crown surrounding the base of each.   
                    </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>demon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>heads, multiple</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>star</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>devil</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>unicorn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>band</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dragon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Dominating the design is the figure of a muscular nude male standing, facing forward with legs spread and bending his legs slightly to crouch. His right leg is on tiptoe and fins are visible along both legs. His arms are at his side, palms down. He has bat-like wings decorated with stars, at least 24 on his right wing and 16 on his left wing. This demon, dragon, or devil has seven heads. The leftmost head is that of a bald male wearing a crown and with a looped horn like a ram's; it faces left and down and may be smiling. The second-to-left head faces left and has a horn like a unicorn's. The third-to-left head is that of a female with long, curly hair that wears a crown or band of gold and has two looped horns; it looks left and down, but faces slightly forward and may be smiling. The middle head has two looped horns like a ram's and is male, facing forward and down with its eyes closed; it wears a spiky crown. The third-to-right head is that of a female with long, curly hair that looks down and to the right but faces slightly forward; it has two looped horns and wears a crown. The second-to-right head faces right and has short hair and a horn like a unicorn's. The rightmost head is that of a bald male wearing a spiky crown; it has one looped horn and looks right and down. This figure also has a tail the extends below the chest of the figure below.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>devil</characteristic>
            <characteristic>demon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dragon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fur</characteristic>
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic>
            <characteristic>heads, multiple</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>teeth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ram</characteristic>
            <characteristic>unicorn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Rising from the sea, with only its upper body exposed is a nude figure of a demon, devil, or dragon, facing forward. There are slight indications of hair or fur on his chest. Its arms are raised at 135 degrees and are lined with fins. In its left hand it holds a scepter topped with a fleur-de-lis, surrounded by flames just above the demon's hand. In its right hand it holds a sword, wrapped around with flames. The figure may be male, but its seven heads are animal-like. The leftmost head faces left and up and has its mouth slightly open with its teeth showing; it may have a mustache and has a large and a small horn like a unicorn that may each have a small, spiky crown surrounding its base. The second-to-left head faces forward and up with its mouth open. The third-to-left head faces forward and slightly up and has its mouth open; it has two horns. The middle (highest) head faces forward and looks up with its mouth open and teeth visible; it has two looped horns like a ram's and each horn may have a crown surrounding its base. The third-to-left head faces forward and to the right, looking up with its mouth partly open; it has two looped horns like a ram's. The second-to-right head faces up, forward, and slightly left with its mouth open; its eyes may be closed. The rightmost head faces right and up and has a large and a small horn resembling a unicorn's, perhaps with a small, spiky crown surrounding each base.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The sky backing the scene is dark, perhaps indicating that it takes place at night. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
            <characteristic>water</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>At the bottom of the design are dark waves of the sea.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="40" justify="left" n="but521.1.wc.01.01">inv</l>
          <l indent="40" justify="left" n="but521.1.wc.01.02">WB</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
      <supplemental>
        <desc dbi="BUT521.1.1-full.RM" id="inscbut521.1.rm.01">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: &quot;And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations&quot;</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">full view including mount inscriptions </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>Blake signed the work, lower right, with his monogram; see the textual transcription.  The inscriptions on the mount (the backing mat) above and below the design are not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>50.6 x 41.5 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="875" width="750"/>
      </physdesc>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT521.1.1-insc-t.RM" id="inscbut521.1.rm.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: &quot;And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations&quot;</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">top mount inscription </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The inscription on the mount (the backing mat) above the design is not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>3.8 x 35.9 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="825"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="1" justify="left" n="inscbut521.1.rm.02.01">And power was given him over all kindreds, &amp; tongues, &amp; nations</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="BUT521.1.1-insc-b.RM" id="inscbut521.1.rm.03">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from the Sea: &quot;And Power Was Given Him Over All Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations&quot;</title>,
            
        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">bottom mount inscriptions </objnumber></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The inscriptions on the mount (the backing mat) below the design are not by Blake.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>7.4 x 35.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="400" width="825"/>
      </physdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
          <l indent="58" justify="left" n="inscbut521.1.rm.03.01">Rev
            <hi rend="superscript">ns</hi>
            : ch: 13: v.1:&amp;2:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="inscbut521.1.rm.03.02">And I stood and saw a beast rise up out of the sea, having seven heads and ten horns, &amp; upon</l>
          <l justify="left" n="inscbut521.1.rm.03.03">his horns ten crowns, &amp; upon his heads the name of blasphemy. And the beast which I saw</l>
          <l justify="left" n="inscbut521.1.rm.03.04">was like unto a leopard, &amp; his feet were as the feet of a bear, &amp; his mouth as the mouth of a lion,</l>
          <l indent="3" justify="left" n="inscbut521.1.rm.03.05">and the dragon gave him his power &amp; his seat &amp; great authority.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
      </supplemental>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>