<bad id="but547.1" type="wc" work="Six Extra-Illustrations to a Second Folio Edition of Shakespeare"
    copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="547">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Six Extra-Illustrations to a Second Folio Edition of Shakespeare">
                    <main>Six Extra-Illustrations to a Second Folio Edition of Shakespeare</main> :
                    electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of Blake’s water color illustrations to the plays of William Shakespeare. 
                 <lb/>
                <lb/>     
Although less extensive and well known than his illustrations of John Milton’s poems, Blake’s water colors based on Shakespeare’s plays constitute a significant group of designs. The earliest, dating from c. 1779, is probably one of Blake’s illustrations of English history but nonetheless evokes Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi>. The series of seven small ovals picturing characters from the plays also dates from Blake’s early years. The concentrated focus on just one or two figures filling most of the pictorial space may be Blake’s response to popular interest in miniature portraiture. The reason for his execution of this group is not known; like the English history designs, they may have been intended for eventual publication as engravings.  The series of Shakespeare character portraits by John Hamilton Mortimer, published as engravings in the mid-1770s, may have influenced Blake’s similar project.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
<hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> is one of Blake’s largest water colors of the 1780s. Its size and quality suggest that it may have been intended for exhibition, like the water colors illustrating the life of Joseph displayed at the Royal Academy in 1785. The circle of dancers and Puck’s stance with arms raised echo similar motifs in George Romney’s <hi rend="i">Leveson-Gower Family</hi>, painted in 1776-77 and published as a mezzotint by John Raphael Smith in 1781.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Blake was clearly attracted to the vision of Queen Katherine in <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, act 4, scene 2, for he executed four versions beginning c. 1783-90 and concluding with the highly finished and complex water color of c. 1825-26. Blake’s water color of Queen Katherine’s dream dated 1809 is part of a series of six illustrations to Shakespeare’s plays commissioned by Joseph Thomas, the clergyman who had earlier employed Blake to illustrate Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. In a letter of 31 July 1801 to William Hayley, John Flaxman added a postscript to Blake, including the following: “he [Thomas] also desired you [Blake] will make two designs in bister or Indian Ink, from Shakespeare’s Troylus &amp; Cressida, Coriolanus, either of the 3 plays of Henry 6.<sup>th</sup> Richard the 3.<sup>d</sup> or Henry the 8.<sup>th</sup> each design for one play for which he will give a Guinea each, the dimensions as follow the paper. an upright square of 12 Inches &amp; half by 8 Inches, within this Space leaving a moderate margin, the principal figure not exceeding 6 Inches high” (Butlin 547). Blake’s designs (most now trimmed) roughly follow these size requirements, necessitated by Thomas’s desire to create an extra-illustrated copy of the 1632 second folio of Shakespeare’s plays, but Blake waited eight years before completing the commission, changed the medium from monochrome drawings to water colors, and illustrated only two plays, <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi> and <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, specified by Flaxman. Blake may have chosen the other passages for illustration, at some point convincing Thomas of their appropriateness.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Many of Blake’s Shakespeare designs show his predilection for scenes dealing with perceptions that extend beyond the world of the physical senses. The four versions of Queen Katherine’s dream epitomize this lifelong interest in imaginative and visionary experiences. A corollary is Blake’s attraction to representations of the arts, demonstrated by <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> and his portrayal of Pegasus, the classical embodiment of poetic inspiration, in <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi> among the designs for Thomas.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, editors <lb/>
                Joseph Fletcher, managing editor, Michael Fox, assistant editor<lb/>
                 The William Blake Archive<lb/>     
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 British Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February - March 2020</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies,</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Dan Gorman</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose</name>
                    <name>Jake Ruta</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>     
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>February 2016</date>
                 <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Laura Bell</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Rachel Lee,</name>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Adam Engel,</name>
<name>Andrea Everett,</name>
<name>Grant Glass,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Eric Loy,</name>
<name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
<name>Adam McCune,</name>
<name>Scott Robinson,</name>
<name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
<name>Miles Simon,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
<name>Alia Wegner,</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
<name>Kirk V. Hastings, </name>
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Six Extra-Illustrations to a Second Folio Edition of Shakespeare*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1806">1806 and 1809<note>Objects 1 (*Jacques and the
                            Wounded Stag*), 4 (*Brutus and Caesar's Ghost*), and
                        5 (*Hamlet and His Father's Ghost*) are inscribed by Blake
                        with the date "1806." Objects 3 (*Queen Katharine's Dream*)
                        and 6 (*As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds*) are
                        inscribed "1809" by Blake. Object 2 (*Richard III and the
                            Ghosts*) can be dated to c. 1806 because of its stylistic
                        similarities to the works with that inscribed date.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>6</numberobj>
                <objsize>each approximately 23.0 x 16.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>6</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>approximately 24.5 x 18.0 cm. (objects 1, 2, 4, 5), 30.8 x 19.4 cm.
                    (object 3), 38.0 x 19.1 cm. (object 6)</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color<note>Blake's inscriptions are in pen and
                        ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>Single framing lines extend around objects 3 and 6.</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1954</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>In part commissioned from Blake by Joseph Thomas in 1801 (see the postscript
                    addressed to Blake in John Flaxman's letter of 31 July 1801 to William Hayley,
                    quoted in Butlin 547) but apparently not delivered until 1806-09 when inserted
                    into a 1632 second folio of Shakespeare's plays; by inheritance to Thomas's
                    widow in 1811; their daughter, Mrs. John Woodford Chase; her son, Drummond Percy
                    Chase, in 1876, probably by inheritance; sold 1880 to Alexander Macmillan; W. E.
                    F. Macmillan; given by the executors of his estate to the British Museum in
                    1954.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings:
                    prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration numbers">1954,1113.1.11, 21, 22, 26, 27,
                    37</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but547.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT547.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Jacques and the Wounded Stag</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 547.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>22.0 x 15.8 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In this illustration of Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">As You Like
                            It</hi>, a male figure sits on the bank of a body of water and turns his
                        head to look up with an open mouth. His left arm is bent upward with palm
                        facing up. He extends his right arm to point toward a deer at left, which
                        appears to be wounded and dripping blood from its left side. The animal
                        bends down, perhaps to drink from the water. At least eight other deer are
                        visible in the forested background. The man is Jacques, one of the noblemen
                        attending Duke Senior who lives in exile in the forest. In Act II, Scene I,
                        of the play, the First Lord narrates a story about observing "melancholy
                        Jacques" as he followed a wounded stag to the edge of a stream and, while
                        overcome with emotion, compared the animal's isolation and death to the ills
                        of human society: "'Poor deer,' quoth he, 'thou mak'st a testament/ As
                        worldlings do, giving thy sum of more/ To that which had too much.'"
                        (49-51).</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Jacques</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this illustration of Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">As You Like
                                It</hi>, a male figure sits on the bank of a body of water and turns
                            his head to look up with an open mouth. He has short hair (perhaps
                            partially bald?) and a mustache and wears a collared shirt, pants, and
                            perhaps sandals. His left arm is bent upward with palm facing up. He
                            extends his right arm and may point toward a deer at left, which appears
                            to be wounded. The male figure represents Jacques, one of the noblemen
                            attending Duke Senior who lives in exile in the forest. In Act II, Scene
                            I, of the play, the First Lord narrates a story about observing
                            "melancholy Jacques" as he followed a wounded stag to the edge of a
                            stream and, while overcome with emotion, compared the animal's isolation
                            and death to the ills of human society.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>deer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stag</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drinking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tears</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A stag with prominent antlers bends forward, possibly to drink
                            from a body of water on the left side of this illustration of
                            Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">As You Like It</hi>. The animal faces
                            forward, and tears stream down from its eyes. A wound is visible on its
                            left side from which blood drips and to which the male figure, Jacques,
                            points. The scene references Jacques' interaction with a wounded, crying
                            stag in Act II, Scene I of the play in which he compares the isolation
                            and eventual death of the animal to the ills of human society. "The
                            wretched animal heaved forth such groans/ That their discharge did
                            stretch his leathern coat/ Almost to bursting, and the big round tears/
                            Coursed one another down his innocent nose/ In piteous chase."
                            (37-41).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>deer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stag</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this illustration of Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">As You Like
                                It</hi>, at least eight deer are visible in the forested background:
                            a group of three stand facing forward between two trees at left while a
                            cluster of five appear to run to the right or away near the center of
                            the image. All of these animals have antlers and are thus stags. These
                            deer likely represent the "careless herd,/ Full of pasture, [who] jumps
                            along by him [the wounded deer]/ And never stays to greet him."
                            (55-57).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stream</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A body of water and a grassy bank (on which the male figure
                            sits) are visible along the bottom edge of the image from which the stag
                            prepares to drink. The water is likely the "brook that brawls along this
                            wood;/ To the which place a poor sequestered stag/ That from the
                            hunter's aim had ta'en a hurt/ Did come to languish."
                            (33-35).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ivy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This illustration likely represents the forest in which Duke
                            Senior and his noblemen attendants, including Jacques, live in exile in
                            Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">As You Like It</hi>. Four tree trunks
                            with leafy foliage dominate the grassy, hilly landscape. Branches are
                            visible on the two middle trees, and a leafy vine (perhaps ivy) grows up
                            the leftmost tree, which is likely the oak "whose antique root peeps
                            out" mentioned in the play (32).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below an area of blue sky upper left, hills are visible in the
                            background forested landscape, with one particularly large hill behind
                            the group of deer at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.01.01" justify="left" indent="46">
                        <hi rend="superscript">inv</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.01.02" justify="left" indent="46">WB 1806</l>
                    <note>Butlin 547.1 records additional inscriptions, but we have not been able to
                        locate these on the work as it presently exists.</note>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but547.1.wc.02" dbi="BUT547.1.2.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Richard III and The Ghosts</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U2">(Butlin 547.2)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.5 x 15.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A central figure in armor raises a sword above his head while at
                        least nine other figures, who are translucent and thus likely ghosts, hover
                        around him. The illustration likely represents the scene from Shakespeare's
                        play <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi>, Act 5, Scene 3, in which King Richard
                        III is visited in his tent by the ghosts of all those he has killed,
                        including his brother, nephews, and wife. Only nine of the play's eleven
                        ghosts, however, are depicted here. Facing forward in the center of the
                        composition with sword raised, Richard leans or steps to the left with legs
                        spread wide. He looks up with a fearful expression, and his mouth is open.
                        Directly below him, two small translucent figures hover or fly with heads at
                        left, facing up. They both have short hair and appear to wear gowns; both
                        point upward toward Richard. They are likely the ghosts of Prince Edward and
                        Richard, Duke of York, the sons of late King Edward IV. Four additional
                        ghostly figures hover near the right margin. Facing away but turned to look
                        left, a female figure with a long gown and veil extends her left arm to
                        touch Richard on the shoulder. Her mouth is open, suggesting she is
                        speaking. This figure is likely the Ghost of Lady Anne, Richard's wife whom
                        he murdered in order to court his niece, Elizabeth of York. Immediately
                        behind and to the left of Lady Anne, an older male figure with a mustache
                        and long beard faces forward and looks down to the left toward Richard. He
                        bends his right arm to point toward Anne. The heads of two additional
                        ghostly figures appear alternatively to the left of the bearded male figure
                        and to the right of the female figure, Anne. On the left side of the image,
                        three additional ghostly male figures appear, all facing right. The
                        rightmost of these is bearded and wears a crown and a long gown. His mouth
                        is open and his brow furrowed as he points accusingly toward bloody wounds
                        in his chest with both bent arms. This is likely King Henry VI, who in the
                        play tells Richard III, "When I was mortal, my annointed body/ By thee was
                        punched full of deadly holes./ Think on the Tower and me. Despair and die!"
                        (132-134). The middle male figure at left has short curly hair and appears
                        to look down in horror at the wounds of the male figure in front of him,
                        King Henry VI. Only the head of the leftmost figure, whose mouth is open, is
                        visible. Behind the figures, the top of a tent is visible; in the play, the
                        ghosts visit Richard in his battlefield tent on the eve of war. There is a
                        bed with sheets and a tubular pillow (?) in the lower part of the
                        composition's background along with a table on which two lighted candles and
                        an open book rest. Areas of dark shadow appear all around the composition,
                        and the areas of darkness in the upper corners of the composition may
                        suggest the time is night.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg exended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Richard the Third</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Facing forward in the center of the composition with sword
                            raised above his head with his bent right arm, a male figure leans or
                            steps to the left with legs spread wide and left leg extended. He has
                            short curly hair and a beard and also wears armor. His left arm is bent
                            and by his side where he holds a scabbard. He looks up with a fearful
                            expression, and his mouth is open. At least nine other figures, who are
                            translucent and thus likely ghosts, hover around him. The illustration
                            likely represents the scene from Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Richard
                                III</hi>, Act 5, Scene 3, in which King Richard III is visited in
                            his tent by the ghosts of all those he has killed, including his
                            brother, nephews, and wife.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scabbard</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The central figure, Richard III, holds a sword in his right
                            hand, which is raised above his head. In his left hand, which is by his
                            side, he holds a scabbard.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prince</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Edward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Richard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>York</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. Directly below Richard,
                            two small translucent figures hover or fly with heads at left, facing
                            up, and bodies horizontal. They both have short, curly hair and appear
                            to wear gowns; both point and look upward toward Richard and have open
                            mouths. They are likely the ghosts of Prince Edward and Richard, Duke of
                            York, the young sons of late King Edward IV, who in the play tell
                            Richard: "Dream on thy cousins smothered in the Tower./ Let us be lead
                            within thy bosom, Richard, And weigh thee down to ruin, shame, and
                            death./ Thy nephews' souls bid thee despair and die." (155-158). Seen
                            from behind and facing left, the foregrounded figure (who has curly
                            hair) raises his left arm vertically and extends his right arm backward
                            to touch his extended left leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prince</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Edward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Richard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>York</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. Directly below Richard,
                            two small translucent figures hover or fly with heads at left, facing
                            up, and bodies horizontal. They both have short hair and appear to wear
                            gowns; both point and look upward toward Richard and have open mouths.
                            They are likely the ghosts of Prince Edward and Richard, Duke of York,
                            the young sons of late King Edward IV, who in the play tell Richard:
                            "Dream on thy cousins smothered in the Tower./ Let us be lead within thy
                            bosom, Richard, And weigh thee down to ruin, shame, and death./ Thy
                            nephews' souls bid thee despair and die." (155-158). The prince behind
                            his companion faces forward and raises his right arm vertically while
                            his left is visible at his side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Anne</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. Four ghostly figures
                            hover near the right margin. Facing away but turned to look left, a
                            female figure with a long gown and veil extends her left arm to touch
                            Richard on the shoulder. Her mouth is open, suggesting she is speaking.
                            Her right leg is slightly bent and extended behind her with the right
                            foot visible. This figure is likely the Ghost of Lady Anne, Richard's
                            wife whom he murdered in order to court his niece, Elizabeth of York. In
                            the play, she tells Richard: "Richard, thy wife, that wretched Anne thy
                            wife,/ That never slept a quiet hour with thee,/ Now fills thy sleep
                            with perturbations./ Tomorrow, in the battle, think on me,/ And fall thy
                            edgeless sword. Despair and die!" (169-173).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. Four ghostly figures
                            hover near the right margin. Immediately behind and to the left of Lady
                            Anne, the female figure, an older male figure with a mustache and long
                            beard who may wear a gown faces forward and looks down to the left
                            toward the central figure, Richard. He bends his right arm to point
                            toward Anne.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. Four ghostly figures
                            hover near the right margin. The heads of two of these ghostly figures
                            appear alternatively to the left of the bearded male figure and to the
                            right of the female figure, Anne. The head at left faces forward and
                            left to look toward the central figure, Richard.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. Four ghostly figures
                            hover near the right margin. The heads of two of these ghostly figures
                            appear alternatively to the left of the bearded male figure and to the
                            right of the female figure, Anne. The gender of the head at right is
                            unclear, but this figure faces directly forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>anger</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Henry the Sixth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. On the left side of the
                            image, three additional ghostly male figures appear to hover, all facing
                            right and leaning forward to look toward the central figure, Richard.
                            The rightmost of these is bearded and wears a crown and a long gown. His
                            mouth is open, perhaps to suggest he is speaking, and his brow furrowed
                            in anger as he points accusingly toward bloody wounds in his chest with
                            both bent arms. His left foot is visible below his gown. This is likely
                            King Henry VI, who in the play tells Richard III, "When I was mortal, my
                            annointed body/ By thee was punched full of deadly holes./Think on the
                            Tower and me. Despair and die!" (132-134).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. On the left side of the
                            image, three additional ghostly male figures appear to hover, all facing
                            right and leaning forward to look toward the central figure, Richard.
                            The middle male figure at left has short curly hair and appears to look
                            down in horror at the wounds of the male figure in front of him, King
                            Henry VI. He raises his bent right arm to his chest (where he appears to
                            point) and may wear a gown. His mouth appears to be open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this depiction of Act 5, Scene 3 in Shakespeare's play <hi
                                rend="i">Richard III</hi>, at least nine ghosts hover around the
                            central figure of Richard III, their murderer. On the left side of the
                            image, three additional ghostly male figures appear to hover, all facing
                            right and leaning forward to look toward the central figure, Richard.
                            Only the short-haired head of the leftmost figure, whose mouth is open,
                            is visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>tent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures in the upper half of the composition, the
                            top of a tent is visible. In the play, the ghosts visit Richard in his
                            battlefield tent on the eve of war.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candle holder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candlestick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower half of the composition, in the background, there
                            is a bed with sheets and a tubular pillow along with a table at left on
                            which two lighted candles and what appears to be an open book rest. The
                            light from the candles emphasizes the translucency of the ghosts at
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Areas of dark shadow appear all around the composition,
                            particularly in the corners. The darkness in the upper corners may
                            suggest the time is night, which correlates with the nighttime setting
                            of the scene in the play.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.02.01" justify="left" indent="6">WB inv</l>
                    <note>Butlin 547.2 records additional inscriptions, but we have not been able to
                        locate these on the work as it presently exists.</note>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but547.1.wc.03" dbi="BUT547.1.3.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Queen Katharine's Dream</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U3">(Butlin 547.3)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>22.2 x 16.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Three large figures, two female and one male, and twenty-four
                        smaller female figures occupy the space of this composition, which
                        represents The Vision of Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of Shakespeare's
                        play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. The central female figure of Queen
                        Katharine lies supine with legs together on a bed or couch with her head at
                        right near the lower third of the scene. She has long hair and wears a gown
                        and veil (perhaps also with a crown?). Both arms are bent by her sides but
                        extended upward from the elbow with fingers spread. She appears to raise her
                        head and shoulders away from the pillow below her, perhaps to better see the
                        visionary activity above her. Queen Katharine is the wife of King Henry VIII
                        who wishes to divorce her (as she has not born a male heir) and marry Anne
                        Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it is during her sickness in which The
                        Vision occurs. The bed or couch on which she lies contains a serpentine arm
                        at right as well as a pillow and heavy drapery on the left side. In front of
                        the bed in both lower corners of the composition, the other two large
                        figures sit facing each other on sizable pillows. Both have their eyes
                        closed and appear to sleep with their heads supported on one bent arm. The
                        figure in the right corner is a gowned female with long hair who rests her
                        elbow on the open book atop the small table behind her. She is probably
                        Patience, servant to the queen. The male figure at left has white hair and a
                        long beard; he is also gowned. This is probably Griffith, the queen's usher.
                        He rests his elbow on a similar table behind him and turns his head to face
                        forward. The twenty-four other smaller figures in the scene, who all appear
                        to be gowned and female, fly upward and around the supine figure of Queen
                        Katharine in serpentine formations. Nine of these figures circle the body of
                        Queen Katharine in the lower half of the image. In the center along the
                        bottom margin, the lowest of these figures face forward but lean and face
                        away from one another as they touch extended hands and perhaps also feet to
                        form a sort of diamond shape between them. Both wear laurel crowns and wispy
                        clouds are visible around them, as if arising from the same origin. The
                        figure at right raises her left arm to hold the hand of a third figure who
                        flies upward facing away. Both legs are bent and her long hair is visible.
                        She raises her right hand to touch the foot of a fourth figure who flies or
                        hovers directly to the right of Queen Katharine's head. This figure faces
                        away but looks left. She wears a laurel crown and holds another such crown
                        in her bent left arm. A fifth figure also holds this crown with her bent
                        left arm while she hovers with body horizontal at left, just above the torso
                        of Queen Katharine. Together, these small figures may be preparing to crown
                        the supine queen, and both point upward with their other free hand. This
                        moment is referenced directly in the play's text: "the first two
                        [Personages] hold a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene 2). Returning
                        to the pair of figures at the bottom of the image, the left figure raises
                        her right arm to hold the hand of a long-haired sixth figure at left who
                        faces forward and raises both arms horizontally. This figure, with her right
                        arm, touches (or almost touches) the foot of a seventh figure who faces away
                        and twists her body to the right in a sort of half-circle around Queen
                        Katharine's feet. This figure holds an object in each raised hand, which may
                        be cymbals. Small clouds are visible beneath this figures at left. To the
                        right of the leftmost figure's torso, two additional figures hover with
                        bodies horizontal and complete the circle of figures around Queen Katharine.
                        The leftmost of these faces forward and plays a harp or lyre. Her companion
                        at right, who appears to wear a laurel crown, faces away and may also play a
                        musical instrument. In the upper half of the image, fifteen figures fly
                        upward or float on small, wispy clouds in a serpentine formation of three
                        approximate tiers. The lowest tier contains four figures with bodies
                        horizontal flying left and two furthest left whose bodies are slightly
                        higher and twisted to the right. The rightmost figure faces forward with
                        arms extended horizontally; in each hand, she holds circular objects that
                        may be cymbals. Behind and slightly to the left of her, a second figure
                        echoes her posture with arms raised horizontally, palms facing forward. The
                        third figure from the right, who has long hair, faces to the left but turns
                        to look back toward her companions. She plays a harp or lyre with her left
                        hand. The fourth figure from the right faces away and holds a similar harp
                        or lyre with bent arms. The two leftmost figures in this tier face away and
                        bend sharply to the right with arms extended vertically; they both appear to
                        hold and play cymbals. Four right-facing figures constitute the second and
                        middle tier of figures. The leftmost figure, just to the right of the
                        cymbal-playing pair below, has long hair and holds a harp or lyre with bent
                        arms. To her right, a long-haired figure faces right and plays two horns,
                        which she holds with extended arms. The rightmost figures in this tier fly
                        upward side-by-side and play horns pointed upward. The figure at left faces
                        away, and it is unclear which direction the figure at right faces. The third
                        and highest tier contains five figures. The rightmost of these faces away
                        and twists her body in a serpentine position to the left. To the left, a
                        figure plays two horns, which she holds up with raised arms. The third
                        figure from the right faces away but appears to turn her head to look right;
                        she raises both arms vertically. The two leftmost figures are very close
                        together and somewhat indistinguishable except for their heads, but they
                        both appear to have their arms upward. Most of the scene's background sky
                        contains colorful beams of light that appear to stream down from the upper
                        margin of the image.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Katharine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three large figures, two female and one male, and twenty-four
                            smaller female figures occupy the space of this composition, which
                            represents The Vision of Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of
                            Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. The central female
                            figure of Queen Katharine lies supine with legs together on a bed or
                            couch with her head at right near the lower third of the scene. She has
                            long hair and wears a gown and veil (perhaps also with a crown?). Both
                            arms are bent by her sides but extended upward from the elbow with
                            fingers spread. She appears to raise her head and shoulders away from
                            the pillow below her, perhaps to better see the visionary activity above
                            her. Her mouth may be open. This figure, Queen Katharine, is the wife of
                            King Henry VIII who wishes to divorce her (as she has not born a male
                            heir) and marry Anne Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it is during her
                            sickness in which The Vision occurs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bed or couch on which the central figure of Queen
                            Katharine lies contains a serpentine arm or headboard at right as well
                            as a pillow and heavy drapery on the left side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Patience</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of the bed in both lower corners of the composition,
                            two large figures sit facing each other on sizable pillows. Both have
                            their eyes closed and appear to sleep with their heads supported on one
                            bent arm. The figure in the right corner is a gowned female with long
                            hair who rests her right elbow on the open book atop the small table
                            behind her. This is probably Patience, a servant to the queen. Her left
                            arm is bent and crossed beneath her right. Her mouth may be open.
                            Although her body faces left, her upper body is twisted to face forward.
                            Her legs are extended and both feet (which are clad in shoes) are
                            visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Griffith</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of the bed in both lower corners of the composition,
                            two large figures sit facing each other on sizable pillows. Both have
                            their eyes closed and appear to sleep with their heads supported on one
                            bent arm. The male figure at left has white hair and a long beard; he is
                            also gowned. This is probably Griffith, the queen's usher. He rests his
                            left elbow on a table behind him and turns his head to face forward. His
                            right arm is bent and by his side with his hand resting on his lap. His
                            legs are bent and extended with one shoe-clad foot visible beneath his
                            gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures sit on large pillows in both lower corners of the
                            image. These pillows each have a single tassel on one corner. A table is
                            also visible in each corner, and both figures rest one arm on it. An
                            open book rests on the table at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. In the center along the bottom
                            margin, the two lowest of these figures face forward but lean and face
                            away from one another as they touch extended hands and perhaps also feet
                            to form a sort of diamond shape between them. Wispy clouds are visible
                            around them, as if arising from the same origin. The figure at right
                            (who may wear a crown or laurels?) raises her left arm to hold the hand
                            of the figure above and right of her toward whom she also
                            looks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. In the center along the bottom
                            margin, the two lowest of these figures face forward but lean and face
                            away from one another as they touch extended hands and perhaps also feet
                            to form a sort of diamond shape between them. Wispy clouds are visible
                            around them, as if arising from the same origin. The figure at left who
                            wears a crown of laurels raises her right arm to hold the hand of the
                            figure above and left of her toward whom she also looks with her head
                            up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. Directly above and to the left
                            of the sleeping female figure in the lower right corner, a female
                            figure, who faces away and is thus seen from behind, flies up and to the
                            right. She has long hair and may wear a laurel crown. Her left arm is at
                            her side, and she holds the hand of the figure below her. Her right arm
                            is extended upward, and she may touch the foot of the figure above her
                            at right. The figure's legs are bent with the right extended backward
                            and the bottom of her foot visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. Directly to the right of Queen
                            Katharine's head, a fourth figure who flies or hovers directly to the
                            right of Queen Katharine's head. Seen from behind, this figure faces
                            away but looks left with right leg extended backward. She has long hair
                            and wears a laurel crown; she holds another such crown in her bent left
                            arm. A fifth figure also holds this crown and flies just above the torso
                            of Queen Katharine. Together, these small figures may be preparing to
                            crown the supine queen, and both point upward with their other free
                            hand. This moment is referenced directly in the play's text: "the first
                            two [Personages] hold a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene
                            2).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. A fifth figure who flies or
                            hovers directly above the torso of Queen Katharine bends both arms
                            upward and points upward with her right hand. She faces forward but
                            turns her head to the right, perhaps to look toward her companion at
                            right. She appears to have short hair and may wear a laurel crown. Her
                            legs are together and extended to the left horizontally. She holds a
                            laurel crown with her bent left arm. The figure to her right also holds
                            this crown. Together, these small figures may be preparing to crown the
                            supine queen, and both point upward with their other free hand. This
                            moment is referenced directly in the play's text: "the first two
                            [Personages] hold a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene
                            2).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. Returning to the central pair
                            of figures at the bottom of the image, the left figure raises her right
                            arm to hold the hand of the sixth figure above and at left. This figure
                            faces forward and leans to the left with her head bent sharply to the
                            right, perhaps to look down toward her companion. She has long hair. She
                            raises her left arm horizontally and her right arm at 135 degrees. She
                            appears to reach for and perhaps touch the foot of the figure above her
                            at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. Directly left of Queen
                            Katharine's feet, a seventh figure who faces away and is thus seen from
                            behind bends her body to the right with both arms raised vertically and
                            legs extended backward (with the left bent upward). She appears to have
                            short hair. In each hand, she holds an object, perhaps a cymbal, which
                            she may play. Small clouds are visible beneath this figures at left, and
                            she may float on these.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. Two figures hover with bodies
                            horizontal over the legs of Queen Katharine to complete the circle of
                            figures around her. The leftmost of these faces forward and plays a harp
                            or lyre, which she holds with bent arms. She has short hair. Both legs
                            are extended to the left and together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-four small, gowned female figures fly or hover in the
                            scene. Nine of these figures form a circle around the body of Queen
                            Katharine in the lower half of the image. Two figures hover with bodies
                            horizontal over the legs of Queen Katharine to complete the circle of
                            figures around her. The figure at right faces away and is thus seen from
                            behind. She appears to have long hair (perhaps in a braid?) and wears
                            some sort of crown or laurel wreath. Her legs are extended to the left
                            and together. Her right arm is bent, and she appears to hold (and likely
                            play) a harp or lyre visible to the right of her torso. Her head is
                            turned to the left, perhaps to look back toward her
                            companion.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cymbal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>harp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures in the lower group of figures that form a circle
                            around the supine Queen Katharine play musical instruments: the leftmost
                            figure near the queen's feet holds circular objects that may be cymbals
                            and the two figures to her right hold and play a harp or (to the right)
                            a harp or lyre.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Wispy clouds are visible near the smaller female figures in
                            the lower half of the margin, where they appear to originate at the same
                            central point where the two figures hover back to back. The clouds
                            extend a short distance diagonally at right but at left rise near the
                            middle of the left margin, terminating just above the feet of Queen
                            Katharine.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper half of the image, fifteen gowned female figures
                            fly upward or float on small, wispy clouds in a serpentine formation of
                            three approximate tiers. The lowest tier contains four figures with
                            bodies horizontal flying left and two additional figures at left whose
                            bodies are slightly higher and twisted to the right. The rightmost
                            figure faces forward with arms extended horizontally; in each hand, she
                            holds circular objects that may be cymbals, which she may play. She has
                            long hair and her mouth may be open. Her head is turned slightly to the
                            right and her legs may be crossed at the ankles.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frowning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper half of the image, fifteen gowned female figures
                            fly upward or float on small, wispy clouds in a serpentine formation of
                            three approximate tiers. The lowest tier contains four figures with
                            bodies horizontal flying left and two additional figures at left whose
                            bodies are slightly higher and twisted to the right. Behind and slightly
                            to the left of the rightmost figure, a second figure echoes her posture
                            with arms raised horizontally, palms facing up. She has long hair and
                            leans her head slightly to the left. She appears to
                            frown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>In the upper half of the image, fifteen gowned female
                            figures fly upward or float on small, wispy clouds in a serpentine
                            formation of three approximate tiers. The lowest tier contains four
                            figures with bodies horizontal flying left and two additional figures at
                            left whose bodies are slightly higher and twisted to the right. The
                            third figure from the right, who has long hair, faces to the left but
                            turns to look back toward her companions. She plays a harp or lyre with
                            her left hand; both arms are bent upward to hold the instrument. Her
                            legs are extended and appear to be together.</characteristic>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>semi-transparent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper half of the image, fifteen gowned female figures
                            fly upward or float on small, wispy clouds in a serpentine formation of
                            three approximate tiers. The lowest tier contains four figures with
                            bodies horizontal flying left and two additional figures at left whose
                            bodies are slightly higher and twisted to the right. The fourth figure
                            from the right faces away but turns her head to look right; she and
                            holds a similar harp or lyre with bent arms. She appears to have short
                            hair. Her gown, which is quite transparent, is only apparent by the
                            serpentine fold of drapery below her left foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper half of the image, fifteen gowned female figures
                            fly upward or float on small, wispy clouds in a serpentine formation of
                            three approximate tiers. The lowest tier contains four figures with
                            bodies horizontal flying left and two additional figures at left whose
                            bodies are slightly higher and twisted to the right. The two leftmost
                            figures in this tier face away and bend sharply to the right with arms
                            extended vertically; they both appear to hold and play tambourines.
                            Their legs are extended and together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cymbal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tambourine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four of the five figures in the lowest tier of gowned female
                            figures who fly or hover in the upper half of the composition hold
                            musical instruments. The rightmost figure holds what appear to be
                            cymbals; the third and fourth figures from the right holds and perhaps
                            play lyres; and the two leftmost figures whose bodies are twisted to the
                            right both hold and play tambourines.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four right-facing female figures constitute the second and
                            middle tier of gowned female figures who fly or hover in the upper half
                            of the composition. The leftmost figure, just to the right of the
                            cymbal-playing pair below, has long hair and holds or perhaps plays a
                            harp or lyre with bent arms. With body horizontal, she turns her head to
                            look forward and her long hair streams behind her. Her right leg is
                            visibly extended behind her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four right-facing female figures constitute the second and
                            middle tier of figures, who fly or hover in the upper half of the
                            composition. The third figure from the right, whose body is horizontal,
                            has long hair and faces right. She plays two horns or trumpets, which
                            she holds with extended arms. Both legs are extended behind her and
                            together. She may be nude or wear a transparent gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four right-facing female figures constitute the second and
                            middle tier of figures, who fly or hover in the upper half of the
                            composition. The two rightmost figures in this tier fly upward
                            side-by-side with bodies twisted to the left. They play horns or
                            trumpets pointed upward that they hold with bent arms raised vertically.
                            Both may be nude or wear transparent gowns. The figure at left has short
                            hair and turns her head to look up and right. Her legs are extended and
                            together, though her right leg may be bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four right-facing female figures constitute the second and
                            middle tier of figures, who fly or hover in the upper half of the
                            composition. The two rightmost figures in this tier fly upward
                            side-by-side with bodies twisted to the left. They play horns or
                            trumpets pointed upward that they hold with bent arms raised vertically.
                            Both may be nude or wear transparent gowns. The rightmost figure appears
                            to face forward with head bent back to face up, but this is not
                            clear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the second, middle tier of figures who fly or hover in the
                            upper half of the composition, all four hold, and likely play, musical
                            instruments. The leftmost figure holds a lyre; the second figure from
                            the left plays two horns or trumpets; and the two rightmost figures
                            whose bodies are twisted up and to the left both play single horns or
                            trumpets.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third and highest tier of figures in the upper half of the
                            composition contains five female(?) figures who fly or hover. The
                            rightmost figure faces away and bends her body in a serpentine position
                            to the left. She may be nude or wear a transparent gown. Her arms are
                            extended vertically and her legs, which are together, are extended
                            backward, perhaps with knees bent. She may hold an indistinguishable
                            object, likely a musical instrument.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third and highest tier of figures in the upper half of the
                            composition contains five female(?) figures who fly or hover. The second
                            figure from the right, who is gowned, faces away and slightly left. She
                            plays two horns or trumpets, which she holds up with raised arms (the
                            left arm is bent). Her legs are together and extended backward (and
                            horizontally) at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third and highest tier of figures in the upper half of the
                            composition contains five female(?) figures who fly or hover. The third
                            figure from the right, who is gowned, faces away but appears to turn her
                            head to look right; she raises both arms vertically. Her legs are
                            together and extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third and highest tier of figures in the upper half of the
                            composition contains five female(?) figures who fly or hover. The two
                            leftmost figures who are both gowned are very close together and
                            somewhat indistinguishable except for their heads, but they both appear
                            to have their arms raised upward. The figure at right may face
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third and highest tier of figures in the upper half of the
                            composition contains five female(?) figures who fly or hover. The two
                            leftmost figures who are both gowned are very close together and
                            somewhat indistinguishable except for their heads, but they both appear
                            to have their arms raised upward. The figure at left faces away and
                            extends at least one leg behind her at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the right in the highest tier of
                            figures in the upper half of the composition holds and plays two horns
                            or trumpets. The other figures in this tier may hold instruments as
                            well, but these are less distinct.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Most of the scene's background sky contains colorful beams of
                            light that appear to stream down from the upper margin of the
                            image.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.03.01" justify="left" indent="6">WBlake 1809</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but547.1.wc.04" dbi="BUT547.1.4.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Brutus and Caesar's Ghost</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U4">(Butlin 547.4)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>25.3 x 16.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Standing on tiptoe at right, a male figure surrounded by a
                        whitish-blue cloud looks down at a second male figure at left who sits at a
                        table and holds an open book but turns to look toward the first figure. An
                        illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Julius Caesar</hi>, this
                        scene represents Act 4, Scene 3, in which the Ghost of Caesar visits Brutus
                        in his tent to tell him they will meet again at Philippi as an omen of
                        Brutus' impending death. The Ghost of Caesar at right wears a long gown and
                        laurel crown above short hair. His face is turned down and his mouth is
                        open. His right arm is raised vertically and he holds a sword pointing up.
                        His left arm is raised at 135 degrees with fingers spread in a gesture of
                        pointing to the left. His left leg is extended backward, though with his
                        foot still on the ground. The cloud enveloping him attests to his ghostly
                        state. The figure of Brutus at left sits on a low chair in front of a table
                        on which two lit candles stand. He holds an open book with his bent right
                        arm, which rests on the table. His left arm is raised at 135 degrees; he
                        points to the left with his left index finger. His upper body faces away but
                        he turns his head and lower body to face right, with his left leg extended
                        and right leg bent beside the chair. He wears a shirt, tights or pants(?),
                        and sandals. His mouth is open and his short curly hair appears to stand on
                        end. Two additional tiny forms appear in the space between the main figures'
                        feet lower right. Although the details of these are indistinguishable, these
                        may be human figures. The one at right who may face left wears a dark gown
                        and a large headdress and perhaps holds a linear object in its left hand.
                        The figure at left who may face right wears a lighter gown. Alternatively,
                        the figure at right could be the shadow of the figure at left. The spine of
                        a second book and the serpentine flourish of a bed's scroll are visible
                        against the left margin. Dark pockets of shadow appear throughout the lower
                        left quadrant.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Caesar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing on tiptoe at right, a male figure surrounded by a
                            whitish-blue cloud looks down at a second male figure at left who sits
                            at a table. An illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Julius
                                Caesar</hi>, this scene represents Act 4, Scene 3, in which the
                            Ghost of Caesar visits Brutus in his tent to tell him they will meet
                            again at Philippi as an omen of Brutus' impending death. The Ghost of
                            Caesar at right wears a long gown and laurel crown above short hair. His
                            face is turned down and his mouth is open; he may be speaking. His right
                            arm is raised vertically and he holds a sword pointing up. His left arm
                            is raised at 135 degrees with fingers spread in a gesture of pointing to
                            the left. His left leg is extended backward, though with his foot still
                            on the ground. He may wear a shoe on his left foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The cloud enveloping the figure at right, the Ghost of Caesar,
                            attests to his ghostly state and perhaps also his sudden
                            apparition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Brutus</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing on tiptoe at right, a male figure surrounded by a
                            whitish-blue cloud looks down at a second male figure at left who sits
                            at a table. An illustration of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Julius
                                Caesar</hi>, this scene represents Act 4, Scene 3, in which the
                            Ghost of Caesar visits Brutus in his tent to tell him they will meet
                            again at Philippi as an omen of Brutus' impending death. The figure of
                            Brutus at left sits on a low chair in front of a table. He holds an open
                            book with his bent right arm, which rests on the table. His left arm is
                            raised at 135 degrees; he points to the left with his left index finger.
                            His upper body faces away but he turns his head and lower body to face
                            right, with his left leg extended and right leg bent beside the chair.
                            He wears a shirt, tights or pants(?), and sandals. His mouth is open (he
                            may be speaking) and his short curly hair appears to stand on
                            end.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candle holder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>candlestick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure at left, Brutus, sits on a low chair, which is set
                            atop a low rectangular plinth or platform. A table is visible in front
                            of him on which two lit candles in candlesticks sit. Brutus hold an open
                            book, which rests on the table. Near the left margin, the spine of a
                            second book is visible below the serpentine flourish of a
                            scroll(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two additional tiny forms, possibly human figures, appear in
                            the space between the main figures' feet lower right. Although the
                            details of these are indistinguishable, the figure at right who may face
                            left wears a dark gown and a large hat/headdress and perhaps holds a
                            linear object in its left hand. The figure at left who may face right
                            wears a lighter gown. Alternatively, the figure at right could be the
                            shadow of the figure at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two additional tiny forms, possibly human figures, appear in
                            the space between the main figures' feet lower right. Although the
                            details of these are indistinguishable, the figure at left who may face
                            right wears a light-colored gown and perhaps also a hat.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two additional tiny figures appear in the space between the
                            main figures' feet lower right. The figure at right could be the shadow
                            of the figure at left, as suggested by its dark form.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Dark pockets of shadow appear throughout the lower left
                            quadrant.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.04.01" justify="left" indent="43">inv</l>
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.04.02" justify="left" indent="43">WB 1806</l>
                    <note>Butlin 547.4 records additional inscriptions, but we have not been able to
                        locate these on the work as it presently exists.</note>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but547.1.wc.05" dbi="BUT547.1.5.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Hamlet and His Father's Ghost</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U5">(Butlin 547.5)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>21.5 x 15.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Two figures, one standing at left and one kneeling at right, face
                        each other in a barren, cloudy landscape. This scene represents the
                        encounter in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi>, Act 1, Scene 5, of
                        Hamlet with the Ghost of his father, the previous king of Denmark, who
                        describes his murder at the hands of Claudius, Hamlet's uncle and new king,
                        and demands that Hamlet avenge the killing. Hamlet, the figure at right,
                        kneels facing left with head up to look at the Ghost. His mouth is open in
                        surprise or fear and his short hair is standing on end. He wears a shirt,
                        breeches or tights, shoes, and a fur-lined cloak. His sword is visible by
                        his left hip. He bends both arms and his hands are raised with palms facing
                        out and left. He bends forward slightly. The Ghost of his father stands
                        facing forward and right with head down at left. He bends slightly to the
                        right. He wears a full suit of armor and a helmet. His eyes are opened
                        widely, and he has a mustache and long beard. His arms are straight and by
                        his sides with fingers extended downward. Blue beams of light, or perhaps
                        fire, emerge from his feet or the ground on which he stands. These, coupled
                        with the barren landscape, may represent the daily existence of the Ghost,
                        which he describes: "I am thy father's spirit/ Doomed for a certain term to
                        walk the night/ And for the day confined to fast in fires/ Till the foul
                        crimes done in my days of nature/ Are burnt and purged away" (14-18).
                        Indeed, the darkness of the background sky and clouds, parted only slightly
                        to make the moon visible at right, suggest the time in night.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fur</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Hamlet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures, one standing at left and one kneeling at right,
                            face each other in a barren, cloudy landscape. This scene represents the
                            encounter in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi>, Act 1, Scene
                            5, of Hamlet with the Ghost of his father, the previous king of Denmark,
                            who describes his murder at the hands of Claudius, Hamlet's uncle and
                            new king, and demands that Hamlet avenge the killing. Hamlet, the figure
                            at right, kneels facing left with head up to look at the Ghost. His
                            mouth is open in surprise or fear and his short hair is standing on end.
                            He wears a shirt, breeches or tights, shoes, and a fur-lined cloak. His
                            sword is visible by his left hip. He bends both arms and his hands are
                            raised with palms facing out and left. He bends forward
                            slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scabbard</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A sword in its scabbard is visible pointing down and to the
                            right beside the left hip of the kneeling figure at right,
                            Hamlet.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures, one standing at left and one kneeling at right,
                            face each other in a barren, cloudy landscape. This scene represents the
                            encounter in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi>, Act 1, Scene
                            5, of Hamlet with the Ghost of his father, the previous king of Denmark,
                            who describes his murder at the hands of Claudius, Hamlet's uncle and
                            new king, and demands that Hamlet avenge the killing. The Ghost of his
                            father stands facing forward and right with head down at left, perhaps
                            to look toward Hamlet at right. He bends slightly to the right. He wears
                            a full suit of armor and a helmet. His eyes are opened widely, and he
                            has a mustache and long beard. His arms are straight and by his sides
                            with fingers extended downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Blue beams of light, or perhaps fire, emerge from the feet of
                            the figure at left, the Ghost of Hamlet's father, or the ground on which
                            he stands. These, coupled with the barren landscape, may represent the
                            daily existence of the Ghost, which he describes: "I am thy father's
                            spirit/ Doomed for a certain term to walk the night/ And for the day
                            confined to fast in fires/ Till the foul crimes done in my days of
                            nature/ Are burnt and purged away" (Act 1, Scene 5,
                            14-18).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>barren</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures, one standing at left and one kneeling at right,
                            face each other in a barren, cloudy landscape.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The darkness of the background sky and clouds, parted only
                            slightly to make the moon visible at right, suggest the time is night.
                            This corresponds to the Ghost's explanation that he is "doomed for a
                            certain term to walk the night" (Act 1, Scene 5, 15).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.05.01" justify="left" indent="2">inv</l>
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.05.02" justify="left" indent="2">WB 1806</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but547.1.wc.06" dbi="BUT547.1.6.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">As If An Angel Dropped Down From The Clouds</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U6">(Butlin 547.6)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>23.1 x 17.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A nude female figure reclines while reading on a cloud above a
                        nude male figure who faces down while hovering in midair. He raises his arms
                        vertically and holds a length of rope in his right hand. Directly below the
                        male figure, a horse rears its front legs while its back legs stand on a
                        portion of rock or cliff visible lower right. Beams of light extend outward
                        from a sun in the lower left corner. This scene illustrates Shakespeare's
                        simile in Act 4, Scene 1 of <hi rend="i">Henry IV, Part I</hi>, in which
                        Vernon describes the young Prince Henry (Harry) before battle: "I saw young
                        Harry with his beaver on,/ His cuisses on this thighs, gallantly armed,/
                        Rise from the ground like feathered Mercury/ And vaulted with such ease into
                        his seat/ As if an angel [dropped] down from the clouds,/ To turn and wind a
                        fiery Pegasus/ And witch the world with noble horsemanship." (110-116). Thus
                        the central figure represents this angel and the horse,
                        Pegasus.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A nude female figure reclines while reading on a cloud above a
                            nude male figure who faces down while hovering in midair above a rearing
                            horse. Lying on her right side facing forward, she crosses her left leg
                            over her right and bends both arms in front of her chest where they rest
                            on the open book in front of her. She has long hair and turns her head
                            down, perhaps to look toward the male figure and horse below or at her
                            book.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A nude female figure reclines on a cloud while reading (and
                            resting her arms on) an open book.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A nude female figure reclines on a cloud in the upper middle
                            of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the illustration, a nude male figure who
                            faces down while hovering or flying in midair looks toward the horse
                            rearing beneath him. He has short hair and extends both legs, which are
                            spread, backward, with his lower body twisted to face forward. His
                            genitals are prominent. He raises his arms vertically and holds a length
                            of rope in his right hand. The image literally illustrates a simile in
                            Act 4, Scene 1 of Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">Henry IV, Part I</hi>, in
                            which Vernon describes the young Prince Henry (Harry) before battle: "I
                            saw young Harry with his beaver on,/ His cuisses on this thighs,
                            gallantly armed,/ Rise from the ground like feathered Mercury/ And
                            vaulted with such ease into his seat/ As if an angel [dropped] down from
                            the clouds,/ To turn and wind a fiery Pegasus/ And witch the world with
                            noble horsemanship." (110-116). Thus the male figure represents this
                            angel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>rope</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The nude male figure in this image holds a length of rope in
                            his right hand that forms a circle beneath his extended body. It is
                            likely the tool Prince Henry would use in the illustrated simile in
                            order "To turn and wind a fiery Pegasus" in Act 4, Scene 1 of
                            Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">Henry IV, Part I</hi> (115).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mane</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rearing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Pegasus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower half of the image, a horse rears its extended
                            front legs while its back legs stand on a portion of rock or land
                            visible lower right. Although the horse faces left, its head is raised
                            to look up. Its mane and tail flow animatedly. The animal is likely the
                            "fiery Pegasus" mentioned in the simile in Act 4, Scene 1 of
                            Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">Henry IV, Part I</hi> (115).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An outcropping of stone or a rocky cliff on which the rear
                            legs of the horse balance is visible in the lower right corner of the
                            scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A circular sun is visible in the lower left corner of the
                            illustration.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The sun visible in the lower left corner radiates beams of
                            light across the lower two thirds of the composition, in which the
                            coloring of the background sky suggests sunrise or
                            sunset.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but547.1.penandink.06.01" justify="left" indent="46">WBlake 1809</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
