<bad id="but548.1" type="wc" work="The Vision of Queen Katharine, 1807" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="butlin" catid="548">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Vision of Queen Katharine, 1807">
                    <main>The Vision of Queen Katharine, 1807</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of Blake’s water color illustrations to the plays of William
                Shakespeare. <lb/>
                <lb/> Although less extensive and well known than his illustrations of John Milton’s
                poems, Blake’s water colors based on Shakespeare’s plays constitute a significant
                group of designs. The earliest, dating from c. 1779, is probably one of Blake’s
                illustrations of English history but nonetheless evokes Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i"
                    >King Lear</hi>. The series of seven small ovals picturing characters from the
                plays also dates from Blake’s early years. The concentrated focus on just one or two
                figures filling most of the pictorial space may be Blake’s response to popular
                interest in miniature portraiture. The reason for his execution of this group is not
                known; like the English history designs, they may have been intended for eventual
                publication as engravings. The series of Shakespeare character portraits by John
                Hamilton Mortimer, published as engravings in the mid-1770s, may have influenced
                Blake’s similar project. <lb/>
                <lb/>
                <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> is one of Blake’s
                largest water colors of the 1780s. Its size and quality suggest that it may have
                been intended for exhibition, like the water colors illustrating the life of Joseph
                displayed at the Royal Academy in 1785. The circle of dancers and Puck’s stance with
                arms raised echo similar motifs in George Romney’s <hi rend="i">Leveson-Gower
                    Family</hi>, painted in 1776-77 and published as a mezzotint by John Raphael
                Smith in 1781. <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake was clearly attracted to the vision of Queen Katherine in <hi rend="i"
                    >Henry VIII</hi>, act 4, scene 2, for he executed four versions beginning c.
                1783-90 and concluding with the highly finished and complex water color of c.
                1825-26. Blake’s water color of Queen Katherine’s dream dated 1809 is part of a
                series of six illustrations to Shakespeare’s plays commissioned by Joseph Thomas,
                the clergyman who had earlier employed Blake to illustrate Milton’s <hi rend="i"
                    >Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. In a letter of 31 July 1801 to
                William Hayley, John Flaxman added a postscript to Blake, including the following:
                “he [Thomas] also desired you [Blake] will make two designs in bister or Indian Ink,
                from Shakespeare’s Troylus &amp; Cressida, Coriolanus, either of the 3 plays of
                Henry 6.<sup>th</sup> Richard the 3.<sup>d</sup> or Henry the 8.<sup>th</sup> each
                design for one play for which he will give a Guinea each, the dimensions as follow
                the paper. an upright square of 12 Inches &amp; half by 8 Inches, within this Space
                leaving a moderate margin, the principal figure not exceeding 6 Inches high” (Butlin
                547). Blake’s designs (most now trimmed) roughly follow these size requirements,
                necessitated by Thomas’s desire to create an extra-illustrated copy of the 1632
                second folio of Shakespeare’s plays, but Blake waited eight years before completing
                the commission, changed the medium from monochrome drawings to water colors, and
                illustrated only two plays, <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi> and <hi rend="i">Henry
                    VIII</hi>, specified by Flaxman. Blake may have chosen the other passages for
                illustration, at some point convincing Thomas of their appropriateness. <lb/>
                <lb/> Many of Blake’s Shakespeare designs show his predilection for scenes dealing
                with perceptions that extend beyond the world of the physical senses. The four
                versions of Queen Katherine’s dream epitomize this lifelong interest in imaginative
                and visionary experiences. A corollary is Blake’s attraction to representations of
                the arts, demonstrated by <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies
                    Dancing</hi> and his portrayal of Pegasus, the classical embodiment of poetic
                inspiration, in <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi> among
                the designs for Thomas. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. <lb/>
                <lb/> Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, editors <lb/> Joseph
                Fletcher, managing editor, Michael Fox, assistant editor<lb/>  The William Blake
                Archive<lb/>
            </updatestmt>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 Fitzwilliam Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February - March 2020</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies,</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Dan Gorman</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose</name>
                    <name>Jake Ruta</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>February 2016</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2005</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Conversion: </resp>
                    <name>Aziza Technology Associates</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>The Vision of Queen Katharine</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1807">1807<note>The date is inscribed on the work lower left; see
                        the Textual Transcription.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>40.1 x 31.3 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>40.1 x 31.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color over pencil<note>The inscription, lower left, is
                        in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1911</date>
                <dealer>Christie's</dealer>
                <price>&#163;52.10s.</price>
                <note>Thomas Butts; by inheritance to Thomas Butts, Jr., in 1845; sold Sotheby's, 26
                    March 1852, lot 166 (&#163;9 to Charles Wentworth Dilke); his son, Charles
                    Wentworth Dilke, 2nd, by inheritance in 1869; sold Christie's, 10 April 1911,
                    lot 127 (&#163;52.10s. to Sidney Cockerell acting for the Friends of the
                    Fitzwilliam Museum); accessioned by the Fitzwilliam Museum in 1911.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline>
                <addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)1223 332900</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)1223 332923</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/index.html</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints:
                    fitzmuseum-pdp@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints:
                    http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/pdp</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 332927</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 768591</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Image Library:
                    fitzmuseum-photography@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Photographic Service:
                    http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/photography</addressline>
                <department>Paintings, Drawings, and Prints</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1911-712</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but548.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT548.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Vision of Queen Katharine</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U3">(Butlin 548)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>40.1 x 31.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Three large figures, two female and one male, and at least
                        twenty-five smaller figures occupy the space of the composition, which
                        represents The Vision of Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of Shakespeare's
                        play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. The central female figure of Queen
                        Katharine reclines on a bed or couch with legs together at left but with her
                        torso raised and facing forward. She has long hair and wears a gown and veil
                        along with a crown. Both arms are bent and raised just above the horizontal
                        with palms facing up. Her head and eyes are also raised, perhaps to better
                        see the visionary activity above her. Queen Katharine is the wife of King
                        Henry VIII who wishes to divorce her (as she has not born a male heir) and
                        marry Anne Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it is during her sickness in
                        which The Vision occurs. The bed or couch on which she sits has arms on both
                        sides and is covered in what appears to be a patterned fabric decorated with
                        Gothic arches and other motifs. A pillow is visible at right and drapery or
                        sheets cover the seat and closest edge of the piece of furniture. In front
                        of the bed in both lower corners of the composition, the other two large
                        figures sit facing each other on straight-backed chairs. Both have their
                        eyes closed and appear to sleep with their heads supported on one bent arm.
                        The figure in the right corner is a gowned female with long, curly hair who
                        rests her elbow on a soft object of some sort (perhaps a pillow?) on the
                        table at her right. This is probably Patience, a servant to the queen. The
                        male figure at left has white hair and a long beard; he is also gowned. This
                        is probably Griffith, the queen's usher. He rests his elbow on a similar
                        table behind him and turns his head to face forward. In his right hand,
                        which is by his side, he holds a scroll and pen or quill. The floor between
                        these two figures is decorated with hexagons and quatrefoils. The
                        twenty-five other smaller figures in the scene fly around the seated figure
                        of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these figures form a
                        semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's body in the lower
                        half of the image. They fly atop a plume of wispy clouds. Just above the
                        center of the lower margin, the lowest of these figures faces right and
                        appears to stand on tiptoe on the floor. She is gowned and female with short
                        (or perhaps coiffed) hair and a crown. Her left leg is bent and her right is
                        extended backward. With her right hand, she holds (and perhaps plays) a lyre
                        and with her left arm, which is extended, she holds the hand of the figure
                        above her at right, who flies upward and faces away and to the right. This
                        figure is also a gowned female who holds a trumpet or horn in her raised
                        right hand. Above and to the right of this figure, a third crowned and
                        gowned female figure flies facing forward and slightly right as an infant or
                        putto flies beside her at left facing away. The female figure plays a harp
                        with both hands. Above and to the left of this pair, a second pair of
                        figures flies upward and to the left. Both figures appear young, perhaps
                        children. The lower figure at right, whose gender is indeterminate, raises
                        one arm upward; the higher figure, who faces forward, has long hair and is
                        likely female. Immediately to the left of this figure, the seventh figure in
                        this group, who has coiffed hair, a crown, and a gown, faces away but bends
                        to the left with arms extended and spread. In her raised right hand, she
                        holds a serpentine object (perhaps a horn or shell?) and with her lowered
                        left, the right side of a laurel crown. Together with another figure at left
                        who holds the other side of the crown, she may be preparing to crown Queen
                        Katharine below. This moment is referenced directly in the play's text: "the
                        first two [Personages] hold a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene 2).
                        A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen Katharine
                        forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle of clouds.
                        The first of these figures near the lower right portion of the circle flies
                        right and extends her left arm to hold the other side of the laurel crown
                        over the head of Queen Katharine. In her right hand, she holds and perhaps
                        plays a lyre. She wears a crown and a gown and her long hair streams behind
                        her at left. Directly below her right arm, a small nude infant or putto
                        faces away and flies up and to the right. Directly above this pair at right,
                        two small figures who wear gowns and face forward and left fly upward with
                        arms raised overhead. A fifth figure flies to the left directly above this
                        pair, and she wears a long gown and extends her left arm to hold a lyre and
                        perhaps touch the right arm of the figure flying at her left whose body is
                        also horizontally and turns to look back toward her companion. She also
                        wears a gown, crown, and has long hair. Below the extended left arm of this
                        figure, a seventh figure whose body is twisted faces and flies downward.
                        With both arms bent and raised, she plays two trumpets or horns. Directly
                        below this figure, the final figure in this circle flies to the right with
                        her left arm raised horizontally and her right extended upward near the
                        above figure. She wears a gown and has long hair. She holds round object,
                        possibly flowers. Above the two figures holding the laurel crown above Queen
                        Katharine, a vertical line of three figures fly upward. The two lower
                        figures face forward and turn their head to look up. The closer figure holds
                        a harp, which she appears to play with her left hand, and the further figure
                        turns her head slightly to the right. A third figure above this pair faces
                        forward and leans to the left. She wears a gown and has long hair. In her
                        right arm she holds a lute; she raised her left arm vertically, palm facing
                        up and forward. Directly above this figure two gowned figures who face away
                        and lean to the left wear gowns and fly upward. Both extend their arms
                        vertically and hold (and play) large tambourines. Between the heads of this
                        pair, the left leg and foot of an otherwise unseen figure is visible against
                        the upper margin. A final group of five figures forms a circle in the upper
                        left portion of the composition. Directly below and left of the lowest
                        tambourine player at top, a gowned female figure flies to the left with her
                        body horizontal and arms extended horizontally. She wears a crown above her
                        long hair. In her left hand she holds a lyre and with her right, she appears
                        to reach for two round objects (possibly flowers, like those associated with
                        figures below) in the encircling clouds. Forming the left side of the
                        circle, a gowned female figure flies upside down with her body twisted to
                        the right. Both of her arms are raised overhead to hold or take flowers or
                        fruit(?) from the basket carried on the head of the gowned female figure to
                        her right who also flies to the right and wears a gown. This figure holds
                        her basket with both arms bent overhead. To her right, the fourth figure
                        flies right, facing away, with arms extended horizontally. She too appears
                        to hold small objects, perhaps fruit or flowers, in both hands. Below her
                        right arm, the final figure in the scene, a small infant or putto, flies up
                        while facing away with arms extended. Two piers or pillars against the
                        margins support (what is likely) a pointed Gothic arch partially visible in
                        the background of the upper half of the scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Katharine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three large figures and at least twenty-five smaller figures
                            occupy the space of the composition, which represents The Vision of
                            Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i"
                                >Henry VIII</hi>. The central female figure of Queen Katharine
                            reclines or sits on a bed or couch with legs together (and right leg
                            bent) at left but with her torso raised and facing forward. She has long
                            hair and wears a gown and veil along with a crown. Both arms are bent
                            and raised just above the horizontal with palms facing up. Her head and
                            eyes are also raised, perhaps to better see the visionary activity above
                            her. Her mouth is slightly open. Queen Katharine is the wife of King
                            Henry VIII who wishes to divorce her (as she has not born a male heir)
                            and marry Anne Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it is during her
                            sickness in which The Vision occurs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>niche</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bed or couch on which Queen Katharine, the central figure,
                            sits large arms on either side. Its fabric is patterned with Gothic
                            arches that resemble the arch in the upper part of the scene. The arches
                            above the queen's legs form niches containing the outlines of standing
                            human figures, facing forward. Scroll-like patterns are above these
                            niches. A pillow is visible at right and drapery or sheets cover the
                            seat and fall over the front edge of the furniture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The arches above the queen's legs on the decorated cloth
                            covering her couch form niches containing pictures of standing human
                            figures, facing forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Patience</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three large figures and at least twenty-five smaller figures
                            occupy the space of this composition, which represents The Vision of
                            Queen Katharine in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. In
                            front of the bed in both lower corners, the other two large figures sit
                            facing each other on straight-backed chairs. Both have their eyes closed
                            and appear to sleep with their heads supported on one bent arm. The
                            figure in the right corner is a gowned female with long, curly hair who
                            rests her right elbow on a soft object of some sort (perhaps a pillow?)
                            on the table at her right and leans her head on her hand. This is
                            probably Patience, a servant to the queen. Her left arm is at her side
                            with her left hand resting in her lap near her knee. Her legs are bent,
                            and her left foot is visible beneath her gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner, a gowned female figure sits in a
                            straight-backed chair facing left and rests her right elbow on a soft
                            object of some sort (perhaps a pillow?) on a table at her right. The
                            back of the chair includes Gothic arches.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Griffith</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three large figures and at least twenty-five smaller figures
                            occupy the space of this composition, which represents The Vision of
                            Queen Katharine in Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. In
                            front of the bed in both lower corners, the other two large figures sit
                            facing each other on straight-backed chairs. Both have their eyes closed
                            and appear to sleep with their heads supported on one bent arm. The male
                            figure at left has white hair and a long beard; he is also gowned. This
                            is probably Griffith, the queen's usher. He rests his elbow on a table
                            behind him and rests his head on his left hand with his head turned to
                            face forward. In his right hand, which is by his side, he holds a scroll
                            and pen or quill. Both legs are bent, and his right is extended with his
                            shoe-clad foot visible beneath his gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner, a gowned male figure sits in a
                            straight-backed chair facing right and rests his right elbow on a table
                            at his left. In his right hand he holds a scroll and a quill or pen by
                            his side. The back of the chair includes Gothic arches.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>marble</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The (stone or marble?) floor between the two large figures in
                            the bottom half of the composition is decorated with hexagons and
                            quatrefoils.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Just above the center of the lower margin, the first figure
                            faces right and appears to stand on tiptoe on the floor. She is gowned
                            and female with short (or perhaps coiffed) hair and a crown. Her left
                            leg is bent and her right is extended backward. With her right hand, she
                            holds (and perhaps plays) a harp or lyre and with her left arm, which is
                            extended, she holds the hand of the figure above her at right toward
                            whom she may also look with her head up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. The second figure right of center flies upward and to the right
                            with her legs together and extended backward. She has hair coiffed in a
                            bun and wears a gown. Her right arm is raised at 135 degrees and holds a
                            horn or trumpet; her left is at her side and with her left hand holds
                            the hand of the figure below her. She faces away but turns her head up
                            and to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Directly right of Queen Katharine's left hand, a third gowned
                            female figure flies facing forward and slightly left as an infant or
                            putto flies beside her at left. The female figure wears a crown (perhaps
                            of laurels?) and plays a harp with both hands. Her legs are together
                            with knees slightly bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Directly right of Queen Katharine's left hand, a third gowned
                            female figure flies facing forward and slightly left as a nude infant or
                            putto flies beside her at left. The child faces away but turns to look
                            right and up, likely toward the female figure at right. Its hair is
                            short, its leg are bent, and both arms are raised
                            vertically.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Above the harp-playing figure near the right margin, a pair of
                            small figures fly up and to the left. The rightmost of these appears to
                            have small hair and wear a gown. The figure raises one arm vertically to
                            touch the shoulder of its companion at left</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Above the harp-playing figure near the right margin, a pair of
                            small figures fly up and to the left. The child at left faces forward
                            but turns her head to look right. She has long hair and wears a gown.
                            Her right arm is extended vertically and her left is at her side,
                            touching or holding the arm of the figure at her right. Her legs are
                            extended and together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-five smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. The seventh figure in this group flies or hovers above and
                            slightly right of Queen Katharine's head. She has coiffed hair, a crown,
                            and a gown, and she faces away but bends to the left with arms extended
                            and spread. In her raised right hand, she holds a serpentine object
                            (perhaps a horn or shell?) and with her lowered left, the right side of
                            a laurel crown. Together with another figure at left who holds the other
                            side of the crown, she may be preparing to crown Queen Katharine below.
                            This moment is referenced directly in the play's text: "the first two
                            [Personages] hold a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene
                            2).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The seven smaller figures who form a semi-circle around the
                            right side of Queen Katharine's body hold and/or play a variety of
                            objects and instruments. The lowest figure holds a lyre in her right
                            hand. The figure above her at right holds a trumpet or horn, and the
                            rightmost figure above her holds and plays a harp. The highest figure in
                            this group holds a serpentine object (perhaps a horn or shell?) in her
                            raised right hand and a laurel crown in her lowered left
                            hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The seven small figures who form a semi-circle around the
                            right side of Queen Katharine's body fly atop a single plume of clouds
                            that appears to rise from the ground below the lowest figure or,
                            alternatively, originate with this figure herself.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. The first of these figures near the lower right portion of
                            the circle flies right and extends her left arm to hold the other side
                            of the laurel crown over the head of Queen Katharine. This moment is
                            referenced directly in the play's text: "the first two [Personages] hold
                            a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene 2). In the figure's right
                            hand, she holds and perhaps plays a harp or lyre. She wears a crown and
                            a gown and her long hair streams behind her at left. Her right leg is
                            bent and extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Directly below the right arm of the first figure, a small
                            nude infant or putto faces away and flies up and to the right. He has
                            short, curly hair and extends both arms vertically. His legs are bent
                            and extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Directly above the first female figure holding the laurel
                            crown, two small figures with short hair who wear gowns fly upward with
                            arms raised overhead, hands together, and at least one leg extended. The
                            leftmost faces forward with an open mouth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Directly above the first female figure holding the laurel
                            crown, two small figures with short hair who wear gowns fly upward with
                            arms raised overhead, hands together, and at least one leg extended. The
                            figure at right twists to look left and bends his left
                            leg.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. The fifth figure with long hair flies to the left directly
                            above the pair of children, and she wears a long gown and extends her
                            left arm to hold a lyre or harp and perhaps touch the right arm of the
                            figure flying at her left toward whom she may also look.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. The sixth figure, at the top center of the circle, flies left
                            with her body horizontal but turns her head to look right, back toward
                            her companion at right. She wears a crown over her long hair and a long
                            gown. Both arms are extended horizontally; with her right arm she
                            touches or perhaps plays a harp or lyre held by the figure at her right
                            and with her left arm she appears to reach for small circular objects
                            that may be flower blossoms(?). Her legs are together and extended to
                            the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upside down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Forming the left upper curve of the circle, the seventh
                            figure, who is upside down, flies or hovers facing down with her body
                            bent to the right. Although her head is up, the rest of her body is seen
                            from behind. She has short hair and wears a gown. With both arms bent
                            and raised, she holds two horns or trumpets, which she plays. Her legs
                            are together and extended upward and to the right. The clouds to the
                            left of his figure looks fiery.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. The final figure flies or hovers to form the lower left bend
                            of the circle, where she flies to the right but faces forward. Her long
                            hair is styled in a ponytail, and she wears a gown. Her left arm is
                            raised horizontally in front of her, where she appears to reach for
                            three circular objects, perhaps blossoms(?). Her right arm is raised
                            vertically, and she holds two of the same round objects in her right
                            hand, which is directly beside the elbow of the figure above her. Her
                            legs are together and extended up and behind her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The eight smaller figures who form a complete circle above and
                            to the left of Queen Katharine hold and/or play a variety of objects and
                            instruments. The lowest figure at right holds a lyre in her right hand
                            and, in her left hand, a laurel crown, also held by the figure at her
                            right. The fourth figure near the upper right bend in the circle holds a
                            lyre, while the seventh figure on the upper left side holds and plays
                            two horns or trumpets.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two of the eight smaller figures who form a complete circle
                            above and to the left of Queen Katharine may hold and/or reach for small
                            circular objects that resemble flower blossoms. The top central figure
                            may reach for them with her extended right arm, and the figure lower
                            left may reach for these with her left arm and hold two blossoms in her
                            right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The eight smaller figures who form a complete circle above and
                            to the left of Queen Katharine fly atop a ring of clouds that connects
                            with the larger plume of clouds on the right side of the picture. The
                            area of clouds left of the leftmost figure in the circle appears to be
                            fiery.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Directly above the two figures holding the laurel crown above
                            Queen Katharine, a vertical line of three figures fly upward. The two
                            lower figures, who are very close together, face forward and turn their
                            heads up. The closer figure, who wears a gown and may have long hair,
                            holds a harp or lyre, which she appears to play with her left hand. She
                            turns her head to look left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Directly above the two figures holding the laurel crown above
                            Queen Katharine, a vertical line of three figures fly upward. The two
                            lower figures, who are very close together, face forward and turn their
                            heads up. The figure further away in the pair may have long hair and may
                            wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Directly above the two figures holding the laurel crown above
                            Queen Katharine, a vertical line of three figures fly upward. The third
                            figure and highest figure in this trio faces forward and leans to the
                            left. She wears a gown and has long hair. In her right arm she holds a
                            lute, which she may play. She raises her left arm at 135 degrees, palm
                            facing up and forward. She turns her head to look slightly left and her
                            mouth may be open. Her legs are extended downward and
                            together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>harp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lute</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures in the vertical trio of figures flying or hovering
                            between and to the right of the two circular groups of figures hold
                            instruments. The lowest and closest figure holds a harp that she appears
                            to play with her left hand and the highest figure holds a lute in her
                            bent left arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vertical line of three figures who fly upward near the
                            right side of the composition fly atop clouds that extend from the
                            larger plume of clouds originating in the lower center of the
                            picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tambourine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Just below the upper margin of the design on the right, two
                            gowned figures with long hair who face away and bend left wear gowns and
                            fly upward or hover. Both extend their arms vertically and hold (and
                            play) large tambourines. The rightmost figure appears to bend her right
                            leg; both legs are extended backward. A cloud is visible beneath
                            her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cloud is visible beneath the figure flying or hovering
                            closest to the top right corner of the composition. This cloud connects
                            with the larger plume of clouds extending upward from the lower center
                            of the picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Just below the upper margin of the design on the right, two
                            gowned figures with long hair who face away and bend left wear gowns and
                            fly upward or hover. Both extend their arms vertically and hold (and
                            play) large tambourines. The figure at left turns to head to face left
                            and points left with her right hand. Her legs are together and extended
                            below her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between the heads of the two figures just below the upper
                            margin who fly upward is a single leg and foot extending from the margin
                            that likely signifies the presence of another figure above these two
                            that echoes their left-leaning posture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of five smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. Directly below and left of the
                            lowest tambourine player at top, a female figure flies to the left or
                            hovers facing forward with her body horizontal and arms extended
                            horizontally. She wears a crown above her long hair and a gown that
                            exposes her breasts. In her left hand she holds a lyre, which she may
                            play, and with her right, she appears to reach with fingers spread for
                            two round objects (perhaps flower blossoms?) in the encircling clouds.
                            She turns her head to look left and her mouth is open. Her left leg is
                            extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upside down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of five smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. Forming the left side of the
                            circle, the second female figure flies or hovers upside down but facing
                            forward with her body bent to the right. She has long hair worn in a
                            ponytail and wears a gown but with breasts exposed. Both of her arms are
                            bent and raised overhead to hold or take fruits or blossoms(?) from the
                            basket carried on the head of the figure to her right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of five smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. The third figure who flies right
                            or hovers at the bottom edge of the circle holds a basket full of fruit
                            or flowers(?) atop her head with both arms bent upward. She faces
                            forward but turns her head slightly left, perhaps to look toward the
                            figure flying to her left. She has short hair and wears a gown that
                            exposes her breasts. Her body is horizontal and her legs are together
                            and extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of five smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. The fourth figure flies right or
                            hovers near the lower right bend in the circle and faces away. She has
                            long hair and wears a gown. Her arms are raised horizontally, and in
                            each hand she appears to hold circular objects, perhaps fruit or
                            blossoms(?) from the basket of the figure at her left. Her body is
                            horizontal, though her torso is bent up and left. She extends her legs,
                            which are together, to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of five smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. Below the right arm of the fourth
                            figure, the final figure in the scene, a small nude infant or putto,
                            flies right or hovers while facing away with arms raised horizontally,
                            perhaps holding a circular object (perhaps a fruit or blossom(?) similar
                            to those held by other members of the group) in its right hand. The
                            figure has short hair and turns its head left, perhaps to look toward
                            the female figure at left. Its right leg is bent back at the knee, but
                            both legs are extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>harp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wicker</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two of the five smaller figures who form a circle in the upper
                            left portion of the composition carry or hold objects: the highest
                            figure holds, and likely plays, a harp or lyre with her left hand, and
                            the third figure in the lower left bend of the circle holds a (wicker?)
                            basket on top of her head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four of the five smaller figures who form a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition appear to hold or reach for small
                            circular objects that may be fruits or flower blossoms from the fourth
                            figure's basket: the top figure reaches for two blossoms with her
                            extended right hand; the second, upside-down figure reaches or holds
                            these with both hands; the third figure holds the basket containing most
                            of these fruits or blossoms; the fourth figure holds one object in each
                            of her extended arms; and the last figure, an infant or putto, may hold
                            one such object in his horizontally raised right hand. Three of the
                            flowers in the basket may be lilies.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The final group of five smaller figures who form a circle in
                            the upper left portion of the composition fly or hover atop a ring of
                            clouds that connects with the larger plume of clouds on the right side
                            of the picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>pier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two piers or pillars against the margins support (what is
                            likely) a pointed, Gothic arch partially visible in the background of
                            the upper half of the scene. The two capitals are decorated but not in a
                            specific architectural order.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but548.1.penandink.01.01" justify="left" indent="3">WB.inv 1807</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
