<bad id="but549.1" type="wc" work="The Vision of Queen Katharine" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="549">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Vision of Queen Katharine">
                    <main>The Vision of Queen Katharine</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>

            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>April-May 2014</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2012</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                    <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                    <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Bihan Zhang</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>*The Vision of Queen Katharine*</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1825">c. 1825-26<note>This is one of two water colors commissioned
                        by Sir Thomas Lawrence near the end of Blake's life (see the Note on
                        Provenance). The other water color commissioned by Lawrence is *The Wise and Foolish Virgins*, Butlin 481. According to Alexander
                        Gilchrist, *Life of William Blake* (London and Cambridge:
                        Macmillan and Co., 1863) 1:357, these were among "the last drawings
                        executed, or at least finished by Blake. ...Sir Thomas gave fifteen guineas
                        apiece for these designs of Blake's."</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>41.0 x 34.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>41.1 x 34.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>water color, Chinese white, and shell gold<note>The inscription, lower
                        right, is scratched into the water color.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Commissioned from Blake by Thomas Lawrence c. 1825-26 for &#163;15.15s. (see
                    the Note on Composition Date, above); sold from Lawrence's collection,
                    Christie's, 21 May 1830, lot 235 (&#163;4.6s. to "Kennedy," probably a dealer);
                    John Clark Strange by 1863; Edward Burnett Tylor; his niece, Mrs. Sydney Morse,
                    probably by inheritance in 1917; sold Christie's, 26 July 1929, lot 16
                    (&#163;1942.10s. to the dealer P. &#38; D. Colnaghi); sold 18 March 1930 to
                    Lessing J. Rosenwald; given by Rosenwald to the National Gallery of Art,
                    Washington, D. C., in 1943.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <addressline>Constitution Avenue NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline>
                <addressline>Washington, DC 20565</addressline>
                <addressline>USA</addressline>
                <addressline>Mailing Address: 2000B South Club Drive, Landover, Maryland
                    20785</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-202-737-4215</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Print Study Rooms: 1-202-842-6380</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 1-202-842-6126</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Visual Services:
                    http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.3.9129</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but549.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT549.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Vision of Queen Katharine</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U3">(Butlin 549.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The verso is inscribed by John Clark Strange, "Bought at the T Lawrence Sale
                        Lot 137 5/5/0 JCS." This note is wrong about the lot number in the Thomas
                        Lawrence sale in 1830 (see the Note on Provenance). Butlin 549 comments that
                        "the increase in the price ... suggests that [the dealer] Kennedy may have
                        bought [the work] on his own account, not on commission for Strange, who
                        otherwise does not seem to have been active as a purchaser of Blakes until
                        1853." This work is a more highly-finished replica, with several variations,
                        of Butlin 548, <hi rend="i">The Vision of Queen Katharine</hi>, in the
                        Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>41.0 x 34.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Three large figures, two female and one male, and at least
                        twenty-six smaller figures occupy the space of the composition, which
                        represents The Vision of Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of Shakespeare's
                        play <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>. The central female figure of Queen
                        Katharine reclines on a bed or couch with legs together at left but with her
                        torso raised and facing forward. She has long hair and wears a gown and
                        veil. Both arms are bent and raised just above the horizontal with palms
                        facing up. Her head and eyes are also raised, perhaps to better see the
                        visionary activity above her. Queen Katharine is the wife of King Henry VIII
                        who wishes to divorce her (as she has not born a male heir) and marry Anne
                        Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it is during her sickness in which The
                        Vision occurs. The bed or couch on which she sits has arms on both sides and
                        is covered in what appears to be a patterned fabric decorated with Gothic
                        arches forming niches with human figures vaguely suggested within them. A
                        pillow is partially visible at right and drapery or sheets cover the seat
                        and closest edge of the piece of furniture. In front of the bed in both
                        lower corners of the composition, the other two large figures sit facing
                        each other on straight-backed chairs that are embellished with patterns
                        similar to the bed or couch. Both figures have their eyes closed and appear
                        to sleep with their heads supported on one bent arm. The figure in the right
                        corner is a gowned female with long hair who rests her elbow on a soft
                        object of some sort (perhaps a pillow?) on the table at her right. This is
                        probably Patience, a servant to the queen. The male figure at left has white
                        hair and a long beard; he is also gowned. This is probably Griffith, the
                        queen's usher. He rests his elbow on a similar table behind him and turns
                        his head to face forward. In his right hand, which is by his side, he holds
                        a scroll and pen or quill. The floor, which may be a carpet or rug, between
                        these two figures is decorated with arch-like patterns evocative of Gothic
                        art similar to that of the couch or bed as well as the chairs on either
                        side. The twenty-six other smaller figures in the scene fly around the
                        seated figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                        figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's body
                        in the lower half of the image. They fly atop a plume of wispy clouds. Just
                        above the center of the lower margin, the lowest of these figures faces
                        forward and right and appears to stand on tiptoe on the floor or hover just
                        above it. She is gowned and female with short (or perhaps coiffed) hair. Her
                        left leg is bent and her right is extended backward. With her right hand,
                        she holds (and perhaps plays) a lyre and with her left arm, which is
                        extended, she holds the hand of the figure above her at right, who flies
                        upward and faces away and to the right. This figure is also a gowned female
                        who holds a trumpet or horn in her raised right hand. Above and to the right
                        of this figure, a third gowned female figure, who has a circle of light
                        around her head and may wear a crown or garland, flies facing forward and
                        slightly right as an infant or putto flies beside her at left facing away.
                        The female figure plays a harp with both hands. Above and to the left of
                        this pair, a second pair of figures flies upward and to the left. The figure
                        at right is a gowned female figure who faces away and turns her head to the
                        left. She raises both arms vertically and holds one or more circular objects
                        in her hand (perhaps flower blossoms?). The lower figure at right, who has
                        long hair and thus may be a female(?) child, raises one arm upward and may
                        hold a similar round object. Immediately to the left of this figure, the
                        seventh figure in this group, who has coiffed hair, a crown/garland, and a
                        gown, faces away but bends to the left with arms extended and spread. In her
                        raised right hand, she holds a serpentine object (perhaps a horn or shell?)
                        and with her lowered left, the right side of a garland or crown. Together
                        with another figure at left who holds the other side of the crown, she may
                        be preparing to crown Queen Katharine below. This moment is referenced
                        directly in the play's text: "the first two [Personages] hold a spare
                        garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene 2). A second group of small figures
                        above and to the left of Queen Katharine forms a complete circle of eight
                        figures who fly atop a circle of clouds. The first of these figures near the
                        lower right portion of the circle flies right and extends her left arm to
                        hold the other side of the laurel crown over the head of Queen Katharine. In
                        her right hand, she holds and perhaps plays a lyre. She wears a crown and a
                        gown that exposes her breasts and her long hair streams behind her at left.
                        Directly below her right arm, a small nude infant or putto faces away and
                        flies up and to the right. Directly above this pair at right, two small nude
                        figures face forward and fly upward with arms raised overhead and may hold
                        similar small round objects, perhaps blossoms(?). A fifth figure, whose body
                        is twisted to the left, flies to the left directly above this pair, and she
                        wears a long gown and extends both arms forward to hold and play a lyre. The
                        figure flying at her left wears a gown that exposes her breasts. Her body is
                        horizontal, and she faces forward but turns her head slightly right. Her
                        mouth may be open. She raises both arms horizontally and may wear a
                        necklace. Below the extended left arm of this figure, a seventh figure who
                        is upside down and twisted to the right flies downward and right. With both
                        arms bent and raised, she plays two trumpets or horns. Directly below this
                        figure, the final figure in this circle flies to the right with her left arm
                        raised horizontally and her right extended upward near the above figure. She
                        wears a gown and a crown or garland above short hair. Above the two figures
                        holding the laurel crown above Queen Katharine, a cluster of five figures
                        fly or hover at right. The two lower figures face forward and turn their
                        head to look up in opposite directions, and both hold harps or lyres. A
                        third figure above this pair faces forward and leans to the left. She wears
                        a gown and a crown over long hair. In her left arm she holds and plays a
                        lute; she raised her bent right arm at 135 degrees, perhaps to reach for one
                        of the small round objects floating to her left. To the right of this
                        figure, a gowned figure who bends forward and faces left holds a (wicker?)
                        basket atop her head with both arms. A second gowned figure flying above her
                        at left faces forward but bends left to reach into the basket with her right
                        arm. Her left arm is raised vertically. Above this cluster of figures at
                        left, two gowned figures who face away fly or hover near the upper margin of
                        the design. They bend sharply to the left and extend their arms vertically
                        and hold (and play) instruments, a lyre at right and a tambourine at left.
                        Above the heads of these figures, traces of the gowns of three additional
                        figures are visible emerging from the upper margin, suggesting additional
                        figures who have flown upward out of the scene. A final group of four
                        figures forms a circle in the upper left portion of the composition.
                        Directly below and left of the tambourine player at top, a gowned female
                        figure flies or hovers facing forward and left with both arms extended
                        horizontally, palms facing up. She has long hair and may wear a crown or
                        garland. Her mouth may be open. Forming the left side of the circle, a
                        gowned female figure who faces forward flies upside down with her body
                        twisted to the right. Both of her arm are raised overhead to hold or take
                        flowers(?) from the (wicker?) basket carried on the head of the gowned
                        female figure to her right who also flies to the right and wears a gown.
                        This figure holds her basket with both arms bent overhead and her mouth may
                        be open. To her right, the fourth figure flies right, facing away, with arms
                        extended horizontally. With her right hand, she appears to reach for or drop
                        small objects, perhaps fruit or blossoms(?). Visible against each side
                        margin near the top of the composition, two piers or pillars with vaguely
                        Corinthian capitals support (what is likely) a pointed arch, though the arch
                        itself is obscured. Beams of light extend outward from the upper middle of
                        the composition, often terminating in dark, spiky points that form
                        concentric bands, particularly on the left side of the
                        design.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Queen Katharine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three large figures and at least twenty-six smaller figures
                            occupy the space of the composition, which represents The Vision of
                            Queen Katharine in Act 4, Scene 2 of Shakespeare's play <hi rend="i"
                                >Henry VIII</hi>. The central female figure of Queen Katharine
                            reclines or sits on a bed or couch with legs together (and right leg
                            bent) at left but with her torso raised and facing forward. She has long
                            hair and wears a gown and veil. Both arms are bent and raised just above
                            the horizontal with palms facing up. Her head and eyes are also raised,
                            perhaps to better see the visionary activity above her. Queen Katharine
                            is the wife of King Henry VIII who wishes to divorce her (as she has not
                            born a male heir) and marry Anne Boleyn. Katharine becomes ill, and it
                            is during her sickness in which The Vision occurs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>niche</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bed or couch on which Queen Katharine, the central figure,
                            sits has large arms on either side. Its fabric is patterned with Gothic
                            arches that resemble the arch in the upper part of the scene. The arches
                            above the queen's legs and on the arms of the couch form niches
                            containing the outlines of standing human figures, facing forward. A
                            pillow is visible at right and drapery or sheets cover the seat and fall
                            over the front edge of the furniture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The arches above the queen's legs on the decorated cloth
                            covering her couch form niches containing pictures of standing human
                            figures, facing forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Patience</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of the bed in both lower corners of the composition,
                            the other two large figures sit facing each other on straight-backed
                            chairs. Both figures have their eyes closed and appear to sleep with
                            their heads supported on one bent arm. The figure in the right corner is
                            a gowned female with long hair who rests her right elbow on a pillow
                            with a tassel lower left on the table at her right, and she bends her
                            right arm upward to rest her head on her hand. This is probably
                            Patience, a servant to the queen. Her left arm is at her side with her
                            left hand near her knee. Her left foot on which she wears a shoe is
                            visible beneath the hem of her gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tassel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner, a gowned female figure sits in a
                            straight-backed chair that is embellished with arch-like patterns
                            evocative of Gothic art similar to the bed or couch. Facing left, she
                            rests her right elbow on a pillow with a tassel lower left on a table at
                            her right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Griffith</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>servant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In front of the bed in both lower corners of the composition,
                            the other two large figures sit facing each other on straight-backed
                            chairs. Both figures have their eyes closed and appear to sleep with
                            their heads supported on one bent arm. The male figure at left has white
                            hair, a mustache, and a long beard; he is also gowned. Bending forward,
                            he rests his left elbow on a table behind him and turns his head to face
                            forward with his head on his hand. This is probably Griffith, the
                            queen's usher. In his right hand, which is by his side, he holds a
                            scroll and pen or quill. His right leg is extended forward, and his
                            right foot on which he wears a shoe is visible beneath the hem of his
                            gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner, a gowned male figure sits in a
                            straight-backed chair that is embellished with arch-like patterns
                            evocative of Gothic art similar to the bed or couch and floor below. He
                            faces right and rests his right elbow on a table at his left. In his
                            right hand he holds a scroll and a quill or pen by his
                            side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The floor, which may be a carpet or rug, between these two
                            figures is decorated with arch-like patterns evocative of Gothic art
                            similar to that of the couch or bed as well as the chairs on either
                            side.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six other smaller figures in the scene fly around the
                            seated figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of
                            these figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen
                            Katharine's body atop of plume of clouds in the lower half of the image.
                            Just above the center of the lower margin, the lowest of these figures
                            faces forward and right and appears to stand on tiptoe on the floor or
                            hover just above it. She is gowned and female with short (or perhaps
                            coiffed) hair. Her left leg is bent and her right is extended backward.
                            With her right hand, she holds (and perhaps plays) a lyre and with her
                            left arm, which is extended, she holds the hand of the figure above her
                            at right, toward whom she may also look with head up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. The second figure right of center flies upward and to the right
                            with her legs together and extended backward. She has hair coiffed in a
                            bun and wears a gown. Her right arm is raised at 135 degrees and she
                            holds a horn or trumpet; her left is at her side and with her left hand
                            holds the hand of the figure below her. She faces away but turns her
                            head up and to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Near the right margin, a third gowned female figure, who has a
                            circle with beams of light around her head and may wear a crown or have
                            short hair, flies facing forward and slightly right as an infant or
                            putto flies beside her at left. The female figure plays a harp with both
                            hands. Her legs are extended together and slightly bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Directly right of Queen Katharine's left hand, a third gowned
                            female figure flies facing forward and slightly left as a nude infant or
                            putto flies beside her at left. The child faces away and is seen from
                            behind. Its hair is short, its leg are bent, and both bent arms are
                            raised vertically.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Above the harp-playing figure near the right margin, another
                            pair of figures flies upward and to the left. The figure at right is a
                            gowned female figure who faces away and turns her head up and to the
                            left. She has coiffed hair. She raises both arms vertically and holds
                            one or more circular objects in her hand (perhaps blossoms?). Her legs
                            are together and extended downward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Above the harp-playing figure near the right margin, another
                            pair of figures fly up and to the left. The child at left faces forward
                            but turns her head to look right, perhaps at the figure above her at
                            right. She has long hair and wears a gown. Her right arm is extended
                            vertically and her left is at her side. With both hands, she may reach
                            for small circular objects, perhaps blossoms(?). Her legs are extended
                            and together, knees bent slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Twenty-six smaller figures fly or hover around the seated
                            figure of Queen Katharine in serpentine formations. Seven of these
                            figures form a semi-circle around the right side of Queen Katharine's
                            body in the lower half of the image and fly atop a plume of wispy
                            clouds. Immediately to the left of the top pair of figures, the seventh
                            figure in this group, who has short hair, a crown/garland, and a gown,
                            faces away but bends to the left with arms extended and spread. Her head
                            is twisted to face forward and down, perhaps to look toward Queen
                            Katharine below. In her raised right hand, she holds a serpentine object
                            (perhaps a horn or shell?) and with her lowered left, the right side of
                            a garland or crown. Together with another figure at left who holds the
                            other side of the crown, she may be preparing to crown Queen Katharine
                            below. This moment is referenced directly in the play's text: "the first
                            two [Personages] hold a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene 2).
                            Her legs are extended downward with her left leg bent at the
                            knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>harp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The seven smaller figures who form a semi-circle around the
                            right side of Queen Katharine's body hold and/or play a variety of
                            objects and instruments. The lowest figure holds a lyre in her right
                            hand. The figure above her at right holds a trumpet or horn, and the
                            rightmost figure above her holds and plays a harp. The highest figure in
                            this group holds a serpentine object (perhaps a horn or shell?) in her
                            raised right hand and a laurel crown in her lowered left
                            hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several figures in the lowest group of smaller figures reach
                            for or hold small circular objects that may be flower
                            blossoms(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The seven small figures who form a semi-circle around the
                            right side of Queen Katharine's body fly atop a single plume of clouds
                            that appears to rise from the ground below the lowest figure or,
                            alternatively, originate with this figure herself.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. The first of these figures near the lower right portion of
                            the circle flies right and extends her left arm to hold the other side
                            of the laurel crown over the head of Queen Katharine. This moment is
                            referenced directly in the play's text: "the first two [Personages] hold
                            a spare garland over her head" (Act 4, Scene 2). In her right hand, she
                            holds and perhaps plays a lyre. She wears a crown and a gown that
                            exposes her breasts and her long hair streams behind her at
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Directly below the right arm of the first figure, a small
                            nude infant or putto faces away and flies up and to the right. He has
                            short hair and extends his right arm vertically. His legs are extended
                            backward with the left leg bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Directly above the first female figure holding the laurel
                            crown, two small nude figures with short hair face forward and fly
                            upward with arms raised overhead and may hold similar small round
                            objects, perhaps blossoms(?). The figure at right faces slightly right,
                            but twists to look left, and bends backward with legs extended backward
                            and together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Directly above the first female figure holding the laurel
                            crown, two small nude figures with short hair face forward and fly
                            upward with arms raised overhead and may hold similar small round
                            objects, perhaps blossoms(?). The figure at left extends its legs
                            backward, and his mouth may be open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Above the pair of children, a fifth figure, whose body is
                            twisted to the left, flies to the left. She wears a long gown and
                            extends both arms forward to hold and play a lyre. She appears to look
                            toward the figure flying at her left. Both legs are extended downward
                            with her right leg bent backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>necklace</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. The sixth figure who flies at the top of the circle facing
                            left and forward wears a gown that exposes her breasts. Her body is
                            horizontal, but she turns her head slightly right. Her hair is long and
                            her mouth may be open. She raises both arms horizontally and may reach
                            for or hold a small circular object, perhaps a blossom(?), with her left
                            hand. She may wear a necklace. Her legs are together and extended to the
                            right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upside down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Forming the left upper curve of the circle, a seventh figure
                            who is upside down and twisted to the right flies downward and right.
                            She has coiffed hair and wears a gown. With both arms bent and raised,
                            she plays two trumpets or horns.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A second group of small figures above and to the left of Queen
                            Katharine forms a complete circle of eight figures who fly atop a circle
                            of clouds. Forming the lower left bend in the circle, the final figure
                            flies to the right with her left arm raised horizontally and her right
                            extended upward near the above figure where she may reach for a small
                            circular object, perhaps a blossom(?). She wears a gown (which may
                            expose her breasts) and a crown or garland above short hair. Her head is
                            turned to face slightly left and her mouth may be open. Her legs are
                            together and extended behind and above her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The eight smaller figures who form a complete circle above and
                            to the left of Queen Katharine hold and/or play a variety of objects and
                            instruments. The lowest figure at right holds a lyre in her right hand
                            and, in her left hand, a laurel crown, also held by the figure at her
                            right. The fourth figure near the upper right bend in the circle holds a
                            lyre, while the seventh figure on the upper left side holds and plays
                            two horns or trumpets.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four of the eight smaller figures who form a complete circle
                            above and to the left Queen Katharine may hold and/or reach for small
                            circular objects that resemble flower blossoms. The pair of children at
                            right may hold them above their heads, the top central figure may reach
                            for them with her extended left arm, and the figure lower left may reach
                            for these with her right arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The eight smaller figures who form a complete circle above and
                            to the left of Queen Katharine fly atop a ring of clouds that connects
                            with the larger plume of clouds on the right side of the
                            picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the two figures holding the laurel crown above Queen
                            Katharine, a cluster of five figures fly or hover at right. The two
                            lower figures, visible only from the waist up, face forward and turn
                            their head to look up in opposite directions, and both hold harps or
                            lyres. They appear to be nude. The figure at right looks up and right;
                            she(?) may have long hair and appears to extend her bent left arm to the
                            left, likely to hold or play the harp.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the two figures holding the laurel crown above Queen
                            Katharine, a cluster of five figures fly or hover at right. The two
                            lower figures, visible only from the waist up, face forward and turn
                            their head to look up in opposite directions, and both hold harps or
                            lyres. They appear to be nude. The figure at left looks up and left
                            (perhaps toward the figure above her); she may have long (or coiffed)
                            hair. With both arms bent upward, she holds and plays a lyre at
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the two figures holding the laurel crown above Queen
                            Katharine, a cluster of five figures fly or hover at right. A third
                            figure above this pair faces forward and leans to the left with her head
                            up. She wears a gown and a crown over long hair. In her left arm she
                            holds and plays a lute; she raised her bent right arm at 135 degrees,
                            perhaps to reach for one of the small round objects floating to her left
                            (which may be blossoms?). Her legs are extended downward and
                            together.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the two figures holding the laurel crown above Queen
                            Katharine, a cluster of five figures fly or hover at right. To the right
                            of the lute-playing figure, a gowned figure who faces away but twists to
                            the left holds a (wicker?) basket atop her head with both arms. She
                            turns her head down and may have coiffed hair. Her legs are extended
                            backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>>Above the two figures holding the laurel crown above Queen
                            Katharine, a cluster of five figures fly or hover at right. The
                            rightmost figure in the group is a gowned female figure with long hair
                            who faces forward but bends left to reach with her right arm into the
                            basket carried on the head of the figure below her at left. Her left arm
                            is raised vertically, and she may reach for a small circular object
                            above, perhaps a blossom(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>harp</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lute</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figures in the group of five figures flying or hovering
                            between and to the right of the two circular groups of figures hold
                            instruments. The two lowest figures hold harps or lyres and the figure
                            immediately above them holds a lute in her bent left arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The group of five figures near the right side of the
                            composition fly atop clouds that extend from the larger plume of clouds
                            originating in the lower center of the picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Just below the upper margin of the design on the right, two
                            gowned figures who face away fly or hover. They bend sharply to the left
                            and extend their arms vertically and hold (and play) instruments. The
                            figure at right holds a harp with her left hand and plays with her
                            right. Her hair appears to be in a bun, and she turns her head to face
                            left, perhaps to look toward her companion at left. Her right leg is
                            bent backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tambourine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Just below the upper margin of the design on the right, two
                            gowned figures who face away fly or hover. They bend sharply to the left
                            and extend their arms vertically and hold (and play) instruments. The
                            figure at left has short hair or wears it coiffed. She twists her head
                            up to face up and holds a tambourine in her right hand and plays the
                            instruments with her left. One of her legs is extended downward and the
                            other at a right angle backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the heads of the two figures closest to the top of the
                            design, traces of the gowns of three additional figures are visible
                            emerging diagonally rightward from the upper margin. These suggest
                            additional figures who have flown upward out of the
                            scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cloud is visible beneath the figure flying or hovering
                            closest to the top right corner of the composition. This cloud connects
                            with the larger plume of clouds extending upward from the lower center
                            of the picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of four figures forms a circle in the upper left
                            portion of the composition. Directly below and left of the tambourine
                            player near the top margin, a gowned female figure flies or hovers
                            facing forward and left with both arms extended horizontally, palms
                            facing up. She may touch the foot of the figure to her left with her
                            extended right hand. She has long hair and may wear a crown or garland.
                            Her mouth may be open. Her legs are together and extended
                            backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upside down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of four smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. Forming the left side of the
                            circle, a gowned female figure who faces forward flies or hovers upside
                            down with her body twisted to the right. She appears to have short hair.
                            Both of her arms are raised overhead (with her left arm bent) to hold or
                            take flowers(?) from the (wicker?) basket carried on the head of the
                            gowned female figure to her right. Her legs are extended upward and her
                            left appears to be bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of four smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. The third figure who flies right
                            or hovers at the bottom edge of the circle holds a (wicker?) basket full
                            of fruit or flowers(?) atop her head with both arms bent upward. She
                            faces forward but turns her head slightly left, perhaps to look toward
                            the figure flying to her left. Her mouth may be open. She has long hair
                            and wears a gown. Her body is horizontal and her legs are together and
                            extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final group of four smaller figures forms a circle in the
                            upper left portion of the composition. In the lower right of the circle,
                            the fourth gowned figure flies right and twists to face away. Her arms
                            are extended horizontally. With her right hand, she appears to reach for
                            or drop small objects, perhaps blossoms(?). Her left hand is extended
                            near the basket carried by the figure at the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>basket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wicker</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lowest figure at left in the topmost group of figures
                            holds a (wicker?) basket, which may contain flowers(?), on top of her
                            head. A similar basket is held on the head of a small figure further to
                            the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>flowers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lowest figure at left in the topmost group of figures
                            holds a basket, which may contain flowers(?), on top of her head.
                            Additional small circular objects that may be blossoms(?) are visible in
                            a horizontal line in the middle of the circle of figures upper
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The final group of four smaller figures who form a circle in
                            the upper left portion of the composition fly or hover atop a ring of
                            clouds that connects with the larger plume of clouds on the right side
                            of the picture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>pier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Visible against each side margin near the top of the
                            composition, two piers with vaguely Corinthian capitals support (what is
                            likely) a pointed arch, though the arch itself is
                            obscured.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beams of light extend outward from the upper middle of the
                            composition, often terminating in dark, spiky points that form
                            concentric bands, particularly on the left side of the
                            design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but549.1.penandink.01.01" justify="left" indent="45">WBlake inv</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
