<bad id="but518.1" type="wc" work="'And the angel which I saw lifted up his hand to Heaven'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="met" catalog="butlin" catid="518" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="'And the angel which I saw lifted up his hand to Heaven'"><main>"And the angel which I saw lifted up his hand to Heaven"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 9KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 137KB to 1500KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible.  All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.  This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
                <lb/><lb/>
                   Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts.  The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation.  While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
                    <lb/><lb/>
                        The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>. 
                    <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This work copyright © 2011 Metropolitan Museum of Art</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>November 2002</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Andrea Dickens</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Gerald Miller,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee,</name><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>June 2002</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Andrea Dickens</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah Trippensee,</name><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>"And the angel which I saw lifted up his hand to Heaven"</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>39.3 x 26.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>39.4 x 26.3 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York</name><date>1914</date><dealer>Frank T. Sabin</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts, c. 1805; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 26 March 1852, lot 154 (£2.6s. to the dealer Henry G. Bohn); B. G. Windus; his daughter Mrs. J. K. de Putron by 1863; sold Christie's, 16 March 1912, lot 5 (£48.6s. to the dealer Frank T. Sabin); sold by Sabin in 1914 to the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Metropolitan Museum of Art</institution><addressline>1000 Fifth Avenue</addressline><addressline>New York, New York 10028-0198</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1 212 535 7710</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Study Room: 1-212-570-3912</addressline><addressline>Fax, Image Library: 1-212-396-5050</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.metmuseum.org</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">14.81.1</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but518.wc.01" dbi="BUT518.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">"And the angel which I saw lifted up his hand to Heaven"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 518)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake signed the work lower right with his monogram; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>39.3 x 26.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>This design illustrates Revelation 10:1-5. Dominating the design is the figure of a male angel who is nearly nude except for an almost transparent piece of cloth that he wears like a sash across his chest and over his genitals. He has short, curly hair and stands, facing forward and slightly right. His right leg is bent and extended backward slightly on tiptoe, which indicates that he may be walking. Flames surround both of his feet. The angel looks up and raises his right arm vertically, palm up. He holds his left arm at his side and in his left hand is an open book with indications of writing on the pages. The sky backing the scene is dark, except for the radiance surrounding the angel's head and upper body. Behind the angel are dark clouds. To the left of the angel's right leg are three male figures on the cloud, all with beards and riding horses. The leftmost figure appears to be old and has long hair. He faces right, wearing a shirt and pants, and sitting on the horse with his right leg bent. His right arm is at his side but bent. The horse ridden by the leftmost figure faces right and down with its back legs extended backward and its front legs extended forward and bent. The middle figure of the group wears a shirt and faces right and forward. He is also riding a horse. The horse ridden by the middle figure faces right and slightly forward. The rightmost figure faces forward and to the right. He may have a crown or hat on his head and wear a shirt. He may also ride a horse, but its form is just hinted at, facing right. Between the angel's legs on the cloud are two male figures with short, curly hair and beards, facing right. The leftmost figure rides a horse and has his right arm and right leg both bent. He may wear a shirt and pants or a gown. The horse ridden by the leftmost figure faces right and may be standing. One rein is pictured on the horse. The rightmost figure faces slightly forward and may be riding a horse, but its form is only hinted at. To the right of the angel's left leg on the cloud are two male figures with beards, facing right. The leftmost figure may wear a shirt and pants or a gown and has long, slightly curly hair. His right arm is bent upward and his right leg is bent as he sits on his horse. The horse ridden by the leftmost figure faces right and up and may be climbing upward. The rightmost figure may have short, curly hair and may wear a shirt and pants or a gown. His right leg is bent as he sits on his horse. The horse ridden by the rightmost figure faces right and up and may be climbing upward. The angel dominating the design stands with his right foot on choppy waves, representing the sea, and with his left foot on earth that may be grassy and rocky. At the bottom center of the design sits a male figure wearing a gown. This is John of Patmos looking at the revelation above him. He has short, curly hair and faces away, looking up and to the left. His left leg is bent and extended backward on tiptoe. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent and in his right hand he holds what may be a quill pen. This figure sits on a rock, over which is a partly open scroll on which John has probably been writing.
                    </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>page</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dominating the design is the figure of a male angel who is nearly nude except for an almost transparent piece of cloth that he wears like a sash across his chest and over his genitals. He has short, curly hair and stands, facing forward and slightly right. His right leg is bent and extended backward slightly on tiptoe, which indicates that he may be walking. Flames surround both of his feet. The angel looks up and raises his right arm vertically, palm up. He holds his left arm at his side and in his left hand is an open book with indications of writing on the pages. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the angel are dark clouds. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the angel's right leg are three male figures on the cloud, all with beards and riding horses. The leftmost figure appears to be old and has long hair. He faces right, wearing a shirt and pants, and sitting on the horse with his right leg bent. His right arm is at his side but bent. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the angel's right leg are three male figures on the cloud, all with beards and riding horses. The horse ridden by the leftmost figure faces right and down with its back legs extended backward and its front legs extended forward and bent. The horse's prominent tail is flame-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the angel's right leg are three male figures on the cloud, all with beards and riding horses. The middle figure of the group wears a shirt and faces right and forward. He is also riding a horse. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the angel's right leg are three male figures on the cloud, all with beards and riding horses. The horse ridden by the middle figure faces right and slightly forward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the angel's right leg are three male figures on the cloud, all with beards and riding horses. The rightmost figure faces forward and to the right. He may have a crown or hat on his head and wear a shirt. He may also ride a horse, but its form is just hinted at, facing right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between the angel's legs on the cloud are two male figures with short, curly hair and beards, facing right. The leftmost figure rides a horse and has his right arm and right leg both bent. He may wear a shirt and pants or a gown. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>rein</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between the angel's legs on the cloud are two male figures with short, curly hair and beards, facing right. The horse ridden by the leftmost figure faces right and may be standing. One rein is pictured on the horse.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Between the angel's legs on the cloud are two male figures with short, curly hair and beards, facing right. The rightmost figure faces slightly forward and may be riding a horse, but its form is only hinted at. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the angel's left leg on the cloud are two male figures with beards, facing right. The leftmost figure may wear a shirt and pants or a gown and has long, slightly curly hair. His right arm is bent upward and his right leg is bent as he sits on his horse. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the angel's left leg on the cloud are two male figures with beards, facing right. The horse ridden by the leftmost figure faces right and up and may be climbing upward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>riding</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>shirt</characteristic><characteristic>pants</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the angel's left leg on the cloud are two male figures with beards, facing right. The rightmost figure may have short, curly hair and may wear a shirt and pants or a gown. His right leg is bent as he sits on his horse. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the angel's left leg on the cloud are two male figures with beards, facing right. The horse ridden by the rightmost figure faces right and up and may be climbing upward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>writing</characteristic><characteristic>quill</characteristic><characteristic>pen</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the bottom center of the design sits a male figure wearing a gown. This is John of Patmos looking at the revelation above him. He has short, curly hair and faces away, looking up and to the left. His leg is bent and extended backward on tiptoe. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and bent and in his right hand he holds what may be a quill pen. John has probably been writing on the scroll before him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><illusobjdesc>a partly opened scroll is draped over the rock in front of the figure just above the bottom of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>ocean</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The angel dominating the design stands with his right foot on choppy waves, representing the sea, and with his left foot on earth that may be grassy and rocky. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky backing the scene is dark, except for the radiance surrounding the angel's head and upper body. </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="15"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but518.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="41">inv</l><l n="but518.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="40">WB</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>