<bad id="but53000.1" type="wc" work="Lear and Cordelia in Prison test" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="53">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Lear and Cordelia in Prison test">
                    <main>Lear and Cordelia in Prison</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
 <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of Blake’s water color illustrations to the plays of William Shakespeare. 
                 <lb/>
                <lb/>     
Although less extensive and well known than his illustrations of John Milton’s poems, Blake’s water colors based on Shakespeare’s plays constitute a significant group of designs. The earliest, dating from c. 1779, is probably one of Blake’s illustrations of English history but nonetheless evokes Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi>. The series of seven small ovals picturing characters from the plays also dates from Blake’s early years. The concentrated focus on just one or two figures filling most of the pictorial space may be Blake’s response to popular interest in miniature portraiture. The reason for his execution of this group is not known; like the English history designs, they may have been intended for eventual publication as engravings.  The series of Shakespeare character portraits by John Hamilton Mortimer, published as engravings in the mid-1770s, may have influenced Blake’s similar project.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
<hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> is one of Blake’s largest water colors of the 1780s. Its size and quality suggest that it may have been intended for exhibition, like the water colors illustrating the life of Joseph displayed at the Royal Academy in 1785. The circle of dancers and Puck’s stance with arms raised echo similar motifs in George Romney’s <hi rend="i">Leveson-Gower Family</hi>, painted in 1776-77 and published as a mezzotint by John Raphael Smith in 1781.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Blake was clearly attracted to the vision of Queen Katherine in <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, act 4, scene 2, for he executed four versions beginning c. 1783-90 and concluding with the highly finished and complex water color of c. 1825-26. Blake’s water color of Queen Katherine’s dream dated 1809 is part of a series of six illustrations to Shakespeare’s plays commissioned by Joseph Thomas, the clergyman who had earlier employed Blake to illustrate Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>. In a letter of 31 July 1801 to William Hayley, John Flaxman added a postscript to Blake, including the following: “he [Thomas] also desired you [Blake] will make two designs in bister or Indian Ink, from Shakespeare’s Troylus &amp; Cressida, Coriolanus, either of the 3 plays of Henry 6.<sup>th</sup> Richard the 3.<sup>d</sup> or Henry the 8.<sup>th</sup> each design for one play for which he will give a Guinea each, the dimensions as follow the paper. an upright square of 12 Inches &amp; half by 8 Inches, within this Space leaving a moderate margin, the principal figure not exceeding 6 Inches high” (Butlin 547). Blake’s designs (most now trimmed) roughly follow these size requirements, necessitated by Thomas’s desire to create an extra-illustrated copy of the 1632 second folio of Shakespeare’s plays, but Blake waited eight years before completing the commission, changed the medium from monochrome drawings to water colors, and illustrated only two plays, <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi> and <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, specified by Flaxman. Blake may have chosen the other passages for illustration, at some point convincing Thomas of their appropriateness.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
Many of Blake’s Shakespeare designs show his predilection for scenes dealing with perceptions that extend beyond the world of the physical senses. The four versions of Queen Katherine’s dream epitomize this lifelong interest in imaginative and visionary experiences. A corollary is Blake’s attraction to representations of the arts, demonstrated by <hi rend="i">Oberon, Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> and his portrayal of Pegasus, the classical embodiment of poetic inspiration, in <hi rend="i">As If an Angel Dropped Down from the Clouds</hi> among the designs for Thomas.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph Viscomi, editors <lb/>
                Joseph Fletcher, managing editor, Michael Fox, assistant editor<lb/>
                 The William Blake Archive<lb/>     
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2020 Tate Collection </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February - March 2020</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies,</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Dan Gorman</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose</name>
                    <name>Jake Ruta</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>     
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>November 2015</date>
               <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Laura Bell</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Rachel Lee,</name>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Adam Engel,</name>
<name>Andrea Everett,</name>
<name>Grant Glass,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Eric Loy,</name>
<name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
<name>Adam McCune,</name>
<name>Scott Robinson,</name>
<name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
<name>Miles Simon,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
<name>Alia Wegner,</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>March 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Lear and Cordelia in Prison* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1779">c. 1779<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations
                        and the relationship between this work and Blake's other water colors
                        illustrating English history.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>12.3 x 17.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.2 x 18.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Tate Collection</name>
                <date>1940</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; sold by Catherine
                    Blake c. 1828-29 to Mrs. Samuel Smith and Julia Smith (see Butlin 53 and
                    Bentley, *Records*, page 484); Julia Smith by 1876, possibly by
                    descent; by descent to Thena Clough; sold Sotheby's, 6 March 1934, lot 337
                    (&#163;30 to Alice G. E. Carthew); bequeathed by Carthew in 1940 to the Tate
                    Gallery (now Tate Collection).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Tate Collection</institution>
                <addressline>Millbank</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 20-7887-8888</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images: 20-7887-8871/4933</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images: 20-7887-8805</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Images: tate.images@tate.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, General: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Images: http://www.tate-images.com</addressline>
                <department/>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">N05189</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but53.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT53.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Lear and Cordelia in Prison test</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 53)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This work is probably part of Blake's series of water colors illustrating
                        English history rather than an illustration of Shakespeare's *King Lear*. Indeed, the scene does not appear in the play, although
                        Blake may be picturing what Lear imagines will happen in his great speech in
                        Act V scene 3 beginning "No, no, no, no! Come, let's away to prison." There
                        Lear and Cordelia will "wear out" their days "in a walled prison." Even if
                        the design is not based directly on Shakespeare's play, his treatment of
                        Lear and his daughters is so culturally powerful that an association of this
                        subject with his play is difficult to avoid. The placement of Lear and
                        Cordelia in prison may have been influenced by Nahum Tate’s adaptation of
                            *King Lear* of 1681. The stage direction to the third
                        scene of Act V places them in "A Prison. Lear asleep, with his head on
                        Cordelia’s lap." An inscription below the drawing on the mat (not shown)
                        reads "Lear and Cordelia (early manner)." An inscription on the back of the
                        mat reads "Bought of Mrs. Blake the first or second year after her husband's
                        death. Price of this and 'the Grave' [Butlin 134] was about &#163;8.8." The
                        longer inscription was probably written by Mrs. Samuel Smith or Julia Smith;
                        another inscription on the back of the mat reads in part "Exhibited at
                        Burlington Fine Arts Club 1876 No. 223 lent by Miss Julia Smith." The
                        catalogue for this exhibition states that the lender was "Miss Julia
                        Smith."</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>13.2 x 18.2 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In a room with stone walls that suggests a prison cell, a gowned
                        female figure with long curly hair sits facing right with her head turned
                        down to look toward an older male figure who lies on the ground with his
                        head in her lap. The female figure wraps her bent right arm across her chest
                        and bends her left arm upward near her face. Her legs are bent with both
                        bare feet visible at left. She wears a swath of drapery around her lower
                        body; additional drapery, which she may hold in her right hand, extends out
                        from her torso at right in a serpentine flourish. The male figure, whose
                        eyes appear to be closed, has white hair and a beard. He may be sleeping. He
                        wears a gown or tunic, and blue drapery covers his torso and the floor below
                        him. He raises both bent arms above his head to rest on the female figure’s
                        lap with his left hand touching his right wrist. Both of his legs are bent
                        but extended to the right. The water color probably represents the
                        characters Lear, the King of Britain, and Cordelia, his youngest daughter.
                        This specific scene does not appear in Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">King
                            Lear</hi>, although Blake may be picturing what Lear imagines will
                        happen in his great speech in Act V scene 3 beginning "No, no, no, no! Come,
                        let's away to prison." There Lear and Cordelia will "wear out" their days
                        "in a walled prison." The scene does occur in Nahum Tate’s adaptation of <hi
                            rend="i">King Lear</hi> of 1681 in the stage direction to the third
                        scene of Act V: "Scene, A Prison. Lear asleep, with his head on Cordelia’s
                        lap." This water color is probably one of Blake's illustrations to English
                        history rather than directly related to Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">King
                            Lear</hi>.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Cordelia</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned female figure with long curly hair sits facing right
                            with her head turned down to look toward an older male figure who lies
                            with his head in her lap. Bending forward slightly, she wraps her bent
                            left arm across her chest and bends her left arm upward near her face,
                            perhaps touching it. She may hold drapery in her left hand. Her legs are
                            bent with both bare feet visible at left. This figure is probably
                            Cordelia, the daughter of Lear, as a prisoner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure wears a swath of drapery around her lower
                            body; additional drapery, which she may hold in her right hand, extends
                            out from her torso at right in a serpentine flourish.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying on side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Lear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A male figure lies on the ground facing forward with his head
                            resting on the lap of the female figure at left. He has short white hair
                            and a beard; his eyes appear to be closed, suggesting he is sleeping. He
                            wears a gown or tunic with long sleeves, and blue drapery covers his
                            torso and the floor below him. Both arms are bent and raised above his
                            head to rest on the female figure’s lap with his left hand touching his
                            right wrist. Both of his legs are bent but extended to the right. This
                            figure is probably Lear, the King of Britain, as a
                            prisoner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prison</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two figures in this scene occupy what appears to be a
                            square interior room with a floor and walls made of stone. It may
                            represent a prison cell.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Dark shadows are visible in the lower left and upper right
                            corners of the room.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
