<bad id="but613.1" type="wc" work="Alternative Design for the Title-Page of Robert Blair's 'The Grave': The Resurrection of the Dead" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="613"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Alternative Design for the Title-Page of Robert Blair's 'The Grave': The Resurrection of the Dead"><main>Alternative Design for the Title-Page of Robert Blair's "The Grave": The Resurrection of the Dead</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 56KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 126KB to 1400KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2014 The British Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>June 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>June 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Eric Forster,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and metadata collection</change><date>September 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Gwen Kern,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Alternative Design for the Title-Page of Robert Blair's The Grave: The Resurrection of the Dead*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1806">1806</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>42.5 x 31.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>45.4 x 33.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>card-like wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1856</date><dealer>Evans (probably A. E. Evans &#38; Son)</dealer><price>£8.8s.</price><note>Possibly commissioned and acquired by Robert H. Cromek; later history unknown until the sale of the work by the dealer "Evans" (probably A. E. Evans &#38; Son) to the British Museum in 1856.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline><addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline><addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Department of Prints and Drawings: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">1856,0712.208</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but613.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT613.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Alternative Design for the Title-Page of Robert Blair's *The Grave*: The Resurrection of the Dead</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 613)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is probably an alternative title page design for Blake's illustrations to Robert Blair's *The Grave*, commissioned in 1805 by Robert H. Cromek.  Alernatively, it may have been intended as a title page for the water color designs, later sold by Cromek as a group, rather than for engraving and publication in Cromek's edition, not published until 1808.  Blake signed and dated the work lower right; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>42.5 x 31.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="650"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>At the center of the design is a blank octagonal box, presumably where the title page text would have been placed. The scene is backed with a blue wash suggesting sky. From the top center of the design, beams of light emanate downward, suggesting a sun or heaven. To the left of the octagonal box hovers a nude, muscular male figure seen from behind. His body is bent so that he faces left and up. He has curly hair. His left leg is extended down, while his right leg is bent. His right arm is at his side but bent, but his left arm is bent over his head. He holds a partly unsheathed sword. Beneath the figure to the left of the octagonal box is a group of five nude, hovering children, perhaps cherubs. The leftmost child is male and faces left and up. His head is bent back and his legs are crossed. Both of his arms are raised at 135 degrees, palms up. The second-to-left figure is a female with curly hair. Her left leg is slightly bent and may be on tiptoe. She faces forward but her upper body is bent to the right. Her arms are at her side but bent upward with her palms vertical and facing the viewer. The center figure may be a male, facing away and bending down and to the right. His feet are on tiptoe, with his left leg bent. He may be looking at the figure to the right. His arms are raised vertically, with his palms vertical as well. The second-from-right figure is a male with short, curly hair. He faces forward, and looks down and to the right, perhaps at the  adultfemale figure to the right. His feet may be on tiptoe and his ankles may be crossed. His arms are at his side. The rightmost figure of the group may be a male child with short, curly hair, facing away and bending to the left. He may be looking at the female figure to the left. Both his arms are raised at 135 degrees, with his left arm bent; his left hand may be touching the hair of the adult female figure to the left. His mouth is open and he may be speaking. His legs are extended behind him and bent slightly, perhaps on tiptoe. In the bottom left corner of the design is a group of five hovering figures. The leftmost figure of the group may be a male with long, curly hair. He wears a transparent gown. He faces forward and looks up and to the left, with his head bent back. His mouth may be open. His body is twisted so that his lower half faces left and his left leg is seen in profile. His left foot is visible on tiptoe beneath the hem of his gown. His right arm is raised vertically, with the palm up. The second-to-left figure is that of a young woman with long hair. She wears a transparent gown and her body faces forward and to the left, although she looks up and to the right, perhaps at the figure to the right. Her right arm is at her side and she holds the hand of the figure to the right with her left hand. Her legs may be crossed and her left foot is on tiptoe. The center figure of the group is that of a woman with long, curly hair. She may be partly clothed by a transparent cloth that drapes from her waist. She faces forward and slightly left, looking up slightly as well. Her feet are on tiptoe, and her left leg is bent back. Her arms are at her side and she holds the hand of the figure to either side of her. The second-to-right figure in the group is that of a nude male with short, curly hair. He faces forward and bends slightly right and down. His left leg is bent and may be on tiptoe. His arms are at his sides and he holds the hand of the figure to either side. The rightmost figure of this group is a female with curly hair, dressed in a transparent gown. Her right leg is bent slightly and both feet are visible beneath the hem of her gown, with her left foot on tiptoe. She faces forward and bends her head slightly up and to the left. Her arms are at her side, with her right hand being held by the figure to the left. In the bottom right corner of the design is a group of four figures, sitting on a rocky surface. Four chains, the leftmost three unclasped, are attached to the stony earth. The leftmost figure of the group is a nude male, facing away and looking to the left. He has short, curly hair. He crouches precariously with his left leg bent slightly and on tiptoe, and his right leg bent at a more extreme angle. His left arm is raised at 45 degrees relative to his body and his right arm is raised vertically, palm vertical. The second-to-left figure is a gowned male with short, curly hair who faces forward and slightly left, looking up. His mouth is partly open. He sits on a rock or boulder. His arms are raised vertically and bent above his head, with his hands meeting, perhaps in a gesture of prayer or supplication. The second-to-right figure is a muscular male wearing a loincloth around his waist. He faces forward and looks to the left, with his mouth partly open. He has short, curly hair. He balances himself on the rocky ground by kneeling on his bent left leg, while his right leg is extended to the side and on tiptoe. His arms are raised vertically and bent above his head, with his hands together in what is perhaps a gesture of prayer or supplication. The rightmost figure in the group is a nude male with short, curly hair. He crouches with his left leg bent and drawn up, his left foot on tiptoe, and his right leg in a kneeling position. He faces forward but looks up and to the left. His arms are raised vertically, palms vertical and fingers spread, perhaps in a gesture of supplication. His mouth is partly open. Above the group of figures in the bottom right corner of the design hovers a gowned male, his body facing away and upside down. He looks to the right, and has short, curly hair. His right arm is raised vertically relative to his body and his left arm is at his side. He holds in his left hand a key topped with a decoration hinting at a fleur-de-lis design that he may use to unlock the chains of the group below him. His feet are visible beneath the hem of his gown, and his left leg is bent. An aura emanates from his body. In the top right corner of the design hovers a muscular, nude male figure with short, curly hair. He faces forward and looks slightly to the left, smiling. His right leg is bent backward slightly and on tiptoe. His right arm is raised at 135 degrees and he holds a pair of scales in his right hand. His left arm is at his side and he holds a partly unfurled scroll in his left hand.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>box</characteristic> <!-- Should we add this search term? I don't know what else to call it --><illusobjdesc>At the center of the design is a blank octagonal box, presumably where the title page text would have been placed. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is backed with a blue wash suggesting a sky. From the top center of the design, beams of light emanate downward, suggesting a sun or heaven. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the octagonal box hovers a nude, muscular male figure seen from behind. His body is twisted so that he faces left and up. He has curly hair. His left leg is extended down, while his right leg is bent. His right arm is at his side but bent, but his left arm is bent over his head. He holds a partly unsheathed sword. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>sword</characteristic><characteristic>sheath</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure in the top left of the design holds a partly unsheathed sword.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the figure to the left of the octagonal box is a group of five nude, hovering children, perhaps cherubs. The leftmost child is male and faces left and up. His head is bent back and his legs are crossed. Both of his arms are raised at 135 degrees, palms up. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>bending right</characteristic><characteristic>arms at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the figure to the left of the octagonal box is a group of five nude, hovering children, perhaps cherubs. The second-to-left figure is a female with curly hair. Her left leg is slightly bent and may be on tiptoe. She faces forward but her upper body is bent to the right. Her arms are at her side but bent upward with her palms vertical and facing the viewer.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>bending right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the figure to the left of the octagonal box is a group of five nude, hovering children, perhaps cherubs. The center figure in this group may be a male, facing away and bending down and to the right. His feet are on tiptoe, with his left leg bent. He may be looking at the figure to the right. His arms are raised vertically, with his palms vertical as well.  His left hand points upward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>feet on tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the figure to the left of the octagonal box is a group of five nude, hovering children, perhaps cherubs. The second-from-right figure is a male with short, curly hair. He faces forward, and looks down and to the right, perhaps at the female figure to the right. His feet may be on tiptoe and his ankles may be crossed. His arms are at his side.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>cherub</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>bending left</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the figure to the left of the octagonal box is a group of five nude, hovering children, perhaps cherubs. The rightmost figure of the group may be a male child with short, curly hair, facing away and bending to the left. He may be looking at the female figure to the left. Both his arms are raised at 135 degrees, with his left arm bent; his left hand may be touching the hair of the female figure to his left. His mouth is open and he may be speaking. His legs are extended behind him and bent slightly, perhaps on tiptoe.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the design is a group of five hovering figures. The leftmost figure of the group may be a male with long, curly hair. He wears a transparent gown. He faces forward and looks up and to the left, with his head bent back. His mouth may be open. His body is twisted so that his lower half faces left and his left leg is seen in profile. His left foot is visible on tiptoe beneath the hem of his gown. His right arm is raised vertically, with the palm up. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the design is a group of five hovering figures. The second-to-left figure is that of a young woman with long hair. She wears a transparent gown and her body faces forward and to the left, although she looks up and to the right, perhaps at the figure to the right. Her right arm is at her side and she holds the hand of the figure to the right with her left hand. Her legs may be crossed and her left foot is on tiptoe. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent backward</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the design is a group of five hovering figures. The center figure of the group is that of a woman with long, curly hair. She may be partly clothed by a transparent cloth that drapes from her waist. She faces forward and slightly left, looking up slightly as well. Her feet are on tiptoe, and her left leg is bent back. Her arms are at her side and she holds the hand of the figure to either side of her. She may be the mother of the other four figures in the group. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>bending right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the design is a group of five hovering figures. The second-to-right figure in the group is that of a nude male with short, curly hair. He faces forward and bends slightly right and down. His left leg is bent and may be on tiptoe. His arms are at his sides and he holds the hand of the figure to either side. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the design is a group of five hovering figures. The rightmost figure of this group is a female with curly hair, dressed in a transparent gown. Her right leg is bent slightly and both feet are visible beneath the hem of her gown, with her left foot on tiptoe. She faces forward and bends her head slightly up and to the left. Her arms are at her side, with her right hand being held by the figure to the left. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the design is a rocky surface, extending along the bottom of the design. A rock or boulder juts up on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four chains, the leftmost three unclasped, are attached to the stony earth in the bottom right corner of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the design is a group of four figures, sitting on a rocky surface. The leftmost figure of the group is a nude male, facing away and looking to the left. He has short, curly hair. He crouches precariously with his left leg is bent slightly and on tiptoe, and his right leg is bent at a more extreme angle. His left arm is raised at 45 degrees relative to his body and his right arm is raised vertically, palm vertical.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the design is a group of four figures, sitting on a rocky surface. The second-to-left figure is a gowned male with short, curly hair who faces forward and slightly left, looking up. His mouth is partly open. He sits on a rock or boulder. His arms are raised vertically and bent above his head, with his hands meeting, perhaps in a gesture of prayer or supplication.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>loincloth</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the design is a group of four figures, sitting on a rocky surface. The second-to-right figure is a muscular male wearing a loincloth around his waist. He faces forward and looks to the left, with his mouth partly open. He has short, curly hair. He balances himself on the rocky ground by kneeling on his bent left leg, while his right leg is extended to the side and on tiptoe. His arms are raised vertically and bent above his head, with his hands together in what is perhaps a gesture of prayer or supplication.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the design is a group of four figures, sitting on a rocky surface. The rightmost figure in the group is a nude male with short, curly hair. He crouches with his left leg bent and drawn up, his left foot on tiptoe, and his right leg in a kneeling position. He faces forward but looks up and to the left. His arms are raised vertically, palms vertical and fingers spread, perhaps in a gesture of supplication. His mouth is partly open. He is chained by his left ankle to the rock beneath him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the group of figures in the bottom right corner of the design hovers a gowned male, his body facing away and upside down. He looks to the right, and has short, curly hair. His right arm is raised vertically relative to his body and his left arm is at his side. He holds in his left hand a key topped with a fleur-de-lis design that he may use to unlock the chains of the group below him. His feet are visible beneath the hem of his gown, and his left leg is bent. An aura emanates from his body. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>key</characteristic><characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure hovering upside down above the bottom right corner of the design holds in a key topped with a decorative pattern hinting at a fleur-de-lis design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top right corner of the design hovers a muscular, nude male figure with short, curly hair. He faces forward and looks slightly to the left, smiling. His right leg is bent backward slightly and on tiptoe. His right arm is raised at 135 degrees and he holds a pair of scales in his right hand. His left arm is at his side and he holds a partly unfurled scroll in his left hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>scales</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure in the top right corner of the design holds a pair of scales in his right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure in the top right corner of the design holds a partly unfurled scroll in his left hand.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="15"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but613.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="20">1806 WBlake inv</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>