<bad id="but619.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': A Figure Ascending in a Glory of Clouds" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="619" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': A Figure Ascending in a Glory of Clouds"><main>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": A Figure Ascending in a Glory of Clouds</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work courtesy of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>September 2002</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editors: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Dickens</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Gerald Miller, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee, </name><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": A Figure Ascending in a Glory of Clouds</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="UI">(Butlin 619)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>22.9 x 18.8 cm</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote><p>The pen and ink inscription lower right is by Frederick Tatham, not Blake.  See the Textual Transcription.</p></objnote></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>At the center of the image is a figure of indeterminable gender, facing left and slightly forward, and bending backward to look up. The figure may be gowned. Its feet are together with its legs bent. Its left arm is raised horizontally and its right arm is raised at 135 degrees, relative to its torso, but vertically within the orientation of the design. A number of sketchy lines, most likely clouds, surround the central figure on the left, bottom, and right. The lines at the top left of the image are flame-like. Next to the lines resembling flames at the top left of the image is a grouping of circular lines that may represent clouds or a human torso, nude and perhaps female, facing forward and slightly right.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the center of the image is a figure of indeterminable gender, facing left and slightly forward, and bending backward to look up. The figure may be gowned. Its feet are together with its legs bent. Its left arm is raised horizontally and its right arm is raised at 135 degrees, relative to its torso, but vertically within the orientation of the design. It may be bald.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>line</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A number of sketchy lines, most likely clouds, surround the central figure on the left, bottom, and right. The lines at the top left of the image are flame-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>hair, bald</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Next to the lines resembling flames at the top left of the image is a grouping of circular lines that may represent clouds or a human head and torso, nude and perhaps female, facing forward and slightly right. She(?) may be looking at the figure to the right.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg justify="left"><l n="but619.1.penc.01.01" justify="left" indent="60">sketched by<note>This pen and ink inscription is by Frederick Tatham</note></l><l n="but619.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="60">William Blake</l><l n="but619.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="60">vouched by</l><l n="but619.1.wc.01.04" justify="left" indent="62">Fred.<hi rend="superscript">k</hi> Tatham</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>