<bad id="but62.1" type="wc" work="The Making of Magna Charta" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="62">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Making of Magna Charta">
                    <main>
                        The Making of Magna Charta</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 27KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>The Making of Magna Charta</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1779.D">c. 1779<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations and the relationship between this work and Blake's other water colors illustrating English history.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>13.2 x 17.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.2 x 17.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1972</date>
                <dealer>Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons</dealer>
                <price>$5452</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by William Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, lot 172 with eight other works by Blake (19s.); Colonel Gould Weston; Alexander Anderdon Weston by 1876, probably by inheritance; his widow; sold anonymously, Christie's, 28 June 1904, lot 9 with Blake's water colors *The Death of Earl Goodwin*, Butlin 60, and *The Keys of Calais*, Butlin 64 (&#163;7.17s.6d. to the dealer E. Parsons); sold 1904 to W. Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 51 with the same two water colors in the 1904 auction, lot 9 (&#163;241.10s. to the Fine Art Society); sold 1957 to George Goyder; offered by Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons, 14 June-15 July 1966 catalogue, item 21 (&#163;550); sold Aug. 1972 by Agnew's to Robert N. Essick ($5452).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <collection>Robert N. Essick</collection>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but62.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT62.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Making of Magna Charta</title>
                <title type="alt">The Making of Magna Carta</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 62)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This work is part of a series of water colors Blake executed c. 1779 illustrating major events in the history of England.  Eight of these works are extant.  These designs may be related to "The History of England, a small book of Engravings" Blake listed in his advertisement "To the Public" of 10 Oct. 1793 (Erdman page 693).  No copy of that "book" has ever been recorded.  See also the list of subjects from the history of England Blake wrote in his Notebook c. 1793 (Erdman page 672).</p></objnote>
                <objsize>13.2 x 17.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design shows the making of the Magna Charta (or "Magna Carta"), with six male figures gathered around a scroll or parchment containing the draft of the document. All of them wear gowns, and several wear additional robes or drapery. In the foreground, two men hold between them a document that reads "MAGNA CHARTA" in large letters, and another man stands to the left holding another paper with the word "CHARTA" written in smaller letters. This man, standing against the design's left border, leans forward and may brace his arms against the table on which he holds part of the Magna Charta document. He may stride forward with his left leg or stand and lean over the table and the document. He has short, curly hair and wears a gown that falls to his knees with a cloth or other garment wrapped around his waist. The man in front of him, the left of the pair holding the main document between them, kneels with his left knee on the ground and his right knee forward as his body faces toward the right. He twists his upper body to face away from the viewer and look at the men in the background. His left hand supports the document from behind, and his right hand holds a writing implement (perhaps a pen) over the front of the document; he may point to the document with his right index finger. He has short, curly hair. The man at right appears older, as indicated by his white hair and long, wavy beard. He sits on a chair and faces left. Both feet are visible beneath a long, voluminous robe. The old man leans forward to look at the document. In his left hand he holds a tablet against his bent left knee; his right hand is bent upward with his palm facing left next to the document. Behind these central men stand three others. They are, from left to right, as follows: a man with short, curly hair who leans to the right and bends his right arm as he holds some object in front of his body; a short-haired man who gazes downward; and a short-haired, bearded man who holds a tablet at his left side (or lifts the lid of a box on the table at his left) and looks forward with a dour expression. Behind the group of male figures, the wall appears to be divided into sections at right. There may be arched doorways behind the men at left. A shadow appears between the two men who hold the Magna Charta, beneath the document. Shadows also appear behind the left of these two men.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design shows the making of the Magna Charta, with six male figures gathered around a scroll or parchment containing the draft of the document. All of them wear gowns, and several wear additional robes or drapery.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground, two men hold the document between them, and one stands to the left holding another portion of it. This man, standing against the design's left border, leans forward, putting his weight on his left leg, and may brace his arms against the table on which he holds part of the Magna Charta document (a smaller section that reads "CHARTA"). Alternatively, he may bring the document to the table, walking or striding forward with his left leg. He has short, curly hair and wears a gown that falls to his knees with a cloth or other draped garment wrapped around his waist. He appears to gaze downward at the document.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground, two men hold the document between them, and one stands behind them holding another portion of it. The left of the pair holding the main document between them kneels with his left knee on the ground and his right knee forward. His body faces toward the right, bent forward slightly, but he twists his upper body to face away from the viewer and look at the men in the background. His left hand supports the Magna Charta from behind, and his right hand holds a writing implement over the front of the document. He may be writing, but he does not appear to be looking at the document. Alternatively, he may point toward the document with his right index finger. He has short, curly hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bishop</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the foreground, two men hold the document between them, and one stands behind them holding another portion of it. The man at right is appears older, as indicated by his white hair and long, wavy beard. He sits on a chair and faces left, bending forward to look at the document. Both legs are bent, and both feet are visible beneath a long, voluminous robe or drapery. The right foot is forward, and the left is tucked backward near one of the chair legs. In his left hand the old man holds a tablet against his bent left knee; his right hand is bent upward with his palm facing left and fingers spread next to the document.  If the mitre on the table behind him and to the right belongs to this figure, he may be a bishop.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind these central men stand three others. At left stands a man with short, curly hair who leans to the right and bends his right arm as he holds a large object, perhaps a cloth or sheet of parchment. His head and eyes are down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
						<characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
						<characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind these central men stand three others. The middle figure is a short-haired man who wears a shirt or gown and gazes downward at something in the center of the group.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lifting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind these central men stand three others. At right stands a short-haired, bearded man with a prominent mustache. He raises his right arm across his body, appearing to hold a tablet at his left side. Alternatively, he may lift open the lid of a box that sits on the table to his right. He looks forward and slightly to the left, a dour expression on his face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Magna Carta</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a large parchment or scroll with the words "MAGNA CHARTA" written on it. At left, a smaller document, probably also a scroll, containing the word "CHARTA" in small writing appears beneath the braced arms of one of the men.  A circle on this smaller documents probably represents a seal.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The old man at the right of the design sits in a chair. The chair's feet curve outward slightly, as does its back.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>table</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>box</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bishop</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A table appears behind the old man in the chair. It holds several unidentified objects. One of these may be a flat box containing still more objects. A triangular object that assembles a bishop's mitre sits on this table at right. There may be another table beneath the secondary portion of the Magna Charta document in the left portion of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the group of male figures, the wall appears to be divided into sections at right. A similar design appears on the wall in the upper left corner. There may be arched doorways behind the men at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A shadow appears between the two men who hold the Magna Charta, beneath the document. Shadows also appear behind the left of these two men.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but62.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="45">MAGNA<note>This line and the next appear on a document, probably a tablet or leaf of paper, held between the two men in the foreground of the design.</note></l>
                    <l n="but62.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="45">CHARTA</l>
                    <l n="but62.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="10">CHARTA<note>This inscription appears on a document, probably a scroll, held by the figure far left in the design.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
        
