<bad id="but629.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="629" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave'"><main>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": "The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 23KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 72KB to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2014 British Museum
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>October 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Gwen Kern, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>
                        *Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": "The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave"*
                    </title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1805">1805<note>This drawing is a preliminary sketch for *The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave*, Object 20 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*.  Both this drawing and the water color were executed in the fall of 1805.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 10 in the Archive.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objorder>1</objorder><objsize>25.2 x 13.9 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>27.5 x 13.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil and/or black chalk</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1874</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Early history unknown, but probably inherited at Blake's death by his wife Catherine in 1827 and then acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 020-7323-8408</addressline><addressline>Fax: 020-7323-8999</addressline><addressline>Email: printsphoto@thebritishmuseum.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">1874,1212.121</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but629.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT629.1.1.PD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": "The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="UI">(Butlin 629)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing is a preliminary sketch for *The Soul Exploring the Recesses of the Grave*, Object 20 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*. Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 10 in the Archive.</p></objnote><objsize>25.2 x 13.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote>
                   
                </objnote></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.10"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.20"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A cave or tomb of stone (the "Grave" of the title) dominates the lower portion of the design. A nude(?) figure, clearly femail in the water color version of the design, stands within the cave; the figure is likely a representation of the soul. The figure is seen from behind and faces away with its head turned to the right. Its hair may be short or drawn back in a bun. Both feet are visible and its left foot is raised on tiptoe; it is probably walking away from the viewer. Its left leg is extended backward. Its arms are at its side but bent and holding a lit candle in its right hand. The figure may look down and to the right toward a corpse, which is difficult to distinguish from the floor of the cave but clearly represented in the water color version. The corpse lies on the ground in a supine position, perhaps partly sunk into a shallow grave; the body is horizontal with the head to the right. The figure appears to be gowned or shrouded. A nude(?) figure, clearly male in the water color version of the design, stands above the cave. Both legs are bent and are spread apart. His body faces forward and is twisted to bend slightly left with his head turned down to the left. He may look down at the soul in the cave beneath him. The figure's arms are at his side but bent to the right with the palms held out. His mouth may be open (clearly so in the water color) and his expression suggests fear or surprise. A crescent moon appears in the sky between the male figure's legs.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>grave</characteristic><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A cave or tomb of stone (the "Grave" of the title) dominates the lower portion of the design. The body lying within the cave may be partly sunk into a shallow grave.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>soul</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>candle</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude(?) figure, clearly female in the water color version of the design, stands within the cave; the figure is likely a representation of the soul. The figure is seen from behind and faces away with its head turned to the right. Its hair may be short or drawn back in a bun. Both feet are visible and its left foot is raised on tiptoe; it is probably walking away from the viewer. Its left leg is extended backward. Its arms are at its side but bent and holding a lit candle in its right hand. The figure may look down and to the right toward a corpse, which is difficult to distinguish from the floor of the cave. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The corpse of a male(?) figure lies supine in the lower portion of the design, though it is difficult to distinguish from the floor of the cave. The body may be partly sunk into a shallow grave; the body is horizontal with the head to the right. The figure appears to be gowned or shrouded. The figure is clearly represented in the water color version of the design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>bending</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude(?) figure, clearly male in the water color version of the design, stands above the cave. Both legs are bent and are spread apart. His body faces forward and is twisted to bend slightly left with his head turned down to the left. He may look down at the soul in the cave beneath him. The figure's arms are at his side but bent to the right with the palms held out. His mouth may be open (clearly so in the water color) and his expression suggests fear or surprise.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>crescent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A crescent moon appears in the sky between the male figure's legs.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>