<bad id="but624v.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="victoria" catalog="butlin" catid="624v" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In'"><main>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In'</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 33KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 54KB to 950KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2014 Victoria and Albert Museum
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color corrected</change><date>August 2003</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Gerald Miller, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>May 2003</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editors: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Dickens</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Gerald Miller, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee, </name><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>
                        Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In'
                    </title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1805">1805<note>The recto (Object 6) is a preliminary sketch for *Death of the Strong Wicked Man*, Object 8 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*.  The verso (Object 7) is a preliminary sketch for *Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In*, Object 13 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*. All four works can be dated to the fall of 1805.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the recto design was published in Cromek's 1808 edition; see Object 6 in the Archive.  The verso design was not published.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1-2</numberobj><objorder>1-2 (recto followed by verso)</objorder><objsize>14.3 x 27.8 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>14.3 x 27.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil</medium><support>wove paper<note>The paper is from the 1802 edition of William Hayley, *Designs to a Series of Ballads*, as indicated by the partly erased letterpress word "run" visible on the recto, lower right, and the partly erased letterpress word "It" visible on the verso, upper right.</note></support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name><date>1881</date><dealer>E. Parsons</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 200 or 201 with other works (2s. for lot 200 or 3s. for lot 201, both to the dealer Francis Harvey); George A. Smith, sold Christie's, 16 July 1880, in lot 118 with two other works by Blake (12s. to the dealer E. Parsons); sold by Parsons in 1881 to the Victoria and Albert Museum.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Victoria and Albert Museum</institution><addressline>South Kensington</addressline><addressline>Cromwell Road</addressline><addressline>London SW7 2RL</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7942 2000</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Images Agency: +44 (0)20 7942 2479</addressline><addressline>Fax, Images Agency: +44 (0)20 7942 2482</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.vam.ac.uk/</addressline><addressline>URL, Finding and Buying Images: http://www.vam.ac.uk/resources/buying/index.html</addressline><repositoryid label="Accession number">8765.C</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but624v.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT624.1.1v.PD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In'</title>,
                        <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="UI">(Butlin 624 verso)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This sketch is a preliminary drawing for *Heaven's Portals Wide Expand to Let Him In*, Object 13 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*. The design was not published in Cromek's 1808 book.</p></objnote><objsize>27.8 x 14.3 cm</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote>
                            
                        </objnote></physdesc><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.13"/><related objectid="but505.1.wc.01"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Three Gothic arches stand in the upper portion of the design, one at the center and two half arches seen on each side. Each arch is separated by a column. This may be the doorway to heaven. Beams of light radiate downward from the portal. In the center of the image floats a gowned figure, probably male and rising, seen from behind. In the water color of this design, this figure is Christ. His legs are together, with his left leg slightly bent and extended backward. His ankles may be crossed and both feet are on tiptoe. His arms are raised at 135 degrees, palms held vertically or upward. To the left of the central figure is a group of at least four gowned figures, facing away or to the right. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even rising with the central figure. The leftmost figure of the group may be a child. The figure second from the left may have long hair or a veil over its head, implying that it is female. The two rightmost figures bend slightly left. The figure second from the right raised its left(?)arm vertically. To the right of the central figure is a group of at least five gowned figures, facing away or to the left. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The leftmost figure extends its left leg backward, slightly bent, with its arms raised vertically, palms together, in a gesture of prayer or supplication. The figure second from the right may have long hair or a veil over her head. She may be holding an infant in her arms. The rightmost figure may be a child. A few lines below the feet of the main, central figure suggest more small figures, possibly standing, hovering, or rising and possibly gowned.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three Gothic arches stand in the upper portion of the design, one at the center and two half arches seen on each side. Each arch is separated by a column. This may be the doorway to heaven. Beams of light radiate downward from the portal.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>line</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the image floats a gowned figure, probably male and rising, seen from behind. In the water color of this design, this figure is Christ. His legs are together, with his left leg slightly bent and extended backward. His ankles may be crossed and both feet are on tiptoe. His arms are raised at 135 degrees, palms held vertically or upward. Lines below his feet may suggest that he is moving rapidly upward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the central figure is a group of at least four gowned figures, facing away or to the right. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending with the central figure. The leftmost figure of the group may be a child. It may face right and look up, perhaps at the figure to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the central figure is a group of at least four gowned figures, facing away or to the right. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The figure second from the left may have long hair or a veil over its head, suggesting that it is female. She(?) may look down and to the left at the figure to the left. Her arms may be at her side.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the central figure is a group of at least four gowned figures, facing away or to the right. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The figure second from the right bends forward and raises its left(?) arm vertically. It may be reaching and looking upward, head bent slightly back.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the central figure is a group of at least four gowned figures, facing away or to the right. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The rightmost figure bends slightly left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the central figure is a group of at least five gowned figures, facing away or to the left. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The leftmost figure extends its left leg backward, slightly bent, with its arms raised vertically, palms together in a gesture of prayer or supplication.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the central figure is a group of at least five gowned figures, facing away or to the left. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The figure second from the left is visible only as a head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the central figure is a group of at least five gowned figures, facing away or to the left. The middle figure may be an infant, held in its mother's arms.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the central figure is a group of at least five gowned figures, facing away or to the left. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The figure second from the right, probably facing left, may have long hair or a veil over her head. She may be a mother, holding an infant in her arms.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the central figure is a group of at least five gowned figures, facing away or to the left. They may be standing or hovering; perhaps they are even ascending after the central figure. The rightmost figure may be a child, facing left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few lines below the feet of the main, central figure suggest more small figures, possibly standing, hovering, or rising and possibly gowned.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>