<bad id="but614r.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for an Alternative Title-Page for Robert Blair's 'The Grave'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="morgan" catalog="butlin" catid="614r" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for an Alternative Title-Page for Robert Blair's 'The Grave'"><main>Sketch for an Alternative Title-Page for Robert Blair's "The Grave"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 25KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 35KB to 1700KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work courtesy Morgan Library and Museum     
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>September 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer: </resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>
                        *Sketch for an Alternative Title-Page for Robert Blair's "The Grave"*
                    </title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1806">c. 1806<note>This design on the recto (Object 1) was probably sketched as an alternative title page for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*, not published until 1808.  It is a preliminary sketch for *Alternative Design for the Title-Page: The Resurrection of the Dead*, a water color in the British Museum signed and dated by Blake "1806" (Butlin 613). Blake began to compose his illustrations to Blair's poem in the fall of 1805, but apparently he did not begin to work on this alternative title page design until early 1806. The very slight sketches on the verso (Object 2) are probably related to the recto.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>51.2 x 36.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>51.2 x 36.2 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>ITAYLOR</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Morgan Library and Museum</name><date>2001</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife, Catherine, at his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; probably the dealer Joseph Hogarth, sold Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 7-30 June 1854, 12th day, lot 5082, probably the work described as "Frontispiece to Blair's Grave, *the first idea*," with 21 other works by or attributed to Blake (16s. to "Edsall," possibly a dealer); Richard Johnson, sold Platt's auction, London, 25 April 1912, lot 702 with 16 other works (price and purchaser unknown); Sotheby's, 28 May 1934, lot 166 (£7 to the dealer Raphael King of York); offered by King, catalogue of 23 Nov. 1934, item 31 (£35); the New York dealer E. Weyhe; inherited by his daughter, Gertrude Weyhe Dennis; given by Dennis in honor of Charles Ryskamp in 2001 to the Morgan Library and Museum.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Morgan Library and Museum</institution><addressline>225 Madison Avenue</addressline><addressline>New York, New York 10016</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1 212 685 0008</addressline><addressline>Fax: 1 212 481 3484</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Photos: 1 212 590 0386</addressline><addressline>Email, Photos: photoservices@themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Photos: http://themorgan.org/research/photo.asp</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">2001.14</repositoryid><repositoryid label="Call number">OS E.2</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but614r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT614.1.1r.PD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sketch for an Alternative Title-Page for Robert Blair's 'The Grave'</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 614 recto)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This design was probably sketched as an alternative title page for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*, not published until 1808.  It is a preliminary sketch for *Alternative Design for the Title-Page: The Resurrection of the Dead*, a water color in the British Museum (Butlin 613).</p></objnote><objsize>51.2 x 36.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote>
                   
                </objnote></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.02"/><related objectid="but612.1.wd.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.01"/><related objectid="but611.1.wc.01"/><related objectid="bb515.1.comb.12" type="compare" copyid="bb515.1" bentley="B12"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>At the center of the image is an oval, probably intended to include text. At the top right corner of the image is a nude figure facing forward, down, and right. It is most likely male. His body is horizontal with his legs together and he appears to be bald. He looks down. His arms are raised horizontally relative to his torso with his right arm bent. He may be hovering. He holds scales in his right hand. He may be a personification of judgment or justice. To the right of the center oval is a series of sketchy circles that may represent a nude, bald figure, sitting and facing right and slightly forward. Its legs may be bent and drawn up. In the bottom right corner of the image is a series of circles and lines that may represent at least five figures. In the bottom left corner of the image is a group of five figures. A central nude female figure, perhaps with long hair, stands or hovers facing forward and slightly left. Her head is bent back to look up. Her arms are raised horizontally, palms up. Her legs are together and may be bent back a little. To the left of the central figure are three heads, facing forward. To the right of the central figure is one head, facing forward. To the left of the  oval at the center of the image is a nude male(?) figure, hovering and facing away. His legs are extended back and bent. His body is twisted so that his lower body faces down, his torso faces away, and his head looks down and to the right. His left arm is raised at 135 degrees, relative to his body, and bent. His right arm is at his side and bent upward. He appears to hold a sword in his right hand. Two circles to the left of the central oval may represent heads or clouds. In the top left corner of the image hovers a nude figure of indeterminable gender, facing down and right. Its legs may be together and bent. Its arms may be raised horizontally relative to its body, and bent. Above the central oval are four circles that may represent heads or clouds, connected to a swirling line. In the top right corner of the image are lines that may indicate a gowned figure, standing or walking and facing right and away. It may have its head down. A wavy line extends from the bottom left corner to the scales on the right edge of the design. This may represent clouds or the top of a cliff or mound of earth.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>circle</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the center of the image is an oval, presumably where the title would have been printed. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scales</characteristic><characteristic>Justice</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top right corner of the image is a nude figure facing forward, down, and right. It is most likely male. His body is horizontal with his legs together and he appears to be bald. He looks down. His arms are raised horizontally relative to his torso with his right arm bent. He may be hovering. He holds scales in his right hand. He may be a personification of judgment or justice. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the center oval is a series of sketchy circles and lines that may represent a nude figure, sitting and facing right and slightly forward. Its legs may be bent and drawn up. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>line</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the image is a series of circles and lines that may represent at least five figures. They may be moving to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hair, long</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the image is a group of five figures. A central nude female figure, perhaps with long hair, stands or hovers facing forward and slightly left. Her head is bent back to look up. Her arms are raised horizontally, palms up. Her legs are together and may be bent back a little. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the image is a group of five figures. To the left of the central figure are three heads, facing forward. To the right of the central figure is one head, facing forward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>sword</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the  oval at the center of the image is a nude male(?) figure, hovering and facing away. His legs are extended back and bent. His body is twisted so that his lower body faces down and left, his torso faces away, and his head looks down and to the right. His left arm is raised at 135 degrees, relative to his body, and bent. His right arm is at his side and bent upward. He appears to hold a sword in his right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two circles to the left of the central oval may represent heads or clouds. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>floating</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top left corner of the image hovers a nude figure of indeterminable gender, facing down and right. Its legs may be together and bent. Its arms may be raised horizontally relative to its body, and bent. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>line</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the central oval are four circles that may represent heads or clouds, connected to a swirling line. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top right corner of the image are lines that may indicate a gowned figure, standing or walking and facing right and away. It may have its head down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>line</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A wavy line extends from the bottom left corner to the scales on the right edge of the design. This may represent clouds or the top of a cliff or mound of earth.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>