<bad id="but620.1" type="wc" work="Design for the Dedication to Blair's 'Grave'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="620"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Design for the Dedication to Blair's 'Grave'"><main>Design for the Dedication to Blair's "Grave"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 25KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 99KB to 1400KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2014 The British Museum</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>June 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Eric Forster,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and metadata collection</change><date>September 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Gwen Kern,</name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Design for the Dedication to Blair's "Grave"*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1807">1807<note>The work was executed between 17 and 20 April 1807 but rejected by Cromek in a letter to Blake of May 1807; see Bentley, *Records*, pages 234-44.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>30.2 x 23.8 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>30.2 x 23.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1894</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Commissioned by Robert H. Cromek but rejected by him in 1807 (see Bentley, *Records*, pages 241-44); Anne (Mrs. Alexander) Gilchrist by 1880; by inheritance in 1885 to her son, Herbert Harlakenden Gilchrist; sold by H. H. Gilchrist to the British Museum in 1894.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline><addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline><addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Department of Prints and Drawings: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">1894,0612.14</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but620.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT620.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Design for the Dedication to Blair's "Grave"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 620)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The two-line inscription is by Blake; see the textual transcription.</p></objnote><objsize>30.2 x 23.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="650"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>In the top right of this design are drooping branches of a leafy plant, perhaps a willow tree. The branches are peeking over or growing from a horizontal line that may represent the top of a wall. The branches on the top right droop over a pair of closed doors. The doors arch to a point in Gothic style, and may represent the doors to a church or to heaven. Each door has a prominent keyhole. The doors are framed with slender spires. Topping the doors are at least six points and six small figures, three on each side of the door. The figures on the right face left and the figures on the left face right, and all stand with their hands together as though in prayer or supplication. These figures represent winged angels, wearing gowns, and may be small statues. The church or heavenly doors stand at the top of six stairs. To the left of the doors hovers a female figure, facing away and to the right. She may represent the soul rising to heaven. She may be partly clothed by a transparent gown draping from her waist. Her right leg is extending backward. Her long hair trails behind her as she looks to the right at the doors. Both of the figure's arms are raised at 45 degrees, and in each hand she holds a key topped by a design hinting at a fleur-de-lis pattern; presumably, the keys will open the doors to the right. Each of her hands is also pointing downward. At the bottom center of this leaf lies a supine body, covered in a shroud. This is likely a dead body, from which its soul rises. A slight aura of light surrounds her head. A trail of clouds rises to divide the soul and its body. Wash behind the body suggests a blue sky. </illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>willow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top right of this design are drooping branches of a leafy plant, perhaps a willow tree. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>line</characteristic><characteristic>wall</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The branches on the top right of the leaf's design peek over or grow from a horizontal line that may represent the top of a wall. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>church</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><characteristic>spire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The branches on the top right of the leaf's design droop over a pair of closed doors. The doors arch to a point in Gothic style, and may represent the doors to a church or to heaven. Each door has a prominent keyhole. Topping the doors are at least six points and six small figures, three on each side of the door. The doors are framed with slender spires.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Topping a pair of arched, Gothic-style doors are at least six points and six small figures, three on each side of the door. The figures on the right face left and the figures on the left face right, and all stand with their hands together as though in prayer or supplication. These figures represent winged angels, wearing gowns. They may be small statues. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The pair of arched, Gothic-style doors stand at the top of six stairs. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Soul</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the pair of arched, Gothic-style doors hovers a female figure, facing away and to the right. She may represent the soul rising to heaven. She may be partly clothed by a transparent gown draping from her waist. Her right leg is extending backward. Her long hair trails behind her as she looks to the right at the doors. Both of the figure's arms are raised at 45 degrees, and in each hand she holds a key. Each of her hands is also pointing downward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>key</characteristic><characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure at the center of the design holds in each hand a key topped by a design hinting at a fleur-de-lis pattern; presumably, the keys will open the doors to the right</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>light</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the bottom center of this leaf lies a supine body, eyes closed and covered in a shroud. This is likely a dead body, from which its soul rises. A slight aura of light surrounds her head. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A trail of clouds rises to divide the soul and its body. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A wash behind the body at the bottom center of the design suggests a blue sky.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="15"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but620.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="10">To The Queen</l><l n="but620.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="10">The D<note>The remainder of this line was either not completed or has worn off the paper.  In the dedicatory poem "To The Queen" published in Robert H. Cromek's 1808 edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*, the full line reads "The Door of Death is made of Gold" (Erdman page 480).</note></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>