<bad id="but625.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="625" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life'"><main>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life'</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 23KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 49KB to 1000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2014 Tate Gallery
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color corrected</change><date>July 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>March 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>
                        Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life'
                    </title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1805">1805<note>This drawing is a preliminary sketch for <hi rend="i">The Soul Hovering over the Body</hi>, Object 9 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>.  Both this drawing and the water color were executed in the fall of 1805.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 7 in the Archive.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>27.2 x 45.6 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>27.2 x 45.6 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><stabholes/></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Tate Collection</name><date>1941</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>bequest</price><note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Joseph Hogarth, sold Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 7-23 June 1854, 12th day, in lot 5082 with 21 other works by or attributed to Blake (16s. to "Edsall," possibly a dealer); Richard Johnson, sold Platt's auction, London, 25 April 1912, in lot 702 with 16 other works (price and purchaser unknown); sold Sotheby's, 28 May 1934, lot 167 (£22 to the dealer James Bain acting for Hugh Walpole); bequeathed by Walpole to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection) in 1941.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Tate Collection</institution><addressline>Millbank</addressline><addressline>London SW1P 4RG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 20-7887-8888</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Images: 20-7887-8871/4933</addressline><addressline>Fax, Images: 20-7887-8805</addressline><addressline>Email, Images: picture.library@tate.org.uk</addressline><addressline>URL, General: http://www.tate.org.uk/</addressline><addressline>URL, Images: http://www.tate.org.uk/research/researchservices/picturelibrary/#copy</addressline><department/><repositoryid label="Accession number">N 05300</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but625.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT625.1.1.PD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'The Soul Hovering over the Body Reluctantly Parting with Life'</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="UI">(Butlin 625)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing is a preliminary sketch for <hi rend="i">The Soul Hovering over the Body</hi>, Object 9 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 7 in the Archive.</p></objnote><objsize>27.2 x 45.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote>
                   
                </objnote></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.07"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.09"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Two horizontal figures dominate this image. The upper figure is a gowned female, presumably the soul of the male below, facing forward and slightly down, with her head to the right of the image. Her legs are together and her ankles might be crossed. She has long, curly hair. Her arms are at her side but bent with her palms up and out relative to her body. This may be a gesture of surprise or mourning. She looks down at the figure beneath her. The lower figure is a muscular, nude male with short, curly hair. He may be wearing a wreath or crown of leaves and/or flowers. He lies, facing forward with his head to the right of the image. His legs are together with his left leg slightly bent. His genitals are clearly pictured. His right arm is at his side but bent to rest on a lyre below and to the right of his head. His eyes are closed and he is presumably dead. The round object below his lower torso may be a bowl or tambourine. A few lines right of the male figure's head do not clearly represent any motif, but might suggest a pillow or other bedding.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>soul</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>surprise</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two horizontal figures dominate this image. The upper figure is a gowned female, presumably the soul of the title, facing forward and slightly down, with her head to the right of the image. Her legs are together and her ankles might be crossed. She has long, curly hair. Her arms are at her side but bent with her palms up and out relative to her body. This may be a gesture of surprise or mourning. She looks down at the figure beneath her. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>wreath</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two horizontal figures dominate this image. The lower figure is a muscular, nude male with short, curly hair. He may be wearing a wreath or crown of leaves and/or flowers. He lies, facing forward with his head to the right of the image. His legs are together with his left leg slightly bent. His genitals are clearly pictured. His right arm is at his side but bent to rest on a lyre below and to the right of his head. His eyes are closed and he is presumably dead.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>lyre</characteristic><characteristic>tambourine</characteristic><characteristic>bowl</characteristic><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male figure's right upper arm and hand rest on a lyre.  The round object below his lower torso may be a bowl or a tambourine, the latter a continuation of the musical theme suggested by the lyre. These motifs do not appear in the water color of this design. A few lines right of the male figure's head do not clearly represent any motif, but might suggest a pillow or other bedding of the sort pictured in the water color version.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext>
                
            </phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>