<bad id="but635.1" type="wc" work="Death Pursuing the Soul Through the Avenues of Life" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="635"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Death Pursuing the Soul Through the Avenues of Life"><main>Death Pursuing the Soul Through the Avenues of Life</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 24KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 71KB to 1000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2014 William Blake Archive</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>October 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>Summer 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Eric Forster,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Sarah Jones,</name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name><name>Michele Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Death Pursuing the Soul Through the Avenues of Life</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist.  In 2009, Martin Butlin expressed the opinion that this work is a pencil drawing by Blake colored by someone else later in the nineteenth century.  In our opinion, the coloring was executed by Blake.  If another hand added any coloring, such work may have been executed by Thomas Hartley Cromek (a skilled artist) early in the drawing's history and confined to the face of the winged figure.  See the Editors' Notes for further comments.</role></origination><compdate value="1805">1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>24.6 x 11.3 cm.<note>The design has probably been trimmed, particularly along the top and right margins.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>24.6 x 11.3 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color over pencil<note>The drawing is primarily executed in shades of gray wash, but there are touches of blue (particularly evident on the right side of the winged figure's chest), blue-green (slight touches on the winged figure's face and on the wing above his left shoulder), and thin red lines on the neck of the descending woman.</note></medium><support>wove paper backed with another piece of wove paper</support><watermark>none visible</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1971</date><dealer>Charles Sessler, Inc.</dealer><price>$2750</price><note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by Robert Hartley Cromek in 1805 as part of Cromek's commission to Blake to produce illustrations for an edition of Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>; probably Cromek's wife, Elizabeth Hartley Cromek, by inheritance in 1812; their son, Thomas Hartley Cromek, probably until at least 1863; possibly with the dealer Francis Harvey in 1863 or bequeathed to a family member by T. H. Cromek upon his death in 1873; possibly George A. Smith by 1876; possibly the work sold Christie's, 16 July 1880, lot 119 (£1.15s. to the dealer Dowdeswell); Col. Fairfax-Rhodes; sold Sotheby's, 11 July 1934, lot 3, mistitled "Illustration to Urizen" (£40 to "Ulysses," a code name for the dealer Jacob Schwartz); George C. Smith, Jr.; his sister, Mrs. Artemas Holmes, probably by gift or inheritance no later than 1938; her estate, on consignment with the book and print dealer Charles Sessler, Inc., Philadelphia; acquired Aug. 1971 by Robert N. Essick ($2750).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline></repository></source><desc id="but635.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT635.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Death Pursuing the Soul Through the Avenues of Life</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 635)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This work was commissioned from Blake by Robert Hartley Cromek as part of his project to publish and illustrate an edition of Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>.  It is listed in Cromek's first prospectus, dated Nov. 1805, for that publication.  The back of the paper on which the drawing is mounted is inscribed by Thomas H. Cromek, Robert H. Cromek's son, "Illustration to 'Urizen' - a poem by William Blake - who also made this drawing -  It belonged to my father.  Thomas - H. Cromek."  The association with Blake's <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> is an error.  Apparently the drawing became detached from other designs for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> and was associated with <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> because of the Urizenic appearance of the winged figure.  In 2009, Martin Butlin stated that this "monochrome drawing" (sic) is a "pencil drawing" by Blake "gone over by someone else to make it more saleable in the later 19th century."  See <hi rend="i">William Blake's Watercolour Inventions in Illustration of</hi> The Grave <hi rend="i">by Robert Blair</hi>, edited with Essays and Commentary by Martin Butlin and an Essay on the Poem by Morton D. Paley (Lavenham: William Blake Trust, 2009) 23-24.  If the design was only a pencil sketch when Cromek acquired it, then it would have been the only design in that medium, rather than a tinted wash drawing or water color, listed in the Nov. 1805 first prospectus.  In our opinion, the washes and colors were applied by Blake.  If another hand added some washes, such work may have been executed early in the drawing's history by T. H. Cromek, a skilled watercolorist, and confined to the face of the winged figure. For further discussion see Robert N. Essick, "Attribution and Reproduction: <hi rend="i">Death Pursuing the Soul through the Avenues of Life</hi>," <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 45.2 (fall 2011): 66-71.</p></objnote><objsize>24.6 x 11.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="725"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The top half of the design is dominated by the figure of a bat-winged, nude, muscular male representing Death. He appears to be old, and has long hair and a beard. Death's mouth is open and his brow is furrowed as though in anger. His right arm is raised just above the horizontal, palm down; his left arm is at his side. He may have just thrown down the figure below. In his lowered left hand, he holds what appears to be a flame, perhaps of a torch, emanating beams of light. Death's right leg is bent, while his left is extended backward and may be on tiptoe. He appears to look forward, but perhaps also at the female figure in the bottom half of the design. The bottom half of the design is dominated by the gowned figure of a woman, facing down and away. This figure likely represents the Soul. She is bent so that her lower body faces right and her upper body hangs down over the edge of a step. She has long, slightly curly hair. Her arms are raised vertically relative to her body, with her fingers spread. Her left leg is bent at the knee. She is probably falling. The scene takes place in what appears to be a catacomb, constructed of blocks of stone. Death stands in an arched, shadowy passage at the top of a set of four stairs. The Soul hangs over the edge of a step over another arched, shadowy passage.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>Death</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>pursuing</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>throwing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>anger</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>torch</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The top half of the design is dominated by the figure of a bat-winged, nude, muscular male representing Death. He appears to be old, and has long hair and a beard. Death's mouth is open and his brow is furrowed as though in anger. His right arm is raised just above the horizontal, palm down; his left arm is at his side. He may have just thrown down the figure below. In his left hand, he holds what appears to be a flame, perhaps of a torch, emanating beams of light. Death's right leg is bent, while his left is extended backward and may be on tiptoe. He appears to look forward, but perhaps also at the female figure in the bottom half of the design. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Soul</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>hanging</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The bottom half of the design is dominated by the gowned figure of a woman, facing down and away. This figure likely represents the Soul. She is bent so that her lower body faces right and her upper body hangs down over the edge of a step. She has long, slightly curly hair. Her arms are raised vertically relative to her body, with her fingers spread. Her left leg is bent at the knee. She is probably falling. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene takes place in what appears to be a catacomb, constructed of blocks of stone. This represents the "Avenues of Life" of the title.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>arch</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Death stands in an arched, shadowy passage at the top of a set of four stairs. The Soul hangs over the edge of a step over another arched, shadowy passage.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>