<bad id="but612.1" type="mono" work="An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="612"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet"><main>An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
            </principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester
            
            </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 27KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 114KB to 953KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries <date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This work copyright © 2014 British Museum.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>Aug. 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake
               <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805(?)</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>10.3 x 7.8 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>11.6 x 9.2</leafsize><medium>pencil with gray and brown washes</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none<note>The leaf is stamped "J.D.F" (John Deffett Francis) in an oval below center.</note></pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1874</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis; given by Francis in Dec. 1874 to the British Museum.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 020-7323-8408</addressline><addressline>Fax: 020-7323-8999</addressline><addressline>Email: printsphoto@thebritishmuseum.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">1874,1212.106</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but612.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT612.1.1.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 612)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This design may be an alternative version of the title page for Blake's illustrations to <i>The Grave</i> or possibly a design for the "characteristic Frontispiece" Cromek listed in the first prospectus for his forthcoming publication.</p></objnote><objsize>10.3 x 7.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="680" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.02"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.01"/><related objectid="but611.1.wc.01"/><related objectid="but614r.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="bb515.1.comb.12" type="compare" copyid="bb515.1" bentley="B12"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male trumpeter hovers upside down in the center of the design. He may be a wingless angel descending to awaken the figures below. His body faces away and his head is bent back slightly, facing down; he likely looks at the figures in the flames below. His hair is short and may also be curly. The figure's legs are together and extend up and to the left, with his right leg bent. His arms are raised vertically with respect to his body with the right arm extended and the left bent. He holds and plays a trumpet. To either side of the central trumpeter are pencil outlines of two other trumpeters, perhaps also wingless angels. The leftmost figure faces down, body curved to the left and leg extended up and to the left. The rightmost figure faces right and down, leg extended up and to the left. Both figures appear to be bald and holding trumpets they may also play. Flames seem to extend out and up from the trumpet of the central male trumpeter. Dark clouds of smoke billow up from the fire in the bottom center of the design. The bottom of the design may be lined with rocks or perhaps even tombstones. At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of the design. The leftmost figure is visible mostly as a head facing forward and slightly right. He(?) may be nude and bald, and may be sitting with one leg drawn up on a rock or tombstone. The figure second from the left faces forward and looking slightly up and to the left. He(?) may be nude and bald, and may have his mouth open. He may be sitting or crouching on a rock or tombstone. The figure third from the left is visible only as a grimacing, bald head above a rock, mouth open and teeth visible. It faces forward. The figure third from the right is mostly visible as a head, facing forward. He(?) may have long hair and grasps the rock in front of him, perhaps trying to pull himself up. His mouth open and he may be afraid or in pain. The figure second from the right is visible as an upper body, facing forward and slightly left. His(?) head is bent back slightly, facing up. He may be bald and has his mouth open in pain or fear. The rightmost figure, only minimally represented, may be an upper body with legs drawn up. The figures with open mouths may be howling. The setting is probably a graveyard.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male trumpeter hovers upside down in the center of the design. He may be a wingless angel descending to awaken the figures below. His body faces away and his head is bent back slightly, facing down; he likely looks at the figures in the flames below. His hair is short and may also be curly. The figure's legs are together and extend up and to the left, with his right leg bent. His arms are raised vertically with respect to his body with the right arm extended and the left bent. He holds and plays a trumpet. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>descending</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To either side of the central trumpeter are pencil outlines of two other trumpeters, perhaps also wingless angels. The leftmost figure faces down, body curved to the left and leg extended up and to the left. The rightmost figure faces right and down, leg extended up and to the left. Both figures appear to be bald and holding trumpets they may also play while hovering upside down. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>graveyard</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Flames seem to extend out and up from the trumpet of the central male trumpeter. Dark clouds of smoke billow up from the fire in the bottom center of the design. The setting is probably a graveyard.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>tombstone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The bottom of the design may be lined with rocks or perhaps even tombstones. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of design. The leftmost figure is visible mostly as a head facing forward and slightly right. He(?) may be nude and bald, and may be sitting with one leg drawn up on a rock or tombstone.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>crouching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of design. The figure second from the left faces forward and looking slightly up and to the left. He(?) may be nude and bald, and may have his mouth open. He may be sitting or crouching on a rock. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>teeth</characteristic><characteristic>anger</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of design. The figure third from the left is visible only as a grimacing, bald head above a rock, mouth open and teeth visible. He may be howling. It faces forward. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>head</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>pulling</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>pain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of design. The figure third from the right is mostly visible as a head, facing forward. He(?) may have long hair and grasps the rock in front of him, perhaps trying to pull himself up. His mouth open and he may be howling in fear or pain. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>bald</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of design. The figure second from the right is visible as an upper body, facing forward and slightly left. His(?) head is bent back slightly, facing up. He may be bald and has his mouth open, perhaps howling in pain or fear. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>ghost</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least six figures, perhaps souls or ghosts, sit at the bottom of design. The rightmost figure, only minimally represented, may be sitting with legs drawn up and head down in a contracted posture.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext>
              
            </phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>