<bad id="but6.1" type="penink" work="Countess Aveline, Detail from Her Tomb" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin" catid="6" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Countess Aveline, Detail from Her Tomb">
                    <main>Countess Aveline, Detail from Her Tomb</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2015, Society of Antiquaries
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>        
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Countess Aveline, Detail from Her Tomb</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>anonymous
                    <role>delineator.  The gold coloring may have been added by someone other than Blake.  The inscriptions are not by Blake; see the Textual Transcription.</role>    
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1775.A">c. 1775<note>This monument was uncovered in the presbytery of Westminster Abbey in the summer of 1775 and was covered again by 1778.  Blake probably drew this design shortly after the monument was revealed.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>33.0 x 15.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>38.1 x 26.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink with shell gold<note>The gold tinting may have been added by someone other than Blake.  The inscription upper left is in pencil.  The collection mark of the Society of Antiquaries, stamped in black ink, appears along the lower left side of the triangular design.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its engraving for Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, first published by the Society of Antiquaries in 1780.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries</institution>
                <addressline>Burlington House</addressline>
                <addressline>Piccadilly</addressline>
                <addressline>London W1J 0BE</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)207 479 7080</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)207 287 6967</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: https://www.sal.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: admin@sal.org.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Library: +44 (0)207 479 7084</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Library: +44 (0)207 287 6967</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Library: library@sal.org.uk</addressline>
                
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 25</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but6.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT6.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Countess Aveline, Detail from Her Tomb</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 6)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>38.1 x 26.6 cm</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This drawing shows the ornament on the spandrels in the pediment of the canopy over the tomb of Countess Aveline in Westminster Abbey.  Swirling vegetative forms appear within an inverse triangular form with a concave upper boundary.  These forms, which appear to constitute a single branch or vine, originate in the upper left corner of the triangle. The branch extends rightward before curving down in a serpentine shape, where it divides into two branches in the middle of the triangle, with the leftmost branch curving to the left and up while the rightmost side extends further down before curving up and to the right.  Nine five-pointed leaves and fifteen bunches of berries extend from the main branch or vine.  An engraving that included this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published in Joseph Ayloffe, <hi rend="i">An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey</hi>, 1780, also published (or republished) as plate 31 in volume 2 of <hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi>, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>berry</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Swirling vegetative forms appear within an inverse triangular form with a concave upper boundary.  These forms, which appear to constitute a single branch or vine, originate in the upper left corner of the triangle. The branch extends rightward before curving down in a serpentine shape, where it divides into two branches in the middle of the triangle, with the leftmost branch curving to the left and up while the rightmost side extends further down before curving up and to the right.  Nine five-pointed leaves and fifteen bunches of berries extend from the main branch or vine.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but6.1.writtennumbers.01" justify="left">N 4<note>This pencil inscription is not by Blake.  It may have been added long after the execution of the drawing.  The number might be 14, with the first digit very lightly written and obscured by one of the vertical chain lines in the laid paper.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but6.1.pennumbers.02" justify="left">Detail from the Tomb of Aveline Countess of Lancaster on the Nr. Side of the Altar. Vet. Mon. Vol. II. pl. 31.<note>This pen and ink inscription is not by Blake.  "Vet. Mon. Vol. II. pl. 31" is a reference to volume 2 of *Vetusta Monumenta*, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.  An engraving that included this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published as plate 31 in that volume.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>