<bad id="but611.1" type="wc" work="An Angel with a Trumpet" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ycba" catalog="butlin" catid="611"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="An Angel with a Trumpet"><main>An Angel with a Trumpet</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 19KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 51KB to 989KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2014 Yale Center for British Art</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning, metadata collection, and color correction</change><date>February-May 2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                           <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke,</name><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*An Angel with a Trumpet*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist.  In his 1981 catalogue of Blake's paintings and drawings, Butlin states that "the colouring and degree of finish are slightly unusual for Blake's style at this period, but the provenance of this watercolour supports its authenticity" (volume 1, page 456).  In a 2009 publication, however, Butlin states that this work "is perhaps not by Blake."  See *William Blake's Watercolour Inventions in Illustration of* The Grave *by Robert Blair*, edited with Essays and Commentary by Martin Butlin and an Essay on the Poem by Morton D. Paley (Lavenham: William Blake Trust, 2009) 30.  This work was sold in 1910 (see the note on provenance) in a lot that included works by Thomas Butts, Jr.  Perhaps he executed this work, at least in part.</role></origination><compdate value="1805">c. 1805 (?)</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>16.7 x 7.0 cm.<note>This is the size of the drawing; the full leaf is shown here.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>19.8 x 10.4 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Yale Center for British Art</name><date>1975</date><dealer>John Baskett</dealer><price>£2,000</price><note>Thomas Butts, at an unknown time, probably from Blake or his wife Catherine; by inheritance in 1845 to Thomas Butts, Jr.; probably by inheritance in 1862 to Frederick J. Butts; probably his widow by inheritance in 1905; sold from the Butts family collection, Sotheby's, 22 March 1910, in lot 447 with drawings by Blake and prints by Thomas Butts, Jr. (£19.10s. to the dealer Robson and Co.); probably a private collector; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 16 Feb. 1949, in lot 16 with several drawings by other artists (£44 to L. G. Duke); sold Sotheby's, 29 April 1971, lot 12 (£2,000 to the dealer John Baskett acting for Paul Mellon); given by Mellon in 1975 to the Yale Center for British Art.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Yale Center for British Art</institution><addressline>1080 Chapel Street</addressline><addressline>Box 208280</addressline><addressline>New Haven, Connecticut 06520-8280</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1-203-432-2840</addressline><addressline>Fax: 1-203-432-7314</addressline><addressline>Email: ycba.info@yale.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: http://britishart.yale.edu</addressline><addressline>Email, Images: ycba.imaging@yale.edu</addressline><department>Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">B1975.4.44</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but611.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT611.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">An Angel with a Trumpet</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 611)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This ascending angel with a trumpet is very similar to the descending angel with a trumpet in Blake's title page design for Robert Blair's *The Grave*, executed as a water color in 1805 and engraved by Louis Schiavonetti for Robert H. Cromek's 1808 edition of Blair's poem.  This water color is thus associated with Cromek's 1805 commission for Blake's illustrations of *The Grave*.  It was not, however, one of Blake's water-color illustrations acquired by Cromek.  The verso is inscribed, not by Blake, "From the collection of Thomas Butts the artist's friend and patron."  It is possible that the design was conceived as a descending, rather than an ascending, figure.  See the Object Information page for a discussion of the attribution of this work to Blake and/or Thomas Butts, Jr.</p></objnote><objsize>19.8 x 10.4 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="650"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.02"/><related objectid="but612.1.wd.01"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.01"/><related objectid="but614r.1.penc.01"/><related objectid="bb515.1.comb.12" type="compare" copyid="bb515.1" bentley="B12"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male trumpeter, perhaps a wingless angel, hovers while ascending. His body faces forward with his genitals clearly visible. His head is bent back and faces up. His hair is short and may also be curly. The figure's legs are together and extend down and to the right. His arms are bent and are raised vertically. He holds and plays a trumpet with his hands together and the fingers of his right hand slightly spread. He appears to be looking upward.  A few pencil lines at the top of the design suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male trumpeter hovers, facing up and forward with his genitals clearly visible. He may be a wingless angel ascending. His head is bent back and faces up. His hair is short and may also be curly. The figure's legs are together and extend down and to the right. His left leg is bent slightly. His arms are also bent slightly and raised vertically. He holds and plays a trumpet or musical horn with his hands together and the fingers of his right hand slightly spread.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few pencil lines at the top of the design suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>