<bad id="but621r.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'Christ Descending into the Grave, with the Keys of Death and Hell'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="621r" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'Christ Descending into the Grave, with the Keys of Death and Hell'"><main>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'Christ Descending into the Grave, with the Keys of Death and Hell'</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 19KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 70KB to 1100KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2014 British Museum
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>October 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Gwen Kern, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>
                        Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'Christ Descending into the Grave, with the Keys of Death and Hell' 
                    </title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1805">1805 and later (recto), c. 1820-25 (verso)<note>The pencil drawing on the recto (Object 1) is a preliminary sketch for *Christ Descending into the Grave*, Object 2 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*.  Both this drawing and the water color can be dated to the fall of 1805.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 3 in the Archive.  The pen and ink drawing of a bird's head, lower right on Object 1, is not related to the *Grave* project and may be of a later date.  It is related to a similar head in *Jerusalem*, Plate 78.  The verso drawing (Object 2) is not related to the *Grave* illustrations and is probably of a considerably later date, c. 1820-25.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2 (recto followed by the verso)</objorder><objsize>23.6 x 18.5 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>23.6 x 18.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>pencil<note>The detail of the bird's head, lower right on Object 1, is in pen and ink.</note></medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>GATER 1805</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum</name><date>1874</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Early history unknown, but probably inherited at Blake's death by his wife Catherine in 1827 and then acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; H. A. Bright, probably acquired between 1863 and 1880; John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 020-7323-8408</addressline><addressline>Fax: 020-7323-8999</addressline><addressline>Email: printsphoto@thebritishmuseum.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">1874.12.12.112</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but621r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT621.1.1r.PD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": 'Christ Descending into the Grave, with the Keys of Death and Hell'</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="UI">(Butlin 621 recto)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This pencil drawing is a preliminary sketch for *Christ Descending into the Grave*, Object 2 among Blake's water color illustrations for Robert H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 3 in the Archive.  The pen and ink drawing of a bird's head, lower right, is not related to the *Grave* project and may be of a later date.  It is related to a similar head in *Jerusalem*, Plate 78. The British Museum collection stamp appears lower left.</p></objnote><objsize>23.6 x 18.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote>
                   
                </objnote></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.03"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.02"/><related objectid="jerusalem.e.illbk.78"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the image is the pen and ink sketch of a bird's head, facing right; it has a beak and crest and its visible eye is squinting. The design is dominated by the figure of Christ, a gowned male with long, curly hair and a beard. He faces forward. His mouth is slightly open and he appears to be looking at something in the distance. His left arm is down at his side, palm out; his right arm is bent with his hand on his chest.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Christ</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The design is dominated by the figure of Christ, a gowned male with long, curly hair and a beard. He stands, facing forward. His mouth is slightly open and he appears to be looking at something in the distance. His left arm is down at his side, palm out; his right arm is bent with his hand on his chest.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>crest</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic/><characteristic>bird</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right corner of the image is the pen and ink sketch of a bird's head, facing right; it has a beak and crest and its visible eye is squinting. </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>