<bad id="but616.1" type="wc" work="Second Alternative Design for Title-Page: A Spirit Rising from the Tomb" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="butlin" catid="616"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Second Alternative Design for Title-Page: A Spirit Rising from the Tomb"><main>Second Alternative Design for Title-Page: A Spirit Rising from the Tomb</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 28KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 88KB to 604KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2014 Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD creation</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color correction</change><date>May 2006</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Digital image acquisition, metadata collection</change><date>October 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Manager:</resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquisition, scanning and metadata collection</change><date>February 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Second Alternative Design for Title-Page: A Spirit Rising from the Tomb*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1806">1806</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>23.8 x 20.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>23.8 x 20.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink and water color</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name><date>1946</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Robert Hartley Cromek, acquired in 1806 from Blake as part of Cromek's project to publish an illustrated edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*; probably Cromek's wife, Elizabeth Hartley Cromek, by inheritance in 1812; their son, Thomas Hartley Cromek, until at least 1865; Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge by 1892, inserted (by Macgeorge?) in a copy of Cromek's 1808 edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave* (a pencil and wash portrait of Blake also inserted); the book with the drawings still inserted sold Sotheby's, 1 July 1924, lot 123 (£98 to the dealer Francis Edwards); the book and its inserted drawings offered by Edwards in Dec. 1924 for £150; Alice (Mrs. George Madison) Millard; George Clinton Ward; Louise Ward Watkins by 1936; Keith Spalding; the book and its inserted drawings given by Spalding to the Huntington Library in July 1946, the drawings removed from the book shortly thereafter.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution><addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline><addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1 626 405 2100</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 1 626 405 2191</addressline><addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 1 626 405 3477</addressline><addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: readerregistration@huntington.org</addressline><department>Art Division</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">000.30</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but616.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT616.1.1.WC"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Second Alternative Design for Title-Page: A Spirit Rising from the Tomb</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 616)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>Blake very probably executed this water color on commission from Robert Hartley Cromek as part of the latter's project to publish an illustrated edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*.  This design was not published in Cromek's 1808 volume.  The inscription on the tomb in the design ("A Series of Designs...Invented &amp; Drawn" rather than "Engraved") suggests that the design may have been intended as a unique title page for Blake's original water colors rather than as a preliminary drawing for an engraving.</p></objnote><objsize>23.8 x 20.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="600" height="650"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The center of the image is dominated by a large tomb or sepulchre, perhaps carved of marble. The top of the tomb is carved with a leafy vine design, with scalloped carvings above the title lettering. To either side of the base of the tomb is the stone or marble carving of a winged figure. The figure to the left of the tomb is a gowned female with bat-like wings. She wears a transparent veil over her head and sits, head down and eyes closed, facing left. Her left leg is bent underneath her, with her left foot visible beneath the hem of her gown. Her left arm rests on her left leg, and she holds a partially unfurled scroll in her left hand. Her right arm rests on her bent right leg, bent upward, with her right hand on her face. She may be mourning. The figure to the right of the tomb is a gowned female with butterfly-like wings. The right wing is marked with five circles. She sits, facing right, with her head bent down and her eyes closed. Her right leg is bent underneath her and her right foot is visible beneath the hem of her gown. Her right arm rests on her right leg. She has long hair that streams down the left side of her face; alternatively, this could be a veil. She may be mourning. On the top right side of the tomb is a cloth, perhaps a shroud left behind by the rising figure above. Dominating the top half of the image is a nude figure of a female with long, curly hair. She may be a soul rising from her tomb, as she trails a transparent cloth, perhaps her shroud. She faces forward and looks up, with her legs extended slightly to the left. Her left leg may be on tiptoe. Her arms are at her side with her hands together in a gesture of prayer or supplication. her lips may be slightly parted. The scene is backed with a partly cloudy sky. From the top center of the image, beams of light emanate downward, suggesting a sun or the light of heaven.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>marble</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>text</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>plinth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The center of the image is dominated by a large tomb or sepulchre, perhaps carved of marble. The top of the tomb is carved with a leafy vine design, with scalloped carvings above the title lettering. The tomb rests on a step or plinth.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>marble</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand on face</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>scroll</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To either side of the base of the tomb is the stone or marble carving of a winged figure. The figure to the left of the tomb is a gowned female with bat-like wings. She wears a transparent veil over her head and sits, head down and left eye closed, facing left. Her left leg is bent underneath her, with her left foot visible beneath the hem of her gown. Her left arm rests on her left leg, and she holds a partially unfurled scroll in her left hand. Her right arm rests on her bent right leg, bent upward, with her right hand on her face. She may be mourning. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>marble</characteristic><characteristic>statue</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>veil</characteristic><characteristic>mourning</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To either side of the base of the tomb is the stone or marble carving of a winged figure. The figure to the right of the tomb is a gowned female with butterfly-like wings. The right wing is marked with five circles. She sits, facing right, with her head bent down and her right eye closed. Her right leg is bent underneath her and her right foot is visible beneath the hem of her gown. Her right arm rests on her right leg. She has long hair that streams down the left side of her face; alternatively, this could be a veil. She may be mourning. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the top right side of the tomb is a cloth, perhaps a shroud left behind by the rising figure above. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Soul</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>cloth</characteristic><characteristic>shroud</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dominating the top half of the image is a nude figure of a female with long, curly hair. She may be a soul rising from her tomb, as she trails a transparent cloth, perhaps her shroud. She faces forward and looks up, with her legs extended slightly to the left. Her left leg may be on tiptoe. Her arms are at her side with her hands together in a gesture of prayer or supplication. Her lips may be slightly parted.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The scene is backed with a partly cloudy sky. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><illusobjdesc>From the top center of the image, beams of light emanate downward, suggesting a sun or the light of heaven.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="15"/><lg justify="left"><l n="but616.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="10">A Series of Designs:</l><l n="but616.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="10">Illustrative of</l><l n="but616.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="10">The Grave.</l><l n="but616.1.wc.01.04" justify="left" indent="10">a Poem</l><l n="but616.1.wc.01.05" justify="left" indent="10">by Robert Blair.</l><l n="but616.1.wc.01.06" justify="left" indent="10">Invented &amp; Drawn by William Blake</l><l n="but616.1.wc.01.07" justify="left" indent="10">1806</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>