<bad id="but623.1" type="penc" work="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'The Meeting of a Family in Heaven'" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="623" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Sketch for Robert Blair's 'The Grave': 'The Meeting of a Family in Heaven'"><main>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": "The Meeting of a Family in Heaven"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 27KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 87KB to 1000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2014 British Museum
      </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>April-May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>October 2001</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Gwen Kern, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Sketch for Robert Blair's "The Grave": "The Meeting of a Family in Heaven"</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="UI">(Butlin 623)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This drawing is an alternative preliminary sketch for *The Meeting of a Family in Heaven*, Object 17 among Blake's water color illustrations for R. H. Cromek's edition of Robert Blair's *The Grave*.  Luigi Schiavonetti's etching/engraving of the water color design was published in Cromek's 1808 volume; see Object 4 in the Archive.</p></objnote><objsize>22.5 x 29.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1100" width="700"/><objnote>
                   
                </objnote></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.04"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.17"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two groups of two figures embrace; this is presumably the family of the title. The leftmost figure of the group is a gowned female with long hair. She kneels facing left and leans forward. Her head is bent back slightly, with her arms raised vertically and wrapped around the neck of the male to the right. She has her one visible eye open, looking up and right. The rightmost figure of the group is an adult male, wearing a gown. He appears to be striding up a set of stairs; perhaps he just entered heaven. His right leg is bent with his left leg extended backward. He faces left and leans down slightly with his visible left arm raised at 135 degrees relative to his torso and embracing the adult female to the left. Beneath the two adult figures are two gowned children. The child on the left faces right and slightly away. It lunges with its left leg bent and its right leg extended backward. It may have short hair. It raises its right arm vertically, relative to its torso, to touch the waist of the male to the right. The second child, to the right, stands facing left. In the bottom right of the image is a set of two or three stairs, leading up from an open doorway. In the top left of the image stand two gowned figures of indeterminable gender, perhaps angels conversing. The leftmost figure faces right, and may have short hair. Its right arm is at its side but bent to hold the hand of the figure to the right, toward which it looks. The rightmost figure of the pair faces forward and left, looking at the figure to the left. Its left arm is at its side but bent slightly to hold the hand of the figure to the left. Two keys (to heaven?) dangle on a string below the figures' hands. </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>soul</characteristic><characteristic>family</characteristic><characteristic>mother</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two groups of two figures embrace; this is presumably the family of the title. The leftmost figure of the group is a gowned female with long hair. She kneels, facing left, and leans forward. Her head is bent back slightly, with her visible right arm raised vertically and wrapped around the neck of the male to the right. She has her one visible eye open, looking up and right. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>soul</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>father</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two groups of two figures embrace; this is presumably the family of the title. The rightmost figure of the group is an adult male, wearing a gown. He appears to be striding up a set of stairs; perhaps he just entered heaven. His right leg is bent with his left leg extended backward. He faces left and leans down slightly with his visible left arm raised at 135 degrees relative to his torso and embracing the adult female to the left. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>soul</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>lunging</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two groups of two figures embrace; this is presumably the family of the title. Beneath the two adult figures are two gowned children. The child on the left faces right and slightly away. It lunges with its left leg bent and its right leg extended backward. It may have short hair. It raises its right arm vertically, relative to its torso, to touch the waist of the male to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>spirit</characteristic><characteristic>soul</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the center of the image, two groups of two figures embrace; this is presumably the family of the title. Beneath the two adult figures are two gowned children. The child on the right stands, facing left.  The child may have short hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="D"><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>stairs</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>heaven</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom right of the image is a set of two or three stairs, leading up from an open doorway, presumably the entrance to heaven. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top left of the image stand two gowned figures of indeterminable gender, perhaps angels conversing. The leftmost figure faces right, and may have short hair. Its right arm is at its side but bent to hold the hand of the figure to the right, toward which it looks. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the top left of the image stand two gowned figures of indeterminable gender, perhaps angels conversing. The rightmost figure of the pair faces forward and left, looking at the figure to the left. Its left arm is at its side but bent slightly to hold the hand of the figure to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>key</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two keys (to heaven?) dangle on a string below the hands of the figures on the left.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>