<bad id="but649r.1" type="paint" work="The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding Leviathan" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="tate" catalog="butlin" catid="649" hidden="false">
<header>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt><title reg="The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding Leviathan"><main>The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding Leviathan</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
<principal>
<resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
<respstmt/>
<sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
<funder/>
</titlestmt>
<editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 500KB to 1800KB</extent>
<publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2021</date></publicationstmt>
  <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
  <updatestmt>
The William Blake Archive is pleased to launch Works in Preview, a new wing presenting designs that are among Blake's largest and most complex. Instead of waiting until the details of the designs are fully encoded—which makes them more fully searchable but can take years to complete—the Archive is presenting the designs in an environment that enables viewers to enlarge them many times their true size to reveal details not previously visible in any reproductions. Viewers zoom in or out by using the Preview window’s "plus" or "minus" buttons, by moving two fingers up or down on the track pad, or by using a mouse’s wheel; viewers move an image by clicking and dragging. Images can also be examined in Full Screen mode, which provides the largest display and is ideal for external monitors. In Preview mode, viewers return to the whole design as initially displayed by clicking Home; in Full Screen mode, they return by clicking Exit Full Screen. Both viewing modes are accompanied by a slider that lightens and darkens the image, enabling users to see details long obscured by darkened paints and varnishes. See the video tutorial on viewing Works in Preview.<lb/>
                <lb/> Our new wing opens with the five extant paintings from Blake's 1809 exhibition: <hi rend="i"
                    >The Spiritual Form of Pitt</hi> (c. 1805), <hi rend="i"
                    >The Spiritual Form of Nelson</hi> (c. 1805-09), and <hi rend="i"
                    >The Bard</hi> (c. 1809) from Tate Britain; <hi rend="i"
                    >Satan Calling Up His Legions, an Experiment Picture</hi> (c. 1799-1805) from the Victoria and Albert Museum; and <hi rend="i"
                    >Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty Pilgrims on Their Journey to Canterbury</hi> (c. 1808) from Pollok House, Glasgow. These five paintings were executed in opaque water-miscible colors on canvas, many heightened with gold, which appear to have been Blake's first use of gold in any of his works. These paintings are usually referred to as "temperas," though Blake called them "frescos" and technically they are a form of "distemper," because the colors were mixed with glue. In the <hi rend="i"
                    >Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, which accompanied the exhibition, Blake defined his new mode of painting as "portable fresco" and discusses the paintings under numbers 1, 2-4, and 9. To these works we are adding <hi rend="i"
                    >Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi> from Petworth House, a later version of the design that Blake mentions in the catalogue (p. 54). We are also publishing the list of Blake's works at Petworth House and Pollok House, which can be found among our Collection Lists in the Resources for Further Research section of the Archive.<lb/>
                <lb/> More designs will enter Works in Preview in the near future, including <hi rend="i"
                    >The Spiritual Condition of Man</hi>, <hi rend="i"
                    >Hervey’s Meditations</hi>, <hi rend="i"
                    >Spenser’s Fairie Queene</hi>, <hi rend="i"
                    >The Sea of Time and Space</hi>, and multiple versions of <hi rend="i"
                    >Visions of the Last Judgment</hi>. The medium, size, date, provenance, and location of each design is given in the Work Information link under the image; also accompanying each design are Editors' Notes and a link to the Lightbox, where images can be moved, rotated, resized, and cropped.<lb/>
                <lb/>As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing
                no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible
                by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester,
                the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt>
<notesstmt/>
</filedesc>
<userestrict>Copyright © <date>2021</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2021 Tate Collection</userestrict>
<encodingdesc/>
<profiledesc/>
<revisiondesc>
  <changestmt>
    <change>BAD created and publication in preview mode</change>
    <date>January–March 2021</date>
    <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester; 
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and 
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf, </name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Natasha Bharucha, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer, </name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian, </name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green, </name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom, </name>
                    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
                    <name>Rob Rich, </name>
                    <name>Madeline Rose, </name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
                    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
                    <name>Iftekhar Uddin, </name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl </name>
                </respstmt>
  </changestmt>
  <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired</change>
                <date>July 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>
                    University of Rochester; 
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and 
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William S. Shaw</name>        
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
</revisiondesc>
</header>
        <objdesc>
        <source>
        <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
        <title>*The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding Leviathan*</title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role>
        <role>delineator, </role>
        <role>colorist</role>
        </origination>
        <compdate value="1805.B">c.1805-09</compdate>
        </objdescid>
        <objinfo>
         <numberobj>1</numberobj>
         <objsize>76.2 x 62.5 cm.</objsize>
         <medium>water-based tempera with a glue and/or gum binder and with some pen and ink outlining</medium>
         <support>canvas</support>
         <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
         <framelines>none</framelines>
         </objinfo>
         <provenance n="1"><name>Tate Collection</name>
               <date>1914</date>
               <dealer>none recorded</dealer>
               <price>not recorded</price>
               <note>Acquired from Blake by Thomas Butts; by inheritance to Thomas Butts, Jr., in 1845; sold from the collection of Thomas Butts, Jr., Foster and Son auction, London, 29 June 1853, lot 70 (&#163;1.2s. to "Robinson," probably a dealer); T. W. Jackson by no later than 1876; sold by the executors of Jackson's estate in 1914 to the Tate Gallery, now Tate Collection.</note>
               </provenance>
               <repository><institution>Tate Collection</institution>
               <repositoryid label="Accession number">N03006</repositoryid>
               </repository>
               </source>
                              
<desc id="but649r.1.pt.01" dbi="BUT649.1.1r.PT">
<objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding Leviathan</title>,
<objid>
<objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
<objcode code="U1">(Butlin 649)</objcode>
</objid>
</objtitle>
<physdesc desclevel="brief">
<objnote><p>Blake included this tempera painting in his 1809 exhibition, number I in the accompanying [*Descriptive Catalogue*](http://www.blakearchive.org/copy/bb32.d?descId=bb32.d.te.05), and in the 1812 exhibition of the Associated Painters in Water Colors, number 280 in the accompanying *Catalogue of the Fifth Annual Exhibition by the Associated Painters in Water Colors*.</p></objnote>
<objsize>76.2 x 62.5 cm.</objsize>
<windowsize width="780" height="600"/></physdesc>
                                             
                                                                           
</desc>
</objdesc>
</bad>
