
<bad id="but7.1" type="wc" work="" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin" catid="7">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="King Sebert, the North Front of His Monument">
                    <main>
                        King Sebert, the North Front of His Monument</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 25KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Society of Antiquaries, London.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *King Sebert, the North Front of His Monument*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1775.B">c. 1775<note>The north side of this monument in Westminster Abbey was uncovered in in the summer of 1775.  Blake probably drew this design shortly after this side of the monument was revealed.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>36.8 x 28.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>39.0 x 28.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The work is numbered in pencil "I." top right and "N<hi rend="supercript">o</hi>. 4" top center.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>3</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its engraving for Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, first published by the Society of Antiquaries in 1780.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries, London</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 29</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but7.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT7.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">King Sebert, the North Front of His Monument</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="B1">(BUT7.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The collection stamp of the Society of Antiquaries appears bottom center below the design.  A monochrome wash replica (Butlin 15) of this water color is in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.  An engraving of this design was published in Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, Plate 4 (1780), and in *Vetusta Monumenta*, volume 2 of c. 1789, Plate 32.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>39.0 x 28.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>On a base of stone blocks sits a wooden monument with a large, rectangular, paneled seat. On the side of the monument closest to the viewer, four posts extend vertically from the stone base and terminate in pointed, decorative finials. The exterior left and right walls(?) of the structure are visible just outside the leftmost and rightmost posts; these walls extend above the rest of the structure and may also be decorated near their tops. The monument's roof is decorated with five additional pointed posts that appear between four arches that feature trefoil designs below triangular points. The decorative tracery of each arch may be made of gold or gilded. Additional lower arches appear faintly inside the monument, forming its ceiling. The back wall of the monument is divided into four (stone?) panels. The third panel from the left features a decorative design. Two figures are painted onto the background panels, one on far left panel and one on the third panel from the left. The figures wear long-sleeved, floor-length gowns and robes. Both have curly hair and wear similar crowns, and both hold scepters over their right shoulders. The figure at left, who likely represents King Sebert, is bearded and looks downward as he faces right toward the other figure. The king at right, who likely represents Henry III, stands erect and gazes at the King Sebert, pointing toward him with the spread fingers of his gloved left hand. Three (stone?) figureheads are affixed to pillars near head-height of the two kings. All three have curly hair. The crowns on the two outer figureheads suggest they may be kings. The central head wears a pointed collar and a crown or hat resembling a miter, perhaps representing a bishop or even the pope. The design represents the north front of the monument of Sebert in Westminster Abbey.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="structure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The main lower section of the monument forms a wooden seat with four horizontal panels in front and topped with a bevelled wooden lid. The entire monument, including this wooden seat, four central pillars, and exterior walls, rests on a base made from stone blocks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four narrow (wooden?) posts or pillars extend upward from the stone base and culminate in decorative finials. The two outermost posts are plainer and extend higher than the others, but they culminate in more decorative spires. The others are segmented near the two main figures' feet and appear to be fluted as they rise vertically. The exterior left and right walls(?) of the structure are visible just outside the leftmost and rightmost posts; these walls extend above the rest of the structure and may also be decorated near their tops.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tracery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The monument's roof is decorated with five additional pointed posts that appear between four arches that feature trefoil designs below triangular points. The decorative, spiky tracery of each arch may be made of gold or gilded. Recessed vaulted arches (fainter but still decorative) appear above the monument's seat and form a ceiling above the two main figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>trefoil</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Decorative trefoils appear above the four arches but below their triangular points.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The back wall of the monument is divided into four main panels. The third panel from the left features a decorative design behind the figure of Henry III. The gray color of all four panels suggests that they may be made of stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure of a crowned man is painted onto the leftmost panel forming the back wall of the monument. He likely represents King Sebert. The king's long-sleeved gown extends to the floor and is partially covered by a long, flowing robe with a bordered, curling hem. His hair and beard are curly, and he wears crown decorated with leaves or crosses. The king faces forward and to the right, bending with his upper body toward the pillar at his right with his head and eyes downward. His left arm is bent upward. His right arm is bent with his forearm raised horizontally, and he holds in his right hand a scepter that extends from his waist over his right shoulder, where it may rest.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>glove</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Henry the Third</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The painted figure of another crowned man, who likely represents Henry III, is visible on the third background panel from the left. He wears a long-sleeved, floor-length robe secured at the waist with a belt or cord. A bordered robe covers his shoulders but remains open in front. This king wears a crown atop short, curly hair. He faces forward, but his head turns to the left, and he appears to gaze toward the other king. He points toward this figure with his raised left hand. His fingers are spread, and he wears a glove that may be decorated with a cross or other emblem. His right arm is bent slightly at his side, and his right gloved hand holds a scepter that extends over (and may rest on) his right shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figureheads, perhaps made of stone, adorn the monument near head-height of the two larger figures. The leftmost figure appears to be affixed to pillar just left of center.  A split collar appears faintly on th pillar below the head. He has curly hair and wears a crown, suggesting that he may represent another king.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bishop</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figureheads, perhaps made of stone, adorn the monument near head-height of the two larger figures. The central head adorns the downward point where two decorative arches meet. The shape of this head, as well as its headwear, differentiate it from the other two figureheads. Below the head extends a large, pointed collar, and atop its curly head sits a crown or hat that resembles a miter. This headwear suggests that the figure may represent a bishop or even the pope.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three figureheads, perhaps made of stone, adorn the monument near head-height of the two larger figures. The rightmost figure appears to be affixed to the pillar just right of center.  A split collar appears faintly on the pillar below the head. He has curly hair and wears a crown, suggesting that he may also be a king. He is similar (though not identical) to the stone figurehead at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Each standing figure holds a scepter in his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design represents the north front of the monument of Sebert in Westminster Abbey.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.01" justify="left" indent="45">I.<note>This pencil inscription was probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.02" justify="left" indent="10">N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 4.<note>This pencil inscription was probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <vspace extent="6"/>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.03" justify="left" indent="44">foot  I<note>This inscription and line 4, both in pen and ink, record the height of the monument.  They are written vertically along the right side of the design.  These inscription were probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                    <p n="but7.1.1.wc.04" justify="left" indent="44">13: 9.<note>See the note to line 3.</note></p>
                <vspace extent="6"/>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.05" justify="left" indent="20">foot  I<note>This inscription and line 6, both in pen and ink, record the width of the monument.  These inscriptions were probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.06" justify="left" indent="20">12. 6.<note>See the note to line 5.</note></p>
                <vspace extent="2"/>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.07" justify="left" indent="45">Basire del. 1775.<note>This pen and ink inscription, a reference to or signature of Blake's engraving master James Basire, was probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <p n="but7.1.1.wc.08" justify="left">The North front of the Monument of King Sebert, on the South side of the Alter in Westminster Abbey - vide Vetust. Mon. Vol. II. plate XXXII.<note>This pen and ink inscription is probably not by Blake.  "Vetust. Mon. Vol. II. plate XXXII" is a reference to volume 2 of *Vetusta Monumenta*, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.  An engraving of this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published as plate 32 in that volume.</note></p>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>