<!DOCTYPE bad PUBLIC "-//University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill::Carolina Digital Library and Archives//DTD bad.dtd (Blake Archive Description) 2005//EN//XML" "http://www.blakearchive.org/blake/bad.dtd">
<bad id="but79r.1" type="penc" work="The Resurrection of the Dead" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="79r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Resurrection of the Dead">
                    <main>The Resurrection of the Dead</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 William Blake Archive
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>April-May 2014</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2012</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                    <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                    <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Bihan Zhang</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Resurrection of the Dead
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author.  Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription, lower right.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.4 x 24.3 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.4 x 24.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The inscription, lower right, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and ink.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>"Pro Patria," lion rampant, and Britannia</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>2011</date>
                <dealer>John Windle</dealer>
                <price>$15,000</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his Nov. 1882 catalogue, item 346 with 39 other works (&#163;36), catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, item 13843, same group and price, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Works on the Fine Arts</hi> of Oct. 1883, item 13843, same group and price, and catalogue of <hi rend="i">William Blake's Original Drawings</hi> of May 1885, no item number, same group and price; sold by Quaritch on 30 June 1886 to W. Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, lot 73 with two other works by Blake and one by his brother Robert (&#163;18.18s. to the dealer Maggs Bros. Ltd.); George Goyder, sold by him or placed on consignment with Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons; sold 1966 to Gwen Mond, Lady Melchett; sold from her collection, Christie's, 9 Nov. 1971, lot 79, titled "The Deluge" (&#163;170.8s.6d. to R. D. McDonald); sold Christie's, 17 Nov. 1992, lot 16 (&#163;7150 to Salander-O'Reilly Galleries, New York); sold Sotheby's, 4 Dec. 2008, lot 120 (&#163;3500 to the dealer John Windle); offered by Windle in his catalogue 46 of Oct. 2009, item 2 ($47,500); acquired Jan. 2011 from Windle by Robert N. Essick ($15,000).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena, California</addressline>
                
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but79r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT79.1.1r.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Resurrection of the Dead</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 79 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote><p>The verso of this leaf bears pencil sketches for Blake's 1802 <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (the verso sketches not in Butlin because not discovered until 2009).  This recto sketch is probably a variant preliminary drawing for a wash drawing, <hi rend="i">The Resurrection of the Dead or The Last Trumpet</hi> (Butlin 617, listed as untraced since 1922) in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, accession number 2011.448.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>18.4 x 24.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This drawing shows the resurrection of the dead (Revelation 20).  A trumpeting figure flies or hovers in the upper half of the drawing above several figures, all visible from approximately the waist up, some of whom raise their arms upward in this resurrection scene.  These figures may emerge from the ground or a body of water (see "the sea gave up the dead," Revelation 20:13).  The above figure appears to fly in from the right and face forward.  It may wear a gown; both arms are raised horizontally and extended to hold the end of a trumpet into which the figure blows.  Lines emerging from the musical instrument may indicate sound or, alternatively, suggest surrounding clouds.  In the lower right quadrant, a group of at least five figures huddle together.  The leftmost of these appears to be a woman (perhaps with long hair arranged in a bun?) who faces right with eyes raised.  She holds a short-haired infant or child who raises its bent right arm at approximately 135 degrees.  Directly to the right of the female figure's head, an adult male's head is visible also facing right and up.  He has short hair and may reach his right arm around the female at left, resting his hand on her right shoulder.  A fourth, smaller figure (perhaps a child or adolescent?) is visible directly below the male's head; this figure faces right, perhaps with eyes closed, and raises its left arm at 135 degrees.  The rightmost figure in this group is the least clear but a head and shoulders appear to be visible behind and to the right of the adult male.  To the left of this group in the bottom center of the drawing, a pair of nude male figures, one in front of the other, raise their arms vertically with fingers spread.  Like the figures to their right, they face right and up.  The mouth of the figure closer to the viewer is open, and he appears to have a beard.  There may be a third group of figures in the lower left quadrant but the details of these figures are indistinct.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trumpeter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A trumpeting figure flies or hovers in the upper half of the drawing.  With body horizontal, the figure appears to fly in from the right and face forward, perhaps with eyes turned down to look at the figures below.  He(?) may wear a gown.  Both arms are raised horizontally and extended to hold the end of a trumpet into which the figure blows.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The flying figure in the upper half of the drawing holds a trumpet that he appears to play.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The swirling lines that emerge from the bell of the trumpet played by the flying figure in the upper half of the composition may indicate sound or, alternatively, suggest surrounding clouds.  Curved lines below the figure in the upper right quadrant may also represent clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>huddled</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right quadrant, a group of at least five figures, who may represent a family, huddle together.  The heads, shoulders, and arms of these figures are the only body parts visible as they may emerge from the ground or the "sea" (see Revelation 20.:13) in this resurrection scene.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure in the group lower right appears to be a woman (perhaps with long hair arranged in a bun?) who faces right with eyes raised.  She may be the mother if the group is a family as her bent right arm supports an infant or child.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost female figure holds a short-haired infant or child who faces right and up and raises its bent right arm at approximately 135 degrees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Directly to the right of the female figure's head, an adult male's head is visible also facing right and up with eyes raised.  He has short hair and may reach his right arm around the female at left, resting his hand on her right shoulder in an embrace.  He may be the father if this group is a family.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A fourth, smaller figure (perhaps a child or adolescent?) is visible directly below the male's head; this figure faces right, perhaps with eyes closed, and raises its bent left arm at 135 degrees.  Some (but not all) of the figure's fingers are extended, perhaps in a gesture of pointing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure in the group at lower right is the least clear, but a head and shoulders appear to be visible behind and to the right of the adult male.  This figure may wear a hat or have short hair(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the bottom center of the drawing, a pair of nude male figures, one in front of the other, raise their bent arms vertically with fingers spread.  Like the figures to their right, they face right and up with eyes raised and appear to emerge from the ground or the "sea" (see Revelation 20:13).  The mouth of the figure closer to the viewer is open, and he appears to have a beard.  He may lean slightly to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the bottom center of the drawing, a pair of nude male figures, one in front of the other, raise their bent arms vertically with fingers spread.  Like the figures to their right, they face right and up with eyes raised and appear to emerge from the ground or the "sea" (see Revelation 20:13).  The figure further from the viewer may be bearded; he leans to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cluster of lines lower left may be two or more figures emerging from the earth or the "sea" (see Revelation 20:13).  Perhaps their heads and upper bodies are visible, but the details are unclear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="5"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but79r.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="46">Drawn by William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but79r.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="48">Vouched by Fred<hi rend="superscript">k</hi>. Tatham</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>