<bad id="but773.1" type="penink" work="The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Destruction of Jerusalem" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="773" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Destruction of Jerusalem">
                    <main>The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Destruction of Jerusalem</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Destruction of Jerusalem
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1821">c. 1821<note>The dating is uncertain.  A date of c. 1821 recommends itself because Blake's only published wood engravings appeared that year in Robert John Thornton's edition of <hi rend="i">The Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>12.5 x 8.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>12.5 x 8.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>India ink over pencil</medium>
                <support>wood block<note>The wood grain appears as reddish-brown curving lines throughout the design.  These are particularly noticeable above and to the right of the head of the central figure.  There is also a brown flaw in the wood curving extending from the central figure's raised right wrist toward the right.</note>
                </support>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1939</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Acquired directly from Blake or his wife Catherine by John Linnell; sold by the Linnell family trustees, Christie's, 2 Dec. 1938, lot 63 (£157.10s. to the National Art Collections Fund); presented by the Fund to the British Museum in 1939.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1967,0617.10</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but773.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT773.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Destruction of Jerusalem</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 773)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>According to Christie's catalogue of 2 Dec. 1938, lot 63, the back of the wood block is inscribed in ink, "A drawing on Wood by Wm. Blake—for J. Linnell."  This inscription is now covered by a frame.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>12.5 x 8.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>An illustration of the biblical narrative from the Book of Isaiah 29:1-6, this scene depicts a seated Isaiah in the foreground as the destruction of Jerusalem (called "Ariel" in the biblical passage) he foretells occurs in the background.  Wearing a long gown with an unbuttoned collar, Isaiah sits facing forward on a stone with legs bent and both bare feet visible beneath his gown.  He has long, curly hair and a beard; his mouth is open, suggesting he is speaking.  His right arm is raised vertically, palm forward, and with his left, which is by his side, he points toward text written on a partially unfurled scroll.  An area of radiance out of which beams of light extend encircles Isaiah's head.  In the upper half of the scene, a castellated wall (presumably of Jerusalem) stretches the width of the drawing and flames appear both above and below it.  At the left terminus of the wall, a group of soldiers (Romans in the narrative) face right.  The closest of these sits atop a horse.  A standing solider is visible to the right of the horse's head and the presence of at least six vertical pikes or spears suggests additional soldiers.  At the right end of the wall, a group of figures, the first two a man and woman with arms raised vertically, appear to run rightward, as if fleeing from the soldiers.  These are likely the Jews fleeing the destruction of Jerusalem.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prophet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Isaiah</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An illustration of the biblical narrative from the Book of Isaiah 29:1-6, this scene depicts a seated Isaiah in the foreground as the destruction of Jerusalem he foretells occurs in the background.  Wearing a long gown with an unbuttoned collar, Isaiah sits facing forward on a stone with legs bent and both bare feet visible beneath the serpentine folds of his gown.  He has long, curly hair and a beard; his mouth is open, suggesting he is speaking.  His right arm is raised vertically, palm out and vertical. With his left, which is by his side, he points toward text written on a partially unfurled scroll.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <illusobjdesc>light</illusobjdesc>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An area of radiance out of which beams of light extend encircles Isaiah's head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>With his left hand, Isaiah points to text on a partially unfurled scroll which rests on a stone lower right.  Marks on the scroll may indicate Hebrew letters, although these do not constitute a legible text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Isaiah sits on a large stone just above the bottom edge of the design.  The scroll to the right also rests on a stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Jerusalem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ariel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the upper half of the scene, a castellated wall of Jerusalem (called Ariel in the biblical text illustrated) stretches the width of the drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>riding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Roman</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the left terminus of the wall, a group of soldiers (Romans in the narrative) face right.  The closest of these sits atop a horse with right leg bent and right arm raised horizontally, likely pointing toward the group of figures at right.  A standing soldier is visible to the right of the horse's head and the presence of at least six vertical pikes or spears suggests additional soldiers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="A">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The closest soldier in the group at upper left rides a horse that faces right. Although its rider extends his arm rightward, the animal leans in the opposite direction, away from the sprouting flames.  Its mouth is open, giving it a fearful expression.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Although only two soldiers are visible in the upper left corner, the presence of at least six vertical pikes or spears suggests additional soldiers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the right end of the wall, a group of figures appear to run rightward, as if away from the soldiers.  These are likely the Jews fleeing the destruction of Jerusalem.  This group may be a family with a mother and father (center) and two children.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the right end of the wall, a group of figures appear to run rightward, as if away from the soldiers.  These are likely the Jews fleeing the destruction of Jerusalem.  The first adult figure from the right, a nude male figure faces right but turns his head up to look left.  His arms are raised vertically with palms facing up and fingers spread.  With left leg bent at the knee and right extended backward, he appears to run or flee to the right.  His mouth may be open.  If the group of fleeing figures is a family, he is likely the father.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the right end of the wall, a group of figures appear to run rightward, as if away from the soldiers.  These are likely the Jews fleeing the destruction of Jerusalem.  To the left of the nude male figure, a gowned female figure with long curly hair faces right but turns her head up to look left.  Echoing the posture of her companion, her arms are raised vertically with palms facing up and fingers spread.  Her right leg is bent and the knee and left extended backward as she runs or flees to the right.  If the group of fleeing figures is a family, she is likely the mother.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the right end of the wall, a group of figures appear to run rightward, as if away from the soldiers.  These are likely the Jews fleeing the destruction of Jerusalem.  The leftmost figure in this group is a child or adolescent who is positioned behind the adult female figure and thus only visible from the torso up.  Like the two adults, the child appears to face right but turn its head up to look left.  The figure appears to have short hair though the gender is indeterminate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the right end of the wall, a group of figures appear to run rightward, as if away from the soldiers.  These are likely the Jews fleeing the destruction of Jerusalem.  The rightmost figure in this group is a young child who, like the other figures in the group, faces right but turns its head up to look left.  The child may have its left arm raised vertically and appears to run or flee right with one leg bent forward at the knee and the other extended backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>