<bad id="but78v.1" type="penc" work="Man with Arms Upraised, Perhaps the Resurrection" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="78v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Man with Arms Upraised, Perhaps the Resurrection">
                    <main>Man with Arms Upraised, Perhaps the Resurrection</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life as an artist.  Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk.  Preliminary work with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]" (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…." (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). 
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works. Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927).
<lb/>
<lb/>
The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* ( Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work courtesy of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
<change>Final proofing and publication</change>
<date>October 2018</date>
<respstmt>
<resp>Editors:</resp>
<name>Morris Eaves,</name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick,</name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
<name>Ashley Reed,</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Erin Francisco,</name>
<name>Ani Govjian,</name>
<name>Alison Harper,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Rob Rich,</name>
<name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
<name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
<name>Emily Tronson,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
</changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>July 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Man with Arms Upraised, Perhaps the Resurrection*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>44.5 x 32.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>44.5 x 32.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history not known; William A. White by no later than 1905; acquired by A. S. W. Rosenbach shortly after White's death in 1927; Lessing J. Rosenwald by no later than 1939; given by Rosenwald in 1943 to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <addressline>Constitution Avenue NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline>
                <addressline>Washington, DC 20565</addressline>
                <addressline>Mailing Address: 2000B South Club Drive, Landover, Maryland 20785</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-202-737-4215</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Print Study Rooms: 1-202-842-6380</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 1-202-842-6126</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Visual Services: http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.3.9003.b</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but78v.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT78.1.1v.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Man with Arms Upraised, Perhaps the Resurrection</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 78 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote><p>For the drawing on the recto, see *A Warring Angel*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>44.5 x 32.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A male figure who has long hair and a beard stands or walks forward with both arms upraised.  He appears to point upward with the index finger of his left hand and turn his head slightly to the right.  He wears a long gown that ends in serpentine swirls of fabric around his feet.  There may be another prostrate figure in the foreground.  The upright figure's right foot is visible, suggesting he is stepping forward with this foot.  There are suggestions of other forms on each side and behind the main figure who may be a sketch of Christ at the Resurrection.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A male figure who has long hair and a beard stands or walks forward with both arms upraised.  He appears to point upward with the index finger of his left hand and turn his head slightly to the right.  He wears a long gown that ends in serpentine swirls of fabric around his feet.  His right foot is visible, suggesting he is stepping forward with this foot.  Rounded forms above his head may be an alternative position for the figure's head and shoulders.  Similarly, a few curving lines right of the figure's lower legs may be an alternative sketch for the lower reaches of his garment.  The figure may be a sketch of Christ at the Resurrection.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be a second figure in this scene lying prostrate in the foreground below the standing figure's feet.  This form is almost impossible to make out in this drawing however.  Swirling lines above this figure suggest a cloud or perhaps a garment such as a cloak.  He(?) may be rising, with one arm raised.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
