<bad id="but769.1" type="mono" work="Drawings for The Pastorals of Virgil" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick fitzwilliam morgan" catalog="butlin" catid="769"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Drawings for &#34;The Pastorals of Virgil&#34;"><main>Drawings for "The Pastorals of Virgil"</main>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
            </principal><respstmt>
            </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester
            
            </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 53KB; 14 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 43KB to 127KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives <date>January 2011</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's illustrations to Robert John Thornton's edition of <hi rend="i">The Pastorals of Virgil</hi> (1821) and a selection of his preliminary drawings for his Virgil wood engravings.  The texts and images in both groups are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.
                <lb/><lb/>
                    When planning a third edition of his successful school text of Virgil's <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi>, Robert John Thornton employed Blake to contribute some of the new designs for the two-volume work.  His assignment was to illustrate Ambrose Philips' English "imitation" of Virgil's first eclogue.  Blake produced four small designs as relief etchings on a single copperplate, but these were rejected by Thornton.  There may have been several reasons, including the unconventional style of etching, the semi-nudity of some of the figures, and the difficulties letterpress printers would have encountered with such an unusual matrix.  Apparently Blake was asked to prepare wood engravings, a medium in which he had never before worked, instead of relief etchings.  He executed a series of at least twenty-one pen, pencil, and wash preliminary drawings; these were probably approved by Thornton.  The wood engravings that Blake produced from them, however, were far less conventional.  Thornton was again taken aback by Blake's bold transgression of contemporary styles and sensibilities.  Several influential artists, including John Linnell and Sir Thomas Lawrence, commended Blake's work; their opinions convinced Thornton to print them in his 1821 edition.  Three designs were engraved by a journeyman for the sake of comparison with Blake's own productions in wood, and Thornton added a statement below Blake's first design implying his hesitations about Blake's artistry.  Pre-publication proofs of Blake's wood engravings show that each group of four were cut on a single block; these were cut apart, slightly reduced in size on all four sides, and printed with brief letterpress captions.  This format, as published in Thornton's Virgil, is preserved in our reproductions.
                <lb/><lb/>
                    In addition to his original wood engravings, Blake contributed six copperplate intaglio engravings picturing famous classical figures.  He also executed a reduced drawing, perhaps directly on the woodblock, based on a painting by Nicolas Poussin.  This was cut in the block by John Byfield.  All these materials are included in our reproductions of Thornton's Virgil.  In addition, the relief etching of four designs, the woodblock of Blake's first wood engraving, and the pre-publication proofs of two groups of designs before they were separated are available under Related Works in the Archive on the Show Me menu for Objects 5-7.
                <lb/><lb/>
                    Twenty of Blake's preliminary drawings for his wood engravings, all executed in monochrome wash, were sold at auction from the Linnell collection in 1918.  These are now widely dispersed; seven are untraced and one drawing in the group was not engraved.  We are now publishing a selection of seven of these drawings and plan to add more as they become available.  
                <lb/><lb/>
                    Although small in size and almost rejected by the man who commissioned them, Blake's Virgil wood engravings have been among his most influential works.  The young artists who gathered around Blake in his final years, including Samuel Palmer, George Richmond, and Edward Calvert, were deeply inspired by the Virgil engravings.  Palmer called them "visions of little dells, and nooks, and corners of Paradise"—an encomium that ignores the darker implications of some designs.  Several twentieth-century British artists, including Graham Sutherland, were also influenced by Blake's wood engravings.                     
                <lb/><lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2011</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduthe graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This image copyright © 2011 Fitzwilliam Museum (Objects 1,6), Robert N. Essick (Objects 2,13), Morgan Library and Museum (Objects 4,10,15).</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Publication prep</change><date>August-December 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>July 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Drawings for "The Pastorals of Virgil"</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake
               <role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1820">1820<note>These preliminary drawings were probably executed the year before the publication of Blake's wood engravings in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>, 1821.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>20</numberobj><objorder>1-20</objorder><objsize>ranging between 3.5 x 8.3 cm. and 4.5 x 7.8 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>20</numberleaves><leafsize>ranging between 3.6 x 8.8 cm. and 4.5 x 9.8 cm.<note>Some of the untraced drawings may be on leaves slightly larger or smaller than these dimensions.</note></leafsize><medium>pencil, pen and ink, and light gray washes</medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none recorded</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>various; see the note on provenance</name><date>see the note on provenance</date><dealer>see the note on provenance</dealer><price>see the note on provenance</price><note>John Linnell, probably acquired c. 1821-25 from Blake and mounted in an album; the album sold from the Linnell collection, Christie's, 15 March 1918, lot 205 (£113.8s. to the dealer E. Parsons &amp; Sons); offered by the dealer Robson, 1920 catalogue, item 24 (£150); American Art Association auction, New York, 22 April 1924, lot 69 ($1625 to the Brick Row Book Shop, New York, and later Austin, Texas); the drawings removed from the album and sold individually by Brick Row Book Shop between 1924 and c. 1954.  Object 1 (Butlin 769.1) acquired by Ward Cheney by 1927; a dealer in Paris; the London dealer H. D. Lyon; acquired by Geoffrey Keynes in 1965; by bequest to the Fitzwilliam Museum in 1982.  Objects 2 and 6 (Butlin 769.2, 13), acquired by Frederick T. Murphy by 1927; sold Sotheby's, 13 Nov. 1997, lot 56 (£71,900 to Nicholas W. Lott acting for Robert N. Essick).  Object 3 (Butlin 769.4) acquired by Mrs. Samuel Insull by 1927; Mrs. H. W. Reed; given by Reed to the Pierpont Morgan Library (now Morgan Library and Museum) in 1979.  Object 4 (Butlin 769.6) acquired c. 1928 by Geoffrey Keynes; by bequest to the Fitzwilliam Museum in 1982.  Object 5 (Butlin 769.10) acquired by David McC. McKell; given by McKell to the Pierpont Morgan Library (now Morgan Library and Museum) in 1959.  Object 7 (Butlin 769.15) acquired by Russell S. Underwood by 1927; Byrne Hackett of the Brick Row Book Shop by 1936; David McC. McKell; given by McKell to the Pierpont Morgan Library (now Morgan Library and Museum) in 1959.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution><addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline><addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 01223-332900</addressline><addressline>Fax: 01223-332923</addressline><addressline>Email: fitzmuseum-pdp@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Department of Paintings, Drawings and Prints</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">PD.163-1985 (Object 1, Butlin 769.1), PD.162-1985 (Object 4, Butlin 769.6)</repositoryid></repository><repository><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena, California (Objects 2 and 6, Butlin 769.2, 13)</addressline></repository><repository><institution>Morgan Library and Museum</institution><addressline>225 Madison Avenue</addressline><addressline>New York, New York 10016</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 1 212 685 0008</addressline><addressline>Fax: 1 212 481 3484</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Photography and Rights Department: 1 212 590 0386</addressline><addressline>Email, Photography and Rights Department: photoservices@themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Photography and Rights Department: http://themorgan.org/research/photo.asp</addressline><department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department><repositoryid label="Accession number">122776 (Object 3, Butlin 769.4), s E.17-18.1, no. 1959.15 (Object 5, Butlin 769.10), s E.17-18, no. 1959.16 (Object 7, Butlin 769.15)</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="but769.1.wd.01" dbi="but769.1.1.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Thenot Remonstrates with Colinet</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="U1">(Butlin 769.1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is Blake's preliminary drawing for the top design in Object 6 among the illustrations in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</p></objnote><objsize>4.0 x 9.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="400" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb504.2.comb.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm raised, palm vertical and facing out. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. Thenot, the older shepherd on the left, faces Colinet with his arms raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture. A dog lays his head on Thenot's right foot, and may be licking it, mouth open. At least three sheep graze to the left and right of Colinet. The sun sets or rises over the hills in the background and a tree trunk frames the right side of the scene.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Colinet</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Colinet, the younger shepherd on the right, stands with his left arm bent upward with his left hand raised above his head and the palm turned out toward the viewer. His right arm is bent upward and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. His hair is long. He faces forward and to the left, perhaps looking toward Thenot. He wears a knee-length gown, possibly with a high-waisted belt.  His mouth may be open; he may be speaking.  His bare feet are clearly pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>Thenot</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>palms out</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An older shepherd, Thenot, stands to the left with his back to the viewer.  His head is turned to the right and he may looking toward Colinet.  His arms are raised between 45 degrees and the horizontal in what may be a questioning or conciliatory gesture; his hands are held out with the palms held out away from his body.  He has long hair and a beard, and wears a full-length gown.  His left foot is on tiptoe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A dog stands to the right of Thenot with its head down at Thenot's right foot. The dog may be greeting Thenot, perhaps by sniffing or licking his foot. The dog's mouth may be open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>ram</characteristic><characteristic>flock</characteristic><characteristic>grazing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least three sheep graze with their heads down to the left and right of Colinet.  The body of a fourth sheep may be visible just to the right of Colinet. The sheep farthest left (a ram?) has prominent horns.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The trunk of a tree rises along the right border of the design. The branches of the tree extend to the left and dangle above the sun on the horizon.  There may be grass in the foreground and some sort of vegetation on the hills, particularly left of Thenot's left knee.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind the figures is a landscape of hillsides, with the sun rising or setting in the center of the design.  Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but769.1.wd.02" dbi="but769.1.2.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Thenot and Colinet Converse Seated Beneath Two Trees</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="U2">(Butlin 769.2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is Blake's preliminary drawing for the design second from the top in Object 6 among the illustrations in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</p></objnote><objsize>3.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="400" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb504.2.comb.06"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Thenot sits on the left under the branches of a fruit tree, with his arms bent and raised. Another figure, Colinet, sits to the right under another tree with his body twisted and head bowed.  He leans on his right elbow; his left hand may be raised to his face. A dog lies, facing forward, to the right of his left foot. Four sheep, perhaps part of a larger flock, lie between the two figures. A sun shines in the sky above hills.  There may be vegetation, possibly grass, in the foreground, particularly below the tree on the left.         
            </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>Thenot</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Thenot sits on the left side of the image, his arms bent upward.  His left palm is turned upward; his right palm is vertical and faces out toward the viewer. His legs and head face slightly to the right and his torso is twisted to face forward towards the viewer. He is old, with long hair and a beard, and wears a gown.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Colinet</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head on shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>arm resting</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Colinet sits to the right under a tree. His head is bowed and may rest on his raised left hand. His right leg is extended to the left while his left leg is bent back; his upper body is twisted and faces away from the viewer. Both arms are bent, and his right elbow leans against a rock or mound of earth. He is gowned, possibly with a belt high on his waist, and has long hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>ram</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four sheep lie on the ground between the human figures.  A head, facing right, is all that is cearly visible of the sheep on the left. The sheep second from the left turns its head to the left; the sheep second from the the right, apparently a horned ram, faces forward. The sheep on the right, behind the ram, also faces right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>fruit</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two trees flank the scene. The branches of the tree on the left arch to the right over Thenot; the branches are leafy and bear at least thirteen round fruits. The tree to the right of Colinet extends its branches over him, with its leafy branches arching to the left.  There is vegetation in the foreground, perhaps grass, particularly below the tree on the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>dog</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of Colinet's right foot, a dog lies on the ground. Its eyes are closed, and it may be sleeping.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>bank</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Thenot, on the left, appears to be sitting on bank or mound of earth.  Colinet, on the right, leans against a similar bank or mound.  The background is a landscape of hills, with the sun in the sky above the hilltops.  Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but769.1.wd.03" dbi="but769.1.4.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Unused Design: Colinet and Thenot Stand Together Conversing, Their Sheep Behind</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="U4">(Butlin 769.4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This design was not published in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.  There is no record that it was ever engraved.</p></objnote><objsize>4.3 x 8.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="400" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>
                     Two male figures stand in the center of the design. Colinet, the younger shepherd to the left, has long, curly hair and wears a gown. He holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand and raises his left arm in front of the figure to the right. Thenot, the older shepherd to the right, has long hair and a beard. He wears a gown and holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His right hand rests on Colinet's right shoulder. A flock of sheep appear to the left and right of the shepherds. In the right middle ground of the image stands a leafy tree with indeterminate leafy vegetation to the right and a fence or gate to the left. The scene is backed by rolling hills and fields, marked with indeterminate leafy vegetation.   
                  </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two male figures stand in the center of the design. Colinet, the younger shepherd to the left, has long, curly(?) hair and wears a knee-length gown. His right arm is at his side, and he holds a shepherd's crook in his right hand. His left arm, held in front of The figure to the right, is raised at 45 degrees and bent at the elbow, palm out and up. Colinet's mouth may be open; he may be speaking. He faces forward, with his head turned slightly to the right. His legs may be slightly bent at the knees, and his right foot may be raised on tiptoe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two male figures stand in the center of the design. Thenot, the older shepherd to the right, has long hair and a beard. He faces forward, with his head turned slightly to the left. He wears a long gown and may also wear shoes. Thenot's left arm is bent slightly upward at 45 degrees; and he holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand. His right hand, fingers slightly spread, rests on Colinet's right shoulder. His right leg is extended in front of his left, perhaps indicating that he is walking forward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>grazing</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>lamb</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A flock appear to the left and right of the shepherds. All the sheep face left with their heads to the ground; they are probably grazing. The two small sheep on the left are probably lambs. The small animal to the left faces forward so that only its head, neck, chest, and front legs are visible. It stands with its head facing right. The small animal to the right faces right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>leafy</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the right middle ground of the image stands a leafy tree with an indeterminate leafy plant to the right. The scene is backed by rolling hills and fields, marked with indeterminate leafy vegetation. There may be grass in the foreground as well.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>fence</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the tree in the middle ground on the right side of the design stands a gate or a span of fence, likely made of wood. There may be a road or path leading from the gate.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but769.1.wd.04" dbi="but769.1.6.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Blighted Corn</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="U6">(Butlin 769.6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is Blake's preliminary drawing for the top design in Object 7 among the illustrations in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</p></objnote><objsize>4.1 x 9.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="400" width="500"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The image is dominated by a large, gnarled tree on the left with branches reaching to the right towards the crescent moon in the cloudy night sky. Shafts of grain, blown down by a stormy wind, dominate the middle distance, with vegetation (possibly trees) in the background.  A small hill or distant mountain rises in the right background.  Horizontal lines in the dark sky indicate rain, hail, or sleet.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The image is dominated by a large, gnarled tree on the left with branches reaching to the right towards the crescent moon. There are a few leaves on the ends of its branches, but on the whole it appears leafless.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>moon</characteristic><characteristic>crescent</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><characteristic>rain</characteristic><characteristic>hail</characteristic><characteristic>sleet</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A crescent moon, with the dark of the moon also visible, appears in the cloudy night sky to the right of the tree.  Diagonal lines in the sky of this storm-tossed scene indicate rain, hail, or sleet. A wind blowing from left to right forces the grain stems to the ground.  A hill or distant mountain rises on the horizon far right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grain</characteristic><characteristic>grain stem</characteristic><characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic><characteristic>trees</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Shafts of grain with prominent tassels dominate the middle distance. They are bent to the ground by a wind blowing from left to right. Behind the grain is some vegetation, possibly trees.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><related objectid="bb504.2.comb.07"/></desc><desc id="but769.1.wd.05" dbi="but769.1.10.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">'A Rolling Stone is Ever Bare of Moss'</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="U10">(Butlin 769.10)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is Blake's preliminary drawing for the top design in Object 8 among the illustrations in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</p></objnote><objsize>4.5 x 9.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="500" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb504.2.comb.08"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A man faces and strides left. With both arms extended back, he holds a handle attached to a large lawn roller. In the right foreground of the image is a large tree with branches extending to the left. To the left of the tree is a neoclassical building, very probably a house, with a grassy(?) lawn below and what may be trees to its left. The house is two stories and has a door and nine windows visible. Its front door is centered over a stoop.  A path extends below the figure and towards the door of the house.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>pulling</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure strides left, bending forward with both legs bent. His left leg is extended backward (to the right) with his left foot raised on tiptoe. The figure is seen in part from behind and may wear breeches.  With both arms extended back, he holds and pulls the handle of a lawn roller.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><characteristic>roller</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure walks on a road or private drive that extends horizontally across the image; a small path leads from the road to the front door of a large house.  The man pulls a lawn roller.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>classical art</characteristic><characteristic>window</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the figure is a large, two-story neoclassical building, very probably a house, with nine windows. Its front door is centered over a stoop.  The segment of the house containing the door is tower-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tree rises along the right border of the design.  Its branches extend to the left, with perhaps one branch extending right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>leafy</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground below the house may be covered with grass.  Indications of leafy vegetationperhaps trees or large bushesappear just left of the house.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but769.1.wd.06" dbi="but769.1.13.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">'For Him Our Yearly Wakes and Feasts We Hold'</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="U13">(Butlin 769.13)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is Blake's preliminary drawing for the bottom design in Object 8 among the illustrations in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</p></objnote><objsize>3.7 x 9.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="400" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb504.2.comb.08"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A group of seven figures appears on the lawn of a large house with multiple pillars and windows visible. Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image. The leftmost figure holds a tambourine above her head. The second figure from the left faces away from the viewer. The third figure from the left faces forward with her arms bent upward. Two musicians sit in chairs in the right half of the design. The figure furthest to the right plays a violin.  To the left, a female musician plays a lyre.  A gowned female(?)possibly a childstands to the left of the female musician.  She(?) bends slightly over and may hold onto a male(?) child to the left.  He(?) stands facing forward with both arms bent upward. To the right of the male musician is a tree trunk, with what may be leafy branches spread overhead.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>tambourine</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image.  The two on the left have their hair pulled back in buns. The leftmost figure faces forward with her lower body twisted to the left and at least her right foot raised on tiptoe. Her head is turned to the right in profile. Her arms are bent upward and she holds (and possibly plays) a tambourine above her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image.  The two on the left have their hair in buns. The second figure from the left faces away from the viewer, but with her head twisted to left profile. Her right leg is bent and extended backwards, foot on tiptoe. Her arms are raised at 45 degrees, palms out.  She may be wearing a hat or a wreath of flowers(?) on her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>palms up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three gowned females dance in the left half of the image. The third figure from the left faces forward with her left leg crossed in front of her right and her left foot raised on tiptoe. Her hair is either short or pulled back in a bun. She may be wearing decorations in her hair, possibly flowers. Her arms are raised and bent upward with the palms up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>coat</characteristic><characteristic>shoes</characteristic><characteristic>breeches</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>violin</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two musicians sit in chairs in the right half of the design.  The figure furthest right is a male wearing a hat, coat, breeches, and probably shoes.  He sits facing left.  He holds a violin with his left hand and plays it with a bow held in his right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>feather</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>left hand</characteristic><characteristic>lyre</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two musicians sit in chairs in the right half of the design. To the left of the violinist is a female wearing a gown and a wide-brimmed hat topped with feathers. Her left arm is bent and she plays a lyre with her left hand.  She faces left and may look towards the dancers.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>chair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The musician on the right, playing a violin, sits in a chair.  His companion to the left probably also sits on a chair, although none is pictured.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female(?)possibly a childstands to the left of the female musician.  She(?) bends slightly to the left (forward with respect to her body) and may hold onto a male(?) child to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned male(?) child stands to the left of a gowned female(?).  He(?) faces forward and slightly to the left with his arms bent and raised at 135 degrees.  His(?) right leg is bent and may be slightly raised off the ground; he(?) may be dancing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="AB"><characteristic>building</characteristic><characteristic>house</characteristic><characteristic>classical art</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>pilaster</characteristic><characteristic>façade</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>triangle</characteristic><characteristic>tower</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A building, probably a large neoclassical house, appears in the background of the image, filling the space between the right border and the second figure from the left. The façade of the structure is decorated with pilasters. Four large pillars support the classical entry porch before the front door above a triangular pediment. There may be a tower-like structure at the left end of the building.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>trunk</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the male musician is a tree trunk, with what may be leafy branches spread overhead.  There may be some grass at the base of the tree.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="but769.1.wd.07" dbi="but769.1.15.WD"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Second Comparison, 'The Briny Ocean Turns to Pastures Dry'</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="U15">(Butlin 769.15)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This is Blake's preliminary drawing for the middle design in Object 9 among the illustrations in R. J. Thornton's <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi>.</p></objnote><objsize>3.7 x 8.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="500" width="500"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb504.2.comb.09"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Seven sailing vessels face rightward on the ocean's surface. A series of waves and the shore are visible in the lower portion of the design.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>ship</characteristic><characteristic>boat</characteristic><characteristic>sailing</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>flag</characteristic><characteristic>pole</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Seven sailing vessels face rightward on the ocean's surface.  The two vessels on the right are larger wooden ships with multiple sails. The second ship from the left is indicated (if present at all) by only a few vertical lines. The third ship from the left has at least three sails. The fourth ship from the left has two masts and five sails; the rightmost mast is topped with a flag.  The second ship from the right has three masts and ten sails; each mast is topped with a flag.  The ship furthest right also has three masts topped with flags and perhaps nine sails in total.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ships sail on an ocean or sea.  A series of waves and the shore are visible in the lower portion of the design.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>