
<bad id="but72v.1" type="penc"
    work="Standing and Seated(?) Figures, Possibly a Drawing Class in the Royal Academy" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="72v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title
                    reg="Standing and Seated(?) Figures, Possibly a Drawing Class in the Royal Academy">
                    <main>Standing and Seated(?) Figures, Possibly a Drawing Class in the Royal
                        Academy</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* ( Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2015 British Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
            <date>October 2018</date>
            <respstmt>
                <resp>Editors:</resp>
                <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                <name>Michael Fox</name>
                <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                <name>Grant Glass</name>
                <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                <name>Eric Loy</name>
                <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
            </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>September 2012</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold, </name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Laura Bell, </name>
                    <name>Lauren Cameron, </name>
                    <name>Katherine Carlson, </name>
                    <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett, </name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher, </name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                    <name>Jennifer Park, </name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
                    <name>Bihan Zhang</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Standing and Seated(?) Figures, Possibly a Drawing Class in the Royal
                        Academy* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1779">c. 1779-1800<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations and the possible link between this drawing and Blake's
                        studies at the Royal Academy&#8212;see the Editors' Note.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>22.6 x 35.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22.6 x 35.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The British Museum collection stamp in ink is in the lower
                        right quadrant of the leaf.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; John Deffett Francis, given by him to the British
                    Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings:
                    prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.110</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but72.1.1v.penc.01" dbi="BUT72.1.1v.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Standing and Seated(?) Figures, Possibly a Drawing Class
                    in the Royal Academy</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 72verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This loose pencil sketch may represent a drawing class in the Royal Academy
                        schools when Blake studied there, 1779-80. The pencil drawing on the recto
                        of this leaf, *Academy Study: Standing Male Nude Seen from Behind*, was
                        almost certainly drawn at the Royal Academy school. The British Museum
                        collection stamp appears in the lower right quadrant of this verso
                        drawing.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>22.6 x 35.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This loose pencil sketch may represent a drawing class in the
                        Royal Academy schools when Blake studied there, 1779-80. Six or seven
                        roughly sketched figures stand or sit in the foreground of the composition.
                        In the center of the design, two figures, indicated only by circular heads
                        and rectangular bodies, stand on a plinth. These may be live models or
                        plaster casts being copied by the other figures, students in the Royal
                        Academy school. In the lower right quadrant, a third figure sits with both
                        arms extended downward. Its legs may be bent and extended to the left. To
                        the left of this figure's head, a circle is visible that may represent the
                        head of a figure not otherwise pictured. In the lower left quadrant
                        diagonally below the central figural pair, two additional figures stand. The
                        rightmost of these raises one arm at 45 degrees. He appears to hold a
                        tablet; he may be drawing on it. The head and shoulders of a final figure,
                        who may lean to the right, are depicted in the lower left corner of the
                        sketch. Vertical lines in the upper part of the drawing may be windows or
                        doors in this room, possibly in Somerset House where the Royal Academy had
                        its schools.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, two figures are indicated only by
                            circular heads and rectangular bodies. These may be live models or
                            plaster casts being copied by some of the other figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two central figures, perhaps plaster casts, stand on a
                            plinth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>room</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Somerset House</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Royal Academy</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The vertical lines in the upper half of the drawing may be the
                            large windows of Somerset House where the Royal Academy had its
                            classes.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>student</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right quadrant, a figure sits or reclines with
                            both arms extended downward and perhaps braced on the ground. Its legs
                            may be bent and extended to the left. The figure leans to the right.
                            This may be a student in a Royal Academy school.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>student</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Between the standing central pair and reclining figure at
                            right, a circle is visible that may represent the head of a figure not
                            otherwise pictured. This may be a student in a Royal Academy
                            school.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drawing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>student</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left quadrant diagonally below the central
                            figural pair, two additional figures stand. The rightmost of these faces
                            right and raises one arm at 45 degrees. He appears to be holding, and
                            possibly drawing upon, a tablet. These may be students in a Royal
                            Academy school.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>student</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The head and shoulders of a final figure, who may lean to the
                            right, are depicted in the lower left corner of the sketch. This may be
                            a student in a Royal Academy school.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>

                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
