<bad id="but73v.1" type="penc"
    work="Study for ‘Glad Day,’ ‘Albion Rose’ or ‘The Dance of Albion’: The Same Figure Seen from Behind"
    copy="1" copyid="1" institution="vanda" catalog="butlin" catid="73v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title
                    reg="Study for ‘Glad Day,’ ‘Albion Rose’ or ‘The Dance of Albion’: The Same Figure Seen from Behind">
                    <main>Study for "Glad Day," "Albion Rose" or "The Dance of Albion": The Same
                        Figure Seen from Behind</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October
                    2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* ( Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2018 Victoria and Albert Museum </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>July 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>May 2003</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Amy Havlan, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> Study for "Glad Day," "Albion Rose" or "The Dance of Albion": The Same
                        Figure Seen from Behind </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780<note>The date of this drawing is based on the "1780"
                        date inscribed on "Albion rose," Blake's etching/engraving of the same
                        design as the sketch on the recto of this drawing. This verso sketch was
                        very probably executed at about the same time as the recto drawing.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>20.6 x 28.8 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>20.6 x 28.8 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Victoria and Albert Museum</name>
                <date>1881</date>
                <dealer>E. Parsons</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Probably inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; by
                    inheritance to Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; apparently
                    sold by Tatham to the dealer Joseph Hogarth; sold from Hogarth's stock,
                    Southgate and Barrett auction, London, 7 June 1854 and seventeen following days,
                    lot 4180 on the tenth day, with three other works by Blake (6s. to the dealer H.
                    Palser); the dealer E. Parsons; sold by Parsons to the Victoria and Albert
                    Museum in 1881.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Victoria and Albert Museum</institution>
                <addressline>South Kensington</addressline>
                <addressline>Cromwell Road</addressline>
                <addressline>London SW7 2RL</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7942 2000</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images Agency: +44 (0)20 7942 2479</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Images Agency: +44 (0)20 7942 2482</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.vam.ac.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Finding and Buying Images:
                    http://www.vam.ac.uk/resources/buying/index.html</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">8764.c</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but73v.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT73.1.1v.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed"> *Study for "Glad Day," "Albion Rose" or "The Dance of
                    Albion": The Same Figure Seen from Behind* </title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 73 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The Victoria and Albert accession number is inscribed in pen and ink lower
                        right. For the pencil sketch on the recto, see *Study for "Glad Day,"
                        "Albion Rose" or "The Dance of Albion"*.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>20.6 x 28.8 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A single male figure seen from behind stands in the center of this
                        composition. The figure is nude with prominent buttocks and has short curly
                        hair. His head is tilted up and both arms are raised horizontally, turning
                        them so that both wrists face up and palms out. His fingers, which are
                        noticeably long, are spread with thumbs pointing up. The expressiveness of
                        this position may communicate the figure's ecstasy. There are additional
                        lines sketched in and near the palms of both hands, though the
                        representational meaning of these is not clear. They may be alternative
                        positions for the fingers. A small circular object, perhaps a ball(?), is
                        visible above and right of his straightened right leg. This circle may be a
                        later addition not by Blake. The figure raises his left leg, which is bent
                        slightly backward at the knee, at 45 degrees. He points his toes of his left
                        foot to the left where they appear to touch or rest on tiptoe on a
                        serpentine diagonal line that extends from the center of the lower edge of
                        the design (below the figure's right foot) to the left side of the
                        composition by the figure's left hand. This line may indicate a geological
                        form such as the outline of a rocky cliff. A horizontal line bisects the
                        right side of the scene and a semicircular shape, likely a rising or setting
                        sun, is visible above this line. The figure is likely the same character in
                        a different position as the one sketched on the recto of this composition, a
                        preliminary drawing for Blake's etching/engraving, "Albion rose." The figure
                        is not specifically identified as Albion until the inscription added to the
                        plate c. 1820.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ecstasy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Albion</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A single male figure seen from behind stands in the center of
                            this composition. The figure is nude with prominent buttocks and has
                            short curly hair. His head is tilted up and both arms are raised
                            horizontally, turning them so that both wrists face up and palms out.
                            His fingers, which are noticeably long, are spread with thumbs pointing
                            up. The expressiveness of this position may communicate the figure's
                            ecstasy. There are additional lines sketched in and near the palms of
                            both hands, though the representational meaning of these is not clear.
                            They may be alternative positions for the fingers. Standing on a
                            straightened right leg, the figure raises his left leg, which is bent
                            slightly backward at the knee, at 45 degrees. He points his toes of his
                            left foot to the left where they appear to touch or rest on tiptoe on a
                            serpentine diagonal line that extends from the center of the lower edge
                            of the design (below the figure's right foot) to the left side of the
                            composition by his left hand. The figure is likely the same character in
                            a different position as the one sketched on the recto of this
                            composition, a preliminary drawing for Blake's etching/engraving,
                            "Albion rose." The figure is not specifically identified as Albion until
                            the inscription added to the plate c. 1820.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>ball</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sphere</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A small circular object, perhaps a ball(?), is visible above
                            and right of the figure's straightened right leg. This may be a later
                            addition not by Blake.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>line</illusobjdesc>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure's raised left leg appears to touch or rest on a
                            serpentine diagonal line that extends from the center of the lower edge
                            of the design (below the figure's right foot) to the left side of the
                            composition by the figure's left hand. This line may indicate a
                            geological form such as the outline of a rocky cliff.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A horizontal line bisects the right side of the scene and a
                            semicircular shape, likely a rising or setting sun, is visible above
                            this line.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
