<bad id="but88r.1" type="wc" work="An Enthroned Old Man Offering Two Children to Heaven" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fogg" catalog="butlin" catid="88">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="An Enthroned Old Man Offering Two Children to Heaven">
                    <main>
                        An Enthroned Old Man Offering Two Children to Heaven</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 23KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *An Enthroned Old Man Offering Two Children to Heaven*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.F">c. 1785-90</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>12.2 x 9.7 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>12.2 x 9.7 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University</name>
                <date>1967</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Early history not known; acquired by Horace E. Scudder, probably c. 1861-65; his daughter Sylvia Church Scudder (Mrs. Ingersoll Bowditch), probably by inheritance in 1902; deposited in the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University, in 1940; purchased by the Fogg Art Museum in 1967.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1967.45</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but88r.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT88.1.1r.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">An Enthroned Old Man Offering Two Children to Heaven</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(BUT88r)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>A pencil sketch of a female with a horse's head, perhaps Hippa, is on the verso of this water color.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>12.2 x 9.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, an old man sits on an elaborate, Gothic style throne as two children kneel on either side of him. The old man has short, curly, white hair and a similarly curly white beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown that gathers in folds to cover his feet. He sits, facing forward, with his upper body and shoulders held erect. His eyes stare blankly toward the viewer, and his mouth opens slightly beneath his heavy mustache. The man raises both arms at nearly 45 degrees away from his knees, and his partly visible palms turn to face the viewer. His fingers are spread. Leaning on the old man's knees are two children-one girl and one boy-who kneel facing one another.The girl at left wears a long-sleeved gown with an adornment on the right side. She has long hair that curls into ringlets at the ends. She kneels, facing right, with her legs extended behind her. She leans forward to rest her right elbow on the old man's right knee. Her arm bends upward, and her palm is raised, facing away from the viewer and toward the old man's waist. Her left arm is not visible, but it may be raised behind her right arm with hands clasped in a position of prayer. Her head tilts downward, and she appears to gaze at the ground. At the old man's left knee is a young boy with short, curly hair. He wears a skirt that may be fastened at his waist with a belt, but he is nude from the waist up. The boy kneels, facing left, with his legs extended behind him. Rather than bending forward at the knees and waist like his female companion, the boy hunches his shoulders forward to rest his chest and bent left arm on the old man's left knee. His upper body faces away, showing the viewer most of his back. His left arm bends sharply, and he may rest his head on his left hand. The boy's head tilts downward, and he looks at the ground between the old man's feet. The man supports these two children from a seated position on a throne, only the back of which is visible. It rises to a point above the man's head, almost giving the illusion that he is wearing a pointed hat. This largest center point may bear a decorative topper at its apex. On either side, smaller decorative points rise above the man's shoulders. The scene is framed by several large columns behind the three figures, and a canopy over their heads. This structure may be composed of six pillars and a thatch roof, or of six tall trees whose branches gather to provide a covering. In the gaps between these pillars or trees, blue skies and clouds hover over a vague landscape that may contain hills or trees, and possibly a river at left. These background details suggest that the throne sits in a gazebo or outdoor shelter of some sort, and that the scene takes place during the daytime. The foreground, however, is much darker, and prominent shadows appear in the thatch or branches over the figures' heads,in the folds of the old man's gown, and behind the boy, in the lower right corner of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design, an old man sits on an elaborate throne as two children kneel on either side of him with arms resting on his knees. The old man has short, curly, white hair and a similarly curly white beard. He wears a long-sleeved gown that gathers in folds to cover his feet. He sits, facing forward, with his upper body and shoulders held erect. His eyes stare blankly toward the viewer, and his mouth opens slightly beneath his heavy mustache. The man raises both bent arms at nearly 45 degrees away from his knees, and his partly visible palms turn to face the viewer. His fingers are spread.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Leaning on the old man's knees are two children-one girl and one boy-who kneel facing one another.The girl at left wears a long-sleeved gown with an adornment (perhaps a loose belt?) on the right side. She has long hair that curls into ringlets at the ends. She kneels, facing right, with her legs extended behind her. She leans forward to rest her right elbow on the old man's right knee. Her arm bends upward, and her palm is raised, facing away from the viewer and toward the old man's waist. Her left arm is not visible, but it may be raised behind her right arm with hands clasped in a position of prayer. Her head tilts downward, and she appears to gaze at the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>back to viewer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the old man's left knee is a young boy with short, curly hair. He wears a skirt that may be fastened at his waist with a belt, but he is nude from the waist up. The boy kneels, facing left, with his legs extended behind him. Rather than bending forward at the knees and waist like his female companion, the boy hunches his shoulders forward to rest his chest and bent left arm on the old man's left knee. His upper body faces away, showing the viewer most of his back. His left arm bends sharply, and he may rest his head on his left hand. The boy's head tilts downward, and he looks at the ground between the old man's feet.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The old man sits on a throne, only the back of which is visible. It rises to a point above the man's head, almost giving the illusion that he is wearing a pointed hat. This largest center point may bear a decorative topper at its apex. On either side, smaller decorative points rise above the man's shoulders.  These forms are evocative of Gothic art.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gazebo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene is framed by several large columns behind the three figures, and a canopy over their heads. This gazebo-like structure may be composed of six pillars and a thatch roof, or of six tall trees whose branches gather to provide a covering.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The scene is framed by several large columns behind the three figures, and a canopy over their heads. This structure may be composed of six pillars and a thatch roof, or of six tall trees whose branches gather to provide a covering.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clouds</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the gaps between the pillars or trees, blue skies and clouds hover over a vague landscape that may contain hills or trees, and possibly a river at left. These background details suggest that the throne sits in an outdoor shelter of some sort, and that the scene takes place during the daytime.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>hills</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design's background contains a vague landscape that may contain hills or trees, and possibly a river at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                	<component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trees</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background landscape visible at left of the throne may contain grassy hills and trees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                   		<characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design's foreground is much darker than its background, and prominent shadows appear in the thatch or branches over the figures' heads,in the folds of the old man's gown, and behind the boy, in the lower right corner of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
