<bad id="but86v.1" type="penink" work="Four Composition Sketches" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="86v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Four Composition Sketches">
                    <main>Four Composition Sketches</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This work copyright © 2015 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Four Composition Sketches*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1785">c. 1785-90
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.2 x 15.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.2 x 15.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>This object is the verso of Butlin 86 recto, *An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple*.  This leaf was originally one half of a larger leaf.  The other half is Butlin 85, with *A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing* on the recto and *Four Composition Sketches* on the verso.</note>
                </support>
                <watermark>PRO PATRIA<note>Only part of this watermark appears on this leaf.  The other half is on Butlin 85, with *A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing* on the recto and *Four Composition Sketches* on the verso.</note>
                </watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The British Museum accession number is stamped just above the bottom margin.</note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis, who gave the work to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-2076-361555</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <collection>none</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.138</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but86v.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT86.1.1v.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Four Composition Sketches</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 86 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    This object is the verso of Butlin 86 recto, *An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple*.  This leaf was originally one half of a larger leaf.  The other half is Butlin 85, with *A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing* on the recto and *Four Composition Sketches* on the verso.
                </objnote>
                <objsize>18.2 x 15.1 cm</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <related objectid="but85v.1.penink.01"/>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper left quadrant contains at least one figure with raised arms leaning right, away from what may be flames at left.  The sketch in the upper right quadrant shows at least one figure seated facing right.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two figures seated on a couch with an elaborate bolster-like arm.  Clouds or perhaps beams of light are visible above the pair at left.  The sketch in the lower right quadrant contains a single gowned figure facing right with one arm raised horizontally. There is a cluster of diagonal brushstrokes of grey wash to the left of this figure.  To the left of the line demarcating the lower left scene, a portion of a sketch continued from another leaf of sketches (Butlin 85 verso) is visible, indicating that the two pages were originally part of the same sheet of paper.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper left quadrant contains at least one figure who stands, runs, or perhaps leans to the right.  Its right leg is extended backward, its right arm raised horizontally, and its left arm raised at 135 degrees.  The figure may twist its head to look back to the left, where lines that suggest flames extend from the left margin of the sketch from which the figure is fleeing.  The multiplicity of lines forming the figure may suggest movement or, alternatively, the presence of a second figure directly behind the first.  This second figure, partly erased, may be an alternative posture for the first figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wave</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lines that suggest flames extend from the left margin of the sketch in the upper left quadrant.  The line below the figure may be the ground, or possibly a body of water with a single wave.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.   The sketch in the upper right quadrant shows at least one figure seated or kneeling on bent legs facing right with one arm raised at 45 degrees.  This figure appears to wear a gown with a belt.  There may be a second head and extended arm suggested behind and to the right of the first figure.  This second figure, perhaps partly erased, may be an alternative posture for the first figure.  Lines on the right side of the sketch suggest fire and smoke.  The figure may be warming its hands at the fire.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lines on the right side of the sketch in the upper right quadrant suggest file and smoke.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two forward-facing figures seated on a couch with an elaborate bolster-like arm at right.  The figure at left appears to be gowned with its right arm raised at 45 degrees.  The figure holds an indistinct object that may be a book or tablet(?), suggesting he or she may be reading.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drawing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two forward-facing figures seated on a couch with an elaborate bolster-like arm at right.  The figure at right has long hair and a beard, suggesting he is male.  In his lap, he holds what appears to be an open book in which he writes or draws with his right hand.  He wears a long gown and his legs may be crossed at the ankle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two forward-facing figures seated on a couch with an elaborate bolster-like arm at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two figures seated on a couch.  The figure at right holds in his lap what appears to be an open book in which he writes or draws.  His companion may also hold a book or tablet in its right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above and to the left the pair of seated figures in the sketch lower left is a cluster of lines suggesting clouds and perhaps diagonal beams of light.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the left of the line demarcating the lower left scene, a portion of a sketch continued from another leaf of sketches (Butlin 85 verso) is visible, indicating that the two pages were originally part of the same sheet of paper.  A figure's left shoulder, arm, and hand braced on the ground extend into this object.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower right quadrant contains a single gowned figure facing right with one arm raised horizontally and slightly bent.  One of his fingers or perhaps his thumb may be raised, pointing upward.  The figure appears to have long, curly(?) hair and a beard, suggesting he is male.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There is a cluster of diagonal brushstrokes of grey wash to the left of the figure in the lower right quadrant.  These may suggest a shadow.  The pen strokes upper left do not clearly represent anything and may only be part of the adjacent framing line.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>