<bad id="but801.1" type="penink" work="Lady Torrens and Family, After John Linnell" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="801" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Lady Torrens and Family, After John Linnell">
                    <main>Lady Torrens and Family, After John Linnell</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Lady Torrens and Family, After John Linnell
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake.  Blake's drawing is based on a painting by John Linnell.  The "Blake" inscription in pencil, lower right, is attributed to his hand in Butlin 801 but may have been inscribed by Linnell. <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>John Linnell.  Blake's drawing is based on a painting by John Linnell.  Linnell wrote the inscription below the design and may have also written the "Blake" inscription lower right, although the latter is attributed to Blake in Butlin 801.<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>author</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1825">c. 1825<note>The date is uncertain, but after 1819 when John Linnell was finishing the painting on which Blake's design is based.  Butlin 801 suggests c. 1825 because "the quavery line supports a late date."</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.7 x 22.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.7 x 22.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink<note>The inscriptions are in pencil.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>1815</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Acquired by John Linnell, probably directly from Blake or his wife Catherine; sold from the Linnell collection, Christie's, 15 March 1918, probably in lot 165 with sixteen other works as specified in Butlin 699 (£46.4s. to the dealer E. Parsons); offered by the dealer Philip Robinson of the firm William H. Robinson and Son in a typescript catalogue of c. 1937, page 35 (not priced); sold by Robinson to Lessing J. Rosenwald on 23 July 1937; given by Rosenwald in 1943 to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <addressline>Constitution Avenue NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline>
                <addressline>Washington, DC 20565</addressline>
                <addressline>Mailing Address: 2000B South Club Drive, Landover, Maryland 20785</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-202-737-4215</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Print Study Rooms: 1-202-842-6380</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 1-202-842-6126</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Visual Services: http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.3.9014</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but801.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT801.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Lady Torrens and Family, After John Linnell</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 801)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The drawing is based on an oil painting of the family of Lady Torrens by John Linnell.  His work, 109.2 x 139.7 cm., was painted in 1819-20 and exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1821, no. 375 in the exhibition catalogue.  Linnell's painting is now in the Chazen Museum of Art, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin.  The figure far left is very differently positioned in the finished oil painting; the figure far right has his arms crossed over his torso and his legs extended to the left in the painting.  Blake's drawing may represent an earlier version of Linnell's painting.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>18.7 x 22.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, likely their mother, in this drawing.  The second figure from the left, the single adult wears a long gown and appears to have short hair.  Her legs face the left but she turns forward to look down on the other children.  Both of her arms are bent as she holds a young child near her lap.  This child faces forward but holds the woman with its left arm.  Below the female figure at left, a child crouches or kneels facing right and wraps at least one of its arms around the woman's legs.  Above the adult figure's left shoulder the head of a third child who has short curly is visible.  Directly below this head, a fourth child with long hair wearing a gown stands facing left.  Likely female, this child rests her bent left arm on the edge of a piece of furniture, probably a chair or couch, and extends her right to touch the small child at left.  The two rightmost figures appear taller than the other children and may be adolescents.  The second figure from the left has long hair and wears a gown (and thus is likely female); she stands facing left, perhaps with her left arm bent and raised in front of her chest.  The rightmost figure sits on a round piece of furniture, possibly a small chair or stool, and appears to wear a shirt with a collar and possibly long pants.  Though its body faces left, the figure twists to the right by placing its right arm across its lap while the left is braced by its hip, palm down.  This drawing is a copy after John Linnell's oil painting of Lady Torrens and family, which was painted 1819-20.  The children in this portrait are Miss Torrens, Miss Hannah Torrens, and Henry, Arthur, Frederic, and Charles Torrens, according to Alfred T. Story, <hi rend="i">The Life of John Linnell</hi> (London: Richard Bentley and Son, 1892) 2: 247.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Torrens</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, likely their mother, in this drawing, based on John Linnell's oil painting of the family of Lady Torrens.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, Lady Torrens, the mother of the other figures.  The second figure from the left, the single adult wears a long gown and appears to have short hair.  Her legs face the left but she turns rightward to look down on the other children.  Both of her arms are bent as she holds a young child near her lap.  Her legs may be crossed at the ankle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, Lady Torrens, the mother of the other figures.  A young child with short hair sits facing forward in the lap of the central adult figure.  Both legs are bent at the knee and its left arm is wrapped around its body, perhaps to hold onto its mother's right arm.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, likely their mother, in this drawing.  Below the female figure at left, a gowned child with short hair crouches or kneels facing right and wraps at least its right arm around the woman's legs on which it leans.  The figure may touch or pull the right foot of the seated child in its mother's lap with its extended right hand.  In Linnell's oil painting, this child, very differently positioned, is male.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, Lady Torrens, the mother of the other figures.  Above the adult figure's left shoulder the head of a third child who has short curly is visible.  This child is male in Linnell's oil painting.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, Lady Torrens, the mother of the other figures.  To the right of the adult figure and below the third child's head, a fourth child with long hair wearing a gown stands facing left with one leg extended backward.  Likely female, as in Linnell's oil painting, this child rests her bent left arm on the edge of a piece of furniture, probably the arm of a chair or couch, and extends her right to touch the small child at left, down at whom she looks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, Lady Torrens, the mother of the other figures.  The two rightmost figures appear taller than the other children and may be adolescents.  The second figure from the left appears to have long hair and wears a gown (and thus is likely female, as in Linnell's oil painting); she stands facing left, perhaps with her left arm bent and raised in front of her chest.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Six children and adolescents surround a seated female figure, Lady Torrens, the mother of the other figures.  The two rightmost figures appear taller than the other children and may be adolescents.  The rightmost figure sits on a round piece of furniture, probably a small chair or stool, and appears to wear a shirt with a collar and possibly pants.  Though its body faces left, the figure twists to the right by placing its right arm across its lap while the left is braced by its hip, palm down.  The figure's head may be down.  Both legs are bent and the figure's feet appear to rest in tiptoe against the side of the furniture.  This figure is male, somewhat differently positioned with his arms folded over his torso and his legs extended to the left, in Linnell's oil painting.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>couch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Though the figures and their clothing obscures much of the furniture, there are various seats in the scene, including what may be a couch or chair with a visible arm near the center of the composition and a small chair or stool at far right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but801.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="85">Blake f<note>This pencil inscription is attributed to Blake in Butlin 801.  We suspect, however, that it was written by John Linnell.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but801.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="20">from my picture of Lady Torrens &amp; Family J L<note>This second line of inscription was written in pencil by John Linnell.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>