<bad id="but81r.1" type="penc" work="A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="81r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches">
                    <main>A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This image copyright © 2018 William Blake Archive </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>July 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>May 1999</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue, </name>
                    <name>Greg Murray</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Frederick Tatham<role>author. Tatham wrote the pen and ink inscription,
                        lower left.</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations
                        and the relationship of motifs in this drawing to others of the 1780-85
                        period.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>31.0 x 18.4 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>31.0 x 18.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil<note>The inscription, lower left, by Frederick Tatham is in pen and
                        ink. See the Textual Transcription.</note>
                </medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>GR<note>A crown appears above the letters "GR."</note>
                </watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1993</date>
                <dealer>Nicholas W. Lott</dealer>
                <price>$9000</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; Frederick Tatham at
                    Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his
                    catalogue of Nov. 1882, in item 346 with forty-four other works (&#163;36),
                    catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1882 and catalogue of Oct. 1883, in item 13,843 in
                    both, "forty [forty-five?] sketches in pencil or chalk" (&#163;36), and May 1885
                    catalogue of *William Blake's Original Drawings*, no item number for the same
                    group of drawings from Tatham's collection (&#163;36); sold June 1886 to W.
                    Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949,
                    lot 74 with two other works (&#163;26.5s. to the dealer Bertram Rota acting for
                    an American private collector); Bodley Bookshop, New York; acquired c. 1955-56
                    by Edwin Wolf 2nd; inherited by a descendent of Wolf's (probably his son) upon
                    Wolf's death in 1991; on consignment with the dealer Nicholas W. Lott by early
                    1993; acquired Dec. 1993 by Robert N. Essick.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline>

            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but81r.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT81.1.1r.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Pastoral Figure and Other Sketches</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 81 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>For the pencil drawings on the verso, see *A Harper and Other Figures*.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>31.0 x 18.4 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, a nude male figure with long
                        hair sits facing forward. His left arm, which is bent upward, rests on his
                        bent left knee; in his left hand, the figure holds a faintly drawn staff or
                        shepherd's crook, which appears to rest against his head. A diagonal strap
                        is visible across his chest and appears to hold a cloak that dangles behind
                        his right arm. His bent right arm rests in his lap on his bent right leg.
                        With his right hand, he holds or supports a lyre that leans against his
                        right leg. This figure may lean against the trunk of a tree visible upper
                        left. There may be a mountain or hill visible upper right. In the lower
                        right corner of the composition, a nude seated figure seen upside down
                        facing left holds a harp. To the left of this figure's left foot is a
                        standing(?) figure drawn sideways with arms at its side. There are also
                        three drawings of a nude man reclining on his side, two on the right, drawn
                        with the paper held horizontally, and one of the left, similarly drawn but
                        with the paper held the other way up. There are additional indeterminate
                        lines and forms throughout the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, a nude male figure with long
                            hair sits facing forward. His left arm, which is bent upward, rests on
                            his bent left knee; in his left hand, the figure holds a staff or
                            shepherd's crook, which appears to rest against his head and suggests he
                            may be a shepherd. A diagonal strap is visible across his chest and
                            appears to hold a cloak that dangles behind his right arm. His bent
                            right arm rests on his bent right leg. With his right hand, he holds or
                            supports a lyre that leans against his right leg. His posture may
                            suggest melancholy. This figure may lean against the trunk of a tree
                            visible upper left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The nude male figure in the center of the composition holds a
                            staff or shepherd's crook in his left hand and supports the lyre leaning
                            against his right leg with his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The central figure may lean against the tree trunk visible in
                            the upper left corner. This tree appears to have three branches (or thin
                            leaves?) visible on either side of the trunk.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A shaded form in the upper right quadrant may be a mountain or
                            hill.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upside down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner of the composition, a nude seated
                            figure facing left is seen upside down. Likely male, this figure whose
                            head is tilted slightly down has short hair and rests his right hand in
                            his lap. Both legs are bent at the knee. He appears to hold a harp,
                            which he may play, in his lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>harp</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The seated figure seen upside down in the lower right corner
                            appears to hold a harp in his lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A standing figure, drawn sideways with head on the right,
                            appears below the main figure. This figure has both arms at its sides
                            and may wear some sort of hood or hat.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are three drawings of a nude man with short hair
                            reclining on his side, two on the right, drawn with the paper held
                            horizontally, and one of the left, similarly drawn but with the paper
                            held the other way up. Each of these figures reclines on his right side
                            with both arms at his side and left leg bent backward and perhaps
                            crossed near the ankles. The bodies face forward but their heads are
                            shown in profile facing the same direction as their extended legs. The
                            figures on the right may wear hats.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are additional indeterminate lines and forms throughout
                            the composition. Those below the central figure may be the ground below
                            him. The lines below Tatham's inscription might be a nascent human
                            form.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="15"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but81r.1.penink.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">William Blake</l>
                    <l n="but81r.1.penink.01.02" justify="left" indent="3">vouched by Frederick
                        Tatham.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
