<bad id="but86r.1" type="mono" work="An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="86r">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple">
                    <main>An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
 <updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>           
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>August 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
              <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                     <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                     <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                     <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                     <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                     <name>Kirk V. Hastings</name>
                    and <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                     <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                     <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                     <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                     <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.B">c. 1785-90<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>13.1 x 11.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.2 x 15.1 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>PRO PATRIA<note>Only part of the watermark is present.  The other part is on Butlin 85, with *A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing* on the recto and *Four Composition Sketches* on the verso.</note></watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
            
                <note>Early history unknown; John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.138</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but86r.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT86.1r.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 86 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>13.1 x 11.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote><p>A pen and ink drawing, *Four Composition Sketches*, is on the verso of this monochrome wash drawing.  This leaf was originally one half of a larger leaf.  The other half is Butlin 85, with *A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing* on the recto and *Four Composition Sketches* on the verso.</p></objnote>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, two figures sit on a shoreline and look up to the left where a third figure appears above them in the upper left corner. The rightmost seated figure is male and has somewhat long, curly hair. He is nude except for a loincloth covering his genitals. He leans back and to the right with his left arm braced on the ground and slightly bent. His right arm appears to be close at his side. His right leg is bent upward with his heel resting on the ground at left, and his left leg is on the ground and bent beneath his right knee. His head is turned up to look toward the figure hovering above at left. Seated on the ground behind and slightly left of the male figure, a female figure also turns her head up to look toward the figure above. She has long hair and appears to be nude. Both arms are bent upward with hands together in front of her chest. Both legs are extended to the left and may be slightly bent. The female figure's right foot appears to be submerged in the water visible across the lower margin of the composition. The third figure emerges from the upper left side of the design, and only his upper body, which is positioned horizontally facing right, is visible. This figure has short hair and may be male(?). He appears to fly or hover in the air. He wears a long-sleeved shirt and additional drapery may be seen around his right shoulder. His right arm is raised and extended to the right with right hand above the seated pair of figures below. Washes and lines suggest clouds in the sky across the upper half of the plate. A shadowy, perhaps leafy tree is visible against the right side of the design. The ground beneath the central seated figures may be sand, and water is visible both below and behind them at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, two figures sit on a shoreline and look up to the left where a third figure appears above them in the upper left corner. The rightmost seated figure is male and has somewhat long, curly hair. He is muscular and nude except for a loincloth covering his genitals. He reclines or leans back and to the right with his left arm braced on the ground and slightly bent. His right arm appears to be close at his side. His right leg is bent upward with his heel resting on the ground at left, and his left leg is on the ground and bent beneath his right knee. His head is turned up to look toward the figure hovering above at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the composition, two figures sit on a shoreline and look up to the left where a third figure appears above them in the upper left corner. Behind and left of the male figure, the female figure also turns her head up to look toward the figure above and leans backward to the right. She has long hair and appears to be nude with prominent breasts. Both arms are bent upward with hands together, perhaps in a position of prayer, in front of her chest. Both legs are extended to the left and may be slightly bent. The female figure's right foot appears to be submerged in the water visible across the lower margin of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third figure emerges from the upper left side of the design, and only his upper body, which is positioned horizontally facing right, is visible. This figure has short hair and may be male(?). He appears to fly or hover in the air. He wears a long-sleeved shirt and additional drapery may be seen around his right shoulder. His right arm, which is slightly bent, is raised and extended to the right with right hand above the seated pair of figures below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clouds</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Washes and lines suggest clouds in the sky across the upper half of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A shadowy, perhaps leafy tree is visible against the right side of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sand</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The central two figures appear to sit on a shore. The ground beneath the central seated figures may be sand, and water is visible both below and behind them at left. Waves appear in the water.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
