<bad id="but828.1" type="ms" work="Genesis" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="butlin" catid="828.1">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Genesis">
                    <main>Genesis</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
               </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
               </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill </principal>
                <respstmt>
                    
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and
               the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 475KB; 22 JPEG
            (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 34KB to 1000KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>February 2016</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of the <hi rend="i">Genesis</hi> manuscript from the Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                    In the last year of his life, Blake began an illuminated manuscript of the biblical Book of Genesis for his patron, John Linnell.  Of its eleven large leaves, probably cut from Whatman Imperial-sized wove paper, the first two are title pages.  The text on leaves 3-11 closely follows chapters 1-4 of the King James Bible, decorated with sketched headpieces, tailpieces, and interlinear designs, with chapter headings of Blake’s own invention that align the biblical creation narrative with his myth of creation, division, and forgiveness.  His insertion of “adamah” after most appearances of “ground” in the English text shows Blake’s (and his patron’s) engagement with the original Hebrew, underscores Blake’s view that the creation of the first man was a descent into materiality, and suggests that Adam was originally androgynous because “adamah” is a feminine noun.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Like the title pages of a number of Blake’s early illuminated books, his lettering of the <hi rend="i">Genesis</hi> titles is closely integrated with the illustrations. The reason for variant title pages is not clear, though perhaps Linnell responded unfavorably to the first version (our object 1) and requested the more elegant second version.  The main text was composed in six stages, beginning with horizontal lines to guide the lettering.  Then Blake drafted the biblical text in light pencil—in a style that mimics the Gothic lettering of medieval illuminated manuscripts—and composed the chapter headings.  In subsequent stages he overwrote his earlier work in darker pencil, red and green ink, and occasional gold leaf. Thus Blake revised his preliminary intentions with forms evolving on the same matrix. <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake’s use of headpiece and tailpiece pairings to denote chapter divisions conforms to eighteenth-century conventions for illustrated books and follows the format of his early illuminated books, such as <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (1789) and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793). Taken together, the headpieces and chapter headings provide visual and verbal introductions to each chapter that signal Blake’s reinterpretations of the narrative.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                The unfinished state of the <hi rend="i">Genesis</hi> designs offers insights into Blake’s method of graphic composition. There is no obvious sequence to the development of the designs. Those on leaves 3–5 have some coloring, including green, over the initial pencil sketches, suggesting that Blake added washes as he overwrote the penciled text in green. The designs on leaves 6–11 are noticeably rougher and uncolored, like the texts on these leaves. Blake clearly did not finish designs before moving on to start others, probably intending to return later to develop his preliminary drawings. The compositional process was evidently non-linear, spontaneous, and rapid.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                The manuscript, left unfinished at Blake’s death in August 1827, leaves off with his interpretation of the story of Cain as an exemplary tale of forgiveness, a major theme in his later writings.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2016</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
         Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
         Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms,
         in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification
         of the publisher, the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities. Permission to
         reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the
         originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>This image copyright © 2016 Huntington Library and Art Gallery.<lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February 2016</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2005</change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
               </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
               </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Project Manager and
                  Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Conversion: </resp>
                    <name>Aziza Technology Associates</name>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Sarah E. Jones, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley </name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>SGML BAD created</change>
                <date>February 2003</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
               </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
               </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Images acquired, scanned and catalogued</change>
                <date>November 1998</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
               </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
               </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Project Manager and
                  Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Greg Murray</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title type="transcribed">*Genesis*</title>
                    <title type="alt">Illustrated Manuscript of Genesis</title>
                    <title type="alt">Illuminated Genesis Manuscript</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist. Blake invented, executed, and colored the designs and delineated both
                  the designs and the text, taken from the King James Bible. He also made changes in
                  the King James text; see the textual transcription and editors' notes. Blake is
                  the author of the chapter headings in objects 3, 6, 8, and 10. For a list of
                  substantive differences between Blake's manuscript and the King James Bible, see
                  Crosby and Essick pages 11-13.</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1827">1827<note>Butlin 828 dates the manuscript to c. 1826-27,
                  but Crosby and Essick say work was not begun until 1827 (Crosby and Essick page 30).</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>11</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-11</objorder>
                <objsize>ranging between 38.1 x 28.0 cm. and 37.8 x 27.2 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>11</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>ranging between 38.1 x 28.0 cm. and 37.8 x 27.2 cm.<note>Each leaf has two
                  contiguous deckled edges and appears to be a quarter of a sheet measuring
                  approximately 76 x 56 cm. in total, the dimensions of James Whatman's
                  "Imperial"-size paper (Crosby and Essick page 31).</note>
                </leafsize>
                <medium>pencil, pen and ink, water color, and shell gold<note>Illustrations are in
                  pencil, with pen and water color in objects 1-5. The text has been written in
                  pencil; often a layer of lighter pencil is visible beneath a darker layer. The
                  text in objects 1 and 2 (the two title pages) also shows the application of a
                  gray-black wash and red water color. Much of the penciled text has been written
                  over in red ink in objects 3-5; green tinting has been applied to the text,
                  presumably at a later stage than the red ink, in objects 3-5 and part of object 6.
                  Shell gold (powdered gold mixed in water with a glue or gum binder) has been added to objects 2 (second title page) and 3. See Crosby and Essick pages 31-32, 36.</note>
                </medium>
                <inkcolor>See the note on medium, above.</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>"J WHATMAN / TURKEY MILL / 1821" and "J WHATMAN / 1826"<note>The 1821
                  watermark appears only on object 1, and the 1826 watermark appears on objects 2
                  and 7. The leaf bearing the 1821 watermark was cut from different stock than the
                  leaves bearing the 1826 watermark (Crosby and Essick pages 31,
               49n70).</note>
                </watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1 <note>Object 1 has one framing line, drawn in pencil. Object 2 has an
                  incomplete framing line, drawn roughly in pencil, that surrounds only the upper
                  part of the illustration.</note>
                </framelines>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name>
                <date>1918</date>
                <dealer>George D. Smith</dealer>
                <price>£157.10s.</price>
                <note>Commissioned and acquired from Blake by John Linnell (although Linnell may not
               have taken possession until after Blake's death); sold by the Linnell estate,
               Christie's, 15 March 1918, lot 192 (£157.10s. to George D. Smith acting for
               Henry E. Huntington).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution>
                <addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline>
                <addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline>
                <addressline>United States</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2100</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 626-405-2191</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 626-405-3477</addressline>
                <addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: readerregistration@huntington.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline>
                <department>Art Division</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">000.32-42</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.01" dbi="but828.1.1.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Genesis</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 828.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>38.1 x 27.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>Crosby and Essick conclude that this title page was created before the title page
                  shown in object 2 (page 36).</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design is compositionally arranged around the title letters and
                  eight human, or at least semi-human figures. The division of the title into three
                  lines may be an allusion to the Trinity, also depicted visually. At the top of the
                  design is a nude, male striding figure, with prominent buttocks and extended arms,
                  raised horizontally, moving left to right. The figure is seen from behind and his
                  head appears to face left. This is the Holy Ghost. Either side of the Holy Ghost
                  are lightly sketched wings. The light wavy pencil lines either side of the wings
                  may depict the firmament or heaven. The figure below and to the left of the Holy
                  Ghost, and next to the "N" of the title, faces forward and is kneeling in a
                  sphere. This figure is male and wears a tight fitting garment. The figure has
                  long, wild hair and a pointed chin or possibly a short beard. This is Christ, God
                  the Son. His left arm extends horizontally to the right, over the top of the "N,"
                  and his left hand, palm downward, may be touching the raised right hand of the
                  figure below. God the Son's right arm is bent slightly at the elbow and partially
                  rests on his left thigh. His left leg is bent at the knee and his left foot is
                  visible. God the Son kneels on his right knee and he may be looking right,
                  although his eyes are only slits. The figure to the right of God the Son occupies
                  a mandorla and is male with long, wild hair and a long beard. This is God the
                  Father. He faces forward and is wearing a long flowing robe. His right arm is
                  raised vertically and is bent slightly at the elbow. His right hand is palm up and
                  his left arm is at his side. His left knee may be bent slightly and the pencil and
                  ink lines below the robe suggest feet. The wavy pencil and water color lines above
                  and below the mandorla may represent water. The positioning of God the Father's
                  arms, his right arm counterbalancing his left, suggests that he is dividing the
                  waters under the firmament (or sky) from the waters above the firmament as
                  described in Genesis 1:7. In the lower center of the design is a standing nude,
                  male figure with curly hair, facing forward. This is Adam. His head and upper
                  torso are surrounded by a large halo. A few lines emanating from the halo suggest
                  that it may also be a radiant sun behind Adam. Adam extends both arms, his right
                  arm is raised vertically and in his right hand he may be touching the left hand of
                  the figure above and to the left. Adam's head is tilted back and to the left
                  slightly. He appears to be looking up. Adam's left arm is raised horizontally at
                  135 degrees. His legs are bent slightly at the knee and he is standing on a convex
                  arc that represents the surface of the Earth. The letter "I" in the title covers
                  his loins, almost like a loincloth. Beneath Adam, four possibly nude creatures are
                  pictured with flames above their heads. They may be sitting or kneeling in water,
                  as indicated by a few serpentine splashes of blue wash, or on the Earth, as the
                  green patches of coloring might suggest. These figures have distinct humanoid
                  features. The leftmost figure faces forward and both arms are raised vertically.
                  The fingers on the right hand are spread and its head is tilted back slightly.
                  This creature's legs appear to be bent and it is possibly kneeling. The second
                  figure from the left faces forward and appears to have its arms bent across the
                  chest, with hand in an attitude of supplication or possibly surprise. The second
                  figure from the right faces forward,with the head facing left, and its right arm
                  is raised vertically. The fingers of its right hand appear to be spread. Its left
                  arm is by its side and may be supporting the creature. The left leg appears to be
                  bent at the knee. The rightmost figure faces forward and to the left. Its right
                  arm is raised vertically and the fingers of its right hand are spread. This
                  creature's eyes are open and it looks up and to the left. Wavy pencil lines below
                  these four creatures probably represent water. Light wavy pencil lines either side
                  of these creatures may represent smoke or clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Holy Ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wings</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>heaven</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the top of the design is a nude, male striding (and perhaps
                     soaring) figure with prominent buttocks and extended arms, raised horizontally,
                     moving left to right. The figure is seen from behind and his head appears to
                     face left. This is the Holy Ghost. Either side of the Holy Ghost are lightly
                     sketched wings. The light wavy pencil lines either side of the wings may depict
                     the firmament. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clothing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sphere</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure below and to the left of the Holy Ghost, and next to the
                     "N" of the title, faces forward and is kneeling in a sphere. This figure is
                     male and wears a tight fitting garment. The figure has long, wild hair and a
                     pointed chin or possibly a short beard. This is Christ, God the Son. His left
                     arm extends horizontally to the right, over the top of the "N" and his left
                     hand, palm downward, may be touching the raised right hand of the figure below.
                     God the Son's right arm is bent slightly at the elbow and partially rests on
                     his left thigh. His left leg is bent at the knee and his left foot is visible.
                     God the Son kneels on his right knee and he may be looking right, although his
                     eyes are only slits.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clothing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knee bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm by side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mandorla</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dividing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure to the right of God the Son occupies a mandorla and is
                     male with long, wild hair and a long beard. This is God the Father. He faces
                     forward and is wearing a long flowing robe. His right arm is raised vertically
                     and is bent slightly at the elbow. His right hand is palm up and his left arm
                     is at his side. His left knee may be bent slightly and the pencil and ink lines
                     below the robe suggest feet. The wavy pencil and water color lines above and
                     below the mandorla may represent water. The positioning of God the Father's
                     arms, his right arm counterbalancing his left, suggests that he is dividing the
                     waters under the firmament (or sky) from the waters above the firmament as
                     described in Genesis 1:7.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>aura</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower center of the design is a standing nude, male figure
                     with curly hair, facing forward. This is Adam. His head and upper torso are
                     surrounded by a large halo. A few lines emanating from the halo suggest that it
                     may also be a radiant sun behind Adam. Adam extends both arms, his right arm is
                     raised vertically and in his right hand may touch the left hand of the figure
                     above and to the left. Adam's head is tilted back and to the left slightly. He
                     appears to be looking up. Adam's left arm is raised horizontally at 135
                     degrees. His legs are bent slightly at the knee and he is standing on a convex
                     arc that represents the surface of the Earth. The letter "I" in the title
                     covers his loins, almost like a loincloth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flames</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplication</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prayer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on the ground</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath Adam, four possibly nude creatures are pictured with flames
                     above their heads. They may be sitting or kneeling in water, as indicated by a
                     few serpentine splashes of blue wash, or on the Earth, as the green patches of
                     coloring might suggest. These figures have distinct humanoid features. The
                     leftmost figure faces forward and both arms are raised vertically. The fingers
                     on the right hand are spread and its head is tilted back slightly. This
                     creature's legs appear to be bent and drawn up, it is possibly kneeling. The
                     second figure from the left faces forward and appears to have its arms bent
                     across the chest, with hand in an attitude of supplication or possibly
                     surprise. The second figure from the right faces forward,with the head facing
                     left, and its right arm is raised vertically. The fingers of its right hand
                     appear to be spread. Its left arm is by its side and may be supporting the
                     creature. The left leg appears to be bent at the knee. The rightmost figure
                     faces forward and to the left. Its right arm is raised vertically and the
                     fingers of its right hand are spread. This creature's eyes are open and it
                     looks up and to the left. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clouds</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Wavy pencil lines below these four creatures probably represent
                     water. Light wavy pencil lines either side of these creatures may represent
                     smoke or clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The convex pencil arc that Adam is standing on may represent the
                     surface of the Earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trinity</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The title, "GENESIS," is divided into three parts, possibly
                     indicating the Trinity. The letter shapes suggest Gothic art. The central
                     horizontal of both letters "E" terminate in a fleur-de-lis; the "I" suggests a
                     pillar. The text is integrated into the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.01.01" justify="left" indent="36">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>G</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>E</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.01.02" justify="left" indent="36">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>N</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>E</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.01.03" justify="left" indent="35">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>S</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>I</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>S</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.02" dbi="but828.1.2.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U2">(Butlin 828.2)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.9 x 27.9 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>Crosby and Essick suggest that the differences in style, coloring, and brushwork
                  between the first and second title pages may reveal Blake's desire to suit the
                  preferences of his sponsor, John Linnell, more fully in the latter design (page
                  40).</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design is compositionally arranged around the title letters and
                  eight human, or at least semi-human figures. The division of the title into three
                  lines may be an allusion to the Trinity, also depicted visually. At the top of the
                  design is a nude, male striding figure, with prominent buttocks and extended arms,
                  raised horizontally, moving left to right. The figure is seen from behind and his
                  head appears to face right. This is the Holy Ghost. Either side of the Holy Ghost
                  are lightly sketched wings. The light wavy pencil lines either side of the wings
                  may depict the firmament (or heaven). The figure below and to the left of the Holy
                  Ghost, and next to the "N" of the title, faces forward in a cruciform pose. This
                  figure is male and wears a flowing diaphanous robe. The figure has long hair and a
                  short beard. This is Christ, God the Son. His head face right and he may be
                  looking. Both arms are raised horizontally, palms down. In his left hand, God the
                  Son holds the end of a scroll. His right leg is bent slightly at the knee and his
                  right foot is on tip toe. He may be hovering. The figure to the right of God the
                  Son occupies a mandorla and is male with long hair and a long beard. This is God
                  the Father. He faces forward and is wearing a long flowing robe. His right arm is
                  raised vertically. His right hand is palm up and his left arm is at his side. His
                  left knee may be bent slightly. The wavy pencil and water color lines above and
                  below the mandorla may represent water. The positioning of God the Father's arms,
                  his right arm counterbalancing his left, suggests that he is dividing the waters
                  under the firmament (sky) from the waters above the firmament as described in
                  Genesis 1:7. In the central area between the upper two lines of the title letters,
                  "G E / N E," are two palm trees. The title letters are decorated with flowering
                  vegetation. The upper arm of the "G" incorporates a large green leaf. Three
                  funnel-shaped forms, possibly seed pods of the lotus, dangle from the lower
                  horizontal arm of the "G." The right vertical of the "G" is formed like a sheaf of
                  grain with grain tassels upper left. The "E" contains three blooming roses and
                  possibly blades of grass or grain. The "N" contains a serpentine stem that
                  terminates in a five- or six-petal bloom, perhaps a lotus flower. The second "E"
                  includes serpentine tendrils and a star-shaped blossom, possibly the lily of
                  Calvary. The final three letters, "S I S," are devoid of flowers. Both letters "S"
                  are composed of sheafs or shafts of grain or grass. The first "S" also contains
                  three ovoid shapes on the upper left. The "I" is depicted as a classical pillar
                  with a curving, circular flourish at the top left. In the lower center of the
                  design is a standing nude, male figure with curly hair, facing forward. This is
                  Adam. His head and upper torso are surrounded by a large halo. Lines emanating
                  from the halo suggest that it may also be a radiant sun behind Adam. Adam extends
                  both arms; his right arm is raised vertically and in his right hand he holds the
                  same scroll held by God the Son. Adam's head faces to the left slightly. Adam's
                  left arm is raised horizontally, bent at the elbow, and his left hand is palm up.
                  His legs are bent slightly at the knee, with his left foot on tiptoe. He is
                  standing on a convex arc that represents the surface of the Earth. Beneath Adam
                  are four possibly nude creatures. They may be sitting or kneeling in water, as
                  indicated by the wavy pencil lines a black washes below them. These figures have
                  distinct humanoid features. The body of the leftmost figure faces forward and his
                  head faces right in profile. The creature is wearing a crown and a flame-like
                  tongue flicks out of its open mouth. It is looking upward and to the right. Its
                  left arm is raised vertically and is bent at the elbow. This arm is covered is
                  scales. The left hand is palm up. The creature's right breast is covered in
                  scales. Its right arms extands downward and the right palm faces downward. The
                  creature is sitting and the right arm appears to be supporting its upper body. The
                  creature's legs are together and are bent. The body of the second figure from the
                  left faces forward and its head faces right. It has a bird-like head with curved
                  beak and large oval eye looking up and right. It is wearing a crown and its left
                  arm is bent across the chest. Its right arm is by its side and may be bent at the
                  elbow(?). The creature's legs are together and are drawn up in a sitting position.
                  The body of second figure from the right faces forward and to the right. The
                  creature's head face forward and slightly to the left. The figure has short curly
                  hair or fur on its head, shoulders and neck. This figure's head suggests a lion.
                  Its eyes and mouth are open and his tongue is visible. The creature's arms are
                  across its chest and its hands are in a position of prayer or supplication. Its
                  legs are together and are drawn up in a sitting posture. The body of the rightmost
                  figure faces forward and to the right while the head faces forward and to the
                  left. This creature has a cow- or ox-like head with two curved horns, two open
                  eyes and large nostrils. This creature is looking to the left. The creature's arms
                  are across its chest and its hands are raised, palms vertical, in a gesture that
                  suggests surprise. Its legs are together and are drawn up in a sitting posture.
                  Wavy pencil lines below these four creatures probably represent water. Behind the
                  rightmost and leftmost creatures are two fruit-bearing trees with thick trunks and
                  leafy branches. The tree on the left of the design bears ovoid-shaped fruit while
                  the tree on the right of the design bears grape-like clusters of fruits. These
                  trees represent the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil and the Tree of
                  Life.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Holy Ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wings</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>heaven</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the top of the design is a nude, male striding (and perhaps
                     soaring) figure with prominent buttocks and extended arms, raised horizontally,
                     moving left to right. The figure is seen from behind and his head appears to
                     face right. This is the Holy Ghost. Either side of the Holy Ghost are lightly
                     sketched wings. The light wavy pencil lines either side of the wings may depict
                     the firmament (or heaven). </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clothing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure below and to the left of the Holy Ghost, and next to the
                     "N" of the title, faces forward in a cruciform pose. This figure is male and
                     wears a flowing diaphanous robe. The figure has long hair and a short beard.
                     This is Christ, God the Son. His head face right and he may be looking. Both
                     arms are raised horizontally, palms down. In his left hand, God the Son holds
                     the end of a scroll. His right leg is bent slightly at the knee and his right
                     foot is on tiptoe. He may be hovering.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clothing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>knee bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm by side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mandorla</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dividing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure to the right of God the Son occupies a mandorla and is
                     male with long, wild hair and a long beard. This is God the Father. He faces
                     forward and is wearing a long flowing robe. His right arm is raised vertically
                     and his right hand is palm up. His left arm is at his side. His left knee may
                     be bent slightly. The wavy pencil and water color lines above and below the
                     mandorla may represent water. The positioning of God the Father's arms, his
                     right arm counterbalancing his left, suggests that he is dividing the waters
                     under the firmament (sky) from the waters above the firmament as described in
                     Genesis 1:7.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>aura</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loincloth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower center of the design is a standing nude, male figure
                     with curly hair, facing forward. This is Adam. His head and upper torso are
                     surrounded by a large halo. Lines emanating from the halo suggest that it may
                     also be a radiant sun behind Adam. Adam extends both arms, his right arm is
                     raised vertically and in his right hand he holds the same scroll held by God
                     the Son. Adam's head faces to the left slightly. Adam's left arm is raised
                     horizontally, bent at the elbow, and his left hand is palm up. His legs are
                     bent slightly at the knee, with his left foot on tip toe. He is standing on a
                     convex arc that represents the surface of the earth. The "I" of the title
                     covers his loins, almost like a loincloth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eye raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on the ground</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath Adam are four possibly nude creatures. They may be sitting
                     or kneeling in water, as indicated by the wavy pencil lines a black washes
                     below them. These figures have distinct humanoid features. The body of the
                     leftmost figure faces forward and his head faces right in profile. The creature
                     is wearing a crown and a flame-like tongue flicks out of its open mouth. It is
                     looking upward and to the right. Its left arm is raised vertically and is bent
                     at the elbow. This arm is covered is scales. The left hand is palm up. The
                     creature's right breast is covered in scales. Its right arms extands downward
                     and the right palm faces downward. The creature is sitting and the right arm
                     appears to be supporting its upper body. The creature's legs are together and
                     are bent. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath Adam are four possibly nude creatures. They may be sitting
                     or kneeling in water, as indicated by the wavy pencil lines a black washes
                     below them. These figures have distinct humanoid features. The body of the
                     second figure from the left faces forward and its head faces right. It has a
                     bird-like head with feathered face, curved beak and large oval eye looking up
                     and right. It is wearing a crown and its left arm is bent across the chest. Its
                     right arm is by its side and may be bent at the elbow(?). The creature's legs
                     are together and are drawn up in a sitting position.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prayer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplication</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fur</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lion</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath Adam are four possibly nude creatures. They may be sitting
                     or kneeling in water, as indicated by the wavy pencil lines a black washes
                     below them. These figures have distinct humanoid features. The body of second
                     figure from the right faces forward and to the right. The creature's head faces
                     forward and slightly to the left. The figure has short curly hair or fur on its
                     head, shoulders and neck. Its face suggests a lion. Its eyes and mouth are open
                     and its tongue is visible. The creature's arms are across its chest and its
                     hands are in a position of prayer or supplication. Its legs are together and
                     are drawn up in a sitting posture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>ox</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fur</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Beneath Adam are four possibly nude creatures. They may be sitting
                     or kneeling in water, as indicated by the wavy pencil lines a black washes
                     below them. These figures have distinct humanoid features.The body of the
                     rightmost figure faces forward and to the right while the head faces forward
                     and to the left. This creature has a cow- or ox-like head with two curved
                     horns, two open eyes and large nostrils. This creature is looking to the left.
                     The creature's arms are across its chest and its hands are raised with palms
                     vertical in a gesture that suggests surprise. Its legs are together and are
                     drawn up in a sitting posture.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Wavy pencil lines below these four creatures probably represent
                     water.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The convex pencil arc that Adam is standing on may represent the
                     surface of the Earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grape</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Tree of Knowledge</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Tree of Life</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the rightmost and leftmost creatures are two fruit-bearing
                     trees with thick trunks and leafy branches. The tree on the left of the design
                     bears ovoid-shaped fruit while the tree on the right of the design bears
                     grape-like clusters of fruits. These trees represent the Tree of the Knowledge
                     of Good and Evil and the Tree of Life.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>vegetation</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blossom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lotus</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rose</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stamen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the central area between the upper two lines of the title
                     letters, "G E / N E," are two palm trees. The title letters are decorated with
                     flowering vegetation. The upper arm of the "G" incorporates a large green leaf.
                     Three funnel-shaped forms, possibly seed pods of the lotus, dangle from the
                     lower horizontal arm of the "G." The right vertical of the "G" is formed like a
                     sheaf of grain with grain tassels upper left. The "E" contains three blooming
                     roses and perhaps blades of grass or grain. The "N" contains are serpentine
                     stem that terminates in a five- or six-petal bloom, perhaps a lotus flower. The
                     second "E" includes serpentine tendrils and a star-shaped blossom with a
                     prominent stamen that could be a lily of Calvary. The final three letters, "S I
                     S," are devoid of flowers. Both letters "S" are composed of sheafs or shafts of
                     grain or grass. The first "S" also contains three ovoid shapes on the upper
                     left. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The title letters are separated into three units, suggestive of the
                     Trinity. The letter forms suggest Gothic art. The "I" is shaped like a
                     classical pillar.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.02.01" justify="left" indent="36">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>G</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>E</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.02.02" justify="left" indent="36">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>N</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>E</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.02.03" justify="left" indent="35">
                        <choice>
                            <orig>S</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <space extent="2"/>I<space extent="2"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>S</orig>
                            <reg>Genesis</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.03" dbi="but828.1.3.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Creation of the Natural Man</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U3">(Butlin 828.3)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.7 x 27.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains red and green ink as well as pencil markings. Crosby and
                  Essick note that the "partly erased" pencil writing visible around the chapter
                  heading suggests that Blake initially wrote Genesis verses 1-2 higher on the page
                  than in his later writing (page 7n). Crosby and Essick call attention to
                  underwriting such as this in the manuscript but do not transcribe it (page 1);
                  they use textual notes to detail many individual occurrences. In this
                  transcription, legible underwriting has been transcribed when it differs
                  significantly from Blake's later writing in content or position. When the
                  underwritten text is identical but appears in a different location, gray font has
                  been used to distinguish underwriting from other text. Please note that gray font
                  is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to describe unclear or conjectural
                  text. </p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="AB">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts a bearded deity in the act of creation. In the
                  center of the design is a male, possibly nude, facing forward, with long beard and
                  hair. This is God the Father in the act of creation. With his left hand, this
                  figure points downward. His right arm is bent upward and the right palm faces
                  outward in a gesture of benediction. Either side of this central figure are the
                  heads and upper bodies of two, possibly male, attendants with curly hair. The
                  figure on the right has its left arm raised between the horizontal and 135 degrees
                  with the left palm upward. This figure appears to be looking down. The attendant
                  figure on the left is looking downward. Its right arm is raised horizontally at
                  135 degrees with the left palm upward. Two large wings extend from both attendant
                  figures suggesting that they are angels. Loose pencil strokes immediately below
                  and either side of these figures could represent clouds. The scene probably takes
                  place in heaven.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>creating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blessing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a male, possibly nude, facing
                     forward, with long beard and hair. The figure may be floating, flying, or
                     hovering. With his left hand, this figure points downward. His right arm is
                     bent upward and the right palm faces outward in a gesture of benediction or
                     blessing. This is God the Father in the act of creation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Either side of this central figure are the heads and upper bodies of
                     two, possibly male, attendants with curly hair. The figure on the right has its
                     left arm raised between the horizontal and 135 degrees with the left palm
                     upward. This figure appears to be looking down. The attendant figure on the
                     left is looking down. Its right arm is raised at 135 degrees with the left palm
                     upward. Two large wings extend from both attendant figures suggesting that they
                     are angels. These figures may be flying, floating, or hovering.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>heaven</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Curving lines below, left, and right of the figures may be clouds.
                     The scene probably takes place in heaven.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="7"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.01" justify="left" indent="25">Chap:<space extent="2"/>1<space extent="24"/>
                        <del type="erasure">&amp; the Earth</del>
                        <note>Bentley reads "I"
                     for "1" (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1344). Illegible
                     underwriting appears in this line in addition to the legible "&amp; the Earth".
                     Crosby and Essick note that the "[f]ragmentary and partly erased" underwriting
                     in the upper part of this object suggests Blake initially wrote verses 1-2 in
                     the area now occupied by the headpiece illustration, chapter heading, and
                     chapter title (page 7n). See also Crosby and Essick page 32.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.02" justify="left" indent="57">
                        <del type="erasure">&amp; the
                     Spirit</del>
                        <note>Illegible underwriting in this line in addition to the legible "&amp; the
                     Spirit". Crosby and Essick note that the "[f]ragmentary and partly erased"
                     underwriting in the upper part of this object suggests Blake initially wrote
                     verses 1-2 in the area now occupied by the headpiece illustration, chapter
                     heading, and chapter title (page 7n). See also Crosby and Essick page
                     32.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.03" justify="left" indent="16">The Creation of the Natural
                  Man.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.04" justify="left">1<space extent="3"/>In the beginning God
                  created the heavens and the earth<note>The King James Bible reads "the heaven and"
                     rather than "the heavens and" (Crosby and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.05" justify="left">2<space extent="3"/>And the earth was without
                  form and void. and darkness was upon the face</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.06" justify="left" indent="7">of the deep &amp; the spirit of
                  God moved upon the face of the waters</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.07" justify="left">3<space extent="3"/>And God said Let there be
                  light and there was light</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.08" justify="left">4<space extent="3"/>And God saw the light
                  that it was good &amp; God divided the light from the darkness</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.09" justify="left">5<space extent="3"/>And God called the light
                  day &amp; the darkness he called night &amp; the evening &amp; the</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.10" justify="left" indent="8">morning were the first day.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.11" justify="left">6<space extent="3"/>And God said Let there be
                  a firmament in the midst of the waters and Let</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.12" justify="left" indent="10">it divide the waters from the
                  waters</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.13" justify="left">7<space extent="3"/>And God made the
                  firmament &amp; divided the waters which were under the firmament</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.14" justify="left" indent="8">from the waters which were above
                  the firmament and it was so<space extent="12"/>
                        <catchword>day</catchword>
                        <note>The
                     word "day", carried over in this line, is the last word of the following line
                     (Crosby and Essick 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.15" justify="left">8<space extent="3"/>And God called the
                  firmament heaven. &amp; the evening &amp; the morning were the second<note>The
                     word "day", carried over in the previous line, is the last word of this line
                     (Crosby and Essick 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.16" justify="left">9<space extent="3"/>And God said Let the
                  waters under the heaven be <choice>
                            <orig>gatherd</orig>
                            <reg>gathered</reg>
                        </choice> together into one place</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.17" justify="left" indent="8">and let the dry land appear and it
                  was so.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.18" justify="left">10<space extent="2"/>And God called the dry
                  land earth. &amp; the gathering together of waters called he<note>The King James
                     Bible reads "together of the waters" rather than "together of waters" (Crosby
                     and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.19" justify="left" indent="8">seas and God saw that it was
                  good.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.20" justify="left">11<space extent="2"/>And God said Let the
                  earth bring forth grass &amp; the herb yielding seed and<note>The King James Bible
                     reads "grass, the herb" rather than "grass &amp; the herb" (Crosby and Essick
                     page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.21" justify="left" indent="7">the fruit tree yielding fruit
                  after its kind whose seed is in itself upon<note>The King James Bible reads "fruit
                     after his kind" rather than "fruit after its kind" (Crosby and Essick page
                     11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.22" justify="left" indent="7">the earth and it was so</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.23" justify="left">12<space extent="2"/>And the earth brought
                  forth grass &amp; herb yielding seed and the tree yielding<note>The King James
                     Bible reads "herb yielding seed after his kind, and the tree" rather than "herb
                     yielding seed and the tree" (Crosby and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.24" justify="left" indent="7">fruit whose seed is in itself
                  after its kind and God saw that it was good<note>The King James Bible reads "whose
                     seed was in itself, after his kind" rather than "whose seed is in itself after
                     its kind" (Crosby and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.25" justify="left">13<space extent="2"/>And the evening &amp;
                  the morning were the third day.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.26" justify="left">14<space extent="2"/>And God said Let there
                  be lights in the firmament of heaven to divide the<note>The King James Bible reads
                     "firmament of the heaven" rather than "firmament of heaven" (Crosby and Essick
                     page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.27" justify="left" indent="8">day from the night and let them be
                  for signs and for seasons and for days</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.28" justify="left" indent="8">and for years:<note>The King James
                     Bible reads "and years" rather than "and for years" (Crosby and Essick page
                     11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.29" justify="left">15<space extent="2"/>And let them be for
                  lights in the firmament of the heaven to give light upon</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.30" justify="left" indent="8">the earth and it was so.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.31" justify="left">16<space extent="2"/>And God made two great
                  lights, the greater light to rule the day and the</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.32" justify="left" indent="8">lesser light to rule the night he
                  made the stars also.</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.33" justify="left">17<space extent="2"/>And God set them in the
                  firmament of heaven to give light upon the earth<note>The King James Bible reads
                     "firmament of the heaven" rather than "firmament of heaven" (Crosby and Essick
                     page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.34" justify="left">18<space extent="2"/>And to rule over the day
                  and over the night and to divide the light from</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.03.35" justify="left" indent="10">the darkness<note>The King James
                     Bible reads "the darkness: and God saw that it was good." rather than, simply,
                     "the darkness" (Crosby and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.04" dbi="but828.1.4.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U4">(Butlin 828.4)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.9 x 27.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains a number of light pencil markings, some of which are legible.
                  These appear to be remnants of Blake's first writing that were erased or
                  overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call attention to this
                  underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual notes to detail
                  many individual occurrences. In this transcription, legible underwriting has been
                  transcribed when it differs significantly from Blake's later writing in content or
                  position. When the underwritten text is identical but appears in a different
                  location, gray font has been used to distinguish underwriting from other text.
                  Please note that gray font is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to
                  describe unclear or conjectural text. Ruled lines, drawn in pencil, are visible in
                  lines 9-14 of this object.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="AB">
                    <illusobjdesc>The three major designs on this leaf appear to be compositionally
                  related, with each panel representing an aspect of creation. At the top of the
                  leaf are three winged, possibly male, figures. Above these figures are four
                  six-pointed stars. Between the three figures are two circle shapes, possibly
                  representing the sun and the moon. The leftmost figure faces to the right, in
                  profile, and has long hair. He is wearing a long flowing robe or gown and his arms
                  are raised at 45 degrees. The central figure faces away and his arms are raised at
                  135 degrees. His left leg is bent and his left is on tiptoe. The rightmost figure
                  faces forward, has long, wild hair and a pointed chin. His arms are raised at 45
                  degrees. He is wearing a long diaphanous robe or gown and his left leg may be
                  slightly bent. Wavy lines beneath these figures could represent waters. A very
                  light convex arc, representing the surface of the Earth, appears behind and on
                  either side of the central figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the top of the leaf are three winged, possibly male, figures. The
                     leftmost figure faces to the right, in profile, and has long hair. He is
                     wearing a long flowing robe or gown and his arms are raised at 45 degrees.
                  </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the top of the leaf are three winged, possibly male, figures. The
                     central figure faces away and his arms are raised at 135 degrees. His left leg
                     is bent and his left foot is on tiptoe.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the top of the leaf are three winged, possibly male, figures. The
                     rightmost figure faces forward, has long, wild hair and possibly a beard. His
                     arms are raised at 45 degrees. He is wearing a long diaphanous robe or gown and
                     his left leg may be slightly bent. This could be Christ, God the
                     Son.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>planet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are four six-pointed stars located above the winged figures.
                     Between the these figures are two circular shapes, possibly representing
                     planets, or the sun and the moon. The circle on the left includes a suggestion
                     of a crescent moon.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wave</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Wavy lines beneath these figures could represent waters. A very
                     light convex arc, representing the surface of the Earth, appears behind and
                     either side of the central figure</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The middle design panel depicts three soaring male figures in a
                  recessional configuration above waves and marine animals. The three figures are
                  flying left to right. The front figure is wearing a long flowing robe, has long
                  hair and a pointed chin. Lines above the shoulder may suggest a wing. This is
                  Christ, God the Son. His left arm is raised horizontally and extends to the right.
                  He may be looking right although his eyes are only slits. Only the head of the
                  second figure is visible. He may have long hair and a beard. His eyes appear open
                  and he may be looking right. Only the outline of the head of the third figure is
                  visible. Below these figures are rolling waves and a leaping dolphin. Very sketchy
                  lines either side of the waves may be placeholders for more sea
                  creatures.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trinity</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Holy Ghost</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The three figures are flying left to right. The front figure is
                     wearing a long flowing robe, has long hair and a pointed chin. Pencil strokes
                     above the shoulder may suggest a wing. This is Christ, God the Son. His left
                     arm is raised horizontally and extends to the right. He may be looking right
                     although his eyes are only slits. Only the head of the second figure is
                     visible. He may have long hair and a beard. His eyes appear open and he may be
                     looking right. Only the outline of the head of the third figure is visible.
                     This may be the Trinity, with Christ as the frontmost figure, God the Father in
                     the center, and the Holy Ghost.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>fish</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fin</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>jumping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the soaring figures are rolling waves and a leaping dolphin
                     with a prominent fin. The animal's eye and mouth are open. Sketchy pencil lines
                     either side of the dolphin could be placeholders for more marine
                     creatures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wave</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the soaring figures are rolling waves.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>The lower design panel comprises three clusters of pencil lines with a
                  broken line connecting them. The line may depict the surface of the Earth. The
                  central cluster of lines are close to the line and may be one or more of the
                  "creeping things" described in the text immediately above. The cluster of lines on
                  the right contains an ovoid shape with smaller ovoids inside. This may be the
                  beginnings of a face. The cluster of lines on the left suggest more living
                  creatures, possibly "kind cattle."</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="animal" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Clusters of pencil lines connected by a central, broken line, may
                     depict the "living creatures," "kind cattle" and "creeping thing" described in
                     the text immediately above. The cluster on the left may be a placeholder for
                     "kind cattle." The central cluster may be a placeholder for "creeping thing"
                     due to the proximity to the broken line. The right hand cluster depicts two
                     small ovoids inside a larger ovoid and may be a face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An broken horizontal line, possibly representing the surface of the
                     Earth, connects the cluster of pencil lines.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.01" justify="left">19<space extent="2"/>And the evening and the
                  morning were the fourth day</l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.02" justify="left">20<space extent="2"/>And God said Let the
                  waters bring forth abundantly the moving creature</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.03" justify="left" indent="8">that hath life and fowl that may
                  fly above the earth in the firmament<note>
                            <illus filename="but828.4.3.note.jpg"/>The King James Bible reads "in the open firmament" rather than "in the
                     firmament" (Crosby and Essick page 11). Crosby and Essick note that the mark to
                     the right of "firmament" is a "decorative flourish" (page 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.04" justify="left" indent="8">of heaven</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.05" justify="left">21<space extent="2"/>And God created great
                  whales and every living creature that moveth which<note>The underwritten verse
                     number "21" overlaps slightly with the number in green; the former is higher on
                     the page and further to the right.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.06" justify="left" indent="8">the waters brought forth
                  abundantly after their kind and every winged fowl</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.07" justify="left" indent="8">after his kind. and God saw that
                  it was good.</l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.08" justify="left">22<space extent="2"/>And God blessed them
                  saying Be fruitful and multiply abundantly &amp; fill<note>The King James Bible
                     reads "multiply, and fill" rather than "multiply abundantly &amp; fill" (Crosby
                     and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.09" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">the waters
                     in the seas &amp; let fowl multiply in the earth.</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.10" justify="left">23<space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">And the evening and the morning were the fifth day<space extent="13"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The underwritten verse number "23" overlaps slightly with the
                     number in green; the former is lower on the page and further to the
                     right.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.11" justify="left">24<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="2"/>And God said. Let the earth bring forth the</hi> living creature after
                     his<note>The underwritten verse number "24" overlaps slightly with the number
                     in green; the former is lower on the page and further to the right.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.12" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="8"/>kind
                        <unclear resp="EA">cattle</unclear> &amp; cre<unclear resp="EA">e</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>ping</orig>
                                <reg>creeping</reg>
                            </choice> thing &amp; beast of the </hi>earth after his kind<note>Crosby and
                     Essick note that "cattle" is unclear but that this word corresponds with the
                     text of the King James Bible (page 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.04.13" justify="left" indent="8">and it was so.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.05" dbi="but828.1.5.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U5">(Butlin 828.5)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.8 x 27.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains red and green ink as well as a number of light pencil
                  markings, some of which are legible. These appear to be remnants of Blake's first
                  writing that were erased or overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call
                  attention to this underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual
                  notes to detail many individual occurrences. Beginning in verse 27, the text in
                  green ink is often in a slightly different position than the pencil writing
                  beneath it (Crosby and Essick page 7n). In this transcription, legible
                  underwriting has been transcribed when it differs significantly from Blake's later
                  writing in content or position. When the underwritten text is identical but
                  appears in a different location, gray font has been used to distinguish
                  underwriting from other text. Please note that gray font is also used in Blake
                  Archive transcriptions to describe unclear or conjectural text. Some of the ruled
                  lines, drawn in pencil, in this object are double, fragmented, or partially
                  erased. In some cases the ruled lines bisect or lie above the text. </p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts four standing male figures in dynamic attitudes.
                  The nude figure on the left has short hair and is facing right in profile. This
                  may be Adam. His arms are raised horizontally and bent upward with fingers spread
                  and palms up. This figure's left leg extends back and is bent slightly at the
                  knee. His left foot is on tiptoe. On the right of the design are three gowned
                  figures in similar poses. All three face forward and left, and their arms are
                  raised. Their left arms are raised at 135 degrees and their right arms are raised
                  at 45 degrees, with palms up. The rightmost figure may have short hair. The
                  central figure has long hair and a beard. This may be God the Father. The leftmost
                  figure of this tripartite grouping, possibly the Trinity, may also have long hair.
                  All three figures may be holding objects in their raised left hands. Swirling
                  pencil lines either side of the four figures may represent clouds. The pencil
                  lines beneath the figures may represent the ground. </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The nude figure on the left has short hair and is facing right in
                     profile. His arms are raised horizontally and bent upward with fingers spread
                     and palms up. This could be Adam. His left leg extends back and is bent
                     slightly at the knee. He may be walking. The left foot is on
                     tiptoe.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees </characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trinity</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right of the design are three gowned figures in similar
                     poses. All three face forward and left, and their arms are raised. Their left
                     arms are raised at 135 degrees and their right arms are raised at 45 degrees,
                     with palms up. All three figures may be holding an object in their raised left
                     hands. The rightmost figure may have short hair. The central figure has long
                     hair and a beard. This may be God the Father. The leftmost figure of this
                     tripartite grouping may also have long hair. This may be the
                     Trinity.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Swirling pencil lines either side of the four figures may represent
                     clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The pencil lines beneath the figures may represent the
                     ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.01" justify="left">25<space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>And God made the beast of the earth after his kind and
                     cattle after their</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.02" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">kind and
                     every thing that creepeth upon the earth <subst>
                                <del type="erasure">af</del>
                                <gap reason="erasure" extent="8" unit="character"/>
                                <del type="erasure">kind</del>
                                <gap reason="erasure" extent="6" unit="character"/>
                                <del type="erasure">God</del>
                            </subst>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Blake may have written "Good" rather than "God". Crosby and
                     Essick note that Blake has rubbed out the the remainder of verse 25, which
                     continues on the next line. They indicate that the erased text reads, "after
                     his kind: and God saw that it was good." Red and green coloring are visible in
                     the deleted text. The "th" in "earth" has been slightly affected by the erasure
                     (page 7n). The King James Bible reads "creepeth upon the earth after his kind:
                     and God saw that it was good" (Crosby and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.03" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <subst>
                                <gap reason="erasure" extent="16" unit="character"/>
                                <del type="erasure">good</del>
                            </subst>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.04" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">26⁋<space extent="1"/>And God said Let us make</hi> man in our image after our
                  likeness &amp; Let<note>The pilcrow that appears after "26" is
                  reversed.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.05" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">them have
                     dominion</hi> over the fish of the sea and over <hi rend="underscore">the fowl
                     of t</hi>he</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.06" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">air and over
                     the ca</hi>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>ttle</orig>
                            <reg>cattle</reg>
                        </choice> and over all the earth and over every thing that<note>The King James
                     Bible reads "over every creeping thing" rather than "over every thing" (Crosby
                     and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.07" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">creepeth
                     upon the earth.<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.08" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">27<space extent="2"/>So
                     God</hi> created man in his own image, in the image of God <hi rend="underscore">created he</hi>
                        <note>The ruled line lies a bit below the
                     words in this line and bisects words in the following line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.09" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">him. male
                     and female created he them<space extent="8"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.10" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">28<unclear resp="EA">⁋</unclear>
                            <space extent="1"/>And God blessed them. and God said unto
                     them: Be <choice>
                                <orig>fruitul</orig>
                                <reg>fruitful</reg>
                            </choice> and multiply</hi>
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="but828.5.10.note.jpg"/>A
                     reverse pilcrow, written in pencil, is visible after the verse number "28";
                     Crosby and Essick do not comment on this underwriting in their textual notes
                     (see page 7). "fruitul": i.e., presumably, "fruitful". The ruled line lies a
                     bit below the words in this line and bisects words in the following
                     line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.11" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">and
                     replenish the earth and subdue it. and have dominion over the</hi>
                        <note>Crosby
                     and Essick note that the mark appearing at the end of this line is a
                     "decorative flourish" that extends down from the "y" in "multiply" at the end
                     of the previous line (page 7n). The ruled line lies a bit below the words in
                     this line and bisects words in the following line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.12" justify="left" indent="7">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>fish of the sea and over the fowl of the air and over every
                     living thing</hi>
                        <note>The ruled line lies a bit below the words in this line
                     and bisects words in the following line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.13" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">that moveth
                     upon the earth.<space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.14" justify="left">29⁋<space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">And God said: Behold I have given you every he</hi>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>rb</orig>
                            <reg>herb</reg>
                        </choice> bearing seed which<note>The pilcrow that appears after "29" is
                     reversed.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.15" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">is upon the
                     face of the earth</hi> and every tree <hi rend="underscore">in which is the
                     fruit of a tree</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "face of all the earth"
                     rather than "face of the earth," and "every tree, in the which" rather than
                     "every tree in which" (Crosby and Essick page 11).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.16" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">yielding
                     seed to you it shall be for meat<unclear resp="EA">for
                     meat</unclear>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"for meat", written in pencil, is visible at the end
                     of the line and has been transcribed in gray. Crosby and Essick note that the
                     partially legible pencil-writing at the end of the line may include these two
                     words as as well as the beginning of verse 30 (page 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.17" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">30<space extent="2"/>And </hi>to every beast of the earth and to every <hi rend="underscore">fowl
                     of the air &amp; to every thing</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.18" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">that
                     creepeth upon the earth wherein there is life I have given ev<unclear resp="EA">e</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>ry</orig>
                                <reg>every</reg>
                            </choice>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The second "e" in "every" is unclear.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.19" justify="left" indent="8">green he<hi rend="underscore">
                            <choice>
                                <orig>rb</orig>
                                <reg>herb</reg>
                            </choice> for meat. and it was so. <space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Crosby and
                     Essick read the mark after "meat" as a period but note that it could belong to
                     the "i" in "thing" in the following line. They add that in the King James Bible
                     there is generally a colon in this location (page 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.20" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">31<space extent="2"/>And God saw every thing that he had made &amp; behold it was v<unclear resp="EA">er</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>y</orig>
                                <reg>very</reg>
                            </choice> good<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The letters "er" in "very" are
                     unclear.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.21" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">and the
                     evening &amp; the morning</hi> were the sixth day</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.06" dbi="but828.1.6.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Natural Man Divided into Male &amp; Female &amp; of the
               Tree of life &amp; of the Tree of Good &amp; Evil</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U6">(Butlin 828.6)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>38 x 27.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The use of green ink in the manuscript stops midway through the first line of
                  verse 5 in this object; from this point forward Blake's text is written only in
                  pencil. The chapter headings and Blake's title are also written in pencil. In
                  addition to dark text in pencil, which has been transcribed here in black font,
                  this object contains a number of light pencil markings, some of which are legible.
                  These appear to be remnants of Blake's first writing that were erased or
                  overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call attention to this
                  underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual notes to detail
                  many individual occurrences. In this transcription, legible underwriting has been
                  transcribed when it differs significantly from Blake's later writing in content or
                  position. When the underwritten text is identical but appears in a different
                  location, gray font has been used to distinguish underwriting from other text.
                  Please note that gray font is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to
                  describe unclear or conjectural text. Some of the ruled lines, drawn in pencil, in
                  this object are double, fragmented, or partially erased. In some cases the ruled
                  lines bisect or lie above the text. </p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts the creation of Adam and Eve. In the center of the
                  design is a nude male, facing forward with arms bent upward with palms up. This is
                  Adam. His head tilts back and to the right slightly. His eyes may be open. Adam's
                  legs are drawn up and he appears to be half sitting and half reclining on a convex
                  arc. Above Adam is a large, possibly male, figure facing forward. Dark pencil
                  lines extending from this figure to the right suggest a beard. This could be God
                  the Father. The figure on the left of the design may be male, faces forward with
                  the head facing left and up. Curved lines left and right of his body indicate
                  wings. The figure's mouth is open and he may be wearing a crown. The figure's legs
                  and arms are bent and he is in a contracted pose. The figure on the right of the
                  design is a nude female, facing forward and to the left. This is Eve. She has long
                  hair; her eyes and mouth may be open. Her arms are bent across her chest, possibly
                  covering her breasts. Her legs extend diagonally to left and appear to touch
                  Adam's left hip or thigh. Above these figures are looping and swirling pencil
                  lines that may represent branches of a tree. Ovoid shapes above the figure on the
                  left may be fruit. Pencil lines either side of the figures may represent tree
                  trunks. Below the figures is a convex arc representing the surface of the Earth. </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design is a nude male, facing forward with arms
                     bent upward with palms up. This is Adam. His head tilts back and to the right
                     slightly. His eyes may be open. Adam's legs are drawn up and he appears to be
                     half sitting and half reclining on a convex arc representing the surface of the
                     Earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above Adam is a large, possibly male and gowned, figure facing
                     forward. The figure may be standing or squatting. Dark pencil lines extending
                     from this figure to the right suggest a beard. This may be God the
                     Father.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure on the left of the design may be male, faces forward with
                     the head facing left and up. This may be Satan. The figure's mouth is open and
                     he may be wearing a crown. His left eye may be open. The figure's legs and arms
                     are bent and he is in a contracted pose. Curving lines left and right of the
                     figure indicate wings.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prayer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure on the right of the design is a nude female, facing
                     forward and to the left. This is Eve. She may be floating or hovering. She has
                     long hair, and her eyes and mouth may be open. She is looking at Adam. Her arms
                     are bent across her chest, possibly covering her breasts. Her legs extend
                     diagonally to left and appear to touch Adam's right hip or
                     thigh.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the figures are looping and swirling pencil lines that may
                     represent branches of a tree. Ovoid shapes above the winged figure may be
                     fruit. Pencil lines either side of the figures may represent tree
                     trunks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The convex line below the figures probably represents the surface of
                     the Earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.01" justify="left" indent="6">Ch · 2<space extent="21"/>Chap<space extent="2"/>2<note>Crosby and Essick
                     indicate that "Ch · 2" may be a substitution for the more lightly written
                     "Chap 2", and they suggest that the illegible underwriting in the following
                     line may refer to "chapter 2, verse I" (page 7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.02" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <hi rend="underscore">The Natural Man divided into Male &amp; Female &amp; of the
                     Tree of life &amp; of the Tree</hi>
                        <note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi>
                     volume 2, page 1344) and Erdman (page 688) read "life" as "Life".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.03" justify="left" indent="29">of Good &amp; Evil</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.04" justify="left">1<space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">Thus</hi> the heavens <hi rend="underscore">and the</hi> earth were finished
                  and all the host of them<hi rend="underscore">.<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.05" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">2<space extent="3"/>And
                     on the seventh day</hi> God <hi rend="underscore">ended his</hi> work which he
                  had made &amp; he rested</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.06" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">on the
                     seventh day from all his work which he had made</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.07" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">3<space extent="3"/>And
                     God blessed the seventh day &amp; sanctified it because</hi> in it <hi rend="underscore">he had <choice>
                                <orig>restid</orig>
                                <reg>rested</reg>
                            </choice>
                        </hi>.<note>The King James Bible reads "because that in it" rather
                     than "because in it" (Crosby and Essick page 11). "restid": i.e., presumably,
                     "rested".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.08" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">from all his
                     works which God created and made</hi>
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="but828.6.8.note.jpg"/>The King James Bible reads "all his work"
                     rather than "all his works" (Crosby and Essick page 11). The mark that overlaps
                     with the lower part of "e" in "made" may be be a "misplaced period"; in the
                     King James Bible there is a period after "made" (Crosby and Essick page
                     7n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.09" justify="left">4<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="3"/>And
                     these are</hi> the gener<hi rend="underscore">
                            <choice>
                                <orig>ations</orig>
                                <reg>generations</reg>
                            </choice> of the heavens and of the earth when they were</hi>
                        <note>The King
                     James Bible reads "These are the" rather than "And these are the" (Crosby and
                     Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.10" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">created in
                     the</hi> day when the Lord God <hi rend="underscore">made the earth</hi> and
                  the heavens<note>The King James Bible reads "in the day that" rather than "in the
                     day when" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.11" justify="left">5<space extent="3"/>And every plant of the
                  field before it was in th<note>This is the last line in which Blake uses green
                     ink; the underwritten text in pencil overlaps with the text in green but is
                     considerably lower on the page and has been transcribed as a separate line.
                  </note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.12" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <unclear resp="EA">5<space extent="3"/>And every plant of
                        the field before it was in th</unclear>e earth and every herb
                     of</hi>
                        <note>The underwriting in this line, transcribed in gray, has been
                     replaced by the text in green ink transcribed in the previous line. From this
                     point forward all text in the manuscript is in pencil.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.13" justify="left" indent="7">
                        <hi rend="underscore">the field
                     before it grew for the Lord God had not caused it to rain up</hi>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>on</orig>
                            <reg>upon</reg>
                        </choice>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.14" justify="left" indent="7">
                        <hi rend="underscore">the earth and there was not a man to till the ground<space extent="10"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.15" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">6<space extent="3"/>But there went up a a mist from the
                     earth and <choice>
                                <orig>waterd</orig>
                                <reg>watered</reg>
                            </choice> the whole face of the</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.16" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">ground<space extent="8"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.17" justify="left" indent="28">
                        <add type="insertion" place="supralinear">
                            <hi rend="subscript">Adam<space extent="21"/>adamah</hi>
                        </add>
                        <note>"Adam" and "adamah" do not appear in chapter 2, verse 7 of the King
                     James Bible (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.18" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">7<space extent="3"/>And the Lord God formed Man of the dust
                     of the ground and breathed into</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "man"
                     rather than "Man" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.19" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">his nostrils the breath of life and man became a living
                        soul<space extent="8"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.20" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">8⁋<space extent="2"/>And the Lord God planted a garden eastward in Eden and there he
                     put th</hi>e<note>The pilcrow that appears after "8" is reversed.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.21" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">man whom he had Formed</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.22" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="4"/>And
                     out of the ground (ad</hi>amah) made the Lord God <hi rend="underscore">to grow
                     every tree that</hi> is<note>"(adamah)" does not appear in the King James Bible
                     (Crosby and Essick page 12). As Crosby and Essick note, the rather large
                     initial "a" in "adamah" appears to be lower case because it does not match
                     Blake's upper-case "A" (page 7n). The verse number "9" appears below this text
                     and has been transcribed as a separate line</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.23" justify="left">9</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.24" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">pleasant to
                     the sight &amp; good for food the tree of life also in the m</hi>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>idst</orig>
                            <reg>midst</reg>
                        </choice> of</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.25" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="26"/>
                            <unclear resp="EA">for food the tree of life also<space extent="9"/>mid</unclear>
                        </hi>
                        <unclear resp="EA">st</unclear>
                        <note>The
                     underwriting in this line, in light pencil, is considerably lower on the page
                     than the darker pencil written over it and has been transcribed as a separate
                     line. Crosby and Essick observe that the underwriting in verse 9 appears lower
                     on the page than the darker overwritten text (see page 7n), but they do not
                     transcribe the legible underwriting.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.26" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">the garden &amp; the tree of knowledge of good &amp;
                        evil<space extent="21"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.27" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <space extent="37"/>
                        <unclear resp="EA">knowledge of good &amp; evil</unclear>
                        <note>The legible
                     underwriting in this line, in light pencil, is lower on the page than and to
                     the right of the darker pencil written over it and has been transcribed as a
                     separate line. Crosby and Essick note the different position of the
                     underwritten words "knowledge of good &amp; evil" (see page 8n), but they do
                     not transcribe the legible underwriting.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.28" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">10<space extent="2"/>And a river went out of Eden to water
                     the garden and from thence it was</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.29" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">parted and became into four heads</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.30" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">11<space extent="2"/>The name of the first is Pison that is
                     it which compasseth the whole<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.31" justify="left" indent="10">
                        <hi rend="underscore">land of Havilah where there is gold<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.32" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">12<space extent="2"/>And the gold of that land is good there
                     is bdellium &amp; the onyx stone</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.33" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="5"/>And the name of the Second River is Gihon
                     the same is it that encompasseth th</hi>e<note>This is the first line of verse
                     13, but the number was left omitted (Crosby and Essick page 8n). The King James
                     Bible reads "compasseth" rather than "encompasseth" (Crosby and Essick page
                     12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.34" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="5"/>
                            <unclear resp="EA">A<space extent="12"/>of the</unclear>
                            <space extent="54"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The underwriting in this
                     line, in light pencil, is considerably lower on the page than the darker pencil
                     written over it and has been transcribed as a separate line. Crosby and Essick
                     note that the underwritten text of verse 13, line 1 appears lower on the page
                     than the darker overwritten text (see page 8n), but they do not transcribe the
                     legible underwriting. Crosby and Essick also indicate that the verse number
                     appears in the underwriting (page 8n), but the "13" could not be identified
                     here and has not been transcribed.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.06.35" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="5"/>whole land of Ethiopia<space extent="52"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.07" dbi="but828.1.7.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U7">(Butlin 828.7)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>38.2 x 28 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains a number of light pencil markings, some of which are legible.
                  These appear to be remnants of Blake's first writing that were erased or
                  overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call attention to this
                  underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual notes to detail
                  many individual occurrences. They note that underwriting is visible through verse
                  21 of this object and that in verses 14 through 17, the underwritten text is in a
                  different position than the text darker text written over it (page 8n). In this
                  transcription, legible underwriting has been transcribed when it differs
                  significantly from Blake's later writing in content or position. When the
                  underwritten text is identical but appears in a different location, gray font has
                  been used to distinguish underwriting from other text. Please note that gray font
                  is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to describe unclear or conjectural
                  text. Some of the ruled lines, drawn in pencil, in this object are double,
                  fragmented, or partially erased. In some cases the ruled lines bisect or lie above
                  the text. </p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design illustrates Eve's creation and contains five figures. There
                  are three figures at the top of the design in a recessional grouping. These
                  figures are soaring left to right. The front figure is male, has long hair and
                  possibly a beard. He is wearing a long gown. His eye is open and he is looking to
                  the right. His arms are at his sides and the fingers of both hands are spread
                  slightly. Only the heads of the second and third figures in this tripartite
                  grouping are visible. They face right. This may be the Trinity. The figure below
                  this group is a nude female with long hair and prominent breasts. She faces
                  forward and to the left. She appears to be hovering soaring left to right. This is
                  Eve. Her left arm is raised horizontally and is bent upward. Her left hand may be
                  supporting her head. Eve's leg extend diagonally to the left with her left foot
                  touching the chest of the figure below. This is Adam, supine with right arm by his
                  side. Adam's head is tilted back. Pencil lines across Adam's chest suggest an
                  incision. Below Adam are loose pencil lines that may depict vegetation or the
                  ground. Curved pencil lines above, below, and to the right of Eve's head may
                  depict clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trinity</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There are three figures at the top of the design in a recessional
                     grouping. These figures are soaring left to right. The front figure is male,
                     has long hair and a beard. This may be God the Father. He is wearing a long
                     gown. Pencil lines above his shoulder suggest a wing. His eye is open and he is
                     looking to the right. His arms are at his sides and the fingers of both hands
                     are spread slightly. Only the heads of the second and third figures in this
                     tripartite grouping are visible. They face right. This may be the
                     Trinity.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breast</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand under head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure below this group is a nude female with long hair and
                     prominent breasts. She faces forward and to the left. Her genitals are visible.
                     She appears to be soaring, floating, flying or hovering from left to right.
                     This is Eve. Her left arm is raised horizontally and is bent at 90 degrees. Her
                     left hand may be supporting her head. Eve's legs extend diagonally to the left
                     with her left foot touching the chest of the figure below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower figure is Adam, supine with right arm at his side. The
                     fingers of his right hand may be spread. His right palm faces down. His legs
                     extend to the right. His right leg may be slightly bent. Adam has curly hair
                     and his head is tilted back. Pencil lines across Adam's chest suggest an
                     incision or wound.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>clouds</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below Adam are loose pencil lines that may depict vegetation or the
                     ground. Curved pencil lines above, below, and to the right of Eve's head may
                     depict clouds. Two curving forms below Adam's legs might be
                     flames.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.01" justify="left" indent="1">14<space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">And the name of the third river is Hiddekel that is it
                     wh</hi>ich<note>The "A" in "And" appears twice; the two writings overlap
                     slightly. Crosby and Essick note that light pencil markings in these verses
                     indicate Blake originally wrote these verses in light pencil in a slightly
                     different position (Crosby and Essick page8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.02" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">goeth toward
                     the east of assyria and the <choice>
                                <orig>nam</orig>
                                <reg>name</reg>
                            </choice>
                        </hi> of the f<note>"nam": i.e., presumably, "name". The "f" at the
                     end of the line appears to be the first letter of "fourth", as the text of the
                     King James Bible reads, "And the fourth river is Euphrates" (Crosby and Essick
                     page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.03" justify="left" indent="29">
                        <add type="insertion" place="supralinear">
                            <hi rend="subscript">adam</hi>
                        </add>
                        <note>"adam" does not appear in chapter 2, verse 15 of the King James Bible
                     (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.04" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">15<space extent="2"/>And the Lord God took the <choice>
                                <orig>m- -</orig>
                                <reg>man</reg>
                            </choice> and put him into the garden to<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The "A" in "And" appears twice; the two writings overlap slightly. Crosby
                     and Essick note that the dashes in "m- -" appear to stand in for the last two
                     letters of "man" (page 8n). The King James Bible reads "God took the man, and"
                     rather than "God took the m- - and" and "the garden of Eden to" rather than
                     "the garden to" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.05" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <unclear resp="EA">to</unclear>
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">dress <choice>
                                <orig>an</orig>
                                <reg>and</reg>
                            </choice> to keep it<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"to" appears to repeat the last word of the previous line. Crosby and Essick
                     do not describe this overlap between the lines. As Crosby and Essick note, the
                     final letter of "and" is missing (page 8n). The King James Bible reads "dress
                     it and to" rather than "dress an to" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.06" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">16<space extent="2"/>And the Lord <choice>
                                <orig>Cood</orig>
                                <reg>God</reg>
                            </choice> commanded the Man saying Of every tree of the<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Blake appears to have written "Cood" rather than "God". Crosby and Essick
                     read "God" (page 4).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.07" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <hi rend="underscore">garden thou mayest freely eat</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.08" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">17<space extent="2"/>But of the tree of the knowledge of
                     good <subst>
                                <del type="overwrite">&amp;</del>
                                <add type="overwrite" place="inline">a</add>
                            </subst>nd evil thou shalt not</hi>
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="but828.7.8.note.jpg"/>A mark in light pencil after "17" may be a pilcrow, written in reverse, or an
                     earlier writing of "B" in "But".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.09" justify="left" indent="8">
                        <hi rend="underscore">eat <subst>
                                <del type="overwrite">of</del>
                                <add type="overwrite" place="inline">eat</add>
                            </subst> of it for in the day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt <unclear resp="EA">surely</unclear>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The second "eat" appears to have been written over "of". Crosby and Essick
                     note that "eat" has been written twice (page 8n) and that this repetition does
                     not occur in the King James Bible (page 12), but they do not mention an
                     overwritten "of". The unclear word at the end of the line appears to be
                     "surely"; if so, the word is repeated at the beginning of the next line (Crosby
                     and Essick page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.10" justify="left" indent="11">
                        <hi rend="underscore">surely die<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"surely", which appears to repeat the last word of the previous line in
                     Blake's manuscript (Crosby and Essick page 8n), is not repeated in chapter 2,
                     verse 17 of the King James Bible (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.11" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <subst>
                                <del type="overwrite">17</del>
                                <add type="overwrite" place="inline">18</add>
                            </subst>
                            <space extent="2"/>And the Lord God said it is not good that the man
                     should be alon</hi>e</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.12" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <hi rend="underscore">I will make him an help meet for him</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.13" justify="left" indent="19">
                        <add type="insertion" place="supralinear">
                            <hi rend="subscript">Adamah</hi>
                        </add>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.14" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="4"/>And out of the ground the Lord God formed
                     every beast of the field<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"Adamah" does not appear in chapter 2, verse 19 of the King James Bible
                     (Crosby and Essick page 12). The verse number "19" appears below this text and
                     has been transcribed as a separate line, along with a second ruled line that
                     appears in this position.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.05.15" justify="left">
                        <hi>
                            <space extent="1"/>19<space extent="27"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.16" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <hi rend="underscore">and every
                     fowl of the air and brought them to Adam to see </hi>what</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.17" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <hi rend="underscore">he would
                     call them &amp; <choice>
                                <orig>what soever</orig>
                                <reg>whatsoever</reg>
                            </choice> Adam called every living crea</hi>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>ture</orig>
                            <reg>creature</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "brought them unto Adam" rather than
                     "brought them to Adam" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.18" justify="left" indent="2">
                        <unclear resp="EA">19⁋</unclear>
                        <space extent="4"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">that was the name thereof <hi rend="superscript">:</hi>
                            <space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The lightly written "19⁋" appears to be a remnant of Blake's first
                     writing, and the pilcrow is reversed. Crosby and Essick do not describe this
                     instance of underwriting.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.19" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">20<space extent="2"/>And Adam gave names to all cattle and to the fowl of the air and
                     to ever</hi>y</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.20" justify="left" indent="9">b<hi rend="underscore">
                            <choice>
                                <orig>east</orig>
                                <reg>beast</reg>
                            </choice> of the field but for Adam there was not found an help meet for
                     hi</hi>m</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.21" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">21⁋<space extent="1"/>And the Lord God caused a deep
                     sleep to fall upon Adam and he<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The pilcrow that appears after "21" is reversed; the King James Bible does
                     not contain a paragraph break at this point in the text (Crosby and Essick page
                     8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.22" justify="left" indent="2">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>slept and he took one of his ribs and
                     closed up the flesh instead</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.23" justify="left" indent="9">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>thereof<space extent="7"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.24" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">22<space extent="2"/>And of the rib which the Lord God had
                     taken from man made he a<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The ruled line bisects or
                     lies above all text in this line. The King James Bible reads "And the rib"
                     rather than "And of the rib" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.25" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        <unclear resp="EA">2</unclear>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="character"/>
                        <space extent="5"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="33"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"2", written lightly in pencil, is followed by another number that is
                     illegible. This two-digit number appears to be a remnant of Blake's first
                     writing that has been replaced by the darker verse number "22" in the previous
                     line. Crosby and Essick do not describe this instance of underwriting.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.26" justify="left" indent="9">woman and brought her unto the
                  man</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.27" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="67"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.28" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">23<space extent="2"/>And Adam Said This is now bone of my
                     bones and flesh of my<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.29" justify="left" indent="11">
                        <hi rend="underscore">flesh she
                     shall be called Woman because she wa<unclear resp="EA">s</unclear> tak<unclear resp="EA">e</unclear>n out of m</hi>an</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.30" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">24<space extent="2"/>Therefore shall a man leave Father
                     &amp; mother and shall cleave to his wife.</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads
                     "leave his father and his mother" rather than "leave Father &amp; mother" and
                     "shall cleave unto" rather than "shall cleave to" (Crosby and Essick page
                     12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.31" justify="left" indent="9">an<hi rend="underscore">d they
                     twain shall be one flesh</hi>
                        <note>The ruled line bisects or lies above all
                     text in this line. The King James Bible reads "they shall be" rather than "they
                     twain shall be" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.07.32" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">25<space extent="2"/>And they were Both Naked the man &amp; <subst>
                                <del type="overwrite">the</del>
                                <add type="overwrite" place="inline">his</add>
                            </subst> wife &amp; were not ash</hi>amed<note>Crosby and Essick note that
                     Blake appears to have replaced "the wife" with "his wife"; the latter phrase
                     matches the King James Bible (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.08" dbi="but828.1.8.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Of the Sexual Nature &amp; its Fall into Generation &amp; death</title>,<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U8">(Butlin 828.8)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>38.1 x 27.5 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains a number of light pencil markings, some of which are legible.
                  These appear to be remnants of Blake's first writing that were erased or
                  overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call attention to this
                  underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual notes to detail
                  many individual occurrences. In this transcription, legible underwriting has been
                  transcribed when it differs significantly from Blake's later writing in content or
                  position. When the underwritten text is identical but appears in a different
                  location, gray font has been used to distinguish underwriting from other text.
                  Please note that gray font is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to
                  describe unclear or conjectural text. Some of the ruled lines, drawn in pencil, in
                  this object are double, fragmented, or partially erased. In some cases the ruled
                  lines bisect or lie above the text.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="AB">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts the judgement of Adam and Eve. On the left of the
                  design are two nude figures. The leftmost figure is Adam. He faces forward and his
                  head is turned to the right in profile. He is kneeling. His right arm is bent
                  behind his back and his left arm is bent upward over his chest, palm possibly
                  vertical. He may be looking at the figure immediately to his right. This is Eve.
                  She faces forward and her head is tilted back and to the right. She has long hair
                  and is kneeling. Her left arm is by her side and bent upward with her hand
                  covering her breasts. Eve's right arm is at her side and bent slightly. Her right
                  hand covers her genitals. She appears to be looking up and to the right. On the
                  right of the design is a tree with a large, thick trunk. Loose pencil lines above
                  and around the trunk may represent branches and leaves. Two ovoid shapes hang from
                  one of the branches. These ovoids are probably fruits, indicating that this is the
                  Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil. At the base of the tree is a large-headed
                  serpent. It faces left and its mouth and eye are open. It may be looking at Adam
                  and Eve. Between Adam and Eve's knees is a semi-round shape with a short vertical
                  line. This is the forbidden fruit, partially eaten by Adam and Eve. The curving
                  lines upper right may be a placeholder for God the Father.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left of the design are two nude figures. The leftmost figure
                     is Adam. He faces forward and his head is turned to the right, in profile. He
                     is kneeling. His right arm is bent behind his back; his left arm is bent upward
                     over his chest, palm possibly vertical. His right foot is visible. He may be
                     looking at the figure immediately to his right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the left is Eve. She faces forward and her
                     head is tilted back and to the right. She has long hair and is kneeling. Her
                     left arm is by her side and bent upward with her hand covering her breasts.
                     Eve's right arm is at her side and is bent slightly. Her right hand covers her
                     genitals. She appears to be looking up and to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="B">
                        <characteristic>serpent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lying at the base of the tree is a large-headed serpent. This is
                     Satan It faces left and its mouth and eye are open. It may be looking at Adam
                     and Eve.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Tree of Knowledge</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right of the design is a tree with a large, thick trunk.
                     Loose pencil lines above and around the trunk may be placeholders for branches
                     and leaves. Two ovoid shapes hang from one of the branches. These ovoids are
                     probably fruits, indicating that this is the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and
                     Evil.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc> Between Adam and Eve's knees in a semi-round shape with a short
                     vertical line. This is the forbidden fruit, partially eaten by Adam and
                     Eve.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>God the Father</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Curving lines upper right may be a placeholder for God the Father in
                     the act of judgement.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.01" justify="left" indent="30">
                        <unclear resp="EA">Chap<space extent="2"/>3.</unclear>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.02" justify="left" indent="27">
                        <unclear resp="EA">C</unclear>
                        <note>"C", transcribed here in gray, appears to be an earlier writing of the first
                     letter of "Chap", which appears in the previous line (Crosby and Essick page
                     8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.03" justify="left" indent="2">Ch 3<space extent="11"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">Of the Sexual Nature &amp; its Fall into Generation &amp;
                     death </hi>
                        <note>Crosby and Essick indicate that "Ch 3" may be a substitution
                     for the more lightly written "Chap 3." in line 1 (page 8n). Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1344) and Erdman (page 688) read
                     "death" as "Death". Illegible underwriting, perhaps including vertical lines,
                     appears below the title.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.04" justify="left">1<space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">Now
                     the Serpent was more <choice>
                                <orig>subtil</orig>
                                <reg>subtle</reg>
                                <reg>subtile</reg>
                            </choice> than any beast of the field that the Lord God had</hi>
                        <note>Crosby
                     and Essick note that two lightly written vertical lines to the right of "1" may
                     indicate Blake that considered putting the verse number in a different position
                     (page 8n). The King James Bible reads "field which the Lord" rather than "field
                     that the Lord" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.05" justify="left" indent="3">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="5"/>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>mad</orig>
                                <reg>made</reg>
                            </choice>. and he said unto the Woman Yea hath God said Ye shall not eat
                     of</hi>
                        <note>"mad": i.e., presumably, "made".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.06" justify="left" indent="3">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="5"/>every tree of the garden<space extent="45"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.07" justify="left">2<space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="2"/>And the woman said unto the Serpent We may eat of
                     the</hi> fruit of the trees of the</l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.08" justify="left">
                        <unclear resp="EA">3</unclear>
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="6"/>garden<space extent="61"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="but828.8.11.note.jpg"/>The verse number "3", transcribed
                     here in gray, has been written more darkly in the following line. Crosby and
                     Essick note that the number and other pencil writing suggest that Blake
                     originally wrote the first line of verse 3 on this line (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.09" justify="left">3<space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="2"/>But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of
                     the garden God hath said Ye<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.10" justify="left" indent="2">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="6"/>shall not eat of it neither shall ye
                     touch it lest ye die<space extent="23"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.11" justify="left">4<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="3"/>And
                     the serpent said unto the woman Ye shall not surely die<space extent="20"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Crosby and Essick note that "shall" could be "shalt", which would
                     accord with the King James Bible; however, they suggest that the appearance of
                     a "t" has been created by a ruled line that passes through the final letter "l"
                     (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.12" justify="left">5<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="3"/>For
                     God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof your eyes shall be opened <unclear resp="EA">&amp;</unclear>
                            <space extent="1"/>
                            <space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "thereof, then your eyes" rather than
                     "thereof your eyes" (Crosby and Essick page 12). Crosby and Essick note that
                     Blake may have written an ampersand at the end of this line at an earlier stage
                     of composition (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.13" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>and ye shall be as Gods (Elohim) knowing
                     good &amp; evil<space extent="20"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "as gods, knowing" rather than "as Gods (Elohim)
                     knowing" (Crosby and Essick page 12). Crosby and Essick note that "Gods" is
                     written with a capital "G" in some seventeenth-century editions of the King
                     James Bible. Among those are the folio editions printed by Robert Barker. Later
                     editions generally use a lower-case "g" (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.14" justify="left">6<hi rend="underscore">¶⁋ And when
                     the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was pleasant<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Two pilcrows, the second of which is reversed, appear
                     after the verse number "6". A pilcrow does not appear in this location in
                     editions of the King James Bible (Crosby and Essick page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.15" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>to the eyes &amp; a tree to be desired to
                     make one wise she took of the fruit thereof<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.16" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>and did eat and gave also to her husband
                     with her and he did eat<space extent="17"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible
                     reads "also unto her husband" rather than "also to her husband" (Crosby and
                     Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.17" justify="left">7<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="3"/>And
                     the eyes of them both were opened and they knew that they were naked and<space extent="7"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>In this case the ruled line bisects the 7 so that it
                     appears both above and below the line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.18" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>they sewed Fig leaves <choice>
                                <orig>togethe</orig>
                                <reg>together</reg>
                            </choice> and made themselves aprons<space extent="22"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"togethe": i.e., presumably, "together".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.19" justify="left">8<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="3"/>And
                     they heard the Voice of the Lord God walking in the garden. in the cool of the
                     day</hi>
                        <note>Crosby and Essick note that what appears to be a period after
                     "garden" may be a "slip of the pencil" (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.20" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>and adam &amp; his wife hid themselves
                     from the presence of the Lord God amongst</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.21" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>the trees of the garden<space extent="53"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.22" justify="left">9 <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="3"/>And the Lord <choice>
                                <orig>Cod</orig>
                                <reg>God</reg>
                            </choice> called unto <unclear resp="EA">Ad</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>am</orig>
                                <reg>Adam</reg>
                            </choice> and said unto him Where art thou<space extent="13"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Blake appears to have written "Cod"
                     rather than "God". Crosby and Essick read "God" (page 5). The first two letters
                     of "Adam" are unclear. Crosby and Essick note that "A" in "Adam" may have been
                     written over a lower-case "a" (page 8n). </note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.23" justify="left">1<hi rend="underscore">0<space extent="2"/>And he said I heard thy voice in the garden and I was afraid because I
                        was<space extent="10"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.24" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>naked and I hid myself<space extent="53"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The ruled line bisects the text in this line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.25" justify="left">1<hi rend="underscore">
                            <subst>
                                <del type="overwrite">0</del>
                                <add type="overwrite" place="inline">1</add>
                            </subst>
                            <space extent="2"/>And he said Who told thee that thou wast naked hast
                     thou eaten of the tree–<space extent="8"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.26" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>whereof I commanded thee that thou
                     shouldest not eat<space extent="25"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.27" justify="left">1<hi rend="underscore">2<space extent="2"/>And <subst>
                                <gap extent="4" reason="overwrite"/>
                                <add place="inline" type="overwrite">Adam</add>
                            </subst> said the woman whom thou gavest me to be with me she gave me of
                        the<space extent="3"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Crosby and Essick suggest that "Adam" may
                     have been written over "the man", which is the term used in the King James
                     Bible (page 8n). The King James Bible reads "thou gavest to be" rather than
                     "thou gavest me to be" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.28" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="7"/>tree and I did eat<space extent="63"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.29" justify="left">1<hi rend="underscore">3<space extent="2"/>And the Lord God said unto the woman what is this that thou hast done and
                     the</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.30" justify="left">
                        <unclear resp="EA">14</unclear>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="4"/>woman said the serpent beguiled me and I
                     did eat<space extent="32"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The verse number "14," transcribed here in gray, has been written more
                     darkly in the following line. Crosby and Essick note that the number and other
                     faint pencil writing suggest that Blake had previously written all of verse 14
                     higher on the page (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.31" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">14<space extent="2"/>And the Lord God said unto the <choice>
                                <orig>srepent</orig>
                                <reg>serpent</reg>
                            </choice> Because thou hast done this thou art<space extent="4"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"srepent": i.e., presumably, "serpent".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.32" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="8"/>accursed above all cattle and above every
                     beast of the field upon they belly<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James
                     Bible reads "cursed" rather than "accursed" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.08.33" justify="left">
                        <space extent="8"/>shalt thou go and dust
                  shalt thou eat all the days of thy life</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.09" dbi="but828.1.9.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U9">(Butlin 828.9)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.8 x 27.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains a number of light pencil markings, some of which are legible.
                  These appear to be remnants of Blake's first writing that were erased or
                  overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call attention to this
                  underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual notes to detail
                  many individual occurrences. In this transcription, legible underwriting has been
                  transcribed when it differs significantly from Blake's later writing in content or
                  position. When the underwritten text is identical but appears in a different
                  location, gray font has been used to distinguish underwriting from other text.
                  Please note that gray font is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to
                  describe unclear or conjectural text. Some of the ruled lines, drawn in pencil, in
                  this object bisect or lie above the text. The last several lines of text in this
                  object overlap with pencil markings that appear to belong to the illustration
                  visible below or to another drawing of Blake's (Crosby and Essick page 9n).</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts the expulsion and consists of two groups of vaguely
                  defined shapes, on the lower left and upper right, connected by large curling
                  lines, possibly flames. The two forms on the lower left may be placeholders from
                  Adam and Eve. Three of the four circular shapes upper right may represent heads of
                  the Trinity, with the fourth and lowest circle indicating part of the body of one
                  member of the group.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This design depicts the expulsion and consists of two groups of
                     vaguely defined shapes, on the lower left and upper right, connected by large
                     curling lines, The two forms on the lower left may be placeholders from Adam
                     and Eve.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Trinity</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>This design depicts the expulsion and consists of two groups of
                     vaguely defined shapes, on the lower left and upper right, connected by large
                     curling lines. Three of the four circular shapes upper right may represent
                     heads of the Trinity, with the fourth and lowest circle indicating part of the
                     body of one member of the group.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Some of the swirling lines may be flames.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.01" justify="left">16<add type="insertion" place="inline">5</add>
                        <hi rend="underscore">¶<space extent="1"/>And I will put enmity
                     between thee and the woman and between</hi>
                        <note>The addition of "5" after "16"
                     indicates that Blake changed the verse number to 15 without deleting the "6"
                     (Crosby and Essick page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.02" justify="left" indent="2">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="6"/>thy seed and her seed he shall <choice>
                                <orig>bruize</orig>
                                <reg>bruise</reg>
                            </choice> thy head &amp; thou shalt <choice>
                                <orig>bruize</orig>
                                <reg>bruise</reg>
                            </choice>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "her seed; it shall bruise"
                     rather than "her seed he shall bruize" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.03" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="8"/>his heel<space extent="57"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.04" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">16¶<space extent="2"/>And unto the woman he said I will
                     greatly multiply thy sorrows and thy<space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "Unto the woman" rather than "And unto the woman"
                     and "multiply thy sorrow" rather than "multiply thy sorrows" (Crosby and Essick
                     page 12). Crosby and Essick note that what appears to be an "s" after "sorrow"
                     may be a "slip of the pencil" (page 8n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.05" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>conception in sorrow shalt thou bring
                     forth children and thy desire shall<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James
                     Bible reads "in sorrow thou shalt" rather than "in sorrow shalt thou" (Crosby
                     and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.06" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>be to thy husband and he shall rule over
                        thee<space extent="27"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.07" justify="left">1<hi rend="underscore">7<space extent="3"/>And unto adam he said Because thou hast <choice>
                                <orig>hearkend</orig>
                                <reg>hearkened</reg>
                                <reg>harkened</reg>
                            </choice> to the voice of thy wife</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads
                     "hearkened unto the" rather than "hearkend to the" (Crosby and Essick page
                     12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.08" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>and hast eaten of the tree of which I <choice>
                                <orig>commaded</orig>
                                <reg>commanded</reg>
                            </choice> thee saying Thou shalt</hi>
                        <note>"commaded": i.e., presumably, "commanded".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.09" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>not eat of it cursed is the ground for
                     thy sake in sorrow shalt thou eat of</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.10" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>it all the days of thy life<space extent="43"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.11" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">18<space extent="3"/>Thorns also and thistles it shall bring
                     forth unto thee and thou shalt eat<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James
                     Bible reads "thistles shall it bring forth to thee" rather than "thistles it
                     shall bring forth unto thee" (Crosby and Essick page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.12" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>the herb of the Field<space extent="43"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.13" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>19.<space extent="2"/>In the sweat of the
                     face thou shalt eat bread till thou return unto the <del type="overstrike_pencil">ground</del>
                            <space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "sweat of thy face shalt thou" rather than "sweat
                     of the face thou shalt" (Crosby and Essick page 12). Blake may have used a
                     strikethrough to delete the word "ground", which has been written a second time
                     at the beginning of the following line (Crosby and Essick page 9n). "ground" is
                     not repeated in chapter 3, verse 19 of the King James Bible (Crosby and Essick
                     page 12).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.14" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>ground (adamah) for dust thou art &amp;
                     unto dust thou shalt return<space extent="7"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible
                     reads "ground; for out of it wast thou taken: for dust thou art" rather than
                     "ground (adamah) for dust thou art" (Crosby and Essick page 12), and it reads
                     "unto dust shalt thou return" rather than "unto dust thou shalt return" (Crosby
                     and Essick page 13). Blake's manuscript also omits the period at the end of
                     this verse (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.15" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>20<space extent="2"/>And <subst>
                                <del type="overwrite">a</del>
                                <add type="overwrite" place="inline">A</add>
                            </subst>dam called his wifes name Eve because she</hi> was<hi rend="underscore"> the mother of all</hi>
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        <choice>
                            <orig>livig</orig>
                            <reg>living</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <note>The darkly written verse number "20" is in a slightly different
                     position than the lighter "20" below it (Crosby and Essick page 9n). "livig":
                     i.e., presumably, "living".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.16" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>21<space extent="2"/>And to Adam also and
                     to his wife did the Lord God make coats of skins<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "Unto Adam" rather than "And to Adam" (Crosby and
                     Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.17" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>and clothed them <unclear resp="EA">and
                        the Lord God said</unclear>
                            <space extent="24"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The legible underwriting in this line, transcribed here in gray, matches the
                     opening text of verse 22. This repetition suggests that Blake started to write
                     verse 22 in this position; he may have later erased some of this writing
                     (Crosby and Essick page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.18" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>22<space extent="2"/>And the Lord God
                     said Behold Adam is become as one of us to know</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible
                     reads "Behold, the man is become" rather than "Behold Adam is become" (Crosby
                     and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.19" justify="left">
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="8"/>good &amp; evil and now lest he put forth his hand &amp;
                     take also of th</hi>e<note>Much of the upper part of the text in this line is
                     bisected by a ruled line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.20" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>tree of life and eat and live for
                        ever<space extent="27"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.21" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>23<space extent="2"/>Therefore the Lord
                     God sent him forth at the garden of Eden to till the gro<unclear resp="EA">un</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>d</orig>
                                <reg>ground</reg>
                            </choice>
                            <space extent="3"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "forth from the garden" rather than "forth at the
                     garden" (Crosby and Essick page 13). The "un" in "ground" is unclear. Crosby
                     and Essick read "ground" without comment (page 5).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.22" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>(adamah) from whence he was taken<space extent="39"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.23" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">24<space extent="3"/>So he drove out Adam and he placed at
                     the east of the garden of Eden<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "he drove out the man; and" rather than "he drove
                     out Adam and" (Crosby and Essick page 13). The underwriting that appears below
                     "the garden of Eden" may be an earlier version of the closing words of either
                     this line or the following line (Crosby and Essick page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.09.24" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>Cherubims &amp; a flam<unclear resp="EA">in</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>g</orig>
                                <reg>flaming</reg>
                            </choice> sword to keep the way of the tree of the life<space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>"in" in "flaming" is unclear. Crosby and Essick read "flaming" without
                     comment (page 5). The King James Bible reads "sword which turned every way, to
                     keep the way" rather than "sword to keep the way" (Crosby and Essick page
                     13).</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.10" dbi="but828.1.10.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">How generation &amp; death took Possession of the Natural Man</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U10">(Butlin 828.10)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.9 x 27.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object contains a number of light pencil markings, some of which are legible.
                  These appear to be remnants of Blake's first writing that were erased or
                  overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call attention to this
                  underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual notes to detail
                  many individual occurrences. Traces of underwriting in lines 5 through 13 suggest
                  that these lines shifted location somewhat between writings (Crosby and Essick
                  9n). In this transcription, legible underwriting has been transcribed when it
                  differs significantly from Blake's later writing in content or position. When the
                  underwritten text is identical but appears in a different location, gray font has
                  been used to distinguish underwriting from other text. Please note that gray font
                  is also used in Blake Archive transcriptions to describe unclear or conjectural
                  text. Some of the ruled lines in this object are double, fragmented, or partially
                  erased. In some cases the ruled lines bisect or lie above the text. The chapter
                  heading in this object overlaps slightly with Blake's illustration.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="AB">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts Cain fleeing in the aftermath of Abel's murder.
                  There are two groupings of figures on either side of the design. At the lower edge
                  of the illustration, sketchy horizontal lines may depict a grave. Above the grave
                  are loose, curving horizontal lines suggesting a supine figure, probably the
                  murdered Abel. The cluster of lines on the left are Abel's head resting on the
                  knee or thigh of one of the two kneeling figures. These are Adam and Eve. The
                  figure on the left faces right in profile; the figure to the right appears to face
                  forward with head down. On the right of the design is a figure facing right, in
                  profile, with his left arm raised vertically and palm facing right or possibly
                  pointing upward. This is probably Cain fleeing. Cain's legs are apart and are bent
                  at the knees. His right leg is extended back and his right foot may be on tiptoe.
                  He is running. The cluster of lines above and slightly to the left of this figure
                  depict a soaring or hovering figure. A circle suggests a head and horizontal lines
                  extending left suggest the outline of a body. This may be God.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Abel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Loose, curving horizontal lines in the lower central and left ares
                     of the design suggest a supine figure, probably the murdered Abel. The cluster
                     of lines on the left are Abel's head resting on the knee or thigh of one of the
                     two kneeling figures. These are Adam and Eve. The figure on the left faces
                     right; the figure to the right appears to face forward with head bent down. The
                     right arm of the figure on the left is at his or her side. This figure may be
                     holding the supine figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Cain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right of the design is a figure facing right, in profile,
                     with their left arm raised vertically and palm vertical or possibly Cain's
                     index finger pointing upward. This is probably Cain fleeing. Cain's legs are
                     apart and are bent at the knees. His right leg is extended back and his right
                     foot may be on tiptoe. He is running.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The cluster of lines above and slightly to the left of this figure
                     depicts a soaring or hovering figure(s). A circle suggests a head and
                     horizontal lines extending left suggest the outline of a body. This may be
                     God.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>grave</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At the lower edge of the illustration, sketchy horizontal lines may
                     depict a grave.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.01" justify="left" indent="40"> V<note>
                            <illus filename="but828.10.1.note.jpg"/> As Crosby and Essick note, the "V" in
                     "Chap IV" is double (page 9n). The "V" transcribed in this line lies above the
                     "V" that has been transcribed in the following line. It is possible that "I"
                     has been written twice as well.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.02" justify="left" indent="32"> Chap<space extent="2"/>IV </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.03" justify="left" indent="1">Ch – V<space extent="9"/>How
                  generation &amp; death took Possession of the Natural Man<note>Blake appears to
                     have written "Ch – V" rather than "Ch – IV" by mistake (Crosby and
                     Essick 9n). Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1345) and Erdman
                     (page 688) read "generation" as "Generation" and "death" as "Death"; Bentley
                     reads "Possession" as "possession" (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page
                     1345). The underwriting in this line is the same as the darker text written
                     over it (Crosby and Essick page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.04" justify="left" indent="13">&amp; of the forgiveness of Sins
                  written upon the Murderers <choice>
                            <orig>forhead</orig>
                            <reg>forehead</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <note>"forhead": i.e., presumably, "forehead". Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1345) and Erdman (page 688) read "forgiveness"
                     as "Forgiveness" and "forhead" as "Forehead".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.05" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">1<space extent="3"/>And Adam knew Eve his wife and she <choice>
                                <orig>conceovd</orig>
                                <reg>conceived</reg>
                            </choice> &amp; bare Cain and said <unclear resp="EA">I
                     h</unclear>
                        </hi>
                        <unclear resp="EA">
                            <choice>
                                <orig>av</orig>
                                <reg>have</reg>
                            </choice>
                        </unclear>
                        <note>Crosby and Essick note that Blake has written either "conceovd" or
                     "conciovd" rather than "conceived". The verse number "1" appears twice, with
                     the more darkly written number to the left of the fainter one (page 9n). The
                     underwritten words "I hav" appear in darker pencil at the beginning of the next
                     line. Reading "hav" as "have", Crosby and Essick note that Blake originally
                     wrote "I have" at the end of this line (page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.06" justify="left" indent="4">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="6"/>I have gotten a man from Jehovah<space extent="38"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "from the Lord" rather
                     than "from Jehovah", and Blake has omitted the period at the end of this verse
                     (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.07" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">2<space extent="3"/>And she again bore his brother Abel and
                     Abel was a keeper of the<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The verse number "2" appears twice, with the more darkly written number a
                     bit to the left of the fainter one (Crosby and Essick page 9n). Crosby and
                     Essick read "bore" but note that it could be "bare", which is the word used in
                     the King James Bible (page 9n). The King James Bible reads "keeper of" rather
                     than "keeper of the" (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.08" justify="left" indent="2">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="8"/>sheep but Cain was a tiller of the
                        ground<space extent="3"/>
                        </hi>
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="13"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.09" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">3<space extent="3"/>And in process of time it came to pass
                     that Cain brought of the fruit of</hi>
                        <note>The verse number "3" appears twice; the two numbers overlap slightly (Crosby
                     and Essick page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.10" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="4"/>
                        </hi>
                        <space extent="4"/>the ground for an Offering to the
                     Lord<space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="24"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The
                     King James Bible reads "ground an offering" rather than "ground for an
                     Offering" (Crosby and Essick page 13). "the Lord" appears to have been written
                     twice. Crosby and Essick note the two writings of "Lord", which overlap
                     slightly (page 9n), but do not mention the two writings of "the".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.11" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">4<space extent="3"/>And Abel he also brought of the
                     firstlings of his flock and of the fat there<space extent="4"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.12" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>of. and the Lord had respect unto Abel
                     and his Offering <unclear resp="EA">But to Cain</unclear>
                            <space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "Abel and to his offering:" rather than "Abel and
                     his Offering" (Crosby and Essick page 13). The underwritten words "But to Cain"
                     appear in darker pencil at the beginning of the next line. Crosby and Essick
                     note that Blake originally wrote the words at the end of this line (page
                     9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.13" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>5<space extent="3"/>But to Cain and to
                     his offering he had not re<unclear resp="EA">s</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>pect</orig>
                                <reg>respect</reg>
                            </choice> and Cain was very wroth</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "But
                     unto Cain" rather than "But to Cain" (Crosby and Essick page 13). The "s" in
                     "respect" is unclear. Crosby and Essick read "respect" without comment (page
                     6).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.14" justify="left" indent="7">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="4"/>and his countenance fell<space extent="43"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.15" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">6<space extent="3"/>And the Lord said unto Cain, Why art
                     thou wroth &amp; why is thy countenance fallen</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.16" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>7<space extent="3"/>If thou doest well
                     shalt thou not be accepted and if thou doest not well sin<space extent="7"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="but828.10.16.note.jpg"/>The verse number "7" has been
                     written twice, one slightly higer and to the left of the other. (Crosby and
                     Essick page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.17" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="10"/>lieth at the door and to thee shall be
                     his desire &amp; thou shalt rule over him</hi>
                        <note>The first several words of this line lie almost completely below the ruled
                     line. The King James Bible reads "And unto thee shall" rather than "and to thee
                     shall" (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.18" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>8<space extent="3"/>And Cain talked with
                     his brother and it came to pass when they were in the</hi>
                        <note>The verse number and first several words of this line lie almost completely
                     below the ruled line. The King James Bible reads "talked with Abel his
                     brother:" rather than "talked with his brother" (Crosby and Essick page
                     13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.19" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="11"/>field that Cain rose up against Abel his
                     brother &amp; slew him<space extent="12"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The first several words of this line lie almost completely below the ruled
                     line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.20" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">9<space extent="3"/>And the Lord said unto Cain Where is
                     Abel thy brother and he said I know<space extent="3"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The verse number "9" lies below the ruled line.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.21" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="10"/>not am I my brothers keeper<space extent="39"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.22" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">10<space extent="2"/>And he said What hast thou done the
                     voice of thy brothers blood crieth<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.23" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>unto me from the ground (Adamah)<space extent="30"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "from the ground" rather
                     than "from the ground (Adamah)", and Blake has omitted the period at the end of
                     this verse (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.24" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">11<space extent="2"/>And now thou art cursed from the
                        g<unclear resp="EA">roun</unclear>
                            <choice>
                                <orig>d</orig>
                                <reg>ground</reg>
                            </choice> (adamah) which hath opened<space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>Crosby and Essick note that the unclear word "ground" may have been written
                     over "earth", which is the term used in the King James Bible (page 9n). The
                     King James Bible reads "And now art thou cursed from the earth, which" rather
                     than "And now thou art cursed from the ground (adamah) which" (Crosby and
                     Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.25" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>her mouth to receive thy brothers blood
                     from thy hand<space extent="15"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.26" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">12<space extent="2"/>When thou tillest the ground (adamah)
                     it shall not henceforth yield unto thee</hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "tillest the ground, it" rather than "tillest the
                     ground (adamah) it" (Crosby and Essick page 13). The initial "a" in "adamah"
                     appears to have been written twice, one character a bit larger than the
                     other.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.27" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="9"/>her strength a fugitive &amp; a vagabond
                     thou shal<unclear resp="EA">
                                <choice>
                                    <orig>t</orig>
                                    <reg>shalt</reg>
                                </choice>
                            </unclear> be in the earth<space extent="11"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "vagabond shalt thou be" rather than "vagabond
                     thou shalt be" (Crosby and Essick page 13). Crosby and Essick note that "shalt"
                     may be "shall" in Blake's manuscript (page 9n).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.28" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">13<space extent="2"/>And Cain said unto the Lord My
                     punishment is greater than I can bear<space extent="2"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.29" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="1"/>14<space extent="2"/>Behold thou hast
                     driven me out this day from the face of the earth &amp; from</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.30" justify="left">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="11"/>thy face shall I be hid and a fugitive
                     &amp; a vagabond in the earth and it<space extent="1"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "and I shall be a fugitive and a vagabond" rather
                     than "and a fugitive &amp; a vagabond" (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.10.31" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="10"/>shall come to pass that every one that findeth me shall
                     slay me<space extent="4"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="but828.1.ms.11" dbi="but828.1.11.MS">
            <objtitle>
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U11">(Butlin 828.11)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>38 x 28 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object has 23 ruled lines. Only the first three of these contain text,
                  suggesting Blake left the work unfinished. This object also contains light pencil
                  markings, some of which are visible. These appear to be remnants of Blake's first
                  writing that were erased of overwritten at a later stage. Crosby and Essick call
                  attention to the underwriting but do not transcribe it (page 1); they use textual
                  notes to detail many individual occurences.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="650" width="470"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>This design depicts God forgiving Cain. In the center of the design are
                  two male figures facing each other. The figure on the left faces right in profile
                  and is bending forward and down. This is God, wearing a long flowing gown. A leg,
                  possibly left leg, extends back toward the left, and the left foot appears to be
                  on tiptoe. God may be partly kneeling. The right arm of God is at the side of his
                  body and extends to the right and suggests an embrace with the figure to the
                  right. God has long hair and one slit-like eye is visible. God's head is bent down
                  and he appears to be touching the forehead of the figure to the right. This is
                  Cain, who faces left in profile and appears to be kneeling. Cain is wearing a gown
                  and his head is tilted back. One eye is open and he looks up at God. Cain's left
                  arm is raised and bent. His lower arm is vertical and rests on God's upper right
                  arm, suggesting an embrace. Cain's left foot is visible. Below God and Cain is a
                  convex arc representing the surface of the Earth. To the right of the design are a
                  cluster of pencil lines that depict a structure with a steep sloping roof. In
                  front of this structure are the outlines of two figures with bowed heads, facing
                  left. These are Adam and Eve. Above the structure and to the left of God are
                  curving lines that may represent clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>God</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the design are two male figures facing each other.
                     The figure on the left faces right in profile and is bending forward and down.
                     This is God, wearing a long flowing gown. A leg, possibly the left leg, extends
                     backward, and the left foot appears to be on tiptoe. God may be partly
                     kneeling. The right arm of God, at the side of his body, is bent slightly and
                     extends to the right suggesting an embrace with the figure to the right. God
                     has long hair and one slit-like eye is visible. God's head is bent down and he
                     appears to be touching or kissing the forehead of the figure to the
                     right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Cain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The smaller central figure is Cain, who faces left in profile and is
                     kneeling. Cain is wearing a gown and his head is tilted back. One eye is open
                     and he looks up at God the Father. Cain's left arm is raised and bent. His
                     lower arm is vertical and rests on God's upper right arm, suggesting an
                     embrace. Cain's left foot is visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prayer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the design and in front of the steep-roofed
                     structure are the outlines of two figures with lowered heads, facing left.
                     These are Adam and Eve. They appear to be wearing gowns and dark pencil lines
                     on the leftmost figure suggest hands clasped together in prayer or
                     supplication. They may be kneeling.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below God and Cain is a convex arc representing the surface of the
                     Earth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the structure and to the left of God are curving lines that
                     may represent clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cottage</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>house</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hut</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the design are a cluster of pencil lines that
                     depicts a structure, probably a cottage-like hut or house but possibly a tent,
                     with a steep sloping roof.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.01" justify="left" indent="1"> 15<hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="2"/>And the Lord said unto Cain Therefore whosoever slayeth<space extent="6"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "said unto him, Therefore"
                     rather than "said unto Cain Therefore" (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.02" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="6"/>Cain vengeance shall be taken of him sevenfold and the<space extent="5"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The ruled line line bisects much of the text in this line. The King James
                     Bible reads "taken on him" rather than "taken of him" and "And the" rather than
                     "and the" (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.03" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="6"/>Lord set a mark upon Cains forehead<space extent="24"/>
                        </hi>
                        <note>The King James Bible reads "Lord set a mark upon Cain, lest any finding
                     him should should kill him" rather than "Lord set a mark upon Cains forehead"
                     (Crosby and Essick page 13).</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.04" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="64"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.05" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="64"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.06" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="64"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.07" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="67"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.08" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="63"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.09" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="65"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.10" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="63"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.11" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="63"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.12" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="64"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.13" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="62"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.14" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="4"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="61"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.15" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="62"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.16" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="4"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="61"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.17" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="62"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.18" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="62"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.19" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="62"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.20" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="4"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="63"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.21" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="63"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.22" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="3"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="61"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                    <l n="but828.1.ms.11.23" justify="left" indent="1">
                        <space extent="2"/>
                        <hi rend="underscore">
                            <space extent="62"/>
                        </hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>