<bad id="but85v.1" type="penink" work="Four Composition Sketches" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="85v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Four Composition Sketches">
                    <main>Four Composition Sketches</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Four Composition Sketches
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1785">c. 1785-90
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>19.4 x 15.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>19.4 x 15.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <support>laid paper<note>This object is the verso of Butlin 85 recto, <hi rend="i">A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing</hi>.  This leaf was originally one half of a larger leaf.  The other half is Butlin 86, with <hi rend="i">An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Couple</hi> on the recto and <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi> on the verso.</note>
                </support>
                <watermark>PRO PATRIA<note>Only part of this watermark appears on this leaf.  The other half is on Butlin 86, with <hi rend="i">An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Couple</hi> on the recto and <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi> on the verso.</note>
                </watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The British Museum accession number is stamped just above the bottom margin on the right.</note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis, who gave the work to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-2076-361555</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <collection>none</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.124</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but85v.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT85.1.1v.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Four Composition Sketches</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 85 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This object is the verso of Butlin 85 recto, <hi rend="i">A Girl and a Bearded Man Embracing</hi>.  This leaf was originally one half of a larger leaf.  The other half is Butlin 86, with <hi rend="i">An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Man</hi> on the recto and <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi> on the verso.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>19.4 x 15.5 cm</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <related objectid="but86v.1.penink.01"/>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper left quadrant contains the partly erased figure of a man(?) facing forward with arms raised at roughly 135 degrees.  Both feet are visible.  Brushstrokes of grey wash on either side of the tree partially obscure background detail which may include vegetation and clouds.  The sketch in the upper right quadrant contains two erect figures preparing to stab a third figure reclining on the ground.  A diagonal brushstroke of grey wash was applied over the figural group.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two figures reclining on the ground, heads at left.  They are very similar to the figures in <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, Bentley plate 38.  Two vertical brushstrokes of grey wash are drawn over the figures' torsos.  There are clouds, or possibly a figure with arms or wings outstretched, above them.  The sketch in the lower right quadrant contains two figures; the lower figure reclines on the ground and looks up and to the left toward the second figure, who appears to rise from clouds.  This sketch runs over onto the verso of another page of sketches (Butlin 86 verso), indicating that the two pages were originally part of the same sheet of paper.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper left quadrant contains the partly erased figure of a man(?) facing forward with arms raised at roughly 135 degrees.  Both feet are visible.  The figure may be walking forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be vegetation right and left of the standing figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be clouds above and below the figure's outstretched arms.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper right quadrant contains three figures.  The leftmost figure, whose gender is indeterminate though likely male, partially stands, though his right knee appears to be bent behind him in a kneeling posture.  His left leg is extended in front of him and also bent.  Facing right, he extends his right arm horizontally and holds what may be a dagger.  He may be preparing to stab the reclining figure below.  He appears to be gowned.  His body is partially obscured by a diagonal brushstroke of grey wash.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper right quadrant contains three figures.  The rightmost erect figure, whose gender is indeterminate but likely male, faces forward and leans to the right.  He may wear a gown.  He extends his left arm horizontally and holds what may be a dagger (though this form is only suggested by a single line).  He appears to look toward the figure at left, although there are indications of an alternative head position facing right.  He may be preparing to stab the reclining figure below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the upper right quadrant contains three figures.  A gowned figure, who may be female as suggested by the long hair, reclines on the ground and faces up.  She lays her head against what may be a pillow or perhaps a stone at right.  The figure's left arm is visible on the ground by her side.  Though her facial features are indistinct, this figure may have closed eyes and be sleeping.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>dagger</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two erect figures appear to hold daggers in their outstretched arms, though the dagger at right is only suggested by a single line.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure, who may be female, reclines on the ground and lays her head against what may be a pillow or perhaps a stone at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two figures reclining on the ground, heads at left.  They are very similar to the figures in <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, Bentley plate 38.  The lower figure may have long hair, suggesting she is female; she may be nude.  She faces up and slightly extends her left arm, perhaps to touch her companion, though the exact division of the bodies is indistinct.  Her eyes appear to be closed, and she may be sleeping.  The portion of her right arm that is visible appears to be raised horizontally.  Two vertical brushstrokes of grey wash cross over her body.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two figures reclining on the ground, heads at left.  They are very similar to the figures in <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, Bentley plate 38.  The figure above, who may be nude, faces up but turns its head away; its gender is indeterminable.  This figure may extend its left arm across its torso to touch its companion's chest at left, though the exact division of the bodies is indistinct.  Although its facial features are not visible, the posture of this figure suggests it may be sleeping.  The vertical brushstroke of grey wash at right crosses over its body.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eagle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower left quadrant contains two figures reclining on the ground, heads at left.  Above them is either a band of clouds or a hovering figure seen head on, arms or wings outstretched.  There is a slight possibility that this is a bird, like the eagle in the very similar design in <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, Bentley plate 38.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm by side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower right quadrant contains two figures. The lower figure is a nude male who reclines on the ground braced by his left arm.  His right arm appears to be by his side; his left leg is extended and his right is bent beneath him.  Facing up, he looks up and to the left toward the second figure, who appears to rise from clouds.  This sketch runs over onto the verso of another page of sketches (Butlin 86 verso), indicating that the two pages were originally part of the same sheet of paper.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blessing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Four composition sketches are each separated by rough framing lines.  The sketch in the lower right quadrant contains two figures.  Only visible from the waist up as he floats or hovers on clouds, the figure at top right faces and leans right and appears to look down toward the reclining figure below.  The gender of this figure is indeterminable, though perhaps male as he wears a gown and may offer a gesture of blessing (two fingers raised on his right hand) with his extended right arm.  His left arm may also be slightly raised.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure at right in the sketch in the lower right quadrant is only visible from the waist up as he appears to float or hover on clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <columns>
                    <column>
                        <vspace/>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but85v.1.pennumbers.01.01" justify="left" indent="20">124<note>These numbers, near the bottom of the margin of the leaf, may not be by Blake.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </column>
                    <column>
                        <vspace/>
                        <lg justify="left">
                            <l n="but85v.1.writtennumbers.01.02" justify="left" indent="40">20</l>
                        </lg>
                    </column>
                </columns>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>