<bad id="but87r.1" type="wc" work="A Man and Woman Kneeling and Warming Themselves at a Fire" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="87">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Man and Woman Kneeling and Warming Themselves at a Fire">
                    <main>
                        A Man and Woman Kneeling and Warming Themselves at a Fire</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 21KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *A Man and Woman Kneeling and Warming Themselves at a Fire*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.E">c. 1785-90</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>12.8 x 10.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.1 x 14.8 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>paper, probably wove</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>A single ink framing line extends around all four sides of the design.</note></framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis; given by Francis in 1874 to the British Museum.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1874,1212.119</repositoryid>
            </repository>
            
        </source>
        <desc id="but87r.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT87.1.1r.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Man and Woman Kneeling and Warming Themselves at a Fire</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 87 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The oval collection stamp (not shown) of John Deffett Francis, "J.D.F.," appears below the design, partly cut off by the edge of the leaf.  A pencil sketch of Anubis is on the verso of this water color.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>12.8 x 10.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In a forest or other wooded area, two figures kneel in a clearing to warm themselves by a fire. The figure at left is a bearded man with long, curly hair. He appears to be almost entirely nude, with a belt or other object wrapped around his waist and slight suggestion of tights or a transparent, draping cloth over his knees and around his right ankle. The man faces right, kneeling with his knees bent sharply and his buttocks nearly resting on the heels of his flexed feet. His upper body hunches forward as he reaches toward the fire with is prominent right arm. His left arm is hidden, either alongside his right arm or at his left side. The man looks toward the right side of the design and may stare at something just above the fire. His eyes express fear or dread. To the right of this man kneels his companion, a partly nude woman with her long hair gathered into a bun. She is nude from the waist up, but her lower body may be covered by a transparent skirt or other drapery. Her body faces forward and to the right as she kneels with her knees together, but she twists to look back over her right shoulder, toward the left side of the design. Her prominent breasts are notably asymmetrical. Her left arm reaches toward the fire at right, her extended hand hovering over the flames. The position of her right arm is unclear, but it may rest along her side with her hand in her lap. At right of this pair, another figure may hide behind one of the trees and wrap an arm around another. There is only slight suggestion of a head and shoulders.  Alternatively, this may not be a figure but only odd wisps of smoke or fire. In the lower righthand corner of the design, a fire blazes over a pile of sticks or wood. It reaches as high as the shoulders of the two figures who warms themselves by it. Red and gray coloring suggest flames and smoke. Below the fire and the two kneeling figures, blue-green coloring indicates grass. Immediately behind the figures and flame are five(?) tall trees, most of which do not have branches. The tree nearest the design's left border leans left from behind the next tree, which rises straight upward behind the kneeling man. From between the heads of the two kneeling figures rises a third tree, much narrower than the first two. Above the woman's outstretched arm rises a fourth tree; it bears a small branch growing upward at 135 degrees from the tree's left side. Finally, a fifth tree leans right toward the right border. This tree may support the third figure. Behind the trees, in the design's background, are rolling hills covered in grass. Above them, alternating blue and white coloring suggests mountains, or perhaps clouds against a dark sky. Shadowy areas are visible underneath the knees of the kneeling man and between the two main figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In a forest or other wooded area, two figures kneel in a clearing to warm themselves by a fire. The figure at left is a bearded man with long, curly hair. He appears to be almost entirely nude, with a belt or other object wrapped around his waist and slight suggestion of tights or a transparent, draping cloth over his knees and around his right ankle. The man faces right, kneeling with his knees bent sharply and his buttocks nearly resting on the heels of his flexed feet. His upper body hunches forward as he reaches toward the fire with is prominent right arm. His left arm is hidden, either alongside his right arm or at his left side. The man looks toward the right side of the design and may stare at something just above the fire. His eyes express fear or dread.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent at knees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left arm</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In a forest or other wooded area, two figures kneel in a clearing to warm themselves by a fire. At right is a partly nude woman with her long hair gathered into a bun. She is nude from the waist up, but her lower body may be covered by a transparent skirt or other drapery. Her body faces forward and to the right as she kneels with her knees together, but she twists to look back over her right shoulder, toward the left side of the design. Her prominent breasts are notably asymmetrical. Her left arm reaches toward the fire at right, her extended hand hovering over the flames. The position of her right arm is unclear, but it may rest along her side with her hand in her lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right of this pair, another nude figure may hide behind one of the trees and wrap an arm around another. There is only slight suggestion of a head and shoulders. Alternatively, this may only be only an odd wisp of smoke or fire.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stick</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower righthand corner of the design, a fire blazes over a pile of sticks or wood. It reaches as high as the shoulders of the two figures who warms themselves by it. Red and gray coloring indicate flames and smoke.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the fire and the two kneeling figures, blue-green coloring indicates grass.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Immediately behind the figures and flame are five(?) tall, leafless trees, most of which do not have branches. The tree nearest the design's left border leans left from behind the next tree, which rises straight upward behind the kneeling man. From between the heads of the two kneeling figures rises a third tree, much narrower than the first two. Above the woman's outstretched arm rises a fourth tree; it bears a small branch growing upward at 135 degrees from the tree's left side. Finally, a fifth tree leans right toward the right border. This tree's trunk may support the third figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the trees, in the design's background, are rolling hills covered in grass. Above them, alternating blue and white coloring suggests mountains, or perhaps clouds against a dark sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>clouds</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the trees, in the design's background, are rolling hills covered in grass. Above them, alternating blue and white coloring suggests mountains, or perhaps clouds against a dark sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be shadowy areas underneath the knees of the kneeling man and between the two main figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
