<info id="but828">
    <worktitle>
        <div id="but828.title">
            <h1>
                <i>Genesis</i>
            </h1>
        </div>
    </worktitle>
    <remarks>
        <div id="but828.top">
            <p>Blake began, probably in the last year of his life, to produce an illustrated
                manuscript of the King James translation of Genesis. The work was probably
                commissioned by John Linnell. At Blake’s death on 12 August 1827, he had transcribed
                the text only as far as Genesis 4:15. The incomplete manuscript, consisting of
                eleven leaves bearing text and designs on rectos only, is now in the Huntington
                Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            <p>Blake began writing the manuscript in pencil and illustrating it with a headpiece and
                tailpiece for each chapter. Two additional designs illustrate the second leaf of the
                first chapter. He then began to illuminate the text in green and red, but this work
                extends only to Genesis 2:5. A few letters, including the initial capital “I” of
                Genesis 1:1, are also highlighted in gold. It is of course regrettable that Blake
                did not live to complete his Genesis manuscript, but its present state does offer
                insights into his working methods.</p>
            <p>Blake prepared two title pages for the manuscript. The energetic version generally
                believed to be the first (object 1) is followed by the calmer but more complex
                second version (object 2). Perhaps Linnell was not pleased with the first effort and
                encouraged Blake to produce an alternative, one more responsive to the aesthetics of
                the beautiful than the sublime.</p>
            <p>Blake made a few alterations and additions to the King James translation that
                indicate his personal understanding of Genesis and his knowledge of the interpretive
                traditions surrounding the Bible. The most significant textual additions are the
                chapter headings of Blake’s own invention that signify his perspective on each
                chapter and serve as captions for the headpieces immediately above. The heading for
                Genesis 4 shows that Blake understood the marking of Cain as a sign of forgiveness
                rather than guilt. At several junctures Blake added the Hebrew word “adamah” to
                “ground” to indicate the material from which God forms “Man” (to which Blake added
                “Adam”) in Genesis 2:7. Blake’s addition of “Elohim” after the plural “Gods” in
                Genesis 2:7 also reveals his knowledge of Hebrew—an interest he shared with
                Linnell—and his awareness of controversies surrounding the different names for God
                in the Hebrew Bible. As with Blake’s illustrations to the works of other poets, the
                designs in the Genesis Manuscript offer a visual commentary on the text. Perhaps
                again responding to scholarly debates, Blake acknowledges the repetition of Eve’s
                creation in Genesis 1:27 and 2:22-23 by picturing the event twice (objects 6 and 7).
            </p>
        </div>
    </remarks>
    <related>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Body of Abel Found by Adam and Eve</i>
            <br/>Water color, c. 664. Butlin
            664.<br/>Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University<br/>Cambridge, Massachusetts</relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Body of Abel Found by Adam and Eve</i>
            <br/>Tempera painting, c. 1826.
            Butlin 806.<br/>Tate Collection at Tate Britain<br/>London</relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Body of Abel Found by Adam and Eve: Perhaps a Replica by John
                Linnell</i>
            <br/>Pen and Ink drawing, date uncertain. Butlin 666.<br/>Keynes
            Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>Cambridge, England</relationship>
    </related>
</info>