<bad id="but80v.1" type="penc"
    work="Two Sketches of a Swordsman Standing Over His Defeated Opponent" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="ngadc" catalog="butlin" catid="80v" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Two Sketches of a Swordsman Standing Over His Defeated Opponent">
                    <main>Two Sketches of a Swordsman Standing Over His Defeated Opponent</main> :
                    electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October
                    2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* ( Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work courtesy of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>November 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Two Sketches of a Swordsman Standing Over His Defeated Opponent* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic
                        considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>25.2 x 36.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>25.2 x 36.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Possibly acquired, from Blake or John Flaxman or John Linnell, by Thomas
                    Chevalier (1767-1824); possibly Chevalier's great-granddaughter, Ellen M.
                    Chevalier, later Mrs. William Dobinson; possibly sold from her collection,
                    Sotheby's, 1 Dec. 1910, in lot 126 with eight other works (&#163;3 to "Fry,"
                    probably acting for the dealer James Tregaskis); the dealer C. A. Stonehill;
                    sold c. 1937 by Stonehill with a group of drawings by Flaxman and his associates
                    to Lessing J. Rosenwald; given by Rosenwald to the National Gallery of Art,
                    Washington, in 1943.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <addressline>Constitution Avenue NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline>
                <addressline>Washington, DC 20565</addressline>
                <addressline>Mailing Address: 2000B South Club Drive, Landover, Maryland
                    20785</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-202-737-4215</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Print Study Rooms: 1-202-842-6380</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 1-202-842-6126</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Visual Services:
                    http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1980.45.182.b</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but80v.1.penc.01" dbi="BUT80.1.1v.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Two Sketches of a Swordsman Standing Over His Defeated
                    Opponent</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 80 verso)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The reference to "Two Sketches" in the title includes a pencil drawing of the
                        same subject and date on the recto.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>25.2 x 36.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Near the center of the composition, a standing male(?) figure
                        faces forward yet turns his head left, perhaps to look toward a group of at
                        least three figures standing behind some sort of low horizontal structure
                        near the left edge of the drawing. The central figure wears a long gown with
                        a sash or length of drapery diagonally draped across his chest; the fabric
                        extends over his left shoulder, ending in a serpentine flourish. Pentimenti
                        to the right of this figure suggest he was originally positioned further to
                        the right. He may have long hair, perhaps worn in a braid over his left
                        shoulder, and in his right hand he holds a sword, which is pointed downward
                        to touch the right shoulder of a reclining, defeated figure facing away from
                        the viewer. This male figure appears nude from the waist up and twists his
                        torso to the left with his left arm bent and braced on the ground. Near the
                        right edge of the drawing, a female figure wearing a long gown stands facing
                        away from the viewer and looks left. With both arms bent, she appears to
                        hold or lead the horse at right that also faces left. Between this figure
                        and the horse, there is a shorter figure very faintly drawn who appears to
                        face left with one arm extended backward (perhaps to touch the horse?) and
                        wear a gown. The smaller size of this figure suggests it is a child.
                        Indeterminate horizontal lines in the upper register of the drawing may
                        suggest distant hills.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpentine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the center of the composition, a standing male(?) figure
                            faces forward yet turns his head left, perhaps to look toward a group of
                            at least three figures at left. The central figure wears a long gown
                            with a belt and a sash or length of drapery diagonally draped across his
                            chest; the fabric extends over his left shoulder, ending in a serpentine
                            flourish. He may have long hair, perhaps worn in a braid over his left
                            shoulder. His right leg may be crossed behind his left, and in his right
                            hand, he holds a sword, which is pointed downward to touch the right
                            shoulder of a reclining, defeated figure below. Both may be
                            soldiers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The central standing figure in the drawing holds a sword in
                            his right hand. He points the weapon downward to touch the right
                            shoulder of the figure lying in the lower left corner below
                            him.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Pentimenti to the right of the central standing figure suggest
                            he was originally positioned further to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying on side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner of the drawing, a reclining male
                            figure who appears to be defeated (and perhaps a soldier?) lies on his
                            left side and faces away from the viewer. He is nude from the waist up
                            and twists his torso to the left with his left arm bent and braced on
                            the ground. Drapery may cover his legs, which are extended to the
                            right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Near the right edge of the drawing, a female figure wearing a
                            long gown (with some sort of belt and diagonal sash) stands facing away
                            from the viewer and looks left, perhaps toward the two male figures at
                            left. She appears to have long hair. With both arms bent, she appears to
                            hold or lead the horse at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mane</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Approximately the front half of a horse with a prominent mane
                            who faces left is visible against the right margin of the
                            drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the drawing between the female figure and
                            the horse, there is a shorter figure very faintly drawn who appears to
                            lean right but face left with one arm extended backward (perhaps to
                            touch the horse) and wear a gown. The smaller size of this figure
                            suggests it is a child.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Indeterminate horizontal lines in the upper register of the
                            drawing may suggest distant hills.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of at least three figures, each depicted from the
                            waist up, is visible near the upper left corner of the drawing. The
                            leftmost of these faces forward and turns to look slightly right. He(?)
                            appears to have short hair and may wear some sort of gown or drapery. He
                            may look toward the central standing figure who turns left perhaps to
                            meet his gaze.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of at least three figures, each depicted from the
                            waist up, is visible near the upper left corner of the drawing. The
                            middle figure faces right to look at its companion at right. This figure
                            may have short hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A group of at least three figures, each depicted from the
                            waist up, is visible near the upper left corner of the drawing. The
                            rightmost figure appears to face left and look left toward its companion
                            at left. This figure may have short hair and wear some sort of gown or
                            drapery.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A fourth head, drawn very faintly and directly above the
                            middle figure in the group of three at left, may suggest additional
                            figures in the background.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A diagonal line separating the group of three figures at left
                            from the foreground figures may signify a short wall or other structure.
                            This line appears to continue right of the central figure with a
                            sword.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
