<bad id="but8.1" type="wc" work="King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above His Monument" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin" catid="8">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above His Monument">
                    <main>
                        King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above His Monument</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 18KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 Society of Antiquaries, London.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above His Monument*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1775.C">c. 1775</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>31.5 x 12.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>39.8 x 26.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The work is numbered "II." in pencil top right.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its engraving for Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, first published by the Society of Antiquaries in 1780.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries, London</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 30</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but8.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT8.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">King Sebert, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above His Monument</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 8)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The collection stamp of the Society of Antiquaries appears bottom center left below the design.  A larger, circular collection stamp of the Society appears lower right.  A water color replica (Butlin 16) of this water color is in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.  An engraving of this design was published in Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, Plate 5 (1780), and in *Vetusta Monumenta*, volume 2 of c. 1789, Plate 33.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>39.8 x 26.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design, part of the wall painting in the sedilia above King Sebert's monument at Westminster Abbey, is a panel with a solid background (perhaps of stone?) and a narrow border, which contains beveling, two columns, and a plain arch. Inside the arch are four points of a decorative tracery, each containing a gilded trefoil design and terminating in a leaf. The two points nearest the arch's top are smaller and more compressed. In the center of the arching panel is a crowned man who represents King Sebert. The king wears a long-sleeved gown, a long robe, gloves, and a crown. His hair and beard are curly. The king faces forward and to the right, bending with his upper body toward the pillar at his right. His left arm is bent upward, and he points upward with his index finger. His right arm is bent with his forearm raised horizontally, and he holds a decorative scepter that extends from his waist over his right shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design represents the wall-painting of King Sebert in the sedilia above his monument in Westminster Abbey. It contains a tall, narrow, painted panel with a solid background (perhaps of stone?) and surrounded by a narrow border. The horizontal lower border suggests a beveled design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tracery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gold</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design represents the wall-painting of King Sebert in the sedilia above his monument in Westminster Abbey. Forming the vertical portions of this border are the inside halves of two columns or pillars; the left column appears to be segmented, and the right bears a cross-hatching pattern. The arching upper portions of this border are plain, but inside the arch are four points of a decorative tracery, each containing a gilded trefoil design and terminating in a leaf. The two points nearest the arch's top are smaller and more compressed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Each of the four points of the decorative tracery near the top
                            of the design appears to end in a decorative leaf.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gloves</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulder</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the arching panel is painted a crowned man who represents King Sebert. The king wears a long-sleeved gown with a decorated collar. The gown extends to the floor and is partially covered by a long, flowing robe with a bordered, curling hem. He wears gloves on both hands. His hair and beard are curly, and a crown decorated with four (visible) leaves sits atop his head. The king faces forward and to the right, bending with his upper body toward the right. His head bends right and downward, but his eyes are raised. His left arm is bent upward, and he points upward with his index finger. The other fingers of his left hand are curled into a loose fist. His right arm is bent with his forearm raised horizontally, and he holds in his extended fingers a decorative scepter that extends from his waist over his right shoulder, where it may rest.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>King Sebert holds a scepter in his right hand. The upper end of the scepter is decorated with a gold design that resembles a Gothic structure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg><l n="but8.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="50">II.<note>This pencil inscription was probably not written by Blake.</note></l></lg>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg><l n="but8.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="42">foot  I<note>This inscription and line 3, both in pen and ink, record the height of the design.  They are written vertically along the right side of the design.  These inscription were probably not written by Blake.</note></l>
                    <l n="but8.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="42">7.  2<note>See the note to line 2.</note></l></lg>
                <vspace extent="18"/>
                <lg><l n="but8.1.wc.01.04" justify="left" indent="35">Basire. del.<note>This pen and ink inscription, a reference to or signature of Blake's engraving master James Basire, was probably not written by Blake.</note></l>
                    <l n="but8.1.wc.01.05" justify="left" indent="18">foot  I<note>This inscription and line 6, both in pen and ink, record the width of the design.  These inscriptions were probably not written by Blake.</note></l>
                    <l n="but8.1.wc.01.06" justify="left" indent="19">2:  8<note>See the note to line 5.</note></l></lg>
                <vspace extent="2"/>
                <lg><l n="but8.1.wc.01.07" justify="left">Figure supposed to be that of King Sebert on the North front of his Tomb. Westm<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Abbey vide Vetutst. Mon. Vol. II. pl. 33.<note>This pen and ink inscription is probably not by Blake.  "Vetutst. Mon. Vol. II. pl. 33" is a reference to volume 2 of *Vetusta Monumenta*, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.  An engraving of this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published as plate 33 in that volume.</note></l></lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
