
<bad id="but82r.1" type="mono" work="Three Figures Under a Yoke with Two Children" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="82r" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Three Figures Under a Yoke with Two Children">
                    <main>Three Figures Under a Yoke with Two Children</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2024</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>              
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2024 British Museum
      </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>August 2018</date>
               <respstmt>
<resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
<name>Ashley Reed, </name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Katherine Calvin, </name>
<name>Erin Francisco, </name>
<name>Ani Govjian, </name>
<name>Alison Harper, </name>
<name>Rachael Isom, </name>
<name>Joey Kingsley, </name>
<name>Mary Learner, </name>
<name>Rob Rich, </name>
<name>Anneke Schwob, </name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta, </name>
<name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat, </name>
<name>Jewell Thomas, </name>
<name>Emily Tronson, </name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name>
<name>Alex Zawacki</name>
</respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>September 2001</date>
                 <respstmt>
                     <resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                     <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                     <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                     <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                     <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                     <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                     <name>Kirk V. Hastings</name>
                    and <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                     <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                     <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                     <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                     <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                 </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        Three Figures Under a Yoke with Two Children
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.B">c. 1780-85<note>The date is based on stylistic considerations.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>15.0 x 14.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>16.0 x 17.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil and monochrome washes</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired at an unknown time by John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.132</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but82.1r.wd.01" dbi="BUT82.1.1r.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Three Figures Under a Yoke with Two Children</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 82 recto)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote><p>For the verso pencil sketch of the same basic design, less fully developed, see *Sketch of Figures Under a Yoke*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>15.0 x 14.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Three adults and two children stand facing forward under a yoke against a dark background in this drawing.  At center, an old male figure with curly hair and a long beard looks forward with an open mouth.  The adult at right is a nude male figure with short curly hair whose arms are also visible above the elbow before being bent behind his back.  He turns his head to look left and stands in a contrapposto position with left foot slightly lifted while his right ankle is shackled.  There appears to be a chain around his waist, possibly also dangling vertically over his lower torso.  The adult at left is a nude female figure with long hair who turns her head to look right.  With both arms extended downward in front of her, she attempts to cover her genitals while holding in her right hand a length of chain extending from the yoke.  A nude child stands beside her and may lean against her left leg.  With head down and arms possibly bent upward, the child extends its left leg backward.  An older child, also nude, stands between the two male adult figures and turns his head to look right and up.  His right leg is bent backward at the knee.  A yoke that appears to be made of wood rests across the shoulders of the three adult figures.  Two lengths of chain dangle from each end of the yoke: at left, the female figure holds the chain in front of her genitals, and at right, the chain may be connected to the male figure's hands behind his back (not pictured) and then extend downward to connect to the shackle visible around his right ankle.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms behind back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three adults and two children stand facing forward under a yoke.  At center, an old male figure with curly hair and a long beard looks forward with an open mouth.  He wears a gown, and his upper arms are visible at his sides with elbows bent behind his back.  His right foot is visible beneath the hem of his gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms behind back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three adults and two children stand facing forward under a yoke.  The adult at right is a nude male figure with short curly hair whose arms are visible above the elbow and then bent behind his back.  He turns his head to look left and stands in a contrapposto position with left foot slightly lifted while his right ankle is shackled.  There appears to be a chain around his waist, possibly also dangling vertically over his lower torso.  Although his hands are not pictured, the position of the chains suggests they too may be shackled behind his back.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands on genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three adults and two children stand facing forward under a yoke.  The adult at left is a nude female figure with long hair who turns her head to face right.  With both arms at her sides, she attempts to cover her genitals while holding in her right hand a length of chain extending from the yoke.  Her left leg is extended slightly backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three adults and two children stand facing forward under a yoke.  A nude child stands to the right of the female figure and may lean against her left leg.  With head down and arms possibly bent upward, the child extends its left leg backward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three adults and two children stand facing forward under a yoke.  An older child, also nude, stands between the two male adult figures and turns his head to look right and up.  His right leg is bent backward at the knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>yoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A yoke that appears to be made of wood rests across the shoulders of the three adult figures.  Two lengths of chain dangle from each end of the yoke: at left, the female figure holds the chain in front of her genitals, and at right, the chain may be connected to the male figure's hands behind his back (not pictured) and then extend downward to connect to the shackle visible around his right ankle.  There appears to be a chain around his waist, possibly also dangling vertically over his lower torso.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
