<bad id="but93.1" type="mono" work="A Woodland Encounter" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ransom" catalog="butlin" catid="93">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="A Woodland Encounter">
                    <main>A Woodland Encounter</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2024 Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        A Woodland Encounter
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1785.D">c. 1785<note>The dating is based on stylistic considerations.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>29.0 x 24.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>29.0 x 24.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink, monochrome wash</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin</name>
                <date>c. 1965</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>    
            
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 174 with seven other works by Blake (9s. to Gould Weston); Mrs. Hunter-Weston, probably by inheritance in 1904; Mrs. Nora Hunter, probably by inheritance; sold Christie's, 15 July 1957, lot 22 (&#163;18.18s. to the dealer Jacob Schwartz); Thomas Edward Hanley; given by Hanley to the University of Texas c. 1965 and now housed in the Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas at Austin</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">70.7</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but93.1.wd.01" dbi="BUT93.1.1.WD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">A Woodland Encounter</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 93)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>29.0 x 24.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Beneath a leafy tree, a standing female figure, at left, looks toward a male figure at right who raises his right arm to touch a horse(?) standing between the figures. The female figure has long, curly hair and wears a long veil that wraps around her right elbow. She wears either a gown or a shirt and skirt; her garment's collar is ruffled. A belt or perhaps the strap of a bag, which may be visible near her right hip, is visible around her waist. She faces right and her eyes may be closed. Both arms are at her sides and bent slightly upward with palms facing up and fingers spread. Her right leg is bent beneath her gown or skirt, which suggests she may walk to the right or stand in a contrapposto position. The male figure at right stands facing left and looks toward the female figure. He has short hair and a beard, and he appears to wear a knee-length gown or tunic. His right arm is raised horizontally and he may touch or point to the shadowy figure or animal at left. His left arm is at his side and bent upwards to hold a walking stick. His right leg is bent suggesting a contrapposto stance. Several spiky lines above his left shoulder may suggest a quiver of arrows as well as a darker, rounded form representing one end of a bow. The form in between the two figures may be a horse, as suggested by the oval shape of its head and lines that suggest a mane. However, the form is covered with dark washes that obscure most details. One front leg is suggested at left of the male standing figure and one back leg may be visible behind and right of the male figure. A tree with a thick trunk that leans to the right and dense, leafy canopy stands over the figures in the foreground. Additional vegetation, perhaps bushes or tall grass, are visible around the base of the tree in the lower left corner, behind the female figure. Vertical lines near the left margin suggest at least two additional trees in the background. Shadowy washes near the right margin may suggest clouds in the background sky or additional vegetation.  The two figures might be Robin Hood (right) and Clorinda (left), as in Blake's engraving of 1783 after J. Meheux, <hi rend="i">Robin Hood and Clorinda</hi>.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>veil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>collar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bag</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Clorinda</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure standing at left has long, curly hair and wears a long veil that wraps around her right elbow. She wears either a gown or a shirt and skirt; her garment's collar is ruffled. A belt or perhaps the strap of a bag, which may be visible near her right hip, is encircles her waist. She faces right toward the male figure and her eyes may be closed. Both arms are at her sides and bent slightly upward with palms facing up and fingers spread. Her right leg is bent beneath her gown or skirt, which suggests she may walk to the right or stand in a contrapposto position.  She might be Clorinda, as in Blake's engraving of 1783 after J. Meheux, <hi rend="i">Robin Hood and Clorinda</hi>.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tunic</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking stick</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quiver</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arrow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Robin Hood</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The male figure at right stands facing left and looks toward the female figure. He has short hair and a beard, and he appears to wear a knee-length gown or tunic. His right arm is raised horizontally and he may touch or point to the shadowy figure or animal at left. His left arm is at his side and bent upwards to hold a walking stick. His right leg is bent suggesting a contrapposto stance. Several spiky lines above his left shoulder may suggest a quiver of arrows as well as a darker, rounded form representing one end of a bow.  He might be Robin Hood, as in Blake's engraving of 1783 after J. Meheux, <hi rend="i">Robin Hood and Clorinda</hi>.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mane</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The form in between the two figures may be a horse, as suggested by the oval shape of its head and lines that suggest a mane. However, the form is covered with shadowy, dark washes that obscure most details. One front leg is suggested at left of the male standing figure and one back leg may be visible behind and right of the male figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tree with a thick trunk that leans to the right and dense, leafy canopy stands over the figures in the foreground. Additional vegetation, perhaps bushes or tall grass, are visible around the base of the tree in the lower left corner, behind the female figure. Vertical lines near the left margin suggest at least two additional trees in the background.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadowy washes near the right margin may suggest clouds in the background sky or additional vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadowy washes near the right margin may suggest clouds in the background sky or additional vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>