<bad id="but94.1" type="penink" work="King Alfred and the Swineherd's Wife (?)" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="94" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="King Alfred and the Swineherd's Wife (?)">
                    <main>King Alfred and the Swineherd's Wife (?)</main>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                 
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 92KB to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>May 2014</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of seventeen pen and ink drawings by Blake. Ranging chronologically from his apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, this group offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium. Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<hi rend="i">The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</hi>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <hi rend="i">Figures from a Greek Vase</hi> and <hi rend="i">Charon</hi>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <hi rend="i">Four Composition Sketches</hi>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<hi rend="i">King Alfred</hi>, <hi rend="i">A Woman Enthroned</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Procession of Monks</hi>) and the Bible (<hi rend="i">Saul and David</hi>, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi>, and two versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <hi rend="i">Garden Path</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah</hi> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <hi rend="i">Lady Torrens</hi>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered. The Archive will publish his pencil sketches decade by decade, beginning with the earliest works, 1779 through 1790.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                This is the first time that works from the Society of Antiquaries, London have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly, we are also publishing the Society's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                           
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
         This image copyright © 2015 British Museum</userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>September-October 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>April 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Abby Brengle,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>February 2007</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Shaw, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>King Alfred and the Swineherd's Wife</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1780">c. 1780-85</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>14.6 x 18.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>14.6 x 18.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium> pen and ink over pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none recorded</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The drawing is inscribed in pencil, lower right, "J D F" (John Deffett Francis—see the Note on Provenance, below).  Bottom center are the same initials very lightly printed from a stamp.</note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history not known; acquired at a unknown time by John Deffett Francis; given by Francis to the British Museum in Dec. 1874.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1874,1212.136</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but94.1.penink.01" dbi="BUT94.1.1.PID">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">King Alfred and the Swineherd's Wife (?)</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(Butlin 94)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>14.6 x 18.9 cm</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The subject of this drawing is uncertain.  Butlin 94 suggests that the scene may be related in subject to Blake's other historical drawings, particularly one titled "Alfred in the countrymans house" in a list of English historical subjects Blake wrote in his Notebook (Erdman page 672).  Two standing figures face each other against an undefined background, possibly with slight indications of clouds at the top.  The male figure at right has short, curly hair and a beard; he wears a knee-length robe or gown and perhaps a cloak.  Facing left, he holds a staff in his bent left arm and points with his right arm, which he raises horizontally.  He frowns distinctly.  He looks at the female figure in front of him who faces right.  She has long, perhaps curly hair and wears a full-length gown.  Both arms are down but slightly bent with palms upturned.  There may be a tree to the left of the figures, though this form is indistinct.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pentimento</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Alfred</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two standing figures face each other against an undefined background.  The male figure at right has short, curly hair and a beard; he wears a knee-length gown or robe and perhaps a cloak.  Facing left, he holds a staff in his bent left arm and points with his right arm, which he raises horizontally.  A few pencil lines suggest a slightly higher position for his right arm and hand.  His right leg was first sketched in pencil further to the left.  He frowns distinctly.  He looks at the female figure across from him at left.  If the identification of the subject of the drawing is correct, this is King Alfred.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>swineherd</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two standing figures face each other against an undefined background.  The female figure at left has long, perhaps curly hair and wears a full-length gown; she may also wear a cloak, which pools on the ground behind her, though this form is less distinct.  Both arms are down but slightly bent with palms upturned and fingers spread.  She may be looking at the man to the right, with her left foot slightly in front of her right.  Her facial expression and gesture may indicate despair.  If the identification of the subject of the drawing is correct, this is the swineherd's wife.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The male figure at right holds a staff in his left hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaves</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may a tree to the left of the figures with some leaves and branches, though this form is indistinct.  Only a few of its pencil lines have been reinforced with pen and ink.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be slight pencil indications of clouds at the top of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>