<bad id="but9.1" type="wc" work="" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="antiquaries" catalog="butlin"
    catid="9">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title
                    reg="Henry III, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above the Monument of King Sebert">
                    <main> Henry III, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above the Monument of
                        King Sebert</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB
                to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>

            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/> This image copyright © 2020 Society of Antiquaries, London.<lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                        Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                        Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *Henry III, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above the Monument of
                        King Sebert* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1775.D">c. 1775</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>31.5 x 12.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>39.8 x 26.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The work is numbered "III." in pencil top right.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Society of Antiquaries, London</name>
                <date>c. 1775</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>acquired on commission</price>
                <note>The Society of Antiquaries commissioned Blake's engraving master, James Basire, to execute this drawing.  Basire assigned Blake to this task.  The drawing was presumably delivered to the Society shortly after its engraving for Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, first published by the Society of Antiquaries in 1780.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Society of Antiquaries, London</institution>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">Red Portfolio, "Westminster Abbey," p. 30</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but9.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT9.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Henry III, from the Wall-Painting in the Sedilia above the
                    Monument of King Sebert</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(BUT9)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The collection stamp of the Society of Antiquaries appears bottom center left below the design.  A larger, circular collection stamp of the Society appears lower right.  A water color replica (Butlin 17) of this water color is in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.  An engraving of this design was published in Joseph Ayloffe, *An Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey*, Plate 5 (1780), and in *Vetusta Monumenta*, volume 2 of c. 1789, Plate 33.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>39.8 x 26.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design, part of the wall painting in the sedilia above King
                        Sebert's monument at Westminster Abbey, is a panel with a patterned
                        background and a narrow border, which contains beveling, two columns, and a
                        plain arch. Inside the arch are four points of a decorative tracery, each
                        containing a gilded trefoil design and terminating in a leaf. The two points
                        nearest the arch's top are smaller and more compressed. In the center of the
                        arching panel is a crowned man who represents King Henry III. The wears a
                        long-sleeved gown, a decorative belt or cord, a floor-length robe, and a
                        leaved crown. He has short, curly hair and slight evidence of stubble or
                        short facial hair. He faces forward, but his head turns to the left with his
                        eyes looking in that direction. He wears ornate gloves and rings on both
                        hands. His left arm is bent at the elbow and raised to the left, where he
                        points with his left hand. His right arm is bent and at his side; his right
                        hand holds a scepter over his right shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gold</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sebert</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design represents the wall-painting of King Henry III in
                            the sedilia above King Sebert's monument in Westminster Abbey. The gray
                            background of the design may suggest stone and the tracery around the
                            top of the arch may be gilded.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tracery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The design represents the wall-painting of King Henry III in
                            the sedilia above King Sebert's monument in Westminster Abbey. It
                            depicts a tall, narrow painted panel that includes a narrow border, the
                            lower portion of which suggests a beveled design. Forming the sides of
                            this border are the inside halves of two columns or pillars; the left
                            column bears a cross-hatched design, and the right appears to be
                            segmented. The arching upper portions of this border are plain, but
                            inside the arch are four points of a decorative tracery, each containing
                            a gilded trefoil design and terminating in a leaf.The two points nearest
                            the arch's top are smaller and more compressed.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Each of the four points of the decorative tracery near the top
                            of the design appears to end in a decorative leaf.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="E">
                        <characteristic>lion</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A pattern of small golden lions that all face to the left is
                            visible against the grey, stone(?) background of the painted
                            panel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Henry the Third</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>glove</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ring</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the center of the painted panel is the figure of Henry III.
                            He wears a long-sleeved, floor-length gown secured at the waist with a
                            decorative belt or cord. A hooded robe with an ornate border covers his
                            shoulders but remains open in front. King Henry wears a leaved crown
                            atop short, curly hair. His chin bears slight evidence of stubble or
                            short facial hair. The wrinkles on his forehead suggest a furrowed brow.
                            He faces forward, but his head turns to the left with his eyes looking
                            in that direction. His left arm is at his side and bent upward and left.
                            He points toward the left with his raised left hand. His fingers are
                            spread, showing a ring on his fifth finger. On both hands, he wears
                            gloves bearing large diamond-shaped emblems and decorative borders. His
                            right arm is bent slightly at his side, and his right gloved hand (also
                            showing a ring on the fifth finger) holds a scepter that extends over
                            (and may rest on) his right shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>King Henry III holds a scepter in his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>King Henry's crown and the upper end of his scepter are decorated with golden leaves.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.01" justify="left" indent="44">III.<note>This pencil inscription was probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                
                <vspace extent="6"/>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.02" justify="left" indent="42">foot  I<note>This inscription and line 3, both in pen and ink, record the height of the design.  They are written vertically along the right side of the design.  These inscription were probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.03" justify="left" indent="42">7:  2.<note>See the note to line 2.</note></p>
                <vspace extent="6"/>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.04" justify="left" indent="27">Basire. del.<note>This pen and ink inscription, a reference to or signature of Blake's engraving master James Basire, was probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.05" justify="left" indent="18">foot  I<note>This inscription and line 6, both in pen and ink, record the width of the design.  These inscriptions were probably not written by Blake.</note></p>
                <vspace extent="2"/>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.06" justify="left" indent="18">2:  8<note>See the note to line 5.</note></p>
                <vspace extent="2"/>
                <p n="but9.1.1.wc.07" justify="left">Figure supposed to be that of Henry III. as painted on the N. front of the Monument of King Sebert in Westm<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Abbey. Vetust. Mon. Vol<note>This pen and ink inscription is probably not by Blake.  "Vetust. Mon. Vol" (with any further inscription trimmed off by the right edge of the leaf) is a reference to volume 2 of *Vetusta Monumenta*, published by the Society of Antiquaries c. 1789.  An engraving of this design, signed by Blake's engraving master James Basire, was published as plate 33 in that volume.</note></p>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
