<bad id="but96.1" type="wc" work="The Awards of Athene" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="96">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Awards of Athene">
                    <main>
                        The Awards of Athene</main> : electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 33KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2020</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of
twenty-seven water color drawings produced by Blake between 1775 and c. 1790.
Blake’s activities as a water colorist from the mid-1770s through the next decade reveal
his increasing skills in that medium, ranging from apprentice work to original
compositions exhibited at the Royal Academy. Assignments from his engraving
instructor, James Basire, included the precise copying of tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey (Objects 1-5). These water colors were later engraved, probably with
Blake’s assistance, as illustrations for Joseph Ayloffe’s Account of Some Ancient
Monuments in Westminster Abbey (1780), republished in volume 2 of the Society of
Antiquaries’ Vetusta Monumenta (c. 1789). This early contact with Gothic art
profoundly affected Blake’s later work as an artist and his writings on the history of art.
Shortly after his release from apprenticeship in 1779, Blake began to develop a series of
designs picturing major events in the history of England (Objects 7-12). He exhibited
one of these, The Death of Earl Goodwin (Object 9) or a more finished version of the
design, at the Royal Academy in 1780. This group of pictures may have culminated in
“The History of England, a small book of Engravings,” advertised in Blake’s prospectus
To the Public in October 1793. Unfortunately, no copy of that work has ever been
recorded. Blake developed at least one work in this series, Pestilence, Probably the
Great Plague of London (Object 12), into a slightly larger and more finished water color
(Object 14). Lear and Cordelia was probably executed as part of the history of England
series but is presented in the Archive under Water Color Drawings, Illustrations to
Shakespeare.
Blake’s early water colors include several designs with biblical subjects (Objects 6, 13,
15, 18, 20-23, 27). The most highly finished and important of these are three illustrations
to the story of Joseph and his brethren recounted in Genesis (Objects 20, 22, 23). These
were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785. One year earlier, Blake’s A Breach in a
City, the Morning after the Battle (object 19), had appeared at the same venue. Blake
was trying, by the mid-1780s, to establish his reputation as a “history” painter—that is, as
a specialist in themes taken from history, the Bible, and canonical literary texts such as
Milton’s Paradise Lost. In the eighteenth century, such subjects were believed to be
appropriate for the greatest artistic ambitions, but all of Blake’s exhibited works were in
water colors rather than the more highly regarded medium of oil painting.
Almost all of Blake’s water colors fit comfortably within the long tradition of water color
drawing, in which one delineates form by line and the tinting is confined within firm
outlines. Water color painting, a style developed by artists such as J. M. W. Turner,
allowed for a freer use of washes, unconfined by pen and ink or pencil boundaries and
without underlying washes laid in for modeling.

As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and
charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North
Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and
museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their
collections in the Archive.</updatestmt><notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2020</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2020 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Awards of Athene*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1780.E">c. 1780-85</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>18.8 x 28.4 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>19.0 x 29.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink and water color<note>The inscriptions by Frederick Tatham, lower right, are in pen and ink.</note></medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1991</date>
                <dealer>Christopher Powney</dealer>
                <price>$8073</price>
                <note>Inherited by Blake's wife Catherine at his death in 1827; acquired by Frederick Tatham, probably at Catherine Blake's death in 1831; the dealer Bernard Quaritch, offered in his Nov. 1882 catalogue, item 346 with 39 other works by Blake (&#163;36), catalogue 350 of 10 Aug. 1883, item 13843, same group and price, *Catalogue of Works on the Fine Arts* of Oct. 1883, item 13843, same group and price, and catalogue of *William Blake's Original Drawings* of May 1885, no item number, same group and price; sold by Quaritch on 30 June 1886 to W. Graham Robertson; sold from Robertson's collection, Christie's, 22 July 1949, in lot 71a with Blake's *Girl Holding a Goblet* (&#163;15.15s. to Maggs Bros.); offered in Maggs' Sept. 1949 catalogue 117, item 492 (&#163;31.10s.); Bradbury P. J. Clarke; sold Mrs. M. Bradbury Clarke, sold from her collection, Sotheby's, 11 Nov. 1982, lot 80 (&#163;1320 to "Astel," probably a dealer); a private collection; offered Sotheby's, 11 April 1991, lot 21 (not sold); acquired Dec. 1991 by Robert N. Essick for $8073 from the estate of the April 1991 vendor through Sotheby's, Christopher Powney acting as agent for Essick.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="but96.1.wc.01" dbi="BUT96.1.1.WC">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Awards of Athene</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="U1">(Butlin 96)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The background shape and its blue coloring suggest that this drawing may be a design for a sculptural group to be placed in a lunette window or some such architectural feature.  The inscriptions lower right are by Frederick Tatham.</p></objnote>
                
                <objsize>18.8 x 28.4 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Standing in the center of the design, the goddess Athena presents awards in the form of laurel wreaths to the six figures seated around her. Athena faces forward and turns her head to look left. She wears a plumed helmet and a long gown or toga with additional drapery over her left shoulder. Her long hair is visible beneath her helmet. Her right arm is bent and raised upward near her right shoulder; her left arm is raised horizontally (though with a slight bend remaining in the elbow) and extended to the left. She holds a laurel wreath or crown in each hand. Two figures are visible on the right side of the design. The larger figure at left sits on a bench or ledge and faces left. This figure appears to be female and has long hair arranged in a bun and wears a gown. Her head is down and she looks toward what appears to be an architectural drawing that rests in her lap.  She is very probably a personification of Architecture. Her left arm is raised at 45 degrees and she holds this drawing with her left hand. Her right arm is bent and rests on an object on the seat behind her that resembles the capital of a Corinthian column. The body of the second figure at right is nearly obscured by the first seated figure, but this figure may stand facing right and down. She(?) rests her raised and bent right arm on the first figure's right shoulder. She holds a triangular object in her raised left hand, possibly a metronome.  She may be a personification of Music. Her eyes may be closed or at least lowered. A vertical pillar or column is visible behind this pair of figures. Left of Athena, three female figures sit on an indistinct bench or ledge and one additional figure appears to stand behind them. The leftmost figure sits in the foreground facing right with head turned down. She wears a gown and has her long hair arranged in a bun or, alternatively, may wear a hat or scarf over her hair. She bends her left arm upward and touches her chin with her left hand in a pensive posture. Her right arm is bent and at her side. She holds a mallet in her right hand. Between her right arm and side, a sculpted bust leans against her hip.  She is probably an allegorical figure of Sculpture. The sculpture faces forward and up and has short hair and an open mouth. Below this figure, part of a drawing depicting a nude male figure from behind is visible. The figure in the drawing appears to look right and raise his right arm horizontally. The second seated figure from the left also wears a long gown and a crown of laurels. She faces right but turns to look forward and up. Her left arm is bent and raised upward, and she touches her left cheek with her extended left index finger, in a pensive posture similar to the figure beside her at left. Her right arm is bent, raised, and rested on a square object in her lap or on her right leg, which is crossed over her left. This object may be a book, as a central vertical line suggests a spine. This figure may be a personification of Poetry or Drama (or Literature in general). The third seated figure from the left faces away and the majority of her body is blocked by the previous two figures. She wears her hair in a bun and raises her right bent arm toward the easel in front of her. She is probably a personification of Painting. The object in her right hand may be a brush suggesting she is painting. Athena holds the crown in her right hand directly over this figure's head, suggesting she may be about to crown her. The fourth and only standing figure at left faces forward and looks down, perhaps toward the seated figures in front of her. She has long hair or wears a hood. Her right arm is extended and rests on the left shoulder of the leftmost seated figure in what may be an embrace. She may be nude and her right breast is suggested in the space between the heads of the leftmost seated figures. The blue coloring of the background may suggest sky, possibly seen through a window or other such opening in a building.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Athena</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Standing in the center of the design, the goddess Athena presents awards in the form of laurel wreaths to the six figures seated around her. Athena faces forward and turns her head to look left. She wears a plumed helmet and a long gown or toga with additional drapery over her left shoulder. Her long hair is visible beneath her helmet. Her right arm is bent and raised upward near her right shoulder; her left arm is raised horizontally (though with a slight bend remaining in the elbow) and extended to the left. She holds a laurel wreath or crown in each hand. The crown in her right hand is directly above the head of the seated figure who is painting at left, suggesting she may be about to crown her. Her right leg appears to be bent beneath her gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wreath</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The central figure Athena holds a crown of laurels in each of her hands and appears to be in the process of crowning the seated figures around her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Architecture</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures are visible on the right side of the design. The larger figure at left sits on an indistinct bench or ledge and faces left, bending forward slightly. This figure appears to be female and has her hair arranged in a bun and wears a gown. Her head is down and she looks toward what appears to be an architectural drawing that rests in her lap. She is probably a personification of Architecture. Her left arm is raised at 45 degrees and she holds this drawing with her left hand. Her right arm is bent and rests on an object on the seat behind her that resembles the capital of a Corinthian column. Both legs are bent beneath her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>drawing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost seated figure holds a drawing that may be of a building in her left hand and rests her right arm on an object that resembles the capital of a Corinthian column.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Music</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>metronome</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures are visible on the right side of the design. The body of the second figure at right is nearly obscured by the first seated figure, but this figure may stand facing right and down. She(?) rests her raised and bent right arm on the first figure's right shoulder. She holds a triangular object, possibly a metronome, in her raised left hand. She may be a personification of Music. Her eyes may be closed. The small size of this figure when compared to the others in the design may suggest she is a child.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vertical pillar or column is visible behind the pair of figures on the right side of the design. </illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Sculpture</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Left of Athena, three female figures sit on an indistinct bench or ledge and one additional figure appears to stand behind them. The leftmost figure sits in the foreground facing right with head turned down. She wears a gown and has her long hair arranged in a bun or, alternatively, may wear a hat or scarf over her hair. She bends her left arm upward and touches her chin with her left hand in a pensive posture. The standing figure behind her touches her right shoulder with her left hand. The seated figure's right arm is bent and at her side. She holds a mallet or hammer in her right hand. Between her right arm and side, a sculpted bust leans against her hip.  This figure is probably a personification of Sculpture. The sculpture faces forward and up and has short hair and an open mouth. Below this figure, part of a drawing depicting a nude male figure from behind is visible. The figure in the drawing appears to look right and raise his right arm horizontally.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>hammer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bust</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drawing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost seated figure holds a hammer or mallet in her right hand. Beneath her right arm, a bust is visible leaning against her right hip. A drawing of a nude male figure is visible below this figure and appears to be on a rectangular piece of paper.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bust beneath the leftmost seated figure's right arm faces up and forward. It has short hair and its mouth is open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the drawing is a nude male who faces away and may turn his head to the right. He has short hair and raises his bent right arm horizontally.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Poetry</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Drama</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Literature</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Left of Athena, three female figures sit on an indistinct bench or ledge and one additional figure appears to stand behind them. The second seated figure from the left also wears a long gown and a crown of laurels. She faces right but turns to look forward and up. Her left arm is bent and raised upward, and she touches her left cheek with her extended left index finger, in a pensive posture similar to the figure beside her at left. Her right arm is bent, raised, and rested on a square object in her lap or on her right leg, which is crossed over her left. This object may be a book, as a central vertical line suggests a spine. She is probably a personification of Poetry or Drama (or Literature in general).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Painting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brush</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Left of Athena, three female figures sit on an indistinct bench or ledge and one additional figure appears to stand behind them. The third seated figure from the left faces away and slightly right and the majority of her body is blocked by the previous two figures. She wears her hair in a bun and raises her right bent arm toward the easel in front of her. She is probably an allegorical representation of Painting. The object in her right hand may be a brush suggesting she is painting. Her bent right knee may be visible to the right of the second seated figure's legs. Athena holds the crown in her right hand directly over this figure's head, suggesting she may be about to crown her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>easel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>brush</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>canvas</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third seated figure from the left holds a slender object in her hand that may be a paintbrush. She looks toward an easel, which stands in the background of the design and is turned slightly to the left. The easel holds a blank leaf of paper or canvas.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Phrygian cap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Left of Athena, three female figures sit on an indistinct bench or ledge and one additional figure appears to stand behind them. The only standing figure at left faces forward and looks down, perhaps toward the seated figures in front of her. She wears a hood or hat similar to a Phrygian cap. Her right arm is extended and rests on the left shoulder of the leftmost seated figure in what may be an embrace. She may be nude and her right breast is suggested in the space between the heads of the leftmost seated figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The blue coloring of the background may suggest sky, possibly seen through a window or some such opening in a building.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="40"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="but96.1.wc.01.01" justify="left" indent="50">William Blake<note>These pen and ink inscriptions, lines 1-4, are by Frederick Tatham.</note></l>
                    <l n="but96.1.wc.01.02" justify="left" indent="33">from Sculpture.</l>
                    <l n="but96.1.wc.01.03" justify="left" indent="52">vouched by Frederick</l>
                    <l n="but96.1.wc.01.04" justify="left" indent="64">Tatham</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
