<bad id="BUTWBA8.1" type="penc" work="" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="butlin" catid="WBA8">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Pestilence">
                    <main>Pestilence</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>      
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2018 Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>July 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
            <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
            <date>October 2005</date>
            <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                  <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                  Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                  Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza
                  Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van
                  Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson,
                  </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C.
                  Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Pestilence*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1784.A">c. 1784</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>22.5 x 28.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>24.2 x 29.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>fleur-de-lis</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name>
                <date>unknown time prior to 1982</date>
                <dealer>not recorded</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>    
            
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, in lot 200 with 14 other works or lot 201 with 17 other works (2s. and 3s. respectively, both to the dealer Francis Harvey); offered by Harvey in a catalogue of c. 1865, titled "Plague," with 15 other "sketches in ink and pencil" (&#163;3.3s.); Frederick Locker-Lampson by 1886; E. Dwight Church, who acquired numerous works from Locker-Lampson through Dodd, Mead, &#38; Co. c. 1905; sold from the Church estate, Anderson Galleries, New York, 29 March 1916, lot 983, laid into a copy of Blake's *Illustrations of Dante* and described as "The Plague, done by Blake in pencil" ($110); removed from the Dante portfolio and acquired by the Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, apparently as part of a large group of miscellaneous drawings (the others not by Blake), at an unrecorded time prior to 1982.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution>
                <department>Art Division</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">82.36</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="butwba8.1.penc.01" dbi="BUTWBA8.1.1.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Pestilence</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="B1">(BUTWBA 8)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The drawing is inscribed lower left in ink, "cker."(?), not by Blake.  The inscription was probably added by a dealer or collector.  This pencil sketch is a preliminary drawing for *Pestilence*, a water color of c. 1784 in the Bateson Collection (Butlin 190) which in turn is a preliminary for the water color of *Pestilence* in the City Art Gallery, Bristol, England (Butlin 192).  Butlin dates the water colors to c. 1790-95 and c. 1795-1800. For the earlier dates of these works given here, see Joseph Viscomi, "*A Breach in a City the Morning After the Battle*: Lost or Found?," *Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly*, 28.2 (fall 1994): 44-61.  </p></objnote>
                <objsize>24.2 x 29.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The scene illustrates at least seven figures-six adults and one child-who appear to be grieving, sick, or dead, perhaps from the plague. The rightmost figure, who is male, stands or walks facing left but bends his torso forward in a contracted position with head down. He has short curly hair and wears a knee-length skirt. His eyes may be closed. Both arms are bent at 90 degrees and raised slightly. He appears to point to the ground in front of him with his extended left index finger and holds a cane or crutch in his right hand. Both knees are bent. An indistinguishable object rests on the ground in between this figure and the second figure from the right, a male who faces and walks right with right leg bent and extended backward. This figure bends his head forward and wears a similar knee-length skirt. His visible right arm is at his side and he carries the front end of a stretcher or litter on which a draped dead(?) body rests facing up with head at right. The majority of this body is obscured by the three figures in the front left corner of the design. A standing gowned female figure with long hair faces forward and bends to the left to look at and hold the body of a second female figure who faces right and up but leans or falls to the left. This second female figure's head is back, her eyes are closed, and her breasts are exposed. She wears a skirt or gown over the lower part of her body. Her knees are bent and her right arm is at her side and may support the infant or child who lies facing up in her lap. This child's head is back and its eyes are closed. Its left arm dangles downward over the female figure's right leg. Both the adult female and the child may be dead or dying. Above this trio, two figures stand facing right near the left margin of the design. The female figure bends forward and raises both bent arms to clutch her head with her left hand and pull her long hair with her right hand. She wears a long-sleeved garment and looks toward the male figure walking to her right. The male figure behind her at left has short curly hair and his head is down. His eyes may be closed or, alternatively, he may look down toward the three figures in the lower left corner. His torso is bare and his right arm is at his side. Faint background lines suggest an architectural structure divided into three sections. It may include a large rectangular door or opening at left, a central arch or arched opening, and a diagonal opening, perhaps a hall or door, at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crutch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plague</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost figure, who is male, stands or walks facing left but bends his torso forward in a contracted position with head down. He has short curly hair and wears a knee-length skirt. His eyes may be closed. Both arms are bent at 90 degrees and raised slightly. He appears to point to the ground in front of him with his extended left index finger and holds a cane or crutch in his right hand. Both knees are bent. He may be old or sick, perhaps from the plague. An indeterminate object rests on the ground in between this figure and the second figure from the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the right, who is male, faces and walks right with right leg bent and extended backward. This figure bends his head forward and down and wears a similar knee-length skirt. He may look down toward the contracted male figure in front of him at right. His visible right arm is at his side and he carries the front end of a stretcher or litter on which a draped dead(?) body rests facing up.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sheet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In addition to the seven visible figures in this design, another figure may lie prone on a stretcher or litter carried by the second figure from the right. This figure's body is draped, perhaps with a sheet, and its head is at right. The figure is likely dead. The majority of the body is obscured by the three figures in the front left corner of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner of the design, a standing gowned female figure with long hair faces forward and bends to the left to look at and hold the body of a second female figure who leans or falls to the left. The standing figure's left arm is extended downward with fingers spread against the body of the second woman. Her right leg is bent and extended forward and may support the weight of the other female figure. Her left leg is extended backward with toes pointed down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supporting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plague</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner, a standing female figure holds the body of a second female figure who faces right and up but leans or falls to the left. This second female figure's head is back, her eyes are closed, and her breasts are exposed. She wears a skirt or gown over the lower part of her body. Her knees are bent sharply and her bent right arm is at her side and may support the infant or child who lies facing up in her lap. Both the adult female and the child may be dead or dying, perhaps from the plague.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plague</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An infant or child with short hair lies with body prone facing up in the lap of the leftmost female figure in the lower left corner of the design. This child's head is back and its eyes are closed. Its left arm dangles downward over the female figure's right leg. Both the adult female and the child may be dead or dying, perhaps from the plague.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand facing right near the left margin of the design. The female figure bends forward to the right and raises both bent arms to clutch her head with her left hand and pull her long hair with her right hand. She wears a long-sleeved garment and looks toward the male figure walking to her right. Her position and expression suggests despair or grief.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand facing right near the left margin of the design. The male figure at left has short curly hair and his head is down. His eyes may be closed or, alternatively, he may look down toward the three figures in the lower left corner. His torso is bare and his right arm is at his side. Although his hands are not visible, he may carry the rear end of the stretcher or litter visible in the middle of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Faint background lines suggest an architectural structure divided into three sections. It may include a large rectangular door or opening at left, a central arch or arched opening, and a diagonal opening, perhaps a hall or door, at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
