<bad id="butwba3.1" type="penc" work="Alternative Designs for Commin's Elegy" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="essick" catalog="butlin" catid="wba3" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Alternative Designs for Commins's 'Elegy'">
                    <main>Alternative Designs for Commins's "Elegy"</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>,
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 92KB
                to 1100KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>October 2018</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a
                digital edition of forty-three pencil drawings produced by Blake during his first
                decade as an independent artist, 1779-1790. Drawing lies at the core of Blake's life
                as an artist. Pencil was his preferred medium for sketching—more flexible, less
                expensive, and more easily corrected than pen and ink or chalk. Preliminary work
                with the pencil preceded more finished work, either as separate sketches for prints
                and paintings or as drawings underlying water colors. Blake's nineteenth-century
                writings on the arts testify to his conviction that drawing was fundamental to all
                pictorial expression: "The distinction that is made in modern times between a
                Painting and a Drawing proceeds from ignorance of art. The merit of a Picture is the
                same as the merit of a Drawing" (*A Descriptive Catalogue*, Erdman page 549); "Let a
                Man who has made a Drawing go on &amp; on &amp; he will produce a Picture or Painting but if
                he chooses to leave off before he has spoild it he will Do a Better Thing[.]"
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 576); "Painting is Drawing on Canvas &amp; Engraving is
                Drawing on Copper &amp; Nothing Else…&amp; he who Draws best must be the best Artist…."
                (*Public Address*, Erdman page 582); "Dear Sir, excuse my enthusiasm or rather
                madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual vision whenever I take a pencil or
                graver into my hand…." (letter to William Hayley, 1804, Erdman page 757). <lb/>
                <lb/> Blake no doubt executed a great many more pencil drawings than those extant
                today. Sketches were not intended for exhibition or sale; most were probably
                discarded, while others may have been retained only because of more developed
                compositions on the other side of the leaves. Even the slightest and least
                aesthetically ambitious drawings offer insights into the origins and earliest
                realizations of Blake’s designs. These first thoughts on paper often tell us more
                about Blake’s habits of mind, when joined by eye and hand, than more finished works.
                Sketches are “the first fruits of [Blake’s] imagination,” as Geoffrey Keynes states
                in the introduction to his *Pencil Drawings of William Blake* (1927). <lb/>
                <lb/> The forty-three pencil drawings presented here, produced in Blake’s first
                decade as an independent artist, show his early debt to academic standards of
                precise copying and to the neoclassical emphasis on outline. The first four works
                may have been drawn while Blake was a student in the Royal Academy schools. Other
                sketches are preliminaries for some of Blake’s most important designs. Among these
                are the *Study for “Glad Day”, or “Albion Rose”* (Object 6), Blake’s iconic vision
                of the human form divine in energetic pose, and three sketches (Objects 34-36) for
                illustrations to *Tiriel*, the only group of finished drawings Blake composed for
                one of his own poems. Several sketches are early efforts at picturing events in the
                Bible, Blake’s main inspiration for designs throughout his life. This biblical
                cluster includes *The Resurrection of the Dead* (Object 10), *Samuel Presenting Saul
                to the People* (Object 15), and *Job’s Wife and Other Sketches* (Object 31). Other
                studies, such as *Ugolino in Prison* and its verso (Objects 21-22), reveal the
                beginnings of subjects also of lifelong interest for Blake. Only a few drawings for
                Blake’s illuminated books have survived, but studies such as *Sketches for “The Book
                of Thel”* and *A Standing and a Recumbent Figure* (Objects 37-39) offer fascinating
                glimpses into Blake’s methods of graphic production and revision. <lb/>
                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            This work copyright © 2018 William Blake Archive </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>October 2018</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Erin Francisco,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Emily Tronson,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Alex Zawacki</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>November 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Grant Glass,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Dasha Lynch,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Miles Simon,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
           <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquired and catalogued</change>
                <date>May 1999</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Jessica Kem, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue, </name>
                    <name>Greg Murray</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Alternative Designs for Commins's "Elegy"</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1786">c. 1786<note>The date is based on the relationship of this
                        group of drawings to Blake's engraving in Thomas Commins, *An Elegy Set to
                        Music*, dated 1786 in the imprint on Blake's engraving.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objsize>30.7 x 46.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>30.7 x 46.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>Fleur-de-lis and shield</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1995</date>
                <dealer>Christie's, Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons acting as agent</dealer>
                <price>$7223 inclusive of all fees</price>
                <note>Possibly the *Sketch for Thomas Commins's "An Elegy"* (the recto design) with
                    the dealer Robson and Co. in 1913 (see Butlin 98, then untraced); private
                    collection; sold Christie's, 17 Nov. 1992, lot 18 (&#163;7150 to
                    Salander-O'Reilly Galleries, New York); sold Christie's, 7 Nov. 1995, lot 73
                    (&#163;4025 to the dealer Thomas Agnew &#38; Sons acting for Robert N.
                    Essick).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena, California</addressline>

            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="butwba3.1.penc.01" dbi="BUTWBA3.1.1.PD">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Alternative Designs for Commins's "Elegy"</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="UI">(BUTWBA 3)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>These sketches, not discovered until 1993 and thus not in Butlin, are
                        alternative designs for Blake's engraving in Thomas Commins, *An Elegy Set
                        to Music*, dated 1786 in the imprint on Blake's engraving. These sketches
                        are on the verso of a monochrome wash drawing also for the Commins
                        engraving. Another pair of recto/verso drawings, both in monochrome wash,
                        for this engraving is in the Essick collection; these drawings are also
                        titled *Alternative Designs for Commins's Elegy* (not in Butlin because not
                        discovered until 1992).</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>30.7 x 46.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1100" width="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Several separate scenes are visible in this drawing. Lower left, a
                        short-haired figure seated in a boat bends both arms to hold oars. He(?)
                        faces left but turns his head to look right, perhaps toward the figures
                        standing on the land at right. The frontmost of these two standing figures
                        appears to face away from the viewer. He(?) wears a gown and possibly a
                        hood. The figure in back may face left; one arm, extended downward, and hand
                        are visible. An unidentifiable motif of some sort is sketched below these
                        figures. Against the right edge of the drawing, a third figure, who may be
                        bearded, appears to lean forward and to the left (perhaps over some sort of
                        horizontal barrier?) with both arms extended downward. A smaller version of
                        a similar figure appears below. An oval form in the upper left corner
                        contains a separate scene drawn upside down that depicts three figures. When
                        viewing the scene right side up, a single figure at left stands facing right
                        with both arms raised horizontally beside what appears to be a boat. There
                        may be a tree with leafy foliage behind this figure at left. He(?) may reach
                        and stride toward the pair of figures standing or walking across from him at
                        right facing left. The shorter figure, who may be a child, raises its right
                        arm at 135 degrees; the taller figure wears a gown and may be female. These
                        two figures appear to stand on an area of ground of a shore, but it is
                        unclear whether the single figure also stands on the ground or partially in
                        the water depicted in the foreground. This scene is likely related to
                        Blake's 1786 engraving for Commins's *An Elegy Set to Music* which has a
                        similar oval composition and figural arrangement. The other vignettes in the
                        drawing probably also relate to this project.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rowing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lower left, a short-haired figure seated in a boat bends both
                            arms to hold oars, which he(?) may row. This figure may have a beard.
                            Both legs are bent at the knees. He faces left but turns his head to
                            look right, perhaps toward the figure standing on the land at
                            right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>oar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the lower left corner of the drawing sits in a
                            long, narrow boat. The oars held by the figure, along with the vessel's
                            size, suggest it is a rowboat. There may be additional objects inside
                            the boat behind the figure, but the significance of these is
                            indeterminate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand in the center of the composition. The
                            frontmost figure wears a gown and perhaps a hood. He(?) appears to be
                            facing away from the viewer. An unidentifiable motif of some sort is
                            sketched below this figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand in the center of the composition. The figure
                            in back of the other appears to face to the left and extends one arm and
                            hand downward. His(?) fingers are slightly spread with palm held out,
                            perhaps in a gesture toward the figure seated in the boat at
                            left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The outline of a cloud appears to the left of the hand of one
                            of the two standing figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Against the right edge of the drawing, a third figure, who may
                            be bearded and thus male, appears to bend forward and to the left
                            (perhaps over some sort of horizontal barrier?). Both arms are extended
                            downward with his hands making fists. Most of his body faces to the
                            right, but his head and shoulders are turned forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A figure appears in the lower right portion of the leaf. He(?)
                            is a smaller version of the figure above. He bends over to the left and
                            extends his arms downward. His hands may be in a fist and he may hold
                            some object dangling below his hands.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaping</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An oval form in the upper left corner contains a separate
                            scene drawn upside down that depicts three figures. When viewing the
                            scene right side up, a single male(?) figure at left stands facing right
                            with both arms raised horizontally. He may bend forward or reach toward
                            the pair of figures across from him at right. The figure appears to wear
                            a garment, perhaps a shirt or gown, that extends outward from his body
                            at right, as if lifted by the wind. He may be striding rapidly to the
                            right or leaping over the water.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>boat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the oval scene upper left, the figure at left stands beside
                            what may be a small boat (perhaps a canoe or rowboat) that appears to
                            float on the body of water visible in the lower foreground of the scene.
                            The figures to the right may stand on the shore of the body of
                            water.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be a tree with leafy foliage behind the figure
                            standing at left in the oval scene top left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Across from the single standing figure at left, a pair of
                            figures who face left stand or walk near the right side of the oval
                            scene. The shorter figure, who may be a child, raises its right arm at
                            135 degrees. This figure may wear a hat and perhaps
                            pants.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Across from the single standing figure at left, a pair of
                            figures who face left stand or walk near the right side of the oval
                            scene. The taller figure has the slight suggestion of long hair,
                            indicating she may be female, and appears to wear a gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
