<bad id="esi.2-2d" type="spb" work="Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion" copy="2" copyid="2" institution="essick" catalog="essickcat" catid="I.2-2D">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion">
                    <main>
                        Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion</main>
                    <copy> Copy 2</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2019 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
<changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>February 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Michael Fox</name>
                                                  <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                                                  <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                                                  <name>Grant Glass</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Coordinator, University of
                                                  Rochester:</resp>
                                                  <name>Eric Loy</name>
                                                  <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                                                  <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                                                  <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                                                  <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                                                  <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                                                  <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                                                  <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                                                  <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                                                  <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                                                  <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                                                  <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                                                  <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                                                  <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                                                  <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                                                  <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                                                  <name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                                                  </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2004</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Conversion: </resp>
                    <name>Aziza Technology Associates</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>author,</role>
                    <role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                 <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                
                <compdate value="1773.A">1773</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1820.A">c. 1820-25</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>22.9 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                <platemark>25.6 x 14.0 cm.</platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>27.8 x 19.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>
                    <note>none</note>
                </watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>2<note>The design is surrounded by two framing lines, closely spaced.</note></framelines>
                <binding/>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1976</date>
                <dealer>Donald Heald</dealer>
                <price>&#163;1000</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; sold Sotheby's, Hodgson's rooms, 12 Nov. 1976, lot 384, inserted in a copy of Robert Blair, *The Grave*, [1870] edition with Blake's illustrations (&#163;1000 to Donald Heald acting for Robert N. Essick).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena</addressline>
                <addressline>California</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esi.2-2d.spb.01" dbi="ESI.2-2D.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESI">(Essick I)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>Although the figure is a close copy of an unidentified figure in Michelangelo's *Crucifixion of St. Peter* (Pauline Chapel, Vatican), the entire composition is usually credited to Blake as the designer.  The landscape setting is Blake's own invention.  This impression is in the second state of two; the title is taken from the inscription upper right added to this second state.  Blake's pen and ink inscription lower right on the only traced impression of the first state indicates that Blake based the figure on "a drawing by Salviati" (probably Francesco Rossi Salviati).  No such drawing has been traced.  Blake may have taken the figure from an engraving of Michelangelo's entire painting or the figure alone, without surrounding background, in an engraving by Nicholas Beatrizet.  This second state with its added inscriptions was probably executed by Blake c. 1820-25.  He probably printed this impression himself.</p></objnote>
                <objectsize>25.6 x 14.0 cm.</objectsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        A single male figure, identified as Joseph of Arimathea in the inscription top right, faces forward and stands on sandy and rocky ground. He has a long beard and turns his head to look down and to the left. He wears a short tunic or gown as well as a hood-like Phrygian cap with a pointed top that falls to the left. Both arms are bent at the elbow and crossed in front of his chest. With his right hand, the figure grasps his left arm just above the elbow; his left hand rests on his right forearm and he appears to touch his right upper arm with a partially extended index finger. He bends forward slightly. The figure's right leg is straight while his left is bent at the knee. Several small rocks are visible to the left of his right foot.  His left foot may rest on a rock behind him or he may be stepping or walking forward.  Shadows fall on the ground beneath him and at right. The rocky and sandy shore on which the figure stands extends behind him at right and appears to rise into a cliff. A body of water, no doubt the sea with waves, extends behind the figure and to the left. Sky is visible in the upper left corner where dark clouds appear above beams of sunlight, which may suggest sunrise or sunset.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>finger</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Joseph of Arimathea</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdes>A single male figure, identified as Joseph of Arimathea in the inscription top right, faces forward and stands on rocky and sandy ground in front of a body of water, no doubt the sea. He has a long beard and turns his head to look down and to the left. He wears a short tunic or gown as well as a hood-like Phrygian cap with a pointed top that falls to the left. Both arms are bent at the elbow and crossed in front of his chest. With his right hand, the figure grasps his left arm just above the elbow; his left hand rests on his right forearm and he appears to touch his right upper arm with a partially extended index finger. He bends forward slightly. The figure's right leg is straight while his left is bent at the knee.  His left foot may rest on a rock behind him or he may be stepping or walking forward.</illusobjdes>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>rock</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdes>Several small rocks are visible to the left of the figure's right foot, and he appears to rest his left foot on a raised, flat rock.  Shadows fall on the ground beneath him and at right.</illusobjdes>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>rock</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdes>The rocky and sandy shore on which the figure stands extends behind him at right and appears to rise into a cliff. The body of water, no doubt the sea with waves, extends behind the figure and to the left.</illusobjdes>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdes>The sky is visible in the upper left corner where dark clouds appear above beams of sunlight, which may suggest sunrise or sunset.  The beams of light are not present in the first state of the plate but were added in this second state.</illusobjdes>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
           <phystext>         
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.01" indent="40">JOSEPH<note>This inscription, lines 1-3, is inscribed in the copperplate on a diagonal in the top right corner of the design.</note></l>
                    <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.02" indent="35">of Arimathea</l>
                    <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.03" indent="30">among The Rocks of Albion</l>
                </lg>
           <vspace  extent="30"/>
                 <lg justify="left">
                     <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.04" indent="15">Engraved by W Blake 1773 from an old Italian Drawing</l> 
                     <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.05" indent="1">This is One of the Gothic Artists who Built the Cathedrals in what we call the Dark Ages</l>
                     <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.06">Wandering about in sheep skins &#38; goat skins of whom the World was not worthy</l>
                     <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.07" indent="20">Michael Angelo Pinxit<space extent="10"/>such were the Christians</l>
                     <l n="esi.2-2d.spb.01.08" indent="40">in all Ages</l>
                 </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
