<bad id="esiii.1" type="spb" work="The Approach of Doom" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="essick" catid="esiii.1">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Approach of Doom">
                    <main>
                        The Approach of Doom</main>
                    <copy>Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2017</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2017 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Approach of Doom*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Robert Blake<role>inventor</role></origination>
                <compdate value="1787.A">c. 1787-88</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1787.A">c. 1787-88</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>29.7 x 20.9 cm.</objsize>
                <platemark>29.7 x 20.9 cm.</platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>33.8 x 24.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>relief and white-line etching</medium>
                <printingstyle>relief</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1894</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>&#163;150 with thirteen other works by Blake</price>
                <note>Probably acquired by Anne (Mrs. Alexander) Gilchrist at an unknown time; probably by inheritance in 1885 to her son, Herbert H. Gilchrist; sold by H. H. Gilchrist with thirteen other works by Blake and his brother Robert, including Robert Blake's drawing of the "Approach of Doom," to the British Museum for &#163;150 in June 1894.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1894,6.12.17</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esiii.1.spb.01" dbi="ESIII.1.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Approach of Doom</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">)Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESIII">(Essick III)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This is the only known impression of "The Approach of Doom."  Although based loosely on a wash drawing of the same title in the British Museum (Butlin R2) by Blake's brother, Robert, this relief and white-line etching is generally considered to be an original work by William Blake.  The print is dated to c. 1792 in Essick page 12.  For the earlier dating of c. 1787-88 given here, see Joseph Viscomi, *Blake and the Idea of the Book* (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1993) pages 188-92.  This may be one of Blake's earliest experiments in relief and white-line etching as a means for reproducing drawings.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>29.7 x 20.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a rocky landmass, possibly a cliff or shoreline, in the lower right corner of the composition. The leftmost figure appears to be male as he has short curly hair and some sort of facial hair, perhaps a mustache or beard. He stands with his body twisted to the right to embrace the waist of the female figure at right. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and rests on his companion's lower back; his left hand is visible just below his right, suggesting his left arm is wrapped around her body from the left. He appears to touch the female figure's thigh with his extended left pinky figure.  Like the other figures, he turns his head to look to the left.  The female figure that the leftmost figure embraces stands second from the left and faces left. She has long hair, and her wide eyes and possibly open mouth suggest fear. Her left arm is at her side but bent upward sharply with left hand raised, palm facing out.  Just above the female figure's head, slightly to the right, another head of curly hair is visible, suggesting there may be another figure standing immediately behind her.  The third figure from the left is an old male with long hair and a long beard who stands facing forward but turns to look left.  Both arms are bent just beyond 90 degrees and crossed in front of his chest where he makes fists with both hands. The figure leans or bends forward slightly.  He is embraced from behind by another male(?) figure with short curly hair who stands facing forward and left.  This figure bends his left arm at a right angle and wraps it around the waist of the older male figure. One of his legs may be extended behind him at right.  To the right of this figure, the fifth clear figure in the group stands far right.  This female(?) figure has short curly hair and faces forward with wide eyes and an open mouth.  The figure may hold a child or infant in front of her chest, like the clearly female figure in Robert Blake's drawing on which this print is based. A circular form to the right of this figure's head may suggest another figure standing behind her at right. Shadowy or cloudy darkness broken only by a lighter diagonal line or bolt of lightning (as in the drawing) fills the upper left corner of the composition.  There may be a body of water, probably the sea, lower left.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>finger</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a rocky landmass, possibly a cliff or shoreline, in the lower right corner of the composition. The leftmost figure appears to be male as he has short curly hair and some sort of facial hair, perhaps a mustache or beard. He stands with his body twisted to the right to embrace the waist of the female figure at right. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and rests on his companion's lower back; his left hand is visible just below his right, suggesting his left arm is wrapped around her body from the left. He appears to touch the female figure's thigh with his extended left pinky figure.  He turns his head to look to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Just above the head of the female figure second from the left, another head of curly hair is visible, suggesting there may be another figure standing immediately behind her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a rocky landmass in the lower right corner of the composition. The female figure that the leftmost figure embraces stands second from the left and faces left. She has long hair, and her wide eyes and possibly open mouth suggest fear. Her left arm is at her side but bent upward sharply with left hand raised, palm facing out</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eye socket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>blind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a rocky landmass in the lower right corner of the composition.  The third figure from the left is an old male figure with long hair and a long beard who stands facing forward but turns to look left. Unlike the other figures, the pupil of his depicted left eye is not visible, suggesting it may be an empty socket.  He may be blind.  Both arms are bent just beyond 90 degrees and crossed in front of his chest where he makes fists with both hands. The figure leans or bends forward slightly.  He is embraced from behind by another male(?) figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a rocky landmass in the lower right corner of the composition.  The fourth figure from the left is a male(?) figure with short curly hair who stands facing forward and left and embraces the old male figure in front of him.  This figure bends his left arm, which is by his side, at a right angle and wraps it around the waist of the older male figure. One of his legs may be extended behind him at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a rocky landmass in the lower right corner of the composition.  The rightmost distinguishable figure, and the fifth in the group, stands facing forward and slightly left.  This female(?) figure has short curly hair, wide eyes, and an open mouth.  The figure may carry a child or infant in front of his chest, as in Robert Blake's drawing on which the print is loosely based. A circular form to the right of this figure's head may suggest another figure standing behind her at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five figures stand on what appears to be a rocky landmass, perhaps a cliff or shoreline, in the lower right corner of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lightning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadowy or cloudy darkness broken only by a lighter diagonal line or bolt of lightning (as in Robert Blake's drawing) fill the upper left portion of the composition.  There may be a body of water, probably the sea with waves, lower left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
