<!DOCTYPE bad PUBLIC "-//University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill::Carolina Digital Library and Archives//DTD bad.dtd (Blake Archive Description) 2005//EN//XML" "http://www.blakearchive.org/blake/bad.dtd">
<bad id="esiii.1.1" type="speng" work="The Approach of Doom" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="essick" catid="esiii.1.1">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Approach of Doom">
                    <main>
                        The Approach of Doom</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2016</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2016 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        The Approach of Doom
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Jean-Antoine Watteau<role>, inventor</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Unknown<role>, printer</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thomas Macklin</publisher>
                    <pubplace>London<note>London is not specificed in the imprint, but the street address indicates as much.</note></pubplace>
                    <date>1782</date>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1782.A">1782</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1782.B">1782</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>25.1 x 30.0 cm. (oval image including frame line), 29.4 x 30.0 cm. (including inscriptions)</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>32.6 x 35.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>stipple etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>A single frame line in stipple surrounds the oval image.</note></framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1982</date>
                <dealer>Donald Heald acting for Essick at a Christie's auction</dealer>
                <price>&#163;918</price>
                <note> Possibly the impression sold from the collection of W. E. Moss, Sotheby's, 2 March 1937, in lot 139, with "Morning Amusement" (possibly Essick impression 2F) and impressions of both prints in colors (&#163;8 to the dealer Dulau and Co.); possibly the impressions offered by Dulau, April 1937 catalogue, item 20 (&#163;14), and 1940 catalogue 281, item 9 (&#163;10.10s.), both times with the other prints in lot 139 in the Christie's auction; acquired by the dealer Charles Sessler from the dealer Stevens and Brown, with "Morning Amusement" (Essick impression 2F) for $13.33 in June 1949; sold by Sessler to Charles J. Rosenbloom, Oct. 1949, for $750 the pair; inherited by Rosenbloom's wife, Lucile Johnson Rosenbloom, in 1973; sold Christie's, 2 Nov. 1982, lot 35, with "Morning Amusement," Essick impression 2F (&#163;918 to Donald Heald acting for Robert N. Essick).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena</addressline>
                <addressline>California</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esiii.1.1.speng.01" dbi="ESIII.1.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Approach of Doom</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="B1">(ESIII.1.1)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>29.4 x 30.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a grassy landmass in the lower right corner of the composition. The leftmost figure appears to be male as he has short curly hair and some sort of facial hair, perhaps a mustache or beard. He stands facing right to embrace the waist of the female figure at right. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and rests on his companion's lower back; his left hand is visible just below his right, suggesting his left arm is wrapped around her body from the left. He appears to touch the female figure's exposed thigh with his extended left pinky figure.  Like the other figures, he turns his head to look to the left.  The female figure that the leftmost figure embraces stands second from the left and faces left. She has long hair, and her wide eyes and potentially open mouth suggest fear. She wears a gown with a high slit, exposing most of her left leg. Her left arm is at her side but bent upward sharply with left hand raised, palm facing out.  Just above the female figure's head, slightly to the right, another head of curly hair is visible, suggesting there may be another figure standing immediately behind her.  The third figure from the left is an old male figure with long hair and a long beard who stands facing forward but turns to look left.  Both arms are bent just beyond 90 degrees and crossed in front of his chest where he makes fists with both hands. The figure leans or bends forward slightly.  He is embraced from behind by another male(?) figure with short curly hair who stands facing forward and left.  This figure bends his left arm at a right angle and wraps it around the waist of the older male figure. One of his legs may be extended behind him at right.  To the right of this figure, the fifth clear figure in the group stands far right.  This male(?) figure has short curly hair and faces forward with wide eyes and an open mouth.  The figure may carry an indistinguishable object in front of his chest. A circular form to the right of this figure's head may suggest another figure standing behind him at right. Shadowy or cloudy darkness broken only by a lighter diagonal line or bolt in the upper left corner encompasses the remainder of the composition.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>finger</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a grassy landmass in the lower right corner of the composition. The leftmost figure appears to be male as he has short curly hair and some sort of facial hair, perhaps a mustache or beard. He stands facing right to embrace the waist of the female figure at right. His right arm is raised at 45 degrees and rests on his companion's lower back; his left hand is visible just below his right, suggesting his left arm is wrapped around her body from the left. He appears to touch the female figure's exposed thigh with his extended left pinky figure.  He turns his head to look to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Just above the head of the female figure second from the left, another head of curly hair is visible, suggesting there may be another figure standing immediately behind her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a grassy landmass in the lower right corner of the composition. The female figure that the leftmost figure embraces stands second from the left and faces left. She has long hair, and her wide eyes and potentially open mouth suggest fear. She wears a gown with a high slit, exposing most of her left leg. Her left arm is at her side but bent upward sharply with left hand raised, palm facing out</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eye socket</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a grassy landmass in the lower right corner of the composition.  The third figure from the left is an old male figure with long hair and a long beard who stands facing forward but turns to look left. Unlike the other figures, the pupil of his depicted left eye is not visible, suggesting it may be a socket.  Both arms are bent just beyond 90 degrees and crossed in front of his chest where he makes fists with both hands. The figure leans or bends forward slightly.  He is embraced from behind by another male(?) figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a grassy landmass in the lower right corner of the composition.  The fourth figure from the left is a male(?) figure with short curly hair who stands facing forward and left and embraces the old male figure in front of him.  This figure bends his left arm, which is by his side, at a right angle and wraps it around the waist of the older male figure. One of his legs may be extended behind him at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five gowned figures stand near the edge of a grassy landmass in the lower right corner of the composition.  The rightmost distinguishable figure, and the fifth in the group, stands facing forward and slightly left.  This male(?) figure has short curly hair, wide eyes, and an open mouth.  The figure may carry an indistinguishable object in front of his chest. A circular form to the right of this figure's head may suggest another figure standing behind him at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five figures stand on what appears to be a grassy landmass or section of earth in the lower right corner of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least five figures stand on what appears to be a landmass or section of earth covered with grass in the lower right corner of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadowy or cloudy darkness broken only by a lighter diagonal line or bolt in the upper left corner encompasses all but the lower right corner of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>