<bad id="esii.1" type="spb" work="Charity" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="essickcat" catid="ii.1">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Charity">
                    <main>
                        Charity</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2019 British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
                        <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
             <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>February 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Michael Fox</name>
                                                  <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                                                  <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                                                  <name>Grant Glass</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Coordinator, University of
                                                  Rochester:</resp>
                                                  <name>Eric Loy</name>
                                                  <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                                                  <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                                                  <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                                                  <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                                                  <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                                                  <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                                                  <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                                                  <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                                                  <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                                                  <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                                                  <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                                                  <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                                                  <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                                                  <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                                                  <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                                                  <name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                                                  </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Charity*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role><role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                 <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1788.A">c. 1788</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1788.A">c. 1788</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>18.7 x 13.3 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>19.0 x 14.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>planographic transfer print with washes added</medium>
                <printingstyle>planographic<note>The image was probably printed by transfer from another leaf of paper or from millboard.</note></printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black<note>The black wash surrounding the figures was added by hand.</note></inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>
                    <note>none</note>
                </watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <binding/>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1958</date>
                <dealer>T. Rowe</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired 1958 by the British Museum from T. Rowe.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1958,1101.6</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esii.1.spb.01" dbi="ESII.1.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Charity</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESII">(Essick II)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This is the only traced impression of *Charity*, a title first published for the work in 1972. A date of c. 1788 is suggested by similarities between the figures and pictures by Blake of that period.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>19.0 x 14.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A nude female figure stands in the center of the composition flanked on both sides by a pair of nude children.  The central adult stands or walks facing forward with her head turned to the right and slightly down, looking toward the children.  She has long hair and prominent breasts. Both arms are by her sides and she holds the hand of the child closest to her on either side. Her right leg appears to be slightly bent and lifted, as if she is stepping or walking forward. This figure may be a personification of Charity. The two nude children on the right side of the composition stand or walk facing forward.  The rightmost child appears to be female as she has long hair.  Her left arm (not clearly pictures below the elbow) may be raised horizontally and bent in front of her chest while she embraces her companion's shoulders with her extended right arm.  She may touch the hand of the adult female figure with her right hand as well. Her right leg is slightly bent and lifted as if she is stepping forward.  The gender of the second child from the right is unclear, though he(?) appears to have short hair. He faces forward but turns his head up and to the left to look toward the adult figure whose hand he holds with his raised right arm. His left leg is extended behind him as if he is walking forward.  The two children on the left side of the composition embrace each other.  The leftmost male child faces forward but twists to the right to embrace his companion with his raised right arm.  He appears to have curly hair and his genitals are pictured. His right leg is extended backward as if he is walking forward.  The second figure from the left, who may be female, faces forward but turns her head to the left, perhaps to touch the head of the figure beside her.  Her mouth is open.  With her raised left arm, she holds the right hand of the adult female figure.  Her right leg is bent and she may walk forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breasts</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Charity</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A nude female figure stands in the center of the composition flanked on both sides by a pair of nude children.  The central adult stands or walks facing forward with her head turned to the right and slightly down, looking toward the children.  She has long hair and prominent breasts. Both arms are by her sides and she holds the hand of the child closest to her on either side. Her right leg appears to be slightly bent and lifted, as if she is stepping or walking forward. This figure may be a personification of Charity.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two nude children on the right side of the composition stand or walk facing forward.  The rightmost child appears to be female as she has long hair.  Her left arm (not clearly represented below the elbow) may be raised horizontally and bent in front of her chest while she embraces her companion's shoulders with her extended right arm.  She may touch the hand of the adult female figure with her right hand as well. Her right leg is slightly bent and lifted as if she is stepping forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <componet type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two nude children on the right side of the composition stand or walk facing forward. The gender of the second child from the right is unclear, though he(?) appears to have short hair. He faces forward but turns his head up and to the left to look toward the adult figure whose hand he holds with his raised right arm. His left leg is extended behind him as if he is walking forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </componet>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two children on the left side of the composition embrace each other.  The leftmost male child faces forward but twists to the right to embrace his companion with his raised right arm.  He appears to have curly hair and his genitals are pictured. His right leg is extended backward as if he is walking forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The two children on the left side of the composition embrace each other.  The second figure from the left, who may be female, faces forward but turns her head to the left, perhaps to touch the head of the figure beside her.  Her mouth is open.  With her raised left arm, she holds the right hand of the adult female figure.  Her right leg is bent and she may walk forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
