<bad id="esiv.1-1b" type="spb" work="Edward &#38; Elenor" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="essickcat" catid="iv.1-1b">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Edward &#38; Elenor">
                    <main>
                        Edward &#38; Elenor</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This work courtesy British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>February 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Michael Fox</name>
                                                  <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                                                  <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                                                  <name>Grant Glass</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Coordinator, University of
                                                  Rochester:</resp>
                                                  <name>Eric Loy</name>
                                                  <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                                                  <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                                                  <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                                                  <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                                                  <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                                                  <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                                                  <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                                                  <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                                                  <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                                                  <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                                                  <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                                                  <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                                                  <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                                                  <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                                                  <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                                                  <name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                                                  </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
             <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Edward &#38; Elenor*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator,</role>
                    <role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher>William Blake</publisher>
                    <pubplace>Lambeth</pubplace>
                    <date>18 August 1793</date>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1793.C">1793</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1793.A">1793</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>30.7 x 45.7 cm.</objsize>
                <platemark>37.5 x 48.7 cm.</platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>41.2 x 53.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1938</date>
                <dealer>none recorded</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquire by the British Museum in April 1938 from Cecil H. Drummond.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Prints and Drawings: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1938,0409.6</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esiv.1-1b.spb.01" dbi="ESIV.1-1B.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Edward &#38; Elenor</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESIV">(Essick IV)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This impression is in the only recorded state of the plate.  The only other known impression was cut by Blake into two pieces and used in his manuscript of *The Four Zoas* (British Library).</p></objnote>
                <objsize>41.2 x 53.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        At least fifteen figures surround the central pair of figures, King Edward the First at left and Queen Elenor (Eleanor of Castile) at right, who sit beneath a draped canopy. Edward has long hair and a beard, and he wears a breastplate, drapery or gown, and sandals.  He sits facing forward and turns his head to the right to look toward Elenor.  His legs are bent, with his right resting on some sort of claw-footed footrest or stool, and his right arm is bent upward in front of his chest.  His left arm is bent but extended horizontally and held at the elbow by Elenor with both hands.  Elenor, who has her long hair coiffed in braids arranged on her head and wears a long gown, sits facing left and bends forward to place her lips on Edward's extended arm.  She is likely sucking the poison out of his wound. The figure to the right of Elenor holds a sizable arrow with his bent left arm that may have been the cause of the injury.  This male figure stands facing forward and slightly left as he looks to the royal couple. He has short hair but a long, curly beard and wears a shirt as well as a cloak. His right arm is at his side. The six female figures on the right side of the composition are likely attendants to Queen Elenor.  Two of these female figures, who wear gowns and drapery, kneel in front of the steps to the royal couple.  The figure at left has long, curly hair and holds a large basin or bowl with both arms raised horizontally. Her companion at right has coiffed curly hair and appears also to extend her arms, in which she holds a swath of drapery, horizontally to the left.  To the right of this group, four additional female figures, all of whom have long hair and wear gowns with drapery, stand at right.  The leftmost of these faces forward and left and looks toward the central pair of figures; her right arm is at her side with her hand raised, palm facing down.  The second figure from the left in this group looks left and raises both arms in front of her chest and folds her hands in a gesture of prayer.  The third figure from the left faces left and bends forward as if to look between the figures standing in front of her.  One of her feet is extended backward and slightly lifted on tiptoe.  The rightmost figure in this group turns to face forward with her head down and raises her left arm in front of her chest. She appears to look down toward the head and shoulders of a dead(?) male figure visible in the lower right corner of the composition. The male figure has short curly hair and a beard; his eyes are closed and his head is turned to face left.  He may lie on drapery or some sort of mat. On the left side of the composition, seven male figures stand facing right. On the step below King Edward stands a young boy who faces forward and right to look toward the central couple.  He has long hair and wears a shirt and pants as well as a cloak or other drapery. With his bent left arm, he supports a large sword and shield, which rest on a higher step. The child is likely their son Edward, future King Edward II. Above the young prince, three men who all wear helmets look toward the king and queen.  The rightmost of these has a beard and wears a breastplate.  His left arm is at his side but bent sharply upward to hold a shield.  The figure to his left also wears armor and holds a shield with his bent left arm.  The third figure in this group stands behind the first two figures at left and only the top of his helmet his visible.  Below and to the left of this trio and the young prince, three additional figures stand in the lower left corner. The rightmost of these stands facing away and looks to the right. He has short curly hair and wears a breastplate, shirt, pants, drapery, and sandals.  His right arm is at his side and raised slightly with palm facing down.  His left arm is at his side but bent upward to hold a long pike or spear at left. To the left the heads of two figures are visible looking right: the figure at right has a mustache while the left figure has a curly beard.  Both may hold similar pikes or spears (although their arms are not visible) as the weapons' tips are visible above the crowd of onlookers. There may be additional figures on the left since the tops of more weapons are visible. The canopy under which Edward and Elenor sit is formed by two vertical posts and one horizontal lintel from which a row of tassels dangles.  Drapery covers both the space inside and the walls flanking the canopy. The level on which the royal couple sits is elevated by two steps, which are covered in a rug or carpet with a diamond pattern.  The floor not covered by this rug or carpet visible along the lower edge of the composition may be made of wood planks.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Edward the First</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breastplate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wound</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fifteen figures surround the central pair of figures, King Edward the First at left and Queen Elenor at right, who sit beneath a draped canopy. Edward has long hair and a beard, and he wears a breastplate, drapery or gown, and sandals.  He sits facing forward and turns his head to the right to look toward Elenor.  His legs are bent, with his right resting on some sort of claw-footed footrest or stool, and his left on the floor.  His right arm is bent upward and his palm faces his chest.  His left arm is bent but extended horizontally and held at the elbow by Elenor with both hands.  She is likely sucking the poison out of the wound on his arm. The figure to the right of Elenor holds a sizable arrow with his bent left arm that may have been the cause of the king's injury.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Elenor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eleanor of Castile</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>braid</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>queen</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sucking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fifteen figures surround the central pair of figures, King Edward the First at left and Queen Elenor (Eleanor of Castile) at right, who sit beneath a draped canopy.  Elenor, who has her long hair coiffed in braids arranged on her head and wears a long gown, sits facing left and bends forward to place her lips on Edward's extended arm.  Her eyes are closed and both of her arms are bent upward.  She is likely sucking the poison out of his wound.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At least fifteen figures surround the central pair of figures, King Edward at left and Queen Elenor at right, who sit beneath a draped canopy. The figure to the right of Elenor holds a sizable arrow with his bent left arm that may have been the cause of the king's injury.  He stands facing forward and slightly left as he looks to the royal couple. He has short hair but a long, curly beard and wears a shirt as well as drapery. His right arm is at his side, and he may reach out to touch Elenor.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>arrow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The male figure who stands to the right of King Edward and Queen Elenor holds in his left hand an arrow, which is likely the cause of the king's arm injury.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The six female figures on the right side of the composition are likely attendants to Queen Elenor.  Two of these female figures, who wear gowns and drapery, kneel in front of the steps to the royal couple.  The figure at left has long, curly hair tied back with a ribbon.  She holds a large basin or bowl with both arms raised horizontally and looks up toward the king and queen above her at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The six female figures on the right side of the composition are likely attendants to Queen Elenor.  Two of these female figures, who wear gowns and drapery, kneel in front of the steps to the royal couple.  The figure at right has coiffed curly hair and appears also to extend her arms, in which she holds a swath of drapery, horizontally to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, four additional female figures, all of whom have long hair and wear gowns with drapery, stand and face left.  The leftmost of these faces forward and left and looks toward the central pair of figures.  She has long, curly hair tied back with a ribbon.  Her right arm is at her side with her hand raised, palm facing down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, four additional female figures, all of whom have long hair and wear gowns with drapery, stand and face left. The second figure from the left in this group looks left and raises both arms in front of her chest and folds her hands in a gesture of prayer.  She has long curly hair worn with a ribbon and tilts her head forward slightly.  She wears a sandal on her left foot.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, four additional female figures, all of whom have long hair and wear gowns with drapery, stand and face left. The third figure from the left faces left and bends forward as if to look between the figures standing in front of her.  Her long hair is worn with a ribbon or scarf.  One of her feet is extended backward and slightly lifted on tiptoe.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>ribbon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the right side of the composition, four additional female figures, all of whom have long hair and wear gowns with drapery, stand and face left.  The rightmost figure in this group turns to face forward with her head down.  Her curly hair is tied with a ribbon or scarf.  She raises her bent left arm in front of her chest with hand raised and palm facing left. She appears to look down toward the head and shoulders of a dead(?) male figure visible in the lower right corner of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner of the composition, the head and shoulders of a dead(?) male figure are visible.  The male figure has short curly hair and a beard; his eyes are closed and his head is turned to face left.  He may lie on drapery or some sort of mat.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mat</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The male figure whose head and shoulders are visible in the lower right corner may lie on drapery or a mat.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>prince</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Edward the Second</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least seven male figures stand facing right. On the step below King Edward stands a young boy who faces forward and right to look toward the central couple.  He has long, curly hair and wears a shirt and pants as well as a cloak or other drapery. With his bent left arm, he supports a large sword and shield, which rest on a higher step. His right arm is at his side.  He stands in contrapposto with his right leg slightly bent; he wears sandals.  The child is likely the son of the royal couple, Edward, the future King Edward the Second.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least seven male figures stand facing right. Above the young prince, three men who all wear helmets, and thus may be soldiers, look toward the king and queen. The rightmost of these has short hair and a beard and wears a breastplate.  His helmet includes a large feathered plume. His left arm is at his side but bent sharply upward to hold a shield. His head is bent down slightly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plume</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least seven male figures stand facing right. Above the young prince, three men who all wear helmets, and thus may be soldiers, look toward the king and queen.  The figure directly above the young prince also wears a helmet with a feathered plume and armor.  His left arm is bent upward to hold a shield and his right arm is at his side but bent forward at a right angle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least seven male figures stand facing right. Above the young prince, three men who all wear helmets, and thus may be soldiers, look toward the king and queen. The third figure from the right in this group stands behind the first two figures at left and only the top of his helmet, which is adorned with a zoomorphic figure, his visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pants</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least seven male figures stand facing right.  Below and to the leftmost trio of soldiers and the young prince, three additional figures stand in the lower left corner. The rightmost of these stands facing away and looks to the right. He has short curly hair and wears a breastplate, shirt, pants, drapery or a cloak, and sandals.  His right arm is at his side and raised slightly with palm facing down, fingers slightly spread.  His left arm is at his side but bent upward to hold a long pike or spear at left.  His left leg is bent and extended backward slightly with his left foot lifted off the ground.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>On the left side of the composition, at least seven male figures stand facing right.  Below and to the leftmost trio of soldiers and the young prince, three additional figures stand in the lower left corner. Against the left edge of the composition, the heads of two figures are visible looking right: the figure at right has a mustache while the left figure has a mustache and curly beard. The figure at right may wear a shirt or drapery. Both figures may hold similar pikes or spears (although their arms are not visible) as the weapons' tips are visible above the crowd of onlookers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arrow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tassel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several additional weapons are visible or partially visible above the group of male figures at left including multiple spears or pikes, some of which include decorative tassels, and a bow and arrow near the middle of the crowd.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>stool</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>claw</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>King Edward'sright foot rests on a claw-footed footrest or stool.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lintel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The canopy under which Edward and Elenor sit, which may be a throne, is formed by two vertical posts and one horizontal lintel from which a row of tassels dangle.  Drapery covers both the space inside and the walls flanking the canopy. The level on which the royal couple sits is elevated by two steps, which are covered in a rug or carpet with a diamond pattern.  The floor not covered by this rug or carpet visible along the lower edge of the composition may be made of wood planks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>throne</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tassel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>carpet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The canopy under which Edward and Elenor sit, which may be a throne, is formed by two vertical posts and one horizontal lintel from which a row of tassels dangles.  Drapery covers both the space inside and the walls flanking the canopy. The level on which the royal couple sits is elevated by two steps, which are covered in a rug or carpet with a diamond pattern.  The floor not covered by this rug or carpet visible along the lower edge of the composition may be made of wood planks.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="30"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esiv.1-1b.spb.01.01" indent="20"><hi rend="i">Painted and Engraved by William Blake</hi></l> 
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esiv.1-1b.spb.01.02" indent="16"><hi rend="i">EDWARD &#38; ELENOR</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esiv.1-1b.spb.01.03" indent="18"><hi rend="i">Published 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. August 1793 by W Blake N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 13 Hercules Buildings Lambeth</hi></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
