<bad id="esviii.3-3d" type="spb" work="The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder" copy="3" copyid="3" institution="boston" catalog="essickcat" catid="viii.3-3d">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder">
                    <main>
                        The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</main>
                    <copy> Copy 3</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2019 Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>February 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Michael Fox</name>
                                                  <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                                                  <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                                                  <name>Grant Glass</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Coordinator, University of
                                                  Rochester:</resp>
                                                  <name>Eric Loy</name>
                                                  <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                                                  <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                                                  <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                                                  <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                                                  <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                                                  <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                                                  <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                                                  <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                                                  <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                                                  <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                                                  <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                                                  <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                                                  <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                                                  <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                                                  <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                                                  <name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                                                  </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>April 2005</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

              <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator,</role>
                    <role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>None.  The imprint of the first and second states has been removed.</imprint>
                <compdate value="1793.A">1793</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1820.A">c. 1820-25</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>18.4 x 10.0 cm. (design)</objsize>
                <platemark>21.8 x 12.1 cm.</platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>25.4 x 16.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>A single frame line surrounds most of the design.</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</name>
                <date>1913</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>bequest</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired at an unknown time by the New York print dealer Frederick Keppel (1845-1912); given by the Frederick Keppel Bequest to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, in Oct. 1913.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Museum of Fine Arts, Boston</institution>
                <addressline>Avenue of the Arts</addressline>
                <addressline>465 Huntington Avenue</addressline>
                <addressline>Boston, Massachusetts 02115-5597</addressline>
                <lb/>
                <addressline>Telephone: 617-267-9300</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 626-859-4972</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.mfa.org/</addressline>
                <department>Prints, Drawings, and Photographs</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">23.452</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esviii.3-3d.spb.01" dbi="esviii.3-3D.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESVIII">(Essick VIII)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This impression is in the third state of three.  The plate was originally etched and engraved in 1793 and converted to this final state c. 1820-25.  Fragments of the second state inscriptions are visible left of the signature below the design ("When") and right of the penultimate line below the design (the upper part of the "P" of "Page").  This impression is inscribed "F.K." (Frederick Keppel) in pen and ink lower left and "Designed and Engraved by William Blake" in pencil just above the bottom edge of the leaf.  Neither inscription is by Blake and they are not shown here.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>21.8 x 12.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right.  The inscription above their heads identifies them as accusers, but the inscription below the design identifies them (reading from left to right?) as the "Accuser," the "Judge," and the "Executioner."  The rightmost figure wears a shirt, breeches, and a laurel crown. He has short curly hair and turns his head to look to the left. His eyes are wide and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. His teeth are visible. Both arms are bent and crossed in front of his chest. With his right hand, he holds the haft of a sword, which is pointed upward. His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left.  In the inscription about the figures, he is identified as the accuser of murder. To his left, the middle figure turns his head to look forward.  He has long hair, a mustache, and a beard; he also wears a spiky crown. His eyes are wide and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. His teeth and tongue are visible. He raises both bent arms upward and clutches his head with both hands. The fingers of both hands appear to be curled inward. This figure wears a cloak that extends down behind his thighs. He may also wear a shirt and breeches(?). His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left. In the inscription about the figures, he is identified as the accuser of adultery. The leftmost figure stands with his body facing right and head turned to look left and slightly down. He has short hair that stands on end, a mustache, and a beard. He wears a shirt composed of small circles, which may indicate chain mail, and pleated breeches or skirt(?).  His costume suggests that of a Roman soldier. His right arm appears to be raised and extended behind the figure to his right. He may hold the spear pointed upward above the middle figure's head with his left hand (which is not visible). Only the right leg and foot of the leftmost figure are visible. In the inscription about the figures, he is identified as the accuser of theft.  Lines below the feet of all three figures suggest sandals, but no straps are pictured. Three tall flames frame the group of figures at right and left. Behind the flames on both sides of the composition are two wooden vertical objects, which may be a door frame, as there appears to be a small horizontal step behind the figures' feet. The ground on which they stand may also be made of wood. Above their heads in the background is sky that may contain wispy clouds. 
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>accuser</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>laurels</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>teeth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right. The inscription above their heads identifies them as accusers, but the inscription below the design identifies them (reading from left to right?) as the "Accuser," the "Judge," and the "Executioner." The rightmost figure, possibly the accuser, wears a shirt, breeches, and a laurel crown. He has short curly hair and turns his head to look to the left. His eyes are wide and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. His teeth are visible. Both arms are bent and crossed in front of his chest. With his right hand, he holds the hilt of a sword, which is pointed upward. His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left. Lines below his feet suggest sandals, but no straps are visible. In the inscription about the figures, he is identified as the accuser of murder.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>haft</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost male figure holds the haft of a sword, which is pointed upward, in his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>accuser</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>judge</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>teeth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right. The inscription above their heads identifies them as accusers, but the inscription below the design identifies them (reading from left to right?) as the "Accuser," the "Judge," and the "Executioner." The middle figure, possibly the judge, turns his head to look forward.  He has long hair, a mustache, and a beard; he also wears a spiky crown. His eyes are wide and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. His teeth and tongue are visible. He raises both bent arms upward and clutches his head with both hands. The fingers of both hands appear to be curled inward. This figure wears a cloak that extends down behind his thighs. He may also wear a shirt and breeches(?). His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left. Lines below his feet suggest sandals, but no straps are pictured. In the inscription about the figures, he is identified as the accuser of adultery.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>accuser</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>executioner</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Roman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right. The inscription above their heads identifies them as accusers, but the inscription below the design identifies them (reading from right to left?) as the "Accuser," the "Judge," and the "Executioner." The leftmost figure, possibly the executioner, stands with his body facing right and head turned to look left and slightly down. He has short hair that stands on end, a mustache, and a beard. He wears a shirt composed of small circles, which may indicate chain mail, and pleated breeches or skirt(?).  His costume suggests that of a Roman soldier. His right arm appears to be raised and extended behind the figure to his right. He may hold the spear pointed upward above the middle figure's head with his left hand (which is not visible). Only the right leg and foot of the leftmost figure are visible.  Lines below his foot suggest a sandal, but no straps are pictured. In the inscription about the figures, he is identified as the accuser of theft.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure may hold the spear visible above the middle figure's head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three tall flames frame the group of figures at right and left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the flames on both sides of the composition are two wooden vertical objects, which may be a door frame, as there appears to be a small horizontal step behind the figures' feet. The ground on which they stand may also be wood.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above the three figures' heads in the background is sky that may contain wispy clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="3"/>
                <lg justify="left" indent="19">
                    <l n="esviii.3-3d.sbp.01.01"><hi rend="i">The Accuse<space extent="2"/>rs of</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <lg justify="left" indent="10">
                    <l n="esviii.3-3d.sbp.01.02"><hi rend="i">Theft<space extent="5"/>Adultery<space extent="8"/>Murder</hi></l>    
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="25"/>
                <lg justify="left" indent="14">
                    <l n="esviii.3-3d.sbp.01.03"><unclear resp="EL"><hi rend="i">When</hi></unclear><space extent="3"/><hi rend="i">WBlake inv &#38; sculp</hi><note>"When", visible to the left of the signature, is a fragment from the second-state title inscription. See object note.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg justify="left" indent="10">
                    <l n="esviii.3-3d.sbp.01.04"><hi rend="i">A Scene in the Last Judgment</hi><space extent="5"/><unclear resp="EL"><hi rend="i">P</hi></unclear><note>Partial character "P" is a fragment from the second-state inscription "Page 56". See object note.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg justify="left" indent="1">
                    <l n="esviii.3-3d.sbp.01.05"><hi rend="i">Satans<unclear resp="EL">'</unclear> holy Trinity The Accuser The Judge &#38; The Executioner</hi><note>The apostrophe in "Satans'" is not clearly printed in this impression.</note></l>
                </lg>       
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
