<bad id="esvi.1-2B" type="spb" work="Ezekiel" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="essickcat" catid="vi.1-2B">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Ezekiel">
                    <main>
                        Ezekiel</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2016</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2016 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Ezekiel*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Jean-Antoine Watteau<role>, inventor</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Unknown<role>, printer</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thomas Macklin</publisher>
                    <pubplace>London<note>London is not specificed in the imprint, but the street address indicates as much.</note></pubplace>
                    <date>1782</date>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1794.A">1794</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1820.A">c. 1820-25</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>25.1 x 30.0 cm. (oval image including frame line), 29.4 x 30.0 cm. (including inscriptions)</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>32.6 x 35.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>stipple etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>A single frame line in stipple surrounds the oval image.</note></framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1982</date>
                <dealer>Donald Heald acting for Essick at a Christie's auction</dealer>
                <price>&#163;918</price>
                <note> Possibly the impression sold from the collection of W. E. Moss, Sotheby's, 2 March 1937, in lot 139, with "Morning Amusement" (possibly Essick impression 2F) and impressions of both prints in colors (&#163;8 to the dealer Dulau and Co.); possibly the impressions offered by Dulau, April 1937 catalogue, item 20 (&#163;14), and 1940 catalogue 281, item 9 (&#163;10.10s.), both times with the other prints in lot 139 in the Christie's auction; acquired by the dealer Charles Sessler from the dealer Stevens and Brown, with "Morning Amusement" (Essick impression 2F) for $13.33 in June 1949; sold by Sessler to Charles J. Rosenbloom, Oct. 1949, for $750 the pair; inherited by Rosenbloom's wife, Lucile Johnson Rosenbloom, in 1973; sold Christie's, 2 Nov. 1982, lot 35, with "Morning Amusement," Essick impression 2F (&#163;918 to Donald Heald acting for Robert N. Essick).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena</addressline>
                <addressline>California</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esvi.1-2B.spb.01" dbi="esvi.1-2B.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Ezekiel</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESVI">(Essick VI)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>29.4 x 30.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. The most prominent figure in the composition is the gowned male figure at left who kneels facing forward with head and eyes raised. He is old with short hair and a long beard.  He crosses his bent arms in front of his chest with palms resting on opposite arms and fingers spread. A halo of light is visible around his head. The figure is likely Ezekiel. In the lower right corner of the composition, a female figure sits facing left in a contracted position bent sharply forward. She has long hair and wears a gown. Her left arm is bent upward to touch her face, which is obscured by her long hair. Her left leg is bent upward and her left foot is visible beneath her gown. Her posture suggests despair or mourning. Behind the two figures in the foreground, a gowned female figure who may be dead lies supine on a draped bed or bier with her head at left. She may wear a hat or drapery around her head; her eyes are closed. A halo with spiky beams of light is visible around her head. This figure is likely Ezekiel's wife after her death. Behind the supine female figure, the heads of two additional figures, who likely sit or kneel on the opposite side of the bed or bier, are visible. Both figures appear to lower their heads and their postures suggest despair or mourning. The figure at right appears to have short hair and raises both hands to touch or grasp his(?) hair. The figure at left may have short curly hair. He(?) raises one hand beside his head with palm out, facing forward. The fifth figure is visible against the left margin behind Ezekiel. This figure appears to have short hair and raises one hand to touch his(?) face. His posture also suggests despair or mourning. The background wall of the composition includes a horizontal frieze of square motifs in a classical design that extends the length of the wall as well as at least three figural pictures. The rightmost image is visible in a frame decorated with intertwined lines and may depict several gowned figures, though the details of the image are unclear. There are two vertical triangular motifs visible on the wall to the right of this image. The two additional images on the background wall are half-moon roundels. The middle image depicts two gowned pairs of figures flying toward each other over two orbs (one large in the center and one small at right). The left arms of the two figures at right are extended horizontally while the figures at left both raise a single bent arm upward. The leftmost image is only partially visible and may include two figures, one of whom stands at right and one who kneels at left. Both of these figures appear to face left and bend forward to the left.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ezekiel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. The most prominent figure in the composition is the gowned male figure at left who kneels facing forward with head and eyes raised. He is old with short hair and a long beard.  He crosses his bent arms in front of his chest with palms resting on opposite arms and fingers spread. A halo of light is visible around his head. The figure is likely Ezekiel.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. In the lower right corner of the composition, a female figure sits facing left in a contracted position bent sharply forward. She has long hair and wears a gown. Her left arm is bent upward to touch her face, which is obscured by her long hair. Her left leg is bent upward and her left foot is visible beneath her gown. Her posture suggests despair or mourning.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two figures in the foreground, the gowned female figure who may be dead lies supine on a draped bed or bier with her head at left. She may wear a hat or drapery around her head; her eyes are closed. A halo with spiky beams of light is visible around her head. This figure is likely Ezekiel's wife after her death.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure in the center of the composition who may be dead lies supine on a bed or bier, which has drapery around its base. She appears to rest her head on a pillow at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. Behind the supine female figure, the heads of two additional figures, who likely sit or kneel on the opposite side of the bed or bier, are visible. Both figures appear to lower their heads and their postures suggest despair or mourning. The figure at right appears to have short hair and raises both hands to touch or grasp his(?) hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. Behind the supine female figure, the heads of two additional figures, who likely sit or kneel on the opposite side of the bed or bier, are visible. Both figures appear to lower their heads and their postures suggest despair or mourning. The figure at left may have short curly hair. He(?) raises one hand beside his head with palm out, facing forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. The fifth figure is visible against the left margin behind Ezekiel. This figure appears to have short hair and raises one hand to touch his(?) face. He may wear a gown. His posture also suggests despair or mourning.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background wall of the composition includes a horizontal frieze of square motifs in a classical design that extends the length of the wall as well as at least three figural pictures. The rightmost image is visible in a frame decorated with intertwined lines and may depict several gowned figures, though the details of the image are unclear. There are two vertical triangular motifs visible on the wall to the right of this image. The two additional images on the background wall are half-moon roundels. The middle image depicts two gowned pairs of figures flying toward each other over two orbs (one large in the center and one small at right). The left arms of the two figures at right are extended horizontally while the figures at left both raise a single bent arm upward. The leftmost image is only partially visible and may include two figures, one of whom stands at right and one who kneels at left. Both of these figures appear to face left and bend forward to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>orb</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost image may depict a group of figures, though the details of the image are unclear. The middle image depicts two gowned pairs of figures flying toward each other over two orbs (one large in the center and one small at right). The left arms of the two figures at right are extended horizontally while the figures at left both raise a single bent arm upward. The leftmost image is only partially visible and may include two figures, one of whom stands at right and one who kneels at left. Both of these figures may wear gowns or drapery and appear to face left and bend forward to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>