<bad id="esvi.1-2b" type="spb" work="Ezekiel" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="essickcat" catid="vi.1-2B">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Ezekiel">
                    <main>
                        Ezekiel</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This work copyright © 2019 Fitzwilliam Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>December 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Michael Fox</name>
                                                  <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                                                  <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                                                  <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                                                  <name>Grant Glass</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Coordinator, University of
                                                  Rochester:</resp>
                                                  <name>Eric Loy</name>
                                                  <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                                                  <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                                                  <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                                                  <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                                                  <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                                                  <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                                                  <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                                                  <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                                                  <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                                                  <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                                                  <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                                                  <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                                                  <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                                                  <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                                                  <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                                                  <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                                                  <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                                                  <name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                                                  </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>November 1998</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Programmers/Analysts: </resp>
                    <name>David Cosca,</name>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistant: </resp>
                    <name>Greg Murray</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Ezekiel*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator,</role>
                    <role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                <imprint>
                    <publisher>William Blake</publisher>
                    <pubplace>London</pubplace>
                    <date>1794</date>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1794.A">1794</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1820.A">c. 1820-25</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>35.5 x 48.0 cm. (design), 41.5 x 48.0 cm. (including inscriptions)</objsize>
                <platemark>46.4 x 54.0 cm.</platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>48.9 x 67.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name>
                <date>1954</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>none</price>
                <note>Inherited in 1827 by Catherine Blake upon her husband's death; sold March 1830 to Haviland Burke acting for John Jebb, Bishop of Limerick (with an impression of Blake's *Job* engraving, &#163;2.2s.); bequeathed in 1833 by Burke to his chaplain, Rev. Charles Forster; by inheritance in 1871 to his son, E. M. L. Forster; by inheritance in 1880 to his sister, Laura M. Forster; by inheritance in 1924 to her nephew, the novelist E. M. Forster; given by him to King's College, Cambridge, in 1953 and transferred by the college to the Fitzwilliam Museum in 1954.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline>
                <addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)1223 332900</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)1223 332923</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/index.html</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints: fitzmuseum-pdp@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/pdp</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 332927</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Image Library: +44 (0)1223 768591</addressline>
                <addressline>Email, Image Library: fitzmuseum-photography@lists.cam.ac.uk</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Photographic Service: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/photography</addressline>
                <department>Paintings, Drawings, and Prints</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">P.4-1953</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esvi.1-2b.spb.01" dbi="esvi.1-2B.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Ezekiel</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESVI">(Essick VI)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This impression is in the second state of two.  There is no known impression of the first state, but the two states of the companion plate, *Job*, strongly suggest that this impression of *Ezekiel* is indeed in a revised, second state. Further, the graphic style, particularly the extensive use of burnishing as an element of design, indicates a much later date, c. 1820-25, than the inscribed date of 1794. When Blake revised a plate, he typically did not change the date of the earlier state.  This is also true of the "1793" date retained in the second state of *Job*.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>41.5 x 48.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design is based on Ezekiel 24:16-18. Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead female figure, Ezekiel's wife, who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. The most prominent figure in the composition is the gowned male figure, Ezekiel, at left who kneels facing forward with head and eyes raised. He is old with short hair and a long beard.  He crosses his bent arms in front of his chest with palms resting on opposite arms and fingers spread. A halo of light is visible around his head. In the lower right corner of the composition, a female figure sits facing left in a contracted position bent sharply forward. She has long hair and wears a gown. Her left arm is bent upward to touch her face, which is obscured by her long hair. Her left leg is bent upward and her left foot is visible beneath her gown. Her posture suggests despair or mourning. Behind the two figures in the foreground, Ezekiel's dead wife lies supine on a draped bed or bier with her head at left. She may wear a hat or drapery around her head; her eyes are closed. A halo with spiky beams of light is visible around her head. Behind the supine female figure, the heads of two additional figures, who likely sit or kneel on the opposite side of the bed or bier, are visible. Both figures appear to lower their heads and their postures suggest despair or mourning. The figure at right appears to have short hair and raises both hands to touch or grasp his(?) hair. The figure at left may have short curly hair. He(?) raises his left hand beside his head with palm out, facing forward. The fifth figure is visible against the left margin behind Ezekiel. This figure appears to have short hair and raises one hand to touch his(?) face. His posture also suggests despair or mourning. The background wall of the composition includes a horizontal frieze of square motifs in a design that extends the length of the wall as well as at least three figural pictures. The rightmost image is visible in a frame decorated with intertwined lines and may depict several gowned figures, though the details of the image are unclear. There are two vertical triangular motifs, perhaps vegetation such as grain stems, visible on the wall to the right of this image. The two additional images on the background wall are half-moon roundels. The middle image depicts two gowned pairs of figures flying toward each other over two orbs (one large in the center and one small at right). The left arms of the two figures at right are extended horizontally while the figures at left both raise a single bent arm upward. The leftmost image is only partially visible and may include two figures, one of whom stands at right and one who kneels at left. Both of these figures appear to face left and bend forward to the left.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ezekiel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead female figure, Ezekiel's wife, who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. The most prominent figure in the composition is the gowned male figure, Ezekiel, at left who kneels facing forward with head and eyes raised. He is old with short hair and a long beard.  He crosses his bent arms in front of his chest with palms resting on opposite arms and fingers spread.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead female figure, Ezekiel's wife, who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. In the lower right corner of the composition, a female figure sits facing left in a contracted position bent sharply forward. She has long hair and wears a gown. Her left arm is bent upward to touch her face, which is obscured by her long hair. Her left leg is bent upward and her left foot is visible beneath her gown. Her posture suggests despair or mourning.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Ezekiel's wife</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two figures in the foreground, the gowned female figure lies supine on a draped bed or bier with her head at left. She may wear a hat or drapery around her head; her eyes are closed. A halo with spiky beams of light is visible around her head. This is Ezekiel's dead wife.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pillow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure in the center of the composition, Ezekiel's dead wife, lies supine on a bed or bier, which has drapery around its base. She appears to rest her head on a pillow at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. Behind the supine female figure, the heads of two additional figures, who likely sit or kneel on the opposite side of the bed or bier, are visible. Both figures appear to lower their heads and their postures suggest despair or mourning. The figure at right appears to have short hair and raises both hands to touch or grasp his(?) hair.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. Behind the supine female figure, the heads of two additional figures, who likely sit or kneel on the opposite side of the bed or bier, are visible. Both figures appear to lower their heads and their postures suggest despair or mourning. The figure at left may have short curly hair. He(?) raises one hand beside his head with palm out, facing forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Five figures sit or kneel around the supine body of a dead(?) female figure who lies on a draped bed or bier at right. The fifth figure is visible against the left margin behind Ezekiel. This figure appears to have short hair and raises one hand to touch his(?) face. He may wear a gown. His posture suggests despair or mourning.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>picture</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The background wall of the composition includes a horizontal frieze of square motifs in a classical design that extends the length of the wall as well as at least three figural pictures. The rightmost image is visible in a frame decorated with intertwined lines and may depict several gowned figures, though the details of the image are unclear. There are two vertical triangular motifs, possibly vegetation such as graim stems, visible on the wall to the right of this image. The two additional images on the background wall are half-moon (crescent) roundels. The middle image depicts two gowned pairs of figures flying toward each other over two orbs (one large in the center and one small at right). The left arms of the two figures at right are extended horizontally while the figures at left both raise a single bent arm upward. The leftmost image is only partially visible and may include two figures, one of whom stands at right and one who kneels at left. Both of these figures appear to face left and bend forward to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>orb</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost image on the background wall may depict a group of figures, though the details of the image are unclear. The middle image depicts two gowned pairs of figures flying toward each other over two orbs (one large in the center and one small at right). The left arms of the two figures at right are extended horizontally while the figures at left both raise a single bent arm upward. The leftmost image is only partially visible and may include two figures, one of whom stands at right and one who kneels at left. Both of these figures may wear gowns or drapery and appear to face left and bend forward to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="30"/>
                <lg>
                    <l n="esvi.1-2b.spb.01.01" justify="left" indent="25"><hi rend="i">Painted &#38; Engraved by W Blake</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l n="esvi.1-2b.spb.01.02" justify="left" indent="36"><hi rend="i">EZEKIEL</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l n="esvi.1-2b.spb.01.03" justify="left" indent="15"><hi rend="i">I take away from thee the Desire of thine Eyes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="12" unit="character"/></hi><note>Illegible text after "Eyes," is recorded as "Ezekiel xxiv" in other impressions (Essick page 21). In addition, Keynes records "C 16" following "xxiv" in *Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates* (Dublin: Emery Walker 1956) page 23.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l n="esvi.1-2b.spb.01.04" justify="left" indent="8"><hi rend="i">Publishd October 27 1794 by W Blake N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 13. Hercules Buildings Lambeth</hi></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
