<bad id="esviii.2-2c" type="spb" work="The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder" copy="2" copyid="2" institution="ngadc" catalog="essickcat" catid="viii.2-2c">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder">
                    <main>
                        The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</main>
                    <copy> Copy 2</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 72KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This work courtesy of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>May 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                    <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator,</role>
                    <role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                    <role>printer,</role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>None visible, but see the Editors' Note about the second state of this plate.</imprint>
                <compdate value="1793.A">1793</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1796.A">1796</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>21.4 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>32.0 x 24.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>intaglio etching and engraving color printed from the surface of the plate with hand coloring and pen and ink drawing on the impression.</medium>
                <printingstyle>planographic color printing</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>not inked</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <binding>Bound with *The Song of Los* Copy B (and perhaps other works by Blake&#8212;see Essick page 32) before 1904 but disbound by that year.</binding>
                <stabholes>Three holes, 8.9 cm. and 7.0 cm. apart.</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Possibly one of the works acquired from Blake in Aug. 1797 by James Curry; acquired when bound with *The Song of Los* Copy B (and perhaps other works by Blake&#8212;see Essick page 32) between 1856 and 1862 by Benjamin D'Israeli, later Earl of Beaconsfield; disbound and sold Hodgson auction, London, 14 Jan. 1904, lot 227 (&#163;15.5s. to the dealer Bernard Quaritch, possibly acting for William A. White); sold from White's collection in May 1929 by the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach to Lessing J. Rosenwald with *Joseph of Arimathea Preaching* Copy 1B for $3000; given by Rosenbach to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C., in 1943.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <addressline>Constitution Avenue NW, between 3rd and 9th Streets</addressline>
                <addressline>Washington, DC 20565</addressline>
                <addressline>Mailing Address: 2000B South Club Drive, Landover, Maryland 20785</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1-202-737-4215</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.nga.gov</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Print Study Rooms: 1-202-842-6380</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Visual Services: 1-202-842-6126</addressline>
                <addressline>URL, Visual Services: http://www.nga.gov/resources/divsdesc.shtm</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.3.8973</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esviii.2-2c.spb.01" dbi="esviii.2-2C.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESVIII">(Essick VIII, </objcode><objcode code="U1">Butlin 285)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This impression is probably in the second state of three. See Essick page 31 for the reasons for believing that this color printed impression is in the second state. The date of the conversion of the plate from its first state, dated 1793 in the imprint, into this second state was no later than 1796 when this color-printed impression was produced.  No inscriptions are visible and there is no traced intaglio impression in the second state. However, an impression (now untraced) with printed inscriptions, owned by Edward D. Hooper, was exhibited at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts in 1891.  The exhibition catalogue, pages 32-33, no. 11, records a title inscription ("When the senses are shaken / And the soul is driven to madness  Page 56") and the same imprint as in the first state ("Publishd June 5: 1793 by W Blake Lambeth").  Fragments of these inscriptions appear in some impressions of the third (final) state. The title in this second state is quoted from "Prologue, Intended for a Dramatic Piece of King Edward the Fourth," page 56 in Blake's *Poetical Sketches* of 1783 (see Erdman page 439). The identification of the figures as "The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder" and "The Accuser The Judge &#38; The Executioner" in the third state inscriptions may not pertain to this second state. This impression is numbered "3" in pen and ink top right, not by Blake.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>21.4 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right.  The rightmost figure is nude above the waist and wears blue breeches. He has short curly hair and turns his head to look to the left. His brow is furrowed and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. Both arms are bent and crossed in front of his chest. With his right hand, he holds the haft of a sword, which is pointed upward. His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left. To his left, the middle figure turns his head to look forward.  He has long hair, a mustache, and a beard; he also wears a spiky crown.  He may be a king. His eyes are wide and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. His teeth and tongue are visible. He raises both bent arms upward and clutches his head with both hands. The fingers of both hands appear to be curled inward. This figure wears a cape or cloak that extends down behind his thighs and a suit of armor. His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left. The leftmost figure stands with his body facing right and head turned to look left and down. He has short hair, a mustache, and a beard. He wears a shirt composed of small circles, which may indicate chain mail, and pleated breeches or skirt(?).  His costume suggests that of a Roman soldier. His right arm appears to be at his side. He may hold the spear pointed upward above the middle figure's head with his left hand (which is not visible). Only the right leg and foot of the leftmost figure are visible. Indeterminate forms that may suggest vegetation(?) are visible around the group of three figures. In the background sky, a red cloud or smoke behind the figures' heads may descend from the top right corner of the composition.  Another cloud or plume of smoke appears lower right behind the figures' legs.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right. The rightmost figure is nude above the waist and wears blue breeches. He has short curly hair and turns his head to look to the left. His brow is furrowed and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. Both arms are bent and crossed in front of his chest. With his right hand, he holds the hilt of a sword, which is pointed upward. His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>haft</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The rightmost male figure holds the haft a sword, which is pointed upward, in his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>teeth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right. The middle figure turns his head to look forward.  He has long hair, a mustache, and a beard; he also wears a spiky crown.  He may be a king. His eyes are wide and his mouth is open, perhaps in an expression of fear. His teeth and tongue are visible. He raises both bent arms upward and clutches his head with both hands. The fingers of both hands appear to be curled inward. This figure wears a cape or cloak that extends down behind his thighs and a suit of armor. His legs are together with the right leg slightly in front of the left.  Lines under his right foot hint at a sandal, but no straps are pictured.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Roman</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sandal</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three male figures stand in a line with bodies turned to face right. The leftmost figure stands with his body facing right and head turned to look left and down. He has short hair, a mustache, and a beard. He wears a shirt composed of small circles, which may indicate chain mail, and pleated breeches or skirt(?).  His costume suggests that of a Roman soldier. His right arm appears to be at his side. He may hold the spear pointed upward above the middle figure's head with his left hand (which is not visible). Only the right leg and foot of the leftmost figure are visible. Lines under his right foot hint at a sandal, but no straps are pictured.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The leftmost figure may hold the spear visible above the middle figure's head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Indeterminate forms that may suggest vegetation(?) are visible around the group of three figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the background sky, a red cloud or smoke behind the figures' heads may descend from the top right corner of the composition. Another cloud or plume of smoke appears lower right behind the figures' legs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
