<bad id="esvii.1-1b" type="spb" work="Albion rose" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="essickcat" catid="vii.1-1b">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Albion rose">
                    <main>
                        Albion rose</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

This work copyright © 2019 Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
<change>BAD creation</change>
<date>March 2017</date>
<respstmt>
<resp>Editors:</resp>
<name>Morris Eaves,</name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick,</name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>
Joseph Viscomi,
</name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>
Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:
</resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
<name>Anna Alden,</name>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
<name>Adam Engel,</name>
<name>Alison Harper,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Adam McCune,</name>
<name>Rob Rich,</name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
</respstmt>
</changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>February 2001</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
<name>Andrea Laue</name>
<resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
<resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
<name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
<name>Kari Kraus, </name>
<name>Gerald Miller, </name>
<name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
<name>Sarah Trippensee</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Albion rose</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator,</role>
                    <role>etcher,</role>
                    <role>engraver,</role>
                    <role>printer,</role>
                    <role>colorist</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1795.A">1795</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1795.A">1795</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>27.2 x 19.9 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>36.8 x 26.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>intaglio etching and engraving color printed from the surface of the plate with hand coloring</medium>
                <printingstyle>planographic (plate surface)</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>color printed without inking of the intaglio lines</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>1794 / J WHATMAN</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name>
                <date>1915</date>
                <dealer>none recorded</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Possibly one of the works acquired from Blake in Aug. 1797 by James Curry; possibly included with *The Song of Los* Copy E when unbound and sold from the collection of the Earl of Crewe, Sotheby's, 30 March 1903, lot 9 (&#163;174 to the dealer Frank T. Sabin, probably acting for Frederic Robert Halsey); acquired by Halsey between 1903 and 1915 and bound by him at the end of *The Song of Los* Copy E; the volume sold with the Halsey library to Henry Huntington in 1915, this print removed from the binding in 1953 by the Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Henry E. Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution>
                <addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline>
                <addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1 626 405 2100</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 1 626 405 2191</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Imaging Services: 1 626 405 2182</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 1 626 405 3477</addressline>
                <addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: reference@huntington.org</addressline>
                <department>Art Division</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">000.124</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esvii.1-1b.spb.01" dbi="esvii.1-1B.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Albion rose</title>
                <title type="alt">Glad Day</title>
                <title type="alt">The Dance of Albion</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESVII">(Essick VII, </objcode><objcode code="U1">Butlin 284)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The underlying etched and engraved image is in the first state of two.  The thinness of the color printing indicates that this is the second impression (or "pull"); the first color printed impression is in *A Large Book of Designs* copy A in the British Museum.  The figure is identified as Albion in the inscription below the design added to the second state of the print, c. 1820-25, but it is not certain that the figure represents Albion in this first state.  Blake's inscribed initials and date within the design were probably also added c. 1820-25.  If however present in the first state, the inscription within the design is completely masked by color printing in both known impressions of the first state.  This impression of the first state is inscribed "9" in pencil below the bottom left corner of the design and, in pencil partly erased, "an additional plate," bottom right.  These inscriptions are not by Blake and pertain to the placement of the plate when bound with *The Song of Los* copy E (see the Provenance).  There are two additional pencil inscriptions on the verso, also not by Blake: "end" and "14," both lower right.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>27.2 x 19.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        A nude male figure stands in the center of the design with his arms raised horizontally and palms facing out. He is identified as Albion in the inscription below the design added to the second state of the print, c. 1820-25, but it is not certain that the figure represents Albion in this first state. He has short hair and faces forward. His legs are spread and his genitals are clearly visible. The ground (apparently a hill, mound, or stone rising from right to left) below is mottled, suggesting moss or lichens. Coloring around the figure indicates a sunrise, sunset, or a burst of radiance with beams of light emanating from the figure. A cloud or clouds may appear right and left of Albion's left leg. Darkness appears in the lower right corner of the design and extends horizontally to the left border between the ground and the radiance. Faint vertical lines lower right may suggest rain.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised, palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Albion</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A nude, muscular male figure stands in the center of the design with his genitals clearly visible.  He is identified as Albion in the inscriptions added to the second state of the print, c. 1820, but it is not certain that the figure represents Albion in this first state.  He faces forward with his legs spread apart and his right leg, slightly bent, positioned higher than the left. His arms are raised horizontally in a manner that suggests a cruciform position; his palms are held vertically and face outward from his body. His hair is short and curly.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure stands on a hill, mound, or stone that rises from right to left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>lichens</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>moss</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Mottled coloring on the ground below the figure suggests moss or lichens.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Coloring around the figure indicates a sunrise, sunset, or a burst of radiance with beams of light emanating from the figure. The effect around his head is halo-like.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cloud or clouds may appear right and left of Albion's left leg. Darkness appears in the lower right corner of the design and extends horizontally to the left border between the ground and the radiance. Faint vertical lines lower right may suggest rain.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
