<bad id="esx.2-1a" type="spb" work="Lucifer and the Pope in Hell" copy="2" copyid="2" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="essickcat" catid="x.2-1a">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Lucifer and the Pope in Hell">
                    <main>
                        Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</main>
                    <copy> Copy 2</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This work courtesy British Museum.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
<change>Bad creation</change>
<date>September 2017</date>
<respstmt>
<resp>Editors:</resp>
<name>Morris Eaves,</name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick,</name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen</name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
<name>Anna Alden,</name>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
<name>Alison Harper,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Rob Rich,</name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
</respstmt>
</changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Lucifer and the Pope in Hell*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>engraver, </role><role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                 <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1794.A">c. 1794</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1794.B">c. 1794</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>18.3 x 24.6 cm.</objsize>
                <platemark>22.0 x 27.9 cm.<note>The leaf of this impression is trimmed inside the platemark.</note></platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>18.8 x 25.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>A single frame line is contiguous with the edges of the design.</note></framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1966</date>
                <dealer>P. &#38; D. Colnaghi</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; acquired no later than July 1966 by the London dealer P. &#38; D. Colnaghi from a private collector; sold by Colnaghi to the British Museum in July 1966.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 44-(0)20-7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>British Museum</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <addressline>Email, Prints and Drawings: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Registration number">1966,0723.3</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esx.2-1a.spb.01" dbi="esx.2-1A.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESX">(Essick X)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This impression is in the second state of two.  The first state is the proof impression in the collection of Robert N. Essick.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>18.3 x 24.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        Two figures stand just right of center in a landscape that appears to depict hell filled with fire and smoke. The rightmost figure, who likely represents the Pope and may be a caricature of King George III, stands facing forward or walking to the left but turns his head to look to the right. He wears a three-tiered spiky hat and a long gown. His brow is furrowed and he frowns slightly. His left arm is raised and bent in front of his chest. He appears to wear a shackle around his left wrist; the connecting chain is held by the figure at the left. The figure at left stands, hovers, or walks behind the Pope and faces forward while looking slightly right. His left foot is raised and extended backward at right. He has short, flame-like hair that stands on end, and his body appears to be nude but covered with scales. This figure likely represents Lucifer. His right arm is raised horizontally and extended to the right. In his right hand, he holds a spear horizontally with its tip pointed left. His left arm is raised slightly and in his left hand he holds the length of chain connected to the Pope's shackle, as if leading him to the left. What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition.  They probably all represent monarchs and their soldiers. Only the heads of the two leftmost figures in the pit are visible: the mouth of the leftmost figure is open while only the top of the head and eyes of the second figure from left (who may wear a helmet or hat) are visible. The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the pit are visible. The third figure from the left faces forward but turns his head to look right and up. He has long hair and a beard; his mouth is open. His right arm is raised and bent to the right with palm facing down. A serpent may coil around his right arm and torso. The fourth figure from the left faces forward and left with his head raised slightly to look up. He has short curly hair and a beard; he wears a spiky crown and his mouth is open. His left arm is at his side. His torso, too, appears to be wrapped by a serpent, whose body may extend horizontally to the right. The fifth figure from the left also wears a spiky crown and has short hair that stands on end. He also has a long beard. This figure faces forward and right with wide eyes and a frown. He may look toward the standing pair at right.  Only the helmet of the second figure from the right is visible.  A final head is clearly visible against the far right side of the pit of fire. This figure's head is turned to face up and its mouth is open. In front of the rightmost heads in the pit, the tail and one leg of a lizard is visible crawling on the body of the serpent(?). Tall flames and smoke rise behind the figures in the pit. Behind the two central figures against the right edge of the composition, a swirling plume of smoke(?) rises diagonally and may contain human and animal bodies. At least one human face is visible to the right of the Pope's hip. This face is turned to face up and right with wide eyes and an open mouth. A second figure may be depicted in profile above this head at right. This figure may also have an open mouth and long hair, which streams to the right. Above these figures, the head, upper neck, and mane of a horse may be visible in profile facing left. At the top of this plume, a tail(?) of a serpent(?) may be visible and curls to the left. Large clouds cover the majority of the background space in the middle of the composition.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>hell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape of the composition appears to depict hell filled with fire and smoke.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Pope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>George III</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frowning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand just right of center in a hellish landscape. The rightmost figure, who likely represents the Pope and may be a caricature of King George III, stands facing forward or walking to the left but turns his head to look to the right. He wears a three-tiered spiky hat and a long gown. His brow is furrowed and he frowns slightly. His left arm is raised and bent in front of his chest. He appears to wear a shackle around his left wrist; the connecting chain is held by the figure at the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Lucifer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>devil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand just right of center in a hellish landscape. The figure at left stands, hovers, or walks behind the Pope and faces forward while looking slightly right. His left foot is raised and extended backward at right. He has short hair that stands on end, and his body appears to be nude but covered with scales. This figure likely represents Lucifer. His right arm is raised horizontally and extended to the right. In his right hand, he holds a spear horizontally with its tip pointed left. His left arm is raised slightly and in his left hand he holds the length of chain connected to the Pope's shackle, as if leading him to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lucifer, the central figure at left, holds a spear horizontally in his extended right hand. With his left hand, he holds the end of a chain attached to the shackle on the arm of the Pope, the central figure at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>pit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. Tall flames and smoke rise behind the figures in the pit.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Only the heads of the two leftmost figures in the fiery pit are visible. The leftmost figure faces forward and up with an open mouth. The figure may wear a hat or helmet; he may be a soldier.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Only the heads of the two leftmost figures in the fiery pit are visible. The eyes of the second figure from left, who faces forward and wears a hat or helmet, are visible.  He may be a soldier.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the fiery pit are visible. The third figure faces forward but turns his head to look right and up. He may be nude. He has long hair and a beard; his mouth his open. His right arm is raised and bent to the right with palm facing down. A serpent may coil around his right arm and torso.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the fiery pit are visible. The fourth figure from the left faces forward and left, twisting his body with his head raised slightly to look up. He has short curly hair and a beard; he wears a spiky crown, perhaps suggesting he is a king, and his mouth is open. He may wear a shirt. His left arm is at his side and his right arm may be bent upward to touch his face. His torso, too, appears to be wrapped by a serpent, whose body may extend horizontally to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frowning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the fiery pit are visible. The fifth figure from the left also wears a spiky crown, perhaps suggesting he is a king, and has short hair that stands on end. He also has a long beard. This figure faces forward and right with wide eyes and a frown. He may look toward the standing pair at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>helmet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>soldier</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Only the top of the head of the second figure from the right in the pit is visible.  He wears a hat or helmet; he may be a soldier.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A final head is clearly visible against the far right side of the pit of fire. This figure's head is turned to face up (perhaps to look toward the standing pair above at right) and its mouth is open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>serpent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lizard</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the fiery pit lower left, the body of a serpent(?) appears to be wrapped around several figures. In front of the rightmost heads in the pit, the tail and one leg of a lizard is visible crawling on the body of the serpent(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two central figures against the right edge of the composition, a swirling plume of smoke(?) rises diagonally and may contain human and animal bodies. At least one human face is visible to the right of the Pope's hip. This face is turned to face up and right with wide eyes and an open mouth.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two central figures against the right edge of the composition, a swirling plume of smoke(?) rises diagonally and may contain human and animal bodies. A second, less clear figure may be depicted in profile above the lower head at right. This figure may also have an open mouth and long hair, which streams to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="B">
                        <characteristic>horse</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mane</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>serpent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Behind the two central figures against the right edge of the composition, a swirling plume of smoke(?) rises diagonally and may contain human and animal bodies. Above the human figures, the head, upper neck, and mane of a horse may be visible in profile facing left. At the top of this plume, a tail(?) of a serpent(?) may be visible and curls to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Large clouds, perhaps of smoke, cover the majority of the background space in the middle of the composition.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
