<bad id="esx.3-1B" type="spb" work="Lucifer and the Pope in Hell" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="essickcat" catid="x.3-1B">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Lucifer and the Pope in Hell">
                    <main>
                        Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</main>
                    <copy>copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2016</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2016 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Lucifer and the Pope in Hell*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>engraver, </role><role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                
                <compdate value="1794.B">c. 1794</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1796.B">1796</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>19.9 x 27.4 cm.<note>The color printing in this impression extends beyond the edges of the underlying etched and engraved design on all four sides.</note></objsize>
                <platemark>22.0 x 27.9 cm.<note>The leaf of this impression is trimmed inside the platemark.</note></platemark>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>19.9 x 27.4 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>etching and engraving with color printing and additions in pen and ink and watercolor</medium>
                <printingstyle>etching and engraving color printed from the surface of the plate</printingstyle>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>none</note></framelines>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</name>
                <date>1923</date>
                <dealer>Robson &#38; Co.</dealer>
                <price>$1500</price>
                <note>Possibly inherited by Catherine Blake upon William Blake's death in 1827; possibly acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; possibly one of the two works "in colours" sold anonymously, Sotheby's, 29 April 1862, lot 185 (15s. to the dealer Francis Harvey); George A. Smith no later than 1876; sold from Smith's collection, Christie's, 16 July 1880, lot 101 (&#163;2.10s. to the dealer John Pearson); Thomas Glenn Arthur no later than 1890; sold from Arthur's collection, Christie's, 20 March 1914, lot 52 (&#163;14.14s. to the dealer Frank T. Sabin); the dealer Robson &#38; Co.; sold July 1923 by Robson to the dealer Charles Sessler ($407); sold by Sessler to Henry E. Huntington in Aug. 1923 for $1500.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens</institution>
                <addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline>
                <addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1 626 405 2100</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 1 626 405 2191</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Images: 1 626 405 2182</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 1 626 405 3477</addressline>
                <addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: reference@huntington.org</addressline>
                <department>Art Division</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">000.125</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esx.3-1B.spb.01" dbi="esx.3-1B.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESX">(Essick X)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>The underlying etching and engraving in this impression is probably in the second state of two, although this cannot be determined with any certainty because the dense color printing from the surface of the plate almost completely covers the intaglio lines.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>19.9 x 27.4 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>
                        Two figures stand just right of center in a landscape that depicts hell against a background of darkness. The rightmost figure, who likely represents the Pope and may be a caricature of King George III, stands facing forward or walking to the left but turns his head to look to the right. He wears a three-tiered spiky hat or crown and a long gown. His brow is furrowed and he frowns slightly. His left arm is raised and bent in front of his chest, where the figure at left may hold his left hand (which is not visible). The figure at left stands, hovers, or walks behind the Pope and faces forward while looking slightly right. His left foot is raised and extended backward at right. He has short hair that stands on end, and his blue body appears to be scaly and nude except for a long cape. This figure likely represents Lucifer. His right arm is raised horizontally and extended to the right. In his right hand, he holds a spear horizontally with its tip pointed left. His left arm is raised slightly and with his left hand he holds the Pope's left hand, as if leading him to the left. The ground on which the central pair walks may be water or earth(?). What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition.  The three with crowns are probably kings.  We see little more than the open mouth of the first figure on the left. Only the top half of the head of the second figure from the left is visible and faces forward. The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the pit are visible. The third figure faces forward but turns his head to look right and up. He has long hair and a beard; his mouth is open. His right arm is raised and bent to the right with palm facing down. A serpent coils around his right arm and torso. The fourth figure from the left faces forward and left with his head raised slightly to look up. He has short curly hair and a beard; he wears a spiky crown and his mouth is open. His left arm may be at his side; alternatively, the large body of a serpent may wrap around his left side torso and extend to the right. The fifth figure from the left also wears a spiky crown and has short hair that stands on end. He also has a long beard. This figure faces forward and right with wide eyes and a frown. He may look toward the standing pair at right. Two final heads are clearly visible against the far right side of the pit of fire. The head of the sixth figure from the left faces forward and leans to the left.  One (closed?) eye is visible. The seventh head from the left faces forward and up, perhaps with an open mouth, to look toward the standing pair above. Tall flames and dark smoke rise behind the figures in the pit.
                    </illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>hell</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape of the composition depicts hell against a background of darkness.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Pope</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>George III</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frowning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand just right of center in a landscape that depicts hell against a background of darkness. The rightmost figure, who likely represents the Pope and may be a caricature of King George III, stands facing forward or walking to the left but turns his head to look to the right. He wears a three-tiered spiky hat or crown and a long gown. His brow is furrowed and he frowns slightly. His left arm is raised and bent in front of his chest, where the figure at left may hold his left hand (which is not visible).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Lucifer</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>devil</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cape</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leading</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures stand just right of center in a landscape that depicts hell against a background of darkness. The figure at left stands, hovers, or walks behind the Pope and faces forward while looking slightly right. His left foot is raised and extended backward at right. He has short hair that stands on end, and his blue body appears to be scaly and nude except for a long cape. This figure likely represents Lucifer. His right arm is raised horizontally and extended to the right. In his right hand, he holds a spear horizontally with its tip pointed left. His left arm is raised slightly and with his left hand he holds the Pope's left hand, as if leading him to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lucifer, the central figure at left, holds a spear horizontally in his extended right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The ground on which the central pair walks may be water or earth(?).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>pit</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. Tall flames and smoke rise behind the figures in the pit.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. We see little more than the open moth of the first figure on the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. Only the top half of the head of the figure second from the left is visible and faces forward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the pit are visible. The third figure faces forward but turns his head to look right and up. He has long hair and a beard and wears a spiky crown, perhaps suggesting he is a king. His mouth is open. He appears to be nude. His right arm is raised and bent to the right with palm facing down. A serpent coils around his right arm and torso.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand on face</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the pit are visible. The fourth figure from the left faces forward and left with his head raised slightly to look up. He has short curly hair and a beard; he wears a spiky crown, perhaps suggesting he is a king, and his mouth is open. His left arm may be at his side; alternatively, the large body of a serpent may wrap around his left side torso and extend to the right. His right arm may be bent upward so that his right hand touches the right side of his face.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>frowning</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>What appears to be a pit of fire with seven figures inside is visible in the lower left corner of the composition. The heads and upper bodies of the third, fourth, and fifth figures from the left in the pit are visible. The fifth figure from the left also wears a spiky crown, perhaps suggesting he is a king, and has short hair that stands on end. He also has a long beard. This figure faces forward and right with wide eyes and a frown. His left arm appears to be at his side. He may look toward the standing pair at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two final heads are clearly visible against the far right side of the pit of fire. The head of the sixth figure from the left faces forward and leans to the left.  One (closed?) eye is visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two final heads are clearly visible against the far right side of the pit of fire. The seventh head from the left faces forward and up, perhaps with an open mouth, to look toward the standing pair above.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>serpent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the fiery pit lower left, the body of a snake or serpent(?) appears to be wrapped around the body of the thrid figure from the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>