<bad id="esxiv.1-1a" type="spb" work="Experimental Relief Plate" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="essickcat" catid="xiv.1-1a">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Experimental Relief Plate">
                    <main>
                        Experimental Relief Plate</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2017</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2017 National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Experimental Relief Plate*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1805.A">c. 1805-22</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1805.A">c. 1805-22</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>16.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.0 x 10.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>relief etching, possibly with a few touches of white-line etching</medium>
                <printingstyle>relief<note>In this impression, the relief plateaus are inked and the recessed, etched areas are not inked. This is the normal way of printing a relief etching.</note></printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none on the printed leaf<note>The single framing line is on the mount, not on the leaf on which the etching is printed.</note></framelines>
                <binding>none<note>The print is mounted in a window cut into a leaf of paper.</note></binding>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine upon his death in 1827; probably acquired by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; acquired by George A. Smith and bound by him in "about 1853" (Bentley page 337) with other works by Blake, including the manuscript "Order" of the *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*; the volume offered, presumably by Smith, at a Puttick and Simpson auction, London, 3-4 July 1863 (&#163;15.15.s., possibly bought-in by Smith given the reappearance of the volume in the Smith auction of 1880); the volume offered by the dealer Bernard Quaritch, 1864 *Catalogue of Books*, item 6521, possibly on consignment from, or in partnership with, Smith (&#163;21); the volume sold by Smith, Christie's, 1 April 1880, lot 168 (&#163;66 to Quaritch); the volume apparently lent by Quaritch to William Muir, who used some works as the basis for his facsimiles; the volume offered by Quaritch, Oct. 1883 *Catalogue of Works on the Fine Arts*, item 10,252 (&#163;80), May 1885 catalogue, *William Blake's Original Drawings*, page 2, no item number (&#163;80), and 1887 *General Catalogue of Books*, volume 2, item 10,252 (&#163;80); the volume acquired by Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge between 1892 and 1906; the volume sold from the Macgeorge collection, Sotheby's, 1 July 1924, lot 133 (&#163;345 to the dealer E. Parsons &#38; Sons); the volume, possibly with some leaves removed, offered by Maggs Bros., 1924 catalogue 456, item 53 (&#163;630); the volume acquired no later than 1927 by George C. Smith who disbound the volume; this print sold from George C. Smith's collection, Parke-Bernet, 2 Nov. 1938, lot 24 ($800 to the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach acting for Lessing J. Rosenwald); given by Rosenwald to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C., in 1943.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <department>Drawings and Prints</department>
                <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1964.8.1777</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esxiv.1-1a.spb.01" dbi="ESXIV.1-1A.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Experimental Relief Plate</title>
                <title type="alt">Let Him Look Up into the Heavens &#38; Laugh in the Bright Air</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESXIV">(Essick XIV)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This print is sometimes called "Let Him Look Up into the Heavens &#38; Laugh in the Bright Air."  The actual subject is not known.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>16.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This experimental relief plate has three main sections. The upper portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure may sit on a small mound or kneel on his bent right knee. His left leg is bent and in front of his body. The figure's arms are bent. The figure appears to grasp a severed human head that faces up and right with his left hand at right. With his right hand, the figure may grasp an indeterminate mass of objects visible beside him at left. A bird with outstretched wings flies in the upper left corner of the design, and an indeterminate form is visible below and right of the bird. A cat is visible below the severed head at right. Lines and other forms on the ground below the figure may indicate grass or other vegetation. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's hand at right. Tightly cross-hatched lines to the right of the figure's torso may suggest a dark background sky. The middle section of the plate is smaller than the surrounding designs and depicts a series of geometric and linear designs. The top row of designs includes a triangle at left, a circle at center, and a square at right, as well as several linear forms in between and around the row. A semi-circular line surrounds the lower portion of the middle section. Both straight and squiggled lines are visible inside the semi-circle. Like the upper portion, the third, lowest portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure appears to sit on grassy ground or kneel on his right knee; his body is twisted or bent to the left. His left leg is bent forward. His right arm is bent and at his side with his left hand braced against the ground at left. His left arm is bent at a right angle and his left hand is also braced on the ground or a rock at right. Below his left hand, two severed heads that face forward are visible in the lower right corner. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's hand at right. Horizontal lines to the left and right of the figure's torso may suggest beams of light in a background sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The upper portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure may sit on a small mound or kneel on his bent right knee. His left leg is bent and in front of his body with his left foot prominent. The figure's arms are bent. The figure appears to grasp a severed human head that faces up and right with his left hand at right. His right arm is at his side and with his right hand, the figure may brace himself on or grasp an indeterminate mass of objects visible beside him at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>severed head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the upper portion of the design may grasp a severed head that is visible near the right edge of the plate. The head has long, curly hair and faces forward and up. Its mouth appears to be open and its eyes are raised.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="A">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A bird with outstretched wings flies in the upper left corner of the design, and an indeterminate form is visible below and right of the bird.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cat is visible below the severed head near the right edge of the design. The cat sits facing forward and left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lines and other forms on the ground below the figure may indicate grass or other vegetation. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's left hand at right and below the figure's right hand at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure may sit on a small mound. Tightly cross-hatched lines to the right of the figure's torso may suggest a dark background sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The middle section of the plate is smaller than the surrounding designs and depicts a series of geometric and linear designs. The top row of designs includes a triangle at left, a circle at center, and a square at right, as well as several linear forms in between and around the row. A semi-circular line surrounds the lower portion of the middle section. Both straight and squiggled lines are visible inside the semi-circle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Like the upper portion, the third, lowest portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure appears to sit on grassy ground or kneel on his right knee; his body is slightly twisted or bent to the left. His left leg is bent forward and his left foot is prominent. His right arm is bent and at his side with his left hand braced against the ground at left. His left arm is bent at a right angle and his left hand is also braced on the ground or a rock at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>severed head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the figure's left hand, two severed heads that face forward are visible in the lower right corner. The head at right appears to have eyes raised and an open mouth. The head at left faces slightly left and has curly hair.  The head on the left may be female; the head on the right may be male.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the lower section of the design appears to sit on grassy ground. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's hand at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower figure appears to brace his hands against the ground or stones both at left and right. Horizontal lines to the left and right of the figure's torso may suggest beams of light in a background sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
