<bad id="esxiv.2-1b" type="spb" work="Experimental Relief Plate" copy="2" copyid="2" institution="ngadc" catalog="essickcat" catid="xiv.2-1b">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Experimental Relief Plate">
                    <main>
                        Experimental Relief Plate</main>
                    <copy> Copy 2</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This work courtesy of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>November 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen</name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
<name>Anna Alden,</name>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
<name>Alison Harper,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Rob Rich,</name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Experimental Relief Plate</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1805.B">c. 1805-22</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1805.C">c. 1805-22</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>16.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.4 x 10.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>relief etching, possibly with a few touches of white-line etching</medium>
                <printingstyle>intaglio<note>In this impression the recessed, etched areas are inked and printed. Accordingly, the relief plateaus appear as white areas. This is the reverse of normal relief printing and constitutes an odd type of intaglio inking and printing.</note></printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The work is inscribed lower left in pencil, "W. Blake fecit".  This inscription is not by Blake.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1964</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Probably the untitled "Blake print" acquired by the dealer Charles Sessler in Feb. 1951 from "Nicholson" for $48 and sold to Carl Zigrosser for $60 in Nov. 1951 (according to Sessler's business records); given by Zigrosser to Lessing J. Rosenwald in June 1961 and presented by Rosenwald in 1964 to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</institution>
                <department>Drawings and Prints</department>
                <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1964.8.1777</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esxiv.2-1b.spb.01" dbi="ESXIV.2-1B.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Experimental Relief Plate</title>
                <title type="alt">Let Him Look Up into the Heavens &#38; Laugh in the Bright Air</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESXIV">(Essick XIV)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This print is sometimes called "Let Him Look Up into the Heavens &#38; Laugh in the Bright Air." The actual subject is not known.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>16.5 x 9.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>This experimental relief plate has three main sections. The upper portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure may sit on a small mound or kneel on his bent right knee. His left leg is bent and in front of his body. The figure's left arm is bent and he appears to grasp a severed human head that faces up and right with his left hand at right. The figure's left arm is either not visible or distorted to appear more snake-like against his body at left. A bird with outstretched wings flies in an area of sky in the upper left corner of the design, and an indeterminate form is visible below and right of the bird. A cat is visible below the severed head at right. Lines and other forms on the ground below the figure may indicate grass or other vegetation. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's hand at right. The middle section of the plate is smaller than the surrounding designs and depicts a series of geometric and linear designs. The top row of designs includes a triangle at left, a circle at center, and a square at right, as well as several linear forms in between and around the row. A shape suggesting a crescent moon is visible below the square at right. A semi-circular line surrounds the lower portion of the middle section. Both straight and squiggled lines are visible inside the semi-circle. Like the upper portion, the third, lowest portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure appears to sit on grassy ground or kneel on his right knee; his body is twisted or bent to the left. His left leg is bent forward. His right arm is bent and at his side with his left hand braced against the ground at left. His left arm is bent at a right angle and his left hand is also braced on the ground or a rock at right. Below his left hand, two severed heads that face forward are visible in the lower right corner. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's hand at right. Horizontal lines to the left and right of the figure's torso may suggest beams of light in a background sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The upper portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure may sit on a small mound or kneel on his bent right knee. His left leg is bent and in front of his body with his left foot prominent. The figure's left arm is bent. The figure appears to grasp a severed human head that faces up and right with his left hand at right. The figure's left arm is either not visible or distorted to appear more snake-like against his body at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>severed head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the upper portion of the design may grasp a severed head that is visible near the right edge of the plate. The head has long, curly hair and faces forward and up. Its mouth appears to be open.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="A">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A bird with outstretched wings flies in an area of sky in the upper left corner of the design, and an indeterminate form is visible below and right of the bird.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="B">
                        <characteristic>cat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A cat is visible below the severed head near the right edge of the design. The cat sits facing forward and left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lines and other forms on the ground below the figure may indicate grass or other vegetation. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's left hand at right and below the figure's right hand at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure may sit on a small mound. The bird flying in the upper left corner may suggest an area of sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crescent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The middle section of the plate is smaller than the surrounding designs and depicts a series of geometric and linear designs. The top row of designs includes a triangle at left, a circle at center, and a square at right, as well as several linear forms in between and around the row. A shape suggesting a crescent moon is visible below the square at right. A semi-circular line surrounds the lower portion of the middle section. Both straight and squiggled lines are visible inside the semi-circle.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>touching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Like the upper portion, the third, lowest portion of the plate depicts a nude male figure who faces forward and is visible from the shoulders down. The figure appears to sit on grassy ground or kneel on his right knee; his body is slightly twisted or bent to the left. His left leg is bent forward and his left foot is prominent. His right arm is bent and at his side with his left hand braced against the ground at left. His left arm is bent at a right angle and his left hand is also braced on the ground or a rock at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>severed head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>open mouth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Below the figure's left hand, two severed heads that face forward are visible in the lower right corner. The head at right appears to have an open mouth. The head at left faces slightly left and has curly hair.  The head on the left may be female; the head on the right may be male.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure in the lower section of the design appears to sit on grassy ground. Additional indeterminate vegetation may be visible above the figure's hand at right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The lower figure appears to brace his hands against the ground or stones both at left and right. Horizontal lines to the left and right of the figure's torso may suggest beams of light in a background sky.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
