<bad id="esxiii.1" type="spb" work="Deaths Door" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="essickcat" catid="XIII" hidden="false"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Deaths Door"><main>Deaths Door</main>,
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the
Library of Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software
grants from Sun Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 26KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918) files ranging in size from 215KB to 685KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH<date>November 2003</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of the following works related to Blake’s development of his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: Preliminary Sketches for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Pencil Sketches; Preliminary Drawings for Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Monochrome Wash Drawings; and Preliminary Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                In addition, we are republishing the following works, previously presented in our Preview mode, to make their designs fully searchable: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the 1808 book listed under Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers; <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, listed under Separate Plates and Plates in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake; and Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the series of twenty finished designs, listed under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings.<lb/><lb/>
                Taken together, these works in a variety of media present a comprehensive overview of one of Blake’s major projects as an illustrator and exemplify his working methods as he developed rough sketches into finished water colors.  The evolution of any one design can be traced via links presented under Related Works in the Archive on the pull-down menus, lower left on the main viewing page for each work. <lb/><lb/>
                In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743.  Cromek originally planned to select twenty of these designs for a deluxe edition of the poem.  Blake launched into the project with great enthusiasm, rapidly sketching out his illustrations in pencil, developing some into wash drawings, and then producing a group of more finished water colors for presentation to Cromek.  In a first prospectus of November 1805, Cromek names Blake as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs.  Blake etched one image, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi>, in white-line, but Cromek rejected it.  The dark power of the print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition.  Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808.  Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century. <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                            
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2014 William Blake Archive.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode</change><date>May 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><compdate value="1805">1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1805">1805</printdate><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>18.6 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>23.5 x 16.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>white-line etching with touches of hand tinting<note>The hand coloring consists only of patches of ink washes very close in color to the printing ink.</note></medium><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>loose</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1986</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>$52,000</price><note>Acquired, probably directly from Blake, by Samuel Palmer at an unknown time; given by Samuel Palmer to his son, Alfred Herbert Palmer, in 1875; sold from A. H. Palmer's collection, Christie's, 20 Feb. 1928, lot 33 (£546 to the dealer Frank T. Sabin); acquired by the dealer Gabriel Wells no later than 1939; sold by Wells to the dealer Charles Sessler Inc., March 1939, with George Richmond's letter to Samuel Palmer of 15 Aug. 1827 concerning Blake's death ($500); sold by Sessler (without the letter) to Charles J. Rosenbloom, Sept. 1939 ($750); inherited by Rosenbloom's widow, Lucile Johnson Rosenbloom, in 1973; acquired from Mrs. Rosenbloom by Robert N. Essick, Jan. 1986.</note></provenance><repository><lb/><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline><lb/></repository></source><desc id="esxiii.1.spb.01" dbi="ESXIII.1.1.SP"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Deaths Door</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="ESXIII">(Essick XIII)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>For Louis Schiavonetti's version of "Death's Door," 
published in the 1808 edition of Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, click <xref targorder="u" doc="BB435.1.comdes.12" from="root" to="ditto">here</xref>.</p></objnote><objsize>18.6 x 12.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="900"/></physdesc><related objectid="bb435.1.comdes.12"/><related objectid="butwba10.1.wc.16"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A tomb is built into a large stone or hill in the lower portion of the design. The doorway is framed by two pillars supporting a lintel and a single step below. There may be a path or road below the tomb, along the lower border of the image. Leafy vegetation appears in the lower right portion of the design, to the right of the right-hand pillar of the door. There is also a plant or vine with spiny leaves and thorns to the left of the left-hand pillar, grass and perhaps leafy plants above the door on the right side of the hill, and grass and perhaps leafy plants above the door on the left side of the hill. The door to the tomb is open. The door has a whorled texture that may indicate wood, and is crossed horizontally and vertically by bands of a different texture (iron?). A dark knocker or handle in the shape of a ring appears in the center of the door, hanging from a securement of a lighter color. The interior of the tomb is dark. A woven mat, possibly made of straw, rests on a bier, bed, or raised platform in the lower right corner of the tomb, but these are far less distinct than in other versions of the image. Vertical and horizontal lines just above the mat may indicate that the back wall of the tomb is made of bricks or stones cut at right angles. An old man with long hair and a beard stands in the lower portion of the design. The figure wears a belted gown and faces right in profile. His right leg is bent with his right heel raised slightly. His left leg is not pictured, but he likely steps up into the doorway. The figure is hunched over and leans on a crutch positioned under his right arm. The figure's right arm is bent at his side and he may hold or touch the crutch with his right hand. The old man's long hair streams out to the right, as though blown by a wind. A nude male with short curly hair sits or kneels above the tomb. The figure faces forward with his head turned up and to the left in profile. His mouth is open and his left eye is raised. Both legs are bent; his right knee is on the ground and his left leg is drawn up. The figure's right arm is at his side and his right hand is not visible. His left arm is bent back; his hand rests on the ground with the palm down and he may be bracing or supporting himself. An aura surrounds the upper half of the figure; beams of light radiate outward. Alternatively, the figure may be positioned in front of the sun at sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>tomb</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>step</characteristic><characteristic>pillar</characteristic><characteristic>lintel</characteristic><characteristic>door</characteristic><characteristic>iron</characteristic><characteristic>wood</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><characteristic>hinge</characteristic><characteristic>circle</characteristic><characteristic>ring</characteristic><characteristic>handle</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>bed</characteristic><characteristic>bier</characteristic><characteristic>mat</characteristic><characteristic>straw</characteristic><characteristic>coil</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><characteristic>brick</characteristic><characteristic>road</characteristic><characteristic>path</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tomb is built into a large stone or hill in the lower portion of the design. The doorway is framed by two pillars supporting a lintel and a single step below. There may be a path or road below the tomb, along the lower border of the image, and there may be small stones on it. The door to the tomb is open. If there is a hinge on the left side of the door, just above the old man's back, it is far less distinct than in other versions of the image. The door has a whorled texture that may indicate wood, and is crossed horizontally and vertically by bands of a different texture (iron?). A dark knocker or handle in the shape of a ring appears in the center of the door, hanging from a securement of a lighter color. The interior of the tomb is dark. A woven mat, possibly made of straw, rests on a stone bed, bier, or raised platform in the lower right corner of the tomb, but these are far less distinct than in other versions of the image. The left end of the mat is coiled. Vertical and horizontal lines just above the mat may indicate that the back wall of the tomb is made of bricks or stones cut at right angles.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>petal</characteristic><characteristic>stem</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><characteristic>grape</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>thorn</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Leafy vegetation appears in the lower portion of the design, to the right of the right-hand pillar of the door. This leafy vegetation includes a fan of flame-like leaves, and a leaf with five or six lobes next to some spirals or squiggles, possibly representing an ivy or grape leaf and the smaller tendrils of an ivy or grape vine. There is also a plant or vine with spiky leaves and thorns to the left of the left-hand pillar, grass and perhaps flowers and perhaps leafy plants above the door on the right side of the hill, and grass and perhaps leafy plants above the door on the left side of the hill.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>belt</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>crutch</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old male with long hair and a beard stands in the lower portion of the design. The figure wears a belted gown and faces right in profile. His right leg is bent with his right heel raised slightly. His left leg is not pictured, but he likely steps up into the doorway. The figure is hunched over and leans on a crutch positioned under his right arm. The figure's right arm is bent at his side and he may hold or touch the crutch with his right hand. His long hair streams out to the right, as though blown by a wind.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>shoulder</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>palm down</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>supporting</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male with short curly hair sits or kneels above the tomb. The figure faces forward with his head turned up and to the left in profile. His mouth is open and his left eye is raised. Both legs are bent; his right knee is on the ground and his left leg is drawn up. His left arm is bent back; his hand rests on the ground with the palm down and he may be bracing or supporting himself, possibly as he rises. The figure’s right hand is hidden. An aura surrounds the upper half of the figure; beams of light radiate outward. Alternatively, the figure may be positioned in front of the sun.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>darkness</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Darkness or shadow fill and surround the tomb, suggesting that this is a night scene. Alternatively, the beams of light radiating from the nude male or from behind him, combined with the semidarkness to the left of the tomb (lighter than the surrounding darkness) may indicate sunlight just entering or finally leaving the darkness at sunrise or sunset. The sun may appear in the sky behind the nude male.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="8"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="esxiii.1.spb.01.01" justify="left" indent="50">DEATHS<note>The title inscription (lines 1-2) is etched in white-line on the right entry post of the tomb.</note></l><l n="esxiii.1.spb.01.02" justify="left" indent="51">DOOR</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>