<bad id="esxvii.1-1a" type="spb" work="The Chaining of Orc" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="essickcat" catid="xvii.1-1a">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Chaining of Orc">
                    <main> The Chaining of Orc</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB
                to 1600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November 2019</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of nineteen separate prints designed and etched or engraved by Blake. The original works are housed in seven collections, including the Bodleian Library, British Museum, Robert N. Essick collection, Fitzwilliam Museum, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and National Gallery of Art, Washington. These separate prints join two others, <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, and four series of prints, all previously published, to complete this important category of Blake's endeavors as a printmaker.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
The new group of nineteen includes Blake’s first separate engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, executed while still an apprentice, and two of his masterpieces in mixed-method etching/engraving, the large <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> plates. <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi>, <hi rend="i">Lucifer and the Pope in Hell</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> depict Blake's response to the political revolutions of the late eighteenth century. Blake printed these three, plus <hi rend="i">A Dream of Thiralatha</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, in colors as part of his development of relief and planographic color printing in the mid-1790s. Other plates, ranging from <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> lithograph and <hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi>, testify to Blake's lifelong experimentation with innovative graphic techniques. He produced <hi rend="i">Deaths Door</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Virgil Relief Etching</hi> as book illustrations but they were never published as such and exist only as unique, separate impressions. Introductions to each work offer information on medium, changes in state, dating, and subject. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> etching/engraving, sometimes considered a separate plate, is included among the Illuminated Books in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
Late in his career, c. 1820-25 or even extending into his final year, Blake returned to several of his earlier separate engravings, dramatically revising the interplay of darkness and light in their designs and adding new inscriptions on some plates that alter their meaning. These final states of <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi>, <hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi>, and Blake's largest and most ambitious print, <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, are included, along with extant earlier states. The publication of these and other multiple states and printings offer insights into Blake's development as a printmaker and changes in his thematic interests over several decades.
                <lb/>
                <lb/> 
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/> This image copyright © 2019 National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C. <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University
                    of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer,</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation</change>
                <date>November 2017</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill 
                    <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
<name>Michael Fox</name>
<resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
<name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
<resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
<name>Grant Glass</name>
<resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
<name>Eric Loy</name>
<resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
<name>Ashley Reed</name>
<name>Nikolaus Wasmoen</name>
<name>Laura Whitebell</name>
<resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
<name>Mark Crosby</name>
<resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
<name>Anna Alden,</name>
<name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
<name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
<name>Alison Harper,</name>
<name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
<name>Rachael Isom,</name>
<name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
<name>Mary Learner,</name>
<name>Rob Rich,</name>
<name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
<name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
<name>Lisa Vandenbossche</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date>September 2002</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum, </name>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Dickens</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>Sarah Trippensee, </name>
                    <name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title> *The Chaining of Orc* </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator,
                        </role><role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1812.A">1812<note>The final digit of the inscribed date is unclear;
                        the date may be 1813.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1812.A">c. 1812-13</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>11.1 x 8.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>11.5 x 8.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>relief etching (?)<note>This work is probably a relief etching, although the
                        technique for producing the stipple-like tones has never been determined.
                        Blake may have used some form of aquatint to achieve this affect. The print
                        may have been tinted with thin wash upper left.</note></medium>
                <printingstyle>relief<note>It appears as though both the relief lines and plateaus
                        and the etched recesses have been lightly inked and
                    printed.</note></printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none on the printed leaf<note>The single pen and ink framing line is on the mount, not on the leaf on which the etching is printed.</note></framelines>
                <binding>none<note>The print is mounted in a window cut into a leaf of
                    paper.</note></binding>
                <stabholes>None on the print itself. There are stab holes along the left edge of the
                    mount.</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D. C.</name>
                <date>1943</date>
                <dealer>A. S. W. Rosenbach</dealer>
                <price>$450</price>
                <note>Probably inherited from Blake by his wife Catherine in 1827; probably acquired
                    by Frederick Tatham upon Catherine Blake's death in 1831; acquired by George A.
                    Smith and bound by him in "about 1853" (Bentley page 337) with other works by
                    Blake, including the manuscript "Order" of the *Songs of Innocence and of
                    Experience*; the volume offered, presumably by Smith, at a Puttick and Simpson
                    auction, London, 3-4 July 1863 (&#163;15.15.s., possibly bought-in by Smith
                    given the reappearance of the volume in the Smith auction of 1880); the volume
                    offered by the dealer Bernard Quaritch, 1864 *Catalogue of Books*, item 6521,
                    possibly on consignment from, or in partnership with, Smith (&#163;21); the
                    volume sold by Smith, Christie's, 1 April 1880, lot 168 (&#163;66 to Quaritch);
                    the volume apparently lent by Quaritch to William Muir, who used some works as
                    the basis for his facsimiles; the volume offered by Quaritch, Oct. 1883
                    *Catalogue of Works on the Fine Arts*, item 10,252 (&#163;80), May 1885
                    catalogue, *William Blake's Original Drawings*, page 2, no item number
                    (&#163;80), and 1887 *General Catalogue of Books*, volume 2, item 10,252
                    (&#163;80); the volume acquired by Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge between 1892 and
                    1906; the volume sold from the Macgeorge collection, Sotheby's, 1 July 1924, lot
                    133 (&#163;345 to the dealer E. Parsons &#38; Sons); the volume, possibly with
                    some leaves removed, offered by Maggs Bros., 1924 catalogue 456, item 53
                    (&#163;630); the volume acquired no later than 1927 by George C. Smith who
                    disbound the volume and rebound this print with three others by Blake, *Albion
                    rose* Copy 2D, *The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder* Copy 3G, and *The Man
                    Sweeping the Interpreter's Parlour* Copy 2K; the volume of four prints sold from
                    George C. Smith's collection, Parke-Bernet, 2 Nov. 1938, lot 42 ($450 to the
                    dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach acting for Lessing J. Rosenwald); disbound and given
                    by Rosenwald to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., in 1943.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>National Gallery of Art, Washington</institution>
                <department>Drawings and Prints</department>
                <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1943.3.8975</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esxvii.1-1a.spb.01" dbi="ESXVII.1-1A.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Chaining of Orc</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESXVII">(Essick XVII)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>11.1 x 8.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In this print, two figures stand above a supine figure against
                        what may be a background of flames. Lying supine with his head at left near
                        the lower edge of the composition, a nude male figure bends his head back
                        and opens his mouth widely. He may look up toward the standing figures
                        above. He has short hair and an area of flames(?) may encircle his head.
                        Both arms are extended outward from his body with his left arm at 45 degrees
                        and his right arm at 135 degrees. Shackles are visible around both wrists
                        and appear to link the figure to the ground below. His torso is twisted
                        slightly forward. His legs are together and shackles are also visible around
                        both ankles. This figure is Orc, the spirit of revolution here restrained.
                        The ground below the figure may be a rock or earth covered in flame-like
                        forms, perhaps grass or other vegetation. Above Orc, a female and a male
                        figure stand facing forward on what may be a rock or higher ground. At left,
                        the nude female figure bends forward and left with legs spread and grasps
                        her head with both hands, as if in mourning or despair. She has long curly
                        hair and a circle, perhaps a halo, is visible around her head. She may be
                        Enitharmon, Orc's mother. At right, the nude male figure stands with legs
                        spread in a contrapposto position. He leans slightly to the left and turns
                        his head to look left and down, perhaps toward the female figure and/or the
                        figure lying below. His arms, with elbows bent, are raised over his head,
                        with his hands raised, palms out, and the fingers of both hands spread
                        apart. His hair is short and his mouth may be open, and he may be speaking
                        or crying out in despair. Like the female figure beside him, a circle that
                        suggests a halo is visible around his head; spiky lines that may indicate
                        beams of light extend outward from his halo. This may be Los, Orc's father.
                        Alternatively, the couple has been identified as Adam and Eve, or as the
                        "Dark virgin" and Urthona (another name for Los). To the right of the male
                        figure's legs, a stone(?) is visible with Blake's signature and date. In the
                        lower left corner of the composition, to the left of the supine figure's
                        head, a structure with a domed roof is visible. A steeple topped with a
                        cross stands in the middle of the dome, which suggests the structure in a
                        church. This structure may suggest St. Paul's Cathedral in London. The
                        majority of the background is indistinguishable, although an area of flames
                        may be visible above the church at left. There may be clouds in the sky to
                        the left of the standing male figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lying supine with his head at left near the lower edge of the
                            composition, a nude male figure bends his head back and opens his mouth
                            widely. He may be speaking or crying out, and his expression suggests
                            pain or terror. He may look up toward the standing figures above. He has
                            short hair and an area of flames(?) may encircle his head. Both arms are
                            extended outward from his body with his left arm at 45 degrees and his
                            right arm at 135 degrees. Shackles are visible around both wrists and
                            appear to link the figure to the ground below. His left palm is clearly
                            turned down. His torso is twisted slightly forward. His legs are
                            together and shackles are also visible around both ankles. This figure
                            is Orc, the spirit of revolution here restrained.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The ground below the supine figure Orc may be a stone or earth
                            covered in fire or flame-like forms, perhaps grass or other
                            vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The ground below the supine figure Orc may be a stone or earth
                            covered in fire or flame-like forms, perhaps grass or other
                            vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands on face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mourning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Enitharmon</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Eve</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>virgin</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above Orc, a female and a male figure stand facing forward on
                            what may be a rock or higher ground. At left, the nude female figure
                            bends forward and left with legs spread and grasps her head with both
                            hands, as if in mourning or despair. She may be crying. She has long
                            curly hair and a circle, perhaps a halo, is visible around her head. Her
                            legs are bent and her right foot is lifted slightly. Her genitals are
                            prominent. She may be Enitharmon, Orc's mother. Alternatively, she has
                            been identified as Eve, or as the "Dark virgin."</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised upward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>crying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Los</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Adam</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Urthona</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Above Orc, a female and a male figure stand facing forward on
                            what may be a rock or higher ground. At right, the nude male figure
                            stands with legs spread in a contrapposto position. He leans slightly to
                            the left and turns his head to look left and down, perhaps toward the
                            female figure and/or the figure lying below. His arms, with elbows bent,
                            are raised over his head, with his hands raised, palms out, and the
                            fingers of both hands spread apart. His hair is short and his mouth may
                            be open, and he may be speaking or crying out in despair. His genitals
                            are prominent. Like the female figure beside him, a circle that suggests
                            a halo is visible around his head; spiky lines that may indicate beams
                            of light extend outward from his halo. This may be Los, Orc's father.
                            Alternatively, he has been identified as Adam, or as Urthona (another
                            name for Los).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the male figure's legs, a stone(?) is visible
                            with Blake's signature and date.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dome</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>church</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>St. Paul's Cathedral</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>London</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In the lower left corner of the composition, to the left of
                            the supine figure's head, a structure with a domed roof is visible. A
                            steeple topped with a cross stands in the middle of the dome, which
                            suggests the structure in a church. This structure may suggest St.
                            Paul's Cathedral in London.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The majority of the background is indistinguishable, although
                            an area of flames may be visible above the church at left. There may be
                            clouds in the sky to the left of the standing male
                            figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esxvii.1-1a.spb.01.01" justify="left" indent="60">Type by</l>
                    <l n="esxvii.1-1a.spb.01.02" justify="left" indent="60">W Blake</l>
                    <l n="esxvii.1-1a.spb.01.03" justify="left" indent="60">181<unclear resp="RR">2</unclear><note>The final digit of the inscribed date is obscured by the background; the date may be 1813.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
