<bad id="esxv.1-1a" type="spb" work="Enoch" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="essickcat" catid="xv.1-1a">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Enoch">
                    <main> Enoch</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 177KB
                to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>

            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/> This image copyright © 2018 British Museum <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                    </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,
                    </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                        Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Technical
                        Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>*Enoch*</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Georg Jacob Vollweiler(?)<role>printer. Printing a lithograph requires
                        a special press. Vollweiler, the London agent for Alois Senefelder, the
                        inventor of lithography, may have supplied Blake with the lithographic stone
                        and also printed this work.</role>
                </origination>

                <compdate value="1806.A">c. 1806-07</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1806.A">c. 1806-07</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>21.7 x 31.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22.6 x 31.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>lithography on white lyas stone<note>According to an inscription by George
                        Cumberland on the verso of an impression of *Enoch* formerly in the
                        collection of Edward Croft-Murray and now in the Metropolitan Museum of Art,
                        New York, Blake delineated his design with a mixture of asphaltum and
                        linseed oil, rather than the customary chalk or lithographic ink, on white
                        lyas stone.</note></medium>
                <printingstyle>planographic</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>1<note>A single framing line is contiguous with the edges of the
                        image.</note></framelines>
                <binding>Mounted on a leaf of wove paper in turn bound as leaf 93 in a volume of
                    miscellaneous lithographs by other artists.</binding>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1874</date>
                <dealer>James Rimmell &#38; Son</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Thomas Fisher (according to the British Museum catalogue); the dealer James
                    Rimell &#38; Son, bound into a collection of early lithographs and one
                    engraving; the volume sold by Rimell in July 1874 to the British Museum.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1874,0711.1028</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esxv.1-1A.spb.01" dbi="ESXV.1-1A.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">Enoch</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESXV">(Essick XV)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objsize>21.7 x 31.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>In this lithograph, an old male figure sits facing forward on a
                        raised plinth-like platform in the center of the composition. He has long
                        hair and a beard and wears a gown. His arms are extended downward and he
                        appears to hold an open book against his lower legs. His legs are bent with
                        his right knee on the floor in a kneeling position. His left foot is visible
                        beneath his gown. He may sit in a chair, the arms of which are visible on
                        either side of his legs. This figure is Enoch, who is described in Genesis
                        5:22-29 as having walked with God. Several sources describe Enoch as the
                        first man to learn writing. Three younger, smaller figures sit or stand
                        around the central old man, who may be their father. All hold instruments of
                        an art. The figure at right, who appears to be nude, sits facing left and
                        bends forward. The figure is likely male(?) and has short hair. His arms are
                        bent and rest on his legs, which are also bent beneath him. He holds an open
                        book and, in his right hand, a long pen or quill. A second nude, male figure
                        stands facing left to the left of the old male figure. He has short hair and
                        bends his head forward. He holds a paintbrush in his right hand and a
                        palette in his left. Below and to the left of this figure, a female figure
                        sits facing right on the corner of the raised platform. She has long hair
                        and wears a gown. She is bending forward and rests a lyre between her legs.
                        She appears to play the instrument with her right hand, which is raised. Her
                        legs are bent beneath her. The platform on which these four figures sit or
                        stand has two tiers. Each tier has an arch-like design on the front. The
                        ground below the platform along the lower edge of the design is grassy. Two
                        groups of flying or hovering figures who may be angels frame the central
                        group. The pair of figures at right fly or hover facing left and away. The
                        rightmost figure, who has short hair and wears a gown, turns his(?) head to
                        face left. He may raise his left arm to point toward the tablet or piece of
                        paper held by the figure at left with his left hand. His left foot is
                        visible beneath his gown. The second figure from the right appears to be a
                        nude male who twists slightly to the right, perhaps to look toward his
                        companion at right. He has short curly hair and extends his straight legs
                        backward slightly. He holds a page of Hebrew text in his left hand. The
                        group of three flying or hovering figures at left face right. The rightmost
                        of these figures is a male figure with curly hair. He appears to wear a
                        semi-transparent gown with a long slit rising above his right leg. His head
                        is bent down. His arms are bent and at his side, and he appears to hold a
                        scroll or piece of paper with both hands. He may be reading. His legs are
                        crossed at the ankle and his feet are pointed down. The leftmost figure in
                        this group, who has long hair, hovers or flies facing right and wears a long
                        gown or cloak, obscuring the body from the shoulders down. The figure's
                        gender is indistinguishable. The figure's right leg appears to be bent
                        backward beneath the gown or cloak. Behind this figure at right, the second
                        figure from the left faces right and forward and appears to have short,
                        curly hair. Only the head of this figure is visible. Leafy, twisted
                        grapevines grow upward along the sides of the design and extend partially
                        toward the center of the top edge. A large cluster of grapes is visible at
                        the base of each plant in the lower right and left corners. Diagonal lines,
                        likely suggesting beams of light or radiance, emanate from the top center of
                        the design where there is an area of void. The edges of clouds may be
                        visible against both the upper halves of the right and left sides of the
                        design.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Enoch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>In this lithograph, an old male figure sits facing forward on
                            a raised platform in the center of the composition. He has long hair and
                            a beard and wears a gown. His arms are extended downward and he appears
                            to hold an open book against his lower legs. His legs are bent with his
                            right knee on the floor in a kneeling position. His left foot is visible
                            beneath his gown. He may sit in a chair whose arms are visible on either
                            side of his legs. This figure may be the biblical figure Enoch, who is
                            described in Genesis 5:22-29 as having walked with God. Several sources
                            describe Enoch as the first man to learn writing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The old male figure in the center of the design holds an open
                            book against his lower legs. Four Hebrew letters are visible on the left
                            page of the book. This figure may sit in a chair, the arms of which are
                            visible on either side of his legs.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>writing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three younger, smaller figures sit or stand around the central
                            old man, who may be their father. All hold instruments of an art. The
                            figure at right, who appears to be nude, sits facing left and bends
                            forward with head down. The figure is likely male(?) and has short hair.
                            His arms are bent and rest on his legs, which are also bent beneath him.
                            He holds an open book and, in his right hand, a long pen or quill. He
                            may be writing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>book</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>quill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pen</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The seated youth to the right of the central male figure holds
                            an open book on his knees and a quill or pen in his right
                            hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>painting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>artist</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three younger, smaller figures sit or stand around the central
                            old man, who may be their father. All hold instruments of an art. A
                            second nude, male figure stands facing left to the left of the old male
                            figure. He has short hair and bends his head forward. He holds a
                            paintbrush in his right hand and a palette in his left. He may be
                            painting.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>brush</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palette</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The standing youth to the left of the central male figure
                            holds a palette with paint in his left hand and a brush in his right
                            hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hand raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three younger, smaller figures sit or stand around the central
                            old man, who may be their father. All hold instruments of an art. On the
                            leftmost corner of the central platform, a female figure sits facing
                            right. She has long hair and wears a gown. She is bending forward and
                            rests a lyre between her legs. She appears to play the instrument with
                            her right hand, which is raised. Her legs are bent beneath
                            her.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>lyre</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The youth seated on the leftmost corner of the central
                            platform holds a lyre in her lap. She appears to play the instrument
                            with her raised right hand.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The plinth-like platform, possibly made of carved stone, on
                            which the central four figures sit or stand has two tiers or steps. Each
                            tier has an arch design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The platform on which these four figures sit or stand has two
                            tiers. Each tier has an arch-like design on the front and may be covered
                            with grass(?). The ground below the platform along the lower edge of the
                            design is also grassy.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of flying or hovering figures who may be angels
                            frame the central group. The pair of figures at right fly or hover
                            facing left and away. The rightmost figure, who has short hair and wears
                            a gown, turns his(?) head to face left. He may raise his left arm to
                            point toward the page of Hebrew text held by the figure at left with his
                            left hand. He appears to look toward the text, which he may read. His
                            left foot is visible beneath his gown.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of flying or hovering figures who may be angels
                            frame the central group. The pair of figures at right fly or hover
                            facing left and away. The second figure from the right appears to be a
                            nude male who twists slightly to the right, perhaps to look toward his
                            companion at right. He has short curly hair and extends his straight
                            legs backward slightly. He holds a page of Hebrew text in his left hand.
                            Both arms are bent upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="B">
                        <characteristic>text</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Hebrew letters</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The second figure from the right who flies or hovers holds in
                            his left hand a piece of paper or tablet containing two lines of Hebrew
                            text (see the Transcription). The figure to his right appears to point
                            toward the text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>semi-transparent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of flying or hovering figures who may be angels
                            frame the central group. The group of three figures at left face right.
                            The rightmost of these figures is a male figure with curly hair. He
                            appears to wear a semi-transparent gown with a long slit rising above
                            his right leg. His head is bent down. His arms are bent and at his side,
                            and he appears to hold a scroll or piece of paper with both hands. He
                            may be reading. His legs are crossed at the ankle and his feet are
                            pointed down.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>paper</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The third figure from the left who flies or hovers facing
                            right holds with both hands a scroll or piece of paper which he may be
                            reading.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of flying or hovering figures who may be angels
                            frame the central group. The group of three figures at left face right.
                            The leftmost figure in this group, who has long hair and perhaps an open
                            mouth, hovers or flies facing right and wears a long gown or cloak,
                            obscuring the body from the shoulders down. The figure's gender is
                            indistinguishable. The figure's right leg appears to be bent backward
                            beneath the gown or cloak.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two groups of flying or hovering figures who may be angels
                            frame the central group. The group of three figures at left face right.
                            The middle figure in this group faces right and forward and appears to
                            have short, curly hair. Only the head of this figure is
                            visible.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>grape</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Leafy, twisted grapevines grow upward along the sides of the
                            design and extend partially toward the center of the top edge. A large
                            cluster of grapes is visible at the base of each plant in the lower
                            right and left corners.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Diagonal lines, likely suggesting beams of light or radiance,
                            emanate from the top center of the design where there is an area of
                            void. The edges of clouds may be visible against both the upper halves
                            of the right and left sides of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="6"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esxv.1-1a.spb.01.01" justify="left" indent="30">
                        <foreign lang="hebrew">ואננו כי לקח</foreign>
                        <note>Lines 1-2, written on a piece of paper or tablet held by a hovering figure upper right, are from Genesis 5:24. Their English
                            translation is "And Enoch walked with God" (Essick page 55). Sheila Spector
                            points out "the omission in [the two figures'] text of the י (*yod*, symbol of the
                            Divinity), which is the third letter (Trinity) of the first word (God)
                            in the biblical text" (“Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew," *Blake/An
                            Illustrated Quarterly* 37.2 [fall 2003]: 71). Hence, the correct spelling of this line would be
                            "וא[י]ננו כי לקח".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="esxv.1-1a.spb.01.02" justify="left" indent="31">
                        <foreign lang="hebrew">אתו אלהים</foreign>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="5"/>
                <lg>
                    <l n="esxv.1-1a.spb.01.03" justify="left" indent="20">
                        <foreign lang="hebrew">חנוך</foreign>
                        <note>This text appears just left of the inner margin of the verso of a leaf in an open book held by the central seated figure. English translation is "Enoch." As Sheila Spector explains, "While the
                            lettering is lexigraphically correct, the text is located on the wrong
                            half of the page. Because Hebrew is read from right to left, the name
                            should either be in the center, as the title, or at the right margin."
                            (“Blake’s Graphic Use of Hebrew”, *Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly*
                            37.2 [fall 2003]: 70).</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="4"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esxv.1-1a.spb.01.04" justify="left" indent="35">WBlake. inv</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
