<bad id="esxxi.1" type="spb" work="George Cumberland's Card" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="essick" catalog="essickcat" catid="XXI.1J"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="George Cumberland's Card"><main>George Cumberland's Card</main>,
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>

            </respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 37KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC
            10918)
            files ranging in size from 67KB to 130KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
               
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died.
                <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”  <lb/><lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London.  His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.  Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite extraordinary thing.  If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/>
                In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.  We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/>
                Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.

            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher, the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2013 William Blake Archive</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Illustration description, final proofing and publication</change><date>February-March 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Technical Consultant:</resp><name>Joseph Ryan</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Duncan Graham, </name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff, </name><name>Adam McCune, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Ted Scheinman, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Alia Wegner, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD created</change><date>September 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image color corrected</change><date>May 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer: </resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Michelle Langston, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Natalie Moix, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Lily Todorinova, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image acquired and catalogued</change><date>March 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer: </resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Michelle Langston, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Natalie Moix, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Lily Todorinova, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*George Cumberland's Card*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>engraver</role></origination><origination>anonymous<role>engraver.  Cumberland's name, line 1 of the text, was probably executed by a writing engraver rather than Blake. Blake's signature (line 2), his age and the year the plate was executed (line 3), were almost certainly executed by Blake.</role></origination><origination>anonymous<role>printer.  The identity of the printer of this impression is not known.</role></origination><compdate value="1827">1827</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="unknown">printdate unknown<note>Impressions from the plate were probably printed at various times in the nineteenth century and possibly even in the first half of the twentieth century.  "The plate is believed to be still in existence, and it is probable ... that many of the existing impressions on paper were taken from it in recent times," according to Geoffrey Keynes, *Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates* (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956) 59.</note></printdate><numberobj>1</numberobj><objsize>3.1 x 7.8 cm.<note>The platemark measures 3.3 x 8.1 cm.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1</numberleaves><leafsize>5.7 x 10.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>Engraving, possibly with drypoint</medium><support>laid paper<note>The chain lines run horizontally, 2.2 cm. apart.</note></support><watermark>none</watermark><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>loose</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Robert N. Essick</name><date>1978</date><dealer>Maggs Bros.</dealer><price>£125</price><note>Printing date and early history not known.  Acquired in June 1978 by the dealer Maggs Bros. as part of a large collection of bookplates; sold to Robert N. Essick in Aug. 1978.</note></provenance><repository><lb/><institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution><addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline><lb/></repository></source><desc id="esxxi.1.spb.01" dbi="ESXXI.1.1J.SP"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Mr. Cumberland.</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber><Objcode code="ESXXI">(Essick XXI)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>3.1 x 7.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="500" height="750"/></physdesc><related objectid="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04" ovp="noindex"/><illusdesc><illustration type="plate"><illusobjdesc>A male with short curly hair flies or hovers in the upper left portion of the design. He faces forward with his head turned slightly down and to the right. The figure is at least partly nude; traces of a skirt or other drapery cover his genitals. An aura or halo of light radiates outward from the figure's head and torso. His right leg is bent slightly and both legs extend down and to the left. The figure's left arm is raised horizontally and the palm of his left hand is turned up. He may be pointing to the right. His right arm is raised horizontally and he holds a sickle in his right hand. Three female figures fly or hover in the upper portion of the design. The figure furthest left has short hair or perhaps wears a cap. She faces forward with her head turned up and to the left. The figure is partly nude with traces of a skirt or other drapery visible at her right hip. Her right leg extends slightly to the left and her left leg is not pictured. Both arms are raised at 135 degrees and her palms may be turned up. The figure second from the left is gowned or at least wears a skirt. She faces forward and her long hair flows to the left as if blown by a wind. Her left leg extends slightly to the left and her right leg is not pictured. The figure's right arm is raised horizontally and her left arm is bent upward at 135 degrees; neither hand is clearly visible. The figure furthest right is gowned and has long hair. She faces forward with her head turned up. The figure's right arm is raised horizontally. Her left arm is raised vertically and the palm of her left hand may be turned up. A nude male(?) with short hair strides in the upper right portion of the design. He faces right in profile. Both legs are bent and spread apart, and he may run to the right. The figure's left arm is raised at 135 degrees. His right arm is bent back and he holds a stick in his right hand; the figure likely plays with the hoop pictured to the right. A figure of uncertain gender with short hair flies or hovers in the lower right portion of the design. He or she is seen from behind and faces away with his or her head turned to the left. The figure is partly nude and a (transparent?) skirt or other drapery covers his or her buttocks. The left leg extends to the left and the right leg is bent with the sole of the right foot turned out towards the viewer. Both arms are raised at 135 degrees; the figure holds a distaff in his or her right hand and a thread in the left hand. A spindle hangs from the thread to the left of the figure. Given the distaff, spindle, and thread, the figure suggests the classical Fate, Clotho, who spins the thread of life.  If this allusion is relevant, then the figure upper left (in spite of his gender) hints at the Fate Atropos who cuts the thread of life. A female(?) with short hair appears in the lower half of the design. She may be partly nude and wears a skirt or other drapery. Both legs are bent and the figure's left foot is raised on tiptoe. Her right leg extends backward, to the right. The figure's right arm is raised vertically and her left arm is raised at 135 degrees; she holds a string in each hand. The strings loosely connect to two birds flying above on outstretched wings. Perhaps the strings are snares that have caught the birds. A gowned female(?) with long hair kneels in the lower left corner of the design. Both legs are bent and her right knee rests on the ground with the right foot raised on tiptoe. She faces right in profile and bends forward with her head turned down slightly. Both arms are raised at 45 degrees and extend to the right. She touches or holds an object with both hands. This object may be a cage-like trap (to catch birds?) consisting of a net supported with a stick. Grain stems with visible tassels appear in the lower right portion of the design. The stems arch slightly to the right. Horizontal lines throughout the design indicate sky; white space in the center may suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>sickle</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>halo</characteristic><characteristic>aura</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>Fates</characteristic><characteristic>Atropos</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male with short curly hair flies or hovers in the upper left portion of the design. He faces forward with his head turned slightly down and to the right. The figure is at least partly nude; traces of a skirt or other drapery cover his genitals. An aura or halo of light radiates outward from the figure's head and torso. His right leg is bent slightly and both legs extend down and to the left. The figure's left arm is raised horizontally and the palm of his left hand is turned up. he may be pointing to the right. His right arm is raised horizontally and he holds a sickle in his right hand. In spite of his gender, the figure hints at the classical Fate Atropos who cuts the thread of life (see the figure lower right with distaff, thread, and spindle—possibly an allusion to the Fate Clotho).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three female figures fly or hover in the upper portion of the design. The figure furthest left has short hair or perhaps wears a cap. She faces forward with her head turned up and to the left. The figure is partly nude with traces of a skirt or other drapery visible at her right hip. Her right leg extends slightly to the left and her left leg is not pictured. Both arms are raised at 135 degrees and her palms may be turned up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three female figures fly or hover in the upper portion of the design. The figure second from the left is gowned or at least wears a skirt. She faces forward and her long hair flows to the left as if blown by a wind. Her left leg extends slightly to the left and her right leg is not pictured. The figure's right arm is raised horizontally and her left arm is bent upward at 135 degrees; neither hand is clearly visible.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>palm up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three female figures fly or hover in the upper portion of the design. The figure furthest right is gowned and has long hair. She faces forward with her head turned up. Her legs extend down and to the left. The figure's right arm is raised horizontally. Her left arm is raised vertically and the palm of her left hand may be turned up.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>stick</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>hoop</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male(?) with short hair strides in the upper right portion of the design. He faces right in profile. Both legs are bent and spread apart, and he may run to the right. The figure's left arm is raised at 135 degrees. His right arm is bent back and he holds a stick in his right hand; the figure likely plays with the hoop pictured to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>transparent</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>buttocks</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>distaff</characteristic><characteristic>spindle</characteristic><characteristic>thread</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>Fates</characteristic><characteristic>Clotho</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure of uncertain gender with short hair flies or hovers in the lower right portion of the design. He or she is seen from behind and faces away with his or her head turned to the left. The figure is partly nude and a (transparent?) skirt or other drapery covers his or her buttocks. The left leg extends to the left and the right leg is bent with the sole of the right foot turned out towards the viewer. Both arms are raised at 135 degrees; the figure holds a distaff in his or her right hand and a thread in the left hand. A spindle hangs from the thread to the left of the figure. Given the distaff, spindle, and thread, the figure suggests the classical Fate, Clotho, who spins the thread of life.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>breasts</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hand raised</characteristic><characteristic>string</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female(?) figure (note the suggestion of female breasts) with short hair appears in the lower half of the design. She may be partly nude and wears a skirt or other drapery. Both legs are bent and the figure's left foot is raised on tiptoe. Her right leg extends backward, to the right. The figure's right arm is raised vertically and her left arm is raised at 135 degrees; she holds a string in each hand. The strings loosely connect to two birds flying above on outstretched wings. The strings may be snares that have caught the birds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>cage</characteristic><characteristic>net</characteristic><characteristic>stick</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female(?) with long hair kneels in the lower left corner of the design. Both legs are bent and her right knee rests on the ground with the right foot raised on tiptoe. She faces right in profile and bends forward with her head turned down slightly. Both arms are raised at 45 degrees and extend to the right. She touches or holds an object with both hands. This object may be a cage-like trap (for catching birds?) consisting of a net supported by a stick.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grain stem</characteristic><characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Grain stems with visible tassels appear in the lower right portion of the design. The stems arch slightly to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Horizontal lines throughout the design indicate sky; white space in the center may suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="esxxi.1.spb.01.01" justify="left" indent="22">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Cumberland.<note>Cumberland's name was probably executed by a writing engraver rather than Blake.</note></l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="esxxi.1.spb.01.02" justify="left" indent="50">WBlake inv &amp; sc:<note>Blake's signature (line 2), his age and the year the plate was executed (line 3), were almost certainly engraved by Blake. Blake was in fact 69 when he died on 12 August 1827. He may have inscribed "70" as his age in anticipation of working on this engraving past what would have been his 70th birthday, 28 November 1827.</note></l><l n="esxxi.1.spb.01.03" justify="left" indent="51">A Æ 70<space extent="2"/>1827<note>See the note on line 2.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>