<bad id="esxx.1-2e" type="spb" work="The Man Sweeping the Interpreter's Parlour" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="ngadc" catalog="essickcat" catid="xx.1-2e">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Man Sweeping the Interpreter's Parlour">
                    <main>
                        The Man Sweeping the Interpreter's Parlour</main>
                    <copy> Copy 1</copy>: electronic edition

</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of 

Rochester;

<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and

<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>

            </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

           and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 12KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC

10918) files ranging in size from 177KB to 3600KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>May 2009</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,

and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be

shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.

Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires

express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the

publisher.

Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been

granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>

         This image copyright © 2018 William Blake Archive.

         <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Michael Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Morgan Lessley,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Kylie Regan,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD creation and image color correction</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
                    <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
                    <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
                    <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli, and</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image cataloguing and metadata collection</change>
                <date/>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;

               <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and

               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue </name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *The Man Sweeping the Interpreter's Parlour*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                
                <compdate value="1822.A">c. 1822<note>The dates of composition and printing are uncertain; see the discussion in Essick pages 107-09.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1822.A">c. 1822</printdate>
                <numberobj>1</numberobj>
                <objorder>1</objorder>
                <objsize>8.0 x 16.1 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.0 x 10.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>white-line etching, possibly with some white-line engraving<note>There is a question about the metal used for the matrix.  It is probably copper, but it may be pewter.  See the discussion in Essick page 110.</note></medium>
                <printingstyle>relief</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Collection of Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>1980</date>
                <dealer>Andrew Edmunds</dealer>
                <price>&#163;2000</price>
                <note>Early history unknown; sold Christie's, 3 Dec. 1980, lot 161 (&#163;2000 to the dealer Andrew Edmunds acting for Robert N. Essick).</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="esxx.1-2e.spb.01" dbi="ESXX.1-2E.1.SP">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">The Man Sweeping the Interpreter's Parlour</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="ESXX">(Essick XX)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc>
                <objnote><p>This impression is in the second state of two.  Inscribed by a later hand (not Blake), "W. Blake" in pencil below the design.  Blake's pencil sketch, *Samson Pulling Down the Pillars of the Temple* (not in Butlin), is on the verso of this impression.</p></objnote>
                <objsize>8.0 x 16.1 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="700"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The design is based on a famous passage in John Bunyan's <hi rend="i">Pilgrim's Progress</hi>.  A winged female figure, a personification of the "Gospel" according to the passage illustrated, stands or walks at left while a bat-winged male figure, a personification of "Law," sweeps at right. The female figure faces right, perhaps to look toward the figure at right, and wears a long gown. Her hair is arranged in a bun and two large folded, feathered(?) wings, perhaps suggesting she is an angel. Her right arm is bent at a right angle by her side. In her right hand, she holds a bowl. Her left arm is raised at 45 degrees and extended to the right. Her hand is turned down with palm facing right, and she appears to drop or throw a liquid(?) on the floor, perhaps from the bowl in her right hand. Her left leg is bent and extended backward to rest on the first step behind her, suggesting she is descending the steps at left. Blake's monogram signature is visible on the side of the lowest step. Diagonal beams of light extend toward this figure from an area of light or radiance in the upper left corner. At right, a nude male figure faces forward and bends right to look down, perhaps toward the smaller winged figure in the lower right corner. He has curly hair and a beard and is muscular. Spiky, bat-like wings extend from his back. Both arms are bent and, with both hands, he holds a broom that he appears to sweep toward the right. His right leg is bent and extended backward. Swirling clouds of dust, caused by the male figure's sweeping, appear in the lower right corner and in the middle of the design between the two largest figures. Three additional male heads and several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. Atop the central swirling cloud, a male head with one spiky bat-wing at left faces forward. The figure appears to have short hair and a mustache. A similar head is visible to the right of the large male figure's hip. This figure faces forward and has short hair that extends horizontally from his head. Left of the male figure's right leg, a third head with a long beard faces forward and leans to the left. In the lower right corner, a small winged figure flies or hovers facing left with body horizontal. The figure's legs appear to be bent upward. Another small winged figure flies or hovers facing left with body horizontal left of the large male figure's right thigh. This figure appears to raise one bent arm upward. Left of the large male figure's left foot, a third winged figure lies on the ground facing away with head at left and wings spread. The figure appears to twist its body to bend right. Its right leg appears to be bent. To the left of this figure, a group of figures that includes at least three figures is visible, though details of this group are unclear. One figure appears to raise an arm horizontally to the right, perhaps to point upward with hand raised.  To the right is a figure (clearer in other impressions), apparently lying prone(?) with arms extended horizontally.  The left-most figure in this group appears to face forward with shoulder hunched.  According to Bunyan's passage illustrated, he man sweeping only stirs up dust, while the woman sprinkles water to settle it and sweeten the room. The parlour represents the heart of man, whose original sin and corruption cannot be settled by the sweeper (the law) but rather can be by the soothing blessing of the woman (the Gospel).</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bowl</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>throwing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>liquid</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Gospel</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure in this composition, a personification of the "Gospel" according to the passage illustrated in John Bunyan's <hi rend="i">Pilgrim's Progress</hi>, stands or walks to the right and may look toward the male figure at right. She wears a long gown. Her hair is arranged in a bun, and she has two large folded, feathered(?) wings, perhaps suggesting she is an angel. Her right arm is bent at a right angle by her side. In her right hand, she holds a bowl. Her left arm is raised at 45 degrees and extended to the right. Her hand is turned down with palm facing right, and she appears to drop or throw a liquid(?) on the floor, perhaps from the bowl in her right hand. Her left leg is bent and extended backward to rest her left foot on tiptoe on the first step behind her, suggesting she is descending the steps at left.  Both feet are prominent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="A">
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Diagonal beams of light extend toward the female figure at left from an area of light or radiance in the upper left corner.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>stairs</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The female figure at left appears to descend three stairs located in the lower left corner of the composition. Blake's signature is visible on the side of the lowest step.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sweeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>broom</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Law</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>At right, a nude male figure who stands facing forward bends right to look down, perhaps toward the smaller winged figure in the lower right corner.  He is a personification of the "Law" according to the passage illustrated in John Bunyan's <hi rend="i">Pilgrim's Progress</hi>. He has curly hair and a beard and is muscular. Spiky, bat-like wings extend from his back. Both arms are bent and, with both hands, he holds a broom that he appears to sweep toward the right. His right leg is bent and extended backward; his left foot is prominent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dust</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Swirling clouds, no doubt dust stirred up by the male figure's sweeping, appear in the lower right corner and in the middle of the design between the two largest figures.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mustache</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three additional male heads and several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. Atop the central swirling cloud, a male head with one spiky bat-wing at left faces forward. The figure appears to have short hair and a mustache.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three additional male heads and several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. A second head is visible to the right of the large male figure's hip. This figure faces forward and has short hair that extends horizontally from his head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three additional male heads and several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. Left of the male figure's right leg, a third head with a long beard faces forward and leans to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. In the lower right corner, a small winged figure flies or hovers facing left with body horizontal. The figure's legs appear to be bent upward. The larger male figure may look at and attempt to sweep this figure away.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. A second small winged figure flies or hovers facing left with body horizontal left of the large male figure's right thigh. This figure appears to raise its head and one bent arm upward.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reclining</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bending right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. Left of the large male figure's left foot, a third winged figure lies or reclines on the ground facing away with head at left and wings spread. The figure appears to twist its body to bend right. Its right leg appears to be bent.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteritic>facing down</characteritic>
                        <characteritic>lying</characteritic>
                        <characteritic>prone</characteritic>
                        <characteristic>shoulders</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Several smaller figures are visible across the right half of the composition. On the ground in the center of the composition, a group of figures that includes at least three figures is visible, though details of this group are unclear. They appear to face right and are positioned to the right of a diagonal log-like(?) object. One figure, second from right in this group, appears to raise an arm horizontally to the right, perhaps to point upward with hand raised.  To the right is a figure (clearer in other impressions), apparently lying prone(?) with arms extended horizontally.  The left-most figure in this group appears to face forward with shoulder hunched.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="20"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="esxx.1-2e.spb.01.01" justify="left" indent="12">in &#38; s</l>
                    <l n="esxx.1-2e.spb.01.02" justify="left" indent="12">WB<note>Blake's signature is in the form of his monogram with a loop from the initials in line 2 arching over the abbreviations for *invenit* and *sculpsit* in line 1.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
