<bad catalog="bentley" catid="A" copy="A" copyid="A" hidden="false" id="europe.a" institution="ycba" type="illbk" work="Europe a Prophecy">
  <header>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <title reg="Europe a Prophecy">
          <main>Europe a Prophecy</main>
          <copy>Copy A</copy>: electronic edition</title>
        <principal>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;

          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and

          <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
          , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
        <respstmt/>
        <sponsor>The
               Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
        <funder/>
      </titlestmt>
      <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
      <extent>1 XML file approx. 258KB; 34 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 170KB to 1100KB</extent>
      <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives
            
        <date>May 2013</date></publicationstmt>
      <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
      <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 
        <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi>
        Copy A. Only nine copies of 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        printed by Blake are extant. In 1794, the date on its title plate, Blake color printed Copies B, C, D, E, F, and G; in 1795 he printed Copies A and H, and in 1821 he printed Copy K. All are in the Archive except Copies C and F, which will be published next year to complete the history of this illuminated book. 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        consists of 18 plates, like its counterpart, 
        <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi>
        , produced the previous year, but most copies, including Copy A, have 17 plates. Only Copies H and K contain Plate 3, a whimsical prefatory statement about the poem's origin. 
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi>
        was the second of Blake's &quot;Continental Prophecies,&quot; followed in 1795 by &quot;Africa&quot; and &quot;Asia,&quot; the two sections of 
        <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
        . Important examples of all three books—
        <hi rend="i">America</hi>
        , 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        , 
        <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
        —are in the Archive. Like the other illuminated books in the Archive, the text and images of 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        Copy A are fully searchable and are supported by the Archive's Compare feature. New protocols for transcription, which produce improved accuracy and fuller documentation in editors' notes, have been applied to Copy A and to all the 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        texts previously published.  
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        Copy A, in the Yale Center for British Art, was printed on large leaves of paper as part of a deluxe set of illuminated books, which included 
        <hi rend="i">America</hi>
        Copy A, 
        <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
        Copy D, and 
        <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
        Copy B, all in the Archive. David Bindman has raised doubts about the coloring in 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        Copy A, suspecting that it may have been added by a later hand, perhaps in the twentieth century. But in our opinion the coloring was done by Blake and his wife Catherine. The frontispiece, with thick dabs of reds and blacks seemingly uncharacteristic of Blake, was probably the result of his experimenting with opaque pigments to create effects similar to his color printing. We see similar opaque reds and blacks applied in like manner in impressions of Plate 8 of 
        <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
        , especially in Copy C. These too were printed and finished in 1795, the year Blake produced his set of 12 large color printed drawings. The color washes of some of the other plates in 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        Copy A, however, appear to be by Catherine Blake (see Joseph Viscomi, 
        <hi rend="i">Blake and the Idea of the Book</hi>
        , 133-34).
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        With the publication of 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        Copy A, the Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of 86 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. In addition to illuminated books, the Archive contains many important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, and water color drawings. 
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        In January the Archive disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Virtual Lightbox has now been re-enabled. Archive users are encouraged to use the latest version of Java compatible with their browsers in order to have the best possible experience with the Lightbox. ImageSizer has not yet been re-enabled, but users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for works in the Archive including 
        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
        Copy A. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the use of Java. 
        <lb/>
        <lb/>
        As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
      <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <userestrict>Copyright © 
      <date>2013</date>
      by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
      <lb/>
      <lb/>
      This work copyright © 2013 Yale Center for British Art.</userestrict>
    <encodingdesc/>
    <profiledesc/>
    <revisiondesc>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
        <date>May 2013</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
                    
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
          <name>Rachel Lee</name>
          <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
          <name>Mark Crosby</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Laura Bell,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Katherine Carlson,</name>
          <name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
          <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
          <name>Adam McCune,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Edward Scheinman,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
          <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
          <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Proofed and prepared for publication</change>
        <date>October 2009</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick,</name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Lauren Cameron,</name>
          <name>Robin Curry,</name>
          <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
          <name>Joseph Lamperez,</name>
          <name>Michelle Langston,</name>
          <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
          <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
          <name>Jennifer Park,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Shaw,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
          <name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Illustration markup created</change>
        <date>September 2007</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick,</name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Kit Curtin,</name>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
          <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
          <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman,</name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
          <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Images color corrected and BAD created</change>
        <date>May-June 2007</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick,</name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>William Shaw</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Ashley Reed</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Kate Attkisson,</name>
          <name>Kit Curtin, </name>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name>
          <name>Sarah Jones,</name>
          <name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name>
          <name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
      <changestmt>
        <change>Images scanned and metadata collected</change>
        <date>January 2004</date>
        <respstmt>
          <resp>Editors: </resp>
          <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               
          <name>Robert Essick, </name>
          University of California, Riverside; and
               
          <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               
          <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
          <name>Andrea Laue</name>
          <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
          <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
          <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
          <name>Sarah H. Ficke, </name>
          <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
          <name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt>
      </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
  </header>
  <objdesc>
    <source>
      <objdescid>
        <objtitle>
          <title>*Europe a Prophecy*</title>
        </objtitle>
        <origination>William Blake 
          <role>author, </role>
          <role>inventor, </role>
          <role>delineator, </role>
          <role>etcher, </role>
          <role>printer, </role>
          <role>colorist</role><note>Several scholars, including David Bindman, have suggested that someone other than Blake or his wife Catherine colored some of the plates in *Europe* Copy A. In our opinion, all the coloring can be attributed to Blake and his wife. The thick black and red colors on Object 1 (Bentley Plate 1, the frontispiece) have been particularly suspect. We believe that the heavy coloring is the product of Blake's experiments with opaque pigments that imitate or complement his color printing effects. Similar coloring can be found in *The Song of Los*, particularly Copy C, Object 2 (Bentley Plate 8). Like these copies of *The Song of Los*, *Europe* Copy A was printed and colored in 1795. For Bindman's views, see his &quot;Afterword on *William Blake: His Art and Times*,&quot; *Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly* 16.4 (spring 1983): 225.</note></origination>
        <origination>Catherine Blake
          <role>printer, </role>
          <role>colorist</role><note>William Blake's wife, Catherine, may have been responsible for most of the coloring of Objects 2-17 (Bentley Plates 2, 4-9, 11-14, 10, 15-18). For discussion, see Joseph Viscomi, *Blake and the Idea of the Book* (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1993) 133-34.</note></origination>
        <imprint>
          <publisher>William Blake</publisher>
          <pubplace>Lambeth</pubplace>
          <date>1794</date>
        </imprint>
        <compdate value="1794.B">1794</compdate>
      </objdescid>
      <objinfo>
        <printdate value="1795.A">1795</printdate>
        <numberobj>17
          <note>This copy does not contain Bentley Plate 3.</note></numberobj>
        <objorder>Bentley Plates 1-2, 4-9, 11-14, 10, 15-18</objorder>
        <objsize>ranging between 23.9 x 17.3 cm. and 23.1 x 16.4 cm.</objsize>
        <numberleaves>17</numberleaves>
        <leafsize>30.5 x 22.0 cm. (Objects 1-5, corresponding to Bentley Plates 1-2, 4-6), 37.3 x 26.4 cm. (Objects 6-17, corresponding to Bentley Plates 7-18)</leafsize>
        <medium>relief and white-line etching with color printing and hand coloring
          <note>The color printing appears only in Objects 1 and 3 (Bentley Plates 1 and 4). See the Notes on Origination, above, for further comments on coloring.</note></medium>
        <printingstyle>relief</printingstyle>
        <inkcolor>brownish-black</inkcolor>
        <support>wove paper</support>
        <watermark>1794/J Whatman
          <note>The watermark appears in Objects 3, 5, 7, 9, 13, and 15 (Bentley Plates 4, 6, 8, 11, 10, and 16).</note></watermark>
        <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
        <pennednumbers>1-15
          <note>The penned numbers, upper right corner of each object, appear in sequence on Objects 3-17 (Bentley Plates 4-9, 11-14, 10, 15-18).</note></pennednumbers>
        <framelines>none</framelines>
        <binding>brown morocco by Riviere and Son</binding>
        <stabholes>originally stabbed through three holes, 8.9 and 7.0 cm. apart</stabholes>
      </objinfo>
      <provenance n="1">
        <name>Yale Center for British Art</name>
        <date>1992</date>
        <dealer>gift</dealer>
        <price>gift</price>
        <note>Possibly the copy acquired by George Romney directly from Blake, c. 1795, and sold from his collection, Christie's, 9 May 1834, in lot 84+, added in pen and ink to at least one copy of the catalogue, with *The Marriage of Heaven and Hell*, possibly copy D (18s. to "Tiffin," possibly Walter E. Tiffin); probably one of the works by Blake acquired by Isaac D'Israeli no later than 1824 and certainly in his collection no later than 1835; 
                    inherited by his son, the Earl of Beaconsfield, in 1848.  Objects 1-5 (Bentley Plates 1, 2, 4-6) were separated from the others by 1856.  
                    Objects 6-17 (Bentley Plates 7-18) were sold from Beaconsfield's collection, Sotheby's, 20 March 1882, lot 57 (£8.5s. to the dealer James Bain, 
                    possibly acting for Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge); this group in the Macgeorge collection no later than 1892.  Objects 1-5 (Bentley Plates 1, 2, 4-6) were sold anonymously at a Hodgson's auction, 
                    London, 14 Jan. 1904, lot 225 (£80 to Hopkins, possibly a dealer acting for Macgeorge).  The two groups of plates were reunited in the Macgeorge collection 
                    no later than 1906; the whole copy sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 1 July 1924, lot 116 (£500 to the dealer Gabriel Wells, possibly acting for George C. Smith); 
                    in Smith's collection no later than 1927; sold from his collection, Parke-Bernet, New York, 2 Nov. 1938, lot 26 ($13,000 to the dealer Charles Sessler, 
                    possibly acting for Moncure Biddle); in Biddle's collection no later than 1939; sold by Biddle through the dealer Thomas J. Gannon to Paul Mellon in 1948; 
                    given by Mellon to the Yale Center for British Art in 1992.</note>
      </provenance>
      <repository>
        <institution>Yale Center for British Art</institution>
        <addressline>1080 Chapel Street</addressline>
        <addressline>Box 208280</addressline>
        <addressline>New Haven, Connecticut 06520-8280</addressline>
        <addressline>Telephone: 203-432-2840</addressline>
        <addressline>Fax: 203-432-7314</addressline>
        <addressline>Email: pdbac@pantheon.yale.edu</addressline>
        <addressline>URL, general: http://ycba.yale.edu</addressline>
        <addressline>Email, Rights and Reproductions: ycba.photorights@yale.edu</addressline>
        <addressline>URL, Rights and Reproductions: http://ycba.yale.edu/departments/depart-ser-rights.html</addressline>
        <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
        <collection>Paul Mellon Collection</collection>
        <repositoryid label="Acquisition number">B1992.8.4 (1-17)</repositoryid>
      </repository>
    </source>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P1" id="europe.a.illbk.01">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1, </objcode>
          <objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode>
          <objcode code="Ki">Keynes i)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>Several Blake scholars have raised doubts about the authorship of the thick black and red colors on Object 1, the frontispiece. We believe that the heavy coloring is by Blake, the product of his experiments with opaque pigments that imitate or complement his color printing effects. Similar coloring can be found in *The Song of Los*, particularly Copy C, Object 2 (Bentley Plate 8). Like these copies of *The Song of Los*, *Europe* Copy A was printed and colored in 1795. See the Copy Information page for further comments on the coloring of this copy.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>23.4 x 16.9 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>An old, nude, but muscular man with long hair and 
beard squats within a circle, perhaps meant to represent the disc 
of the sun.  His hair and beard extend horizontally to the left, 
as though blown by a strong wind from right to left.  His left 
leg is bent at the knee, with both left knee and left foot 
prominent.  His right leg is kneeling, with the lower leg bent 
back, on the edge of the circle.  He is hunched over and looks 
down or has his eyes closed; his left arm is extended down.  He holds a pair of dividers 
or compasses in his left hand, with his forefinger spread away 
from his other fingers.  Slight indications of a robe or some 
sort of drapery appear just right of the figure's left foot.  
Beams of light emanate from the circle, surrounded by clouds 
except where the man's arm extends downward.  Wisps of cloud obscure the face of the circle above the figure's back.  The figure is very 
probably Urizen in the act of creating and/or circumscribing the 
material universe.  This design, perhaps Blake's most famous, has 
also been titled by critics &quot;The Ancient of Days&quot; and &quot;God 
Creating the Universe.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Urizen</characteristic>
            <characteristic>God</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Ancient of Days</characteristic>
            <characteristic>creating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>An old, nude, but muscular man with long hair and 
beard squats within a circle, perhaps meant to represent the disc 
of the sun.  His hair and beard extend horizontally to the left, 
as though blown by a strong wind from right to left.  His left 
leg is bent at the knee, with both left knee and left foot 
prominent.  His right leg is kneeling, with the lower leg bent 
back, on the edge of the circle.  He is hunched over and looks 
down or has his eyes closed; his left arm is extended down.  He holds a pair of dividers 
or compasses in his left hand, with his forefinger spread away 
from his other fingers.  Slight indication of a robe or some sort 
of drapery appear just right of the figure's left foot.  The 
figure is very probably Urizen in the act of creating and/or 
circumscribing the material universe.  This design, perhaps 
Blake's most famous, has also been titled by critics &quot;The Ancient 
of Days&quot; and &quot;God Creating the Universe.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sphere</characteristic>
            <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
            <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure kneels within a circle or sphere, perhaps the sun from which beams of light emanate.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>compasses</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dividers</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure holds dividers or compasses.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure and the disc in which he squats are 
surrounded by clouds except where his left arm 
descends.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The horizontal position of the figure's hair and 
beard suggest a strong wind blowing from right to 
left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <!-- [Full-page design] -->
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P2" id="europe.a.illbk.02">
      <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">EUROPE a PROPHECY</title>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode>
          <objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii, </objcode>
          <objcode code="Kii">Keynes ii)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.9 x 17.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1260" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The pictorial image is treated as a full-plate 
design.  A giant snake is coiled just above the imprint.  Its 
upper body reaches upward in two loops, suggesting a spiral, with its head facing to 
the right.  A small crest rises from the top of its head.  Its mouth is open; both its long forked tongue and 
teeth are prominent.  Its body extends beyond the lower right 
margin of the plate and then returns under the imprint, with its 
tail ending below &quot;Blake&quot; in the imprint.  The mottled color 
printing of the snake's body suggests scales.  Below the two 
large coils of its lower body and right of &quot;Lambeth&quot; (line 4) in the 
imprint are some vegetative forms with leaves.  The washes 
behind the snake's coils suggest a large stone, or perhaps clouds, hills, or mountains. The blue wash at the top of the plate suggests sky.  The snake 
has been identified as the serpent-form of Orc, the 
personification of revolutionary energy.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="animal">
            <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coiled</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>teeth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crest</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A giant snake is coiled just above the imprint.  Its 
upper body reaches upward in two loops, suggesting a spiral, with its head facing to 
the right.  A small crest rises from the top of its head.  Its mouth is open; both its long forked tongue and 
teeth are prominent.  Its body extends beyond the lower right 
margin of the plate and then returns under the imprint, with its 
tail ending below &quot;Blake&quot; (line 5) in the imprint.  The mottled color 
printing of the snake's body suggests scales.  The snake has been 
identified as the serpent-form of Orc, the personification of 
revolutionary energy.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below the two large coils of the snake's lower body 
and right of &quot;Lambeth&quot; (line 4) in the imprint are some vegetative forms with leaves.  On the left is more vegetation with at least one leaf.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Washes between and on each side of the snake's coils 
indicate a large stone, or perhaps clouds, hills, or distant mountains. The line of blue wash at the top of the plate suggests sky.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A line of blue wash at the top of the plate suggests sky.  The yellow tinting below &quot;Prophecy&quot; may suggest a sunrise or sunset. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="A" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>A vine with three loops extends from the top of the 
first letter of the first word (&quot;Europe&quot;) in the title.  A vine 
with one loop, and perhaps leaves at its end, extends 
horizontally beneath &quot;Europe&quot; from its third 
letter.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with three loops extends from the top of the 
first letter of the first word (&quot;Europe&quot;) in the 
title.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop, and perhaps leaves at its end, 
extends horizontally beneath &quot;Europe&quot; from its third 
letter.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.02.01">EUROPE</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.02.02">a</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.02.03">PROPHECY</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="6"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.02.04">LAMBETH </l>
          <l indent="25" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.02.05">Printed by Will: Blake: 1794
               </l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P3-4" id="europe.a.illbk.03">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B4">(Bentley 4, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E1">Erdman 1, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K1">Keynes 1)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objnote>
          <p>The brownish color printing on the rocks above and to the left of the man holding a dagger may be the same ink Blake used to print the text rather than his usual color-printing medium. See the Copy Information page for further comments on the coloring of this copy.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>23.6 x 17.1 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1227" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Two figures appear in the landscape above the text.  
A nude male sits crouching in a contracted posture within a cave 
surrounded at its mouth with large stones.  His legs are drawn up 
and his legs crossed at the ankles.  He faces to the left, toward 
the other figure.  His left arm is bent at the elbow, with his 
forearm and index finger on his left hand pointing up.  He grasps a 
knife or dagger in his right hand.  He may be an assassin, 
contemplating the murder of the figure to the left.  This figure 
on the left is a youthful male wearing tights, a hat, a bundle or 
backpack on his back, and belts over his chest.  He strides 
forward and to the left.  He faces left and holds a walking-stick 
in his right hand.  His left arm is bent at the elbow, with his 
left forearm and hand behind his back.  He is probably one of 
Blake's representations of a traveler.  Below his feet is a path 
or road.  Vegetation, perhaps the leaves of trees, grows right and left of this walking figure, and above the 
cave with the assassin.
There is additional vegetation with leaves above the cave and to the right and left of its entrance.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>assassin</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>knife</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dagger</characteristic>
            <characteristic>smiling</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude male sits crouching in a contracted posture 
within a cave surrounded at its mouth with large stones.  His 
legs are drawn up and his legs crossed at the ankles.  He faces 
to the left, toward the other figure.  His left arm is bent at 
the elbow, with his forearm and index finger on his left hand 
pointing up.  He grasps a knife or dagger in his right hand.  His mouth is drawn into an evil smile.  He may 
be an assassin, contemplating the murder of the figure to the 
left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>backpack</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bundle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking-stick</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A youthful male wearing tights, a hat, a bundle or backpack 
on his back, and belts over his chest, strides forward and to the 
left.  He faces left and holds a walking-stick in his right hand. 
His left arm is bent at the elbow, with his left forearm and hand 
behind his back.  He is probably one of Blake's representations 
of a traveler.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure with a dagger crouches within a 
cave formed of large stones.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="object">
            <characteristic>road</characteristic>
            <characteristic>path</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The walking figure strides forward on a road or 
path.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Vegetation, perhaps the leaves of trees, surrounds the walking figure 
and extends above the cave in which the crouching figure sits.  There is also undifferentiated vegetation 
at the base of the cave on the right.  The large leaves left of the cave may be oak leaves. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Below the text, we see a human (and apparently male) 
head, facing directly at us, with a pained or despairing 
expression.  This head seems to be surrounded tightly by the 
figure's arms and snake-like drapery.  The ends of this drapery 
curve over the head and to the left, where it forms two loops.  
The figure seems to be flying on its large, bat-like wings.  At 
least ten birds fly near the figure, above him and below and to 
the right of his left wing.  Further to the right, a nude male 
falls head-first.  His legs are bent at the knees, with the left 
leg drawn up near his chest.  His arms are raised over his head 
and bent at the elbows with his hands behind his head.  A large 
weight is attached to his hands or arms, apparently with a single 
link of a chain that disappears behind his head (because attached 
to his hands?).  This weight apparently pulls him 
downwards.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below the text, we see a human (and apparently male) 
head, facing directly at us, with a pained or despairing 
expression.  This head seems to be surrounded tightly by the 
figure's arms and snake-like drapery.  The ends of this drapery 
curve over the head and to the left, where it forms two loops.  
The figure seems to be flying on its large, bat-like 
wings.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands behind head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude male falls head-first.  His legs are bent at 
the knees, with the left leg drawn up near his chest.  His arms 
are raised over his head and bent at the elbows with his hands 
behind his head.  A large weight is attached to his arms or hands, 
apparently with a single link of a chain that disappears behind 
his head (because attached to his hands?).  This weight apparently 
pulls him downwards.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>weight</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large weight is attached to the arms or hands of the descending figure, apparently with a single link of a chain that disappears behind 
his head (because attached to his hands?).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>At least ten birds fly near the bat-winged figure, 
above him and below and to the right of his left 
wing.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>There is a good deal of interlinear decoration, 
particularly in the margins of the text.  Most consists of vines 
and leaves, but there are also a few animals.  The first letter 
of the first word in line 3 twists into a spiral vine on the left; it (or another, detached vine) descends with one further loop in the left margin to line 11.  A long, wavy vine extends between lines 5 and 6.  On it is a 
long-legged spider, just above &quot;other sons&quot; in line 6.  Further to the left, under the first word of line 5, is a small 
form that may be a fly, moth, or butterfly.  A vine trails 
downward from this same first word (&quot;And&quot;) in line 5.  Just left of the beginning of line 14 is a 
flying creature, perhaps an insect of some sort.  In the bottom 
left corner of the plate, a vine descends from the first letter 
of the first word in the last line of text (line 17).  In the right margin, 
another branch of the vine extending between lines 5 and 6 descends from the design above the text all the way to the lower 
margin.  It bears loops, at least two types of leaves, and perhaps some fruit or flowers.  A butterfly sits on the upper reaches of this vine (opposite line 5); a worm or caterpillar inches its way across the upper reaches of a large, slender leaf opposite the space between lines 9 and 10.  Other branches of this vine extend above the falling figure and intertwine with the large leaf to the right of this same figure.  A separate vine with spiky leaves twists right of lines 6 and 7, growing from the &quot;d&quot; in &quot;thunder.&quot;  Below one of its tendrils, and just to the right of line 9, is a flying insect, perhaps a beetle or fly.  A somewhat 
jagged vine extends horizontally following line 8; to the right 
is another vine, growing from the top of the second letter of 
&quot;of&quot; in line 9.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A butterfly sits on the upper reaches of the vine 
in the far right margin, right of the space between lines 5 and 6 
of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A worm (perhaps an inch worm) or caterpillar rises above the large vine right of the space between lines 9 and 10.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The first letter of the first word, line 3 of the 
text, twists into a spiral vine on the left.  It (or another, detached vine) extends with one further loop in the left margin to line 11.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A long vine—a branch of the main vine in the right margin—extends horizontally between lines 5 and 6 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine trails downward from the first word (&quot;And&quot;) 
in line 5.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the plate, a vine 
descends from the first letter of the first word in the last line 
of text (line 17).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fruit</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the right margin of the text, a loopy vine with leaves of at least two types (including very long ones) and perhaps flowers and/or fruit 
descends from the design above the text all the way to the lower 
margin.  A branch with spiky leaves extends above the falling figure; another branch is intertwined with the long leaf right of this figure.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with three tendrils or branches and perhaps 
some spiky leaves twists right of lines 6 and 7 of the 
text, growing from the &quot;d&quot; in &quot;thunder.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A somewhat jagged vine extends horizontally 
following line 8 of the text; to the right is another vine, 
growing from the top of the second letter of &quot;of&quot; in line 
9.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>On the long vine running between lines 5 and 6 of 
the text is a long-legged spider, just above &quot;other sons&quot; in line 
6.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>fly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Under the first word of line 5 of the text is a 
small form that may be a fly, moth, or butterfly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the left of the beginning of line 14 in the text is a flying creature, perhaps an insect of some sort, or possibly a flower. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fly</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of line 9 of the text is a flying 
insect, perhaps a beetle or fly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="62" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">1</physnumber>
          </l>
          <l indent="20" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.02">PRELUDIUM</l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="6"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="4" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.03">The nameless shadowy female rose from out the breast of Orc:</l>
          <l indent="4" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.04">Her snaky hair brandishing in the winds of Enitharmon;</l>
          <l indent="4" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.05">And thus her voice arose.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.06">O mother Enitharmon wilt thou bring forth other sons?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.07">To cause my name to vanish, that my place may not be found,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.08">For I am faint with travel!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.09">Like the dark cloud disburdend in the day of dismal thunder,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.10">My roots are brandish'd in the heavens, my fruits. in earth beneath</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.11">Surge, foam, and labour into life, first born &amp; first consum'd!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.12">Consumed and consuming!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.13">Then why shouldst thou accursed mother bring me into life?</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.14">I wrap my turban of thick clouds around my lab'ring head;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.15">And fold the sheety waters as a mantle round my limbs,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.16">Yet the red sun and moon,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.03.17">And all the overflowing stars rain down prolific pains. </l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P4-5" id="europe.a.illbk.04">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B5">(Bentley 5, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E2">Erdman 2, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K2">Keynes 2)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.6 x 17.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1227" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Although containing considerable text, the plate is 
treated as a full-page design showing four nude males in a dark 
sky, perhaps at night.  The two text panels are shaped like 
clouds.  Upper right, we see a figure from behind with his left 
leg bent and his left foot poised on a blue-green cloud extending 
down and to the left.  His right leg is extended; he may be 
rising.  We do not see his arms, but his hands clutch his head.  
This gesture suggests despair.  His hair may be curly.  Below is 
a group of three wrestling figures, all nude and bald.  The 
central figure has his legs spread, with his left leg extended 
and his right bent at the knee with his right foot below his 
prominent (if somewhat abstractly rendered) genitals.  He looks 
down and to the right. With his right arm he grasps another bald 
nude around the neck, apparently in an attempt to strangle him.  
This central figure's left arm is bent at the elbow and he grasps 
the neck of another bald nude with his left hand.  The blue-green 
coloring of this figure suggests that the central male has been 
successful in strangling this figure on the right.  The figure on 
the left has his legs spread and bent at the knees.  He looks up 
and to the right and tries, with both hands, to release the 
central male's arm from around his neck.  The wrestler on the 
right has his legs spread, with his left leg extended vertically 
and his right leg bent at the knee.  His arms are bent back over 
his shoulders and grasp the left leg of the central male.  All 
three figures have caricature-like facial expressions suggesting fear and pain (figures right and left) or desperation and cruelty (central figure).  The dark background surrounding the struggling figures suggests a night scene.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Upper right, we see a nude male from behind with his left 
leg bent and his left foot poised on a blue-green cloud extending 
down and to the left.  His right leg is extended; he may be 
rising.  We do not see his arms, but his hands clutch his head.  
This gesture suggests despair.  His hair may be 
curly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wrestler</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fighting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A group of three wrestlers, all nude and bald males, 
hovers in the night sky.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>strangling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wrestler</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fighting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The central bald, nude and muscular male in the 
group of three wrestlers hovering in the sky has his legs spread, 
with his left leg extended and his right bent at the knee with 
his right foot below his prominent (if somewhat abstractly 
rendered) genitals.  He looks down and to the right.  With his 
right arm he grasps another bald nude around the neck, apparently 
in an attempt to strangle him.  The central figure's left arm is 
bent at the elbow and he grasps the neck of another bald nude 
with his left hand.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wrestler</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fighting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure on the left in the group of three nude 
and bald male wrestlers hovering in the sky has his legs spread 
and bent at the knees.  He looks up and to the right and tries, 
with both hands, to release the central male's arm from around 
his neck.  His face expresses pain and terror, and his mouth is slightly open.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wrestler</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fighting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms drawn back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The wrestler on the right in the group of three nude 
and bald males has his legs spread, with his left leg extended 
vertically and his right leg bent at the knee.  His arms are bent 
back over his shoulders and grasp the left leg of the central 
male.  His head is bent back as he is being strangled, and his mouth is slightly open; his face 
expresses pain and terror.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
            <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The two text areas are shaped like, and perhaps are 
supposed to represent, clouds.  These clouds extend to the right margin below the figure upper right.  Dark clouds appear below the text, where the wrestling figures are backed by a dark and perhaps stormy sky.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>Several vegetative and avian motifs decorate the 
text.  A vine twists into the left margin from the bottom of the 
first letter of the first word in line 3.  A similar vine 
connects the last letter of &quot;bind&quot; and the second letter of the 
next word (&quot;the&quot;) in line 14.  A spiky vine with tendrils or 
branches hovers above &quot;my voice&quot; in line 17.  The descender of &quot;my&quot; 
in this same line becomes a twisting vine.  A single bird flies 
above &quot;progeny&quot; in line 9, a flock of four birds flies right of 
line 12, a single bird soars over &quot;infinite with&quot; in line 14, and 
a flock of three birds follows line 16.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A single bird flies above &quot;progeny&quot; in line 9 of the 
text, a flock of four birds flies right of line 12, a single bird 
soars over &quot;infinite with&quot; in line 14, and a flock of three birds 
follows line 16.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine twists into the left margin from the bottom 
of the first letter of the first word in line 3 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine connects the last letter of &quot;bind&quot; and the 
second letter of the next word (&quot;the&quot;) in line 14 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A spiky vine with tendrils or branches hovers above 
&quot;my voice&quot; in line 17 of the text.  The descender of &quot;my&quot; in this 
same line becomes a twisting vine.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="75" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">2</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.02">Unwilling I look up to heaven! unwilling count the stars!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.03">Sitting in fathomless abyss of my immortal shrine.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.04">I 
            <space extent="2"/>
            eze their burning power
            <note>In Copy A, the &quot;si&quot; in &quot;sieze&quot; did not print.</note></l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.05">And bring forth howling terrors, all devouring fiery kings.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.06">Devouring &amp; devoured roaming on dark and desolate mountains  </l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.07">In forests of eternal death, shrieking in hollow trees.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.08">Ah mother Enitharmon!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.09">Stamp not with solid form this vig'rous progeny of fires.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.10">I bring forth from my teeming bosom myriads of flames.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.11">And thou dost stamp them with a signet, then they roam abroad</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.12">And leave me void as death;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.13">Ah! I am drown'd in shady woe, and visionary joy.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.14">And who shall bind the infinite with an eternal band?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.15">To compass it with swaddling bands? and who shall cherish it</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.16">With milk and honey? </l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.17">I see it smile &amp; I roll inward &amp; my voice is past.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.18">She ceast &amp; rolld her shady clouds</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.04.19">Into the secret place.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P5-6" id="europe.a.illbk.05">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B6">(Bentley 6, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E3">Erdman 3, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K3">Keynes 3)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.6 x 16.7 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1227" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Although the plate contains a good deal of text and 
a great deal of interlinear decoration, the major pictorial 
      motifs—the sky and the two largest figures—constitute a full- 
plate design.  The three text panels are shaped like, and may 
represent, clouds floating in the sky.  The largest figure, 
hovering horizontally in the air just below the heading, is a 
gowned female.  The hem of her garment forms a snake-like tail.  Her body is twisted, facing forward below the waist and facing down above the waist.  Her long, curled hair cascades over (and 
hence obscures) her face.  Her arms are bent at the elbows and 
her hands are clasped behind her head.  She has large 
wings, and thus may be an angel.  More specifically, in the 
context of this poem, she has been identified as Enitharmon, a 
nature goddess of fallen time and space, and as the &quot;nameless 
shadowy female&quot; (Plate 3, line 3) who wraps a 
&quot;turban of thick clouds&quot; around her &quot;lab'ring head&quot; (Plate 3, line 14).  Below 
her cascading hair is a nude, youthful male in a contracted 
posture.  He seems confined by the circle in which he sits.  This 
circle may be meant to represent a globe; it has been described 
as a comet, although there is no tail.  It may be a planet.  His 
legs are bent at the knees and drawn up to his chest; his arms 
are bent at the elbows with his hands, formed into fists, against 
his cheeks just below his eyes.  He faces forward.  Flames surround him within the globe.  This may be Orc, the spirit of revolution here confined, 
the &quot;secret child&quot; (of Enitharmon?) mentioned on the plate (line 5), 
or one of Enitharmon's &quot;vig'rous progeny of fires&quot; (Plate 4, line 9).  The other motifs on this plate, including many human figures, will be treated as interlinear designs.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands behind head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nameless shadowy female</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The largest figure on the plate, hovering 
horizontally in the air just below the heading, is a gowned 
female.  Her body is twisted, facing forward below the waist and facing down above the waist.  The hem of her garment forms a snake-like tail.  Her long, curled hair cascades over (and hence 
obscures) her face.  Her arms are bent at the elbows and her 
hands are clasped behind her head.  She has large wings, 
and thus may be an angel.  More specifically, in the context of 
this poem, she has been identified as Enitharmon, a nature 
goddess of fallen time and space, and as the &quot;nameless shadowy 
female&quot; (Plate 3, line 3) who wraps a &quot;turban of 
thick clouds&quot; around her &quot;lab'ring head&quot; (Plate 3, line 14).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon's son</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands on face</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude, youthful male in a very contracted posture 
sits within a circle.  This circle may be meant to represent a 
globe; it has been described as a comet, although there is no 
tail.  His legs are bent at the knees and drawn up to his chest; 
his arms are bent at the elbows with his hands, formed into 
fists, against his cheeks just below his eyes.  Flames surround him within the 
globe.  This may be Orc, the spirit of revolution here confined, 
the &quot;secret child&quot; (of Enitharmon?) mentioned on the plate (line 5), 
or one of Enitharmon's &quot;vig'rous progeny of fires&quot; (Plate 4, line 9).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>planet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>globe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>circle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>comet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure squats or sits within a circle which may be meant to represent a globe.  It has been described as a comet, although there is no tail.  Hence, this may be a planet.  Flames surround the figure within the globe.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The three text panels are shaped like, and may be 
intended to represent, clouds.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>The heading is surrounded by several figures and 
vegetative motifs.  The figures, particularly the larger ones, 
may be the &quot;sons &amp; daughters&quot; (line 8) of Enitharmon referred to on 
the plate.  The lower left corner of &quot;A&quot; (in &quot;A / PROPHECY&quot; [lines 2-3]) grows 
into a long vine with branches.  Standing on this vine, near the 
left foot of the letter, is a human figure facing forward.  His 
or her arms, raised vertically, grow into limbs of a tree that 
bend downwards, as with a willow.  The motif suggests the 
classical myth of Daphne and her vegetating metamorphosis.  This 
parallel suggests that the figure is female.  On the right foot 
of &quot;A&quot; is a tree, possibly a palm, with branches that bend 
downward.  To the left of the &quot;A&quot; and slightly below it is a male(?) 
embracing a female.  Both hover in the air, with the male on the 
right and facing to the left.  Both have long hair and appear 
nude, although the woman has a long, snake-like tail of drapery 
extending from her right leg.  The man's body is twisted into a 
curve, seen from behind.  His left arm is raised horizontally and 
embraces the woman's waist.  His right leg is extended 
horizontally.  We also see the woman from behind, with her body 
twisted into a curve matching the man's.  Both her arms are 
raised horizontally, with her head facing down.  These gestures 
suggest that she is trying to escape from the man.  In contrast, 
the couple right of the letter &quot;A&quot; is embracing mutually and 
appear to be kissing.  The winged male(?), possibly an angel, hovers 
horizontally in the air, with his arms raised at 45 degrees to 
embrace the woman(?) who hovers vertically.  She too is winged and 
may be an angel.  Her legs are bent back and her arms raised at 
135 degrees to embrace her companion.  He faces down and to the 
left; she faces up and to the right.  Below the &quot;A&quot; is a hunched 
over, and apparently gowned, figure facing to the left.  This 
extremely contracted figure, with his or her upper body and head 
bent down to touch the upper legs, sits on a cloud outline.  
Other cloud outlines extend to the upper right and below 
&quot;PROPHECY&quot; in the heading.  On the right, below a cloud outline 
and above the last letter of &quot;PROPHECY,&quot; two nude figures seen 
from behind soar in the sky, left arms raised horizontally and 
right arms raised at 135 degrees.  The letters of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; are 
well decorated with eight human figures and vines.  Proceeding 
from left to right, these include a vine with leaves or lily-like 
flowers intertwined with the first letter and extending to the 
second.  A small standing figure holds the vertical of the first 
&quot;P,&quot; and what may be another figure dangles from the base of the letter.  Another figure stands on the foot of the vertical of the 
&quot;R&quot; and faces to the left with arms raised vertically.  Above 
this figure is a small form that may be a descending child or 
infant, arms stretched downward toward the adult.  The right foot 
of the &quot;R&quot; bears a very small seated figure, hunched over and 
facing to the right.  The letter &quot;O&quot; has two vines with lily-like 
flowers.  Standing within the &quot;O&quot; is a figure facing forward and 
with left arm raised horizontally to hold a shepherd's crook.  To 
the right of this shepherd is a small flock of sheep.  Three 
vines, or perhaps flames, spring from the foot of the second &quot;P.&quot; 
A vine, perhaps with a few leaves, is intertwined with the next 
three letters (&quot;HEC&quot;).  The final vine in this group springs from 
the foot of the final letter and forms a spiral above and to the 
right of the letter.  This &quot;Y&quot; also bears three human figures.  
One, seen from behind and with legs spread and arms raised 
vertically, seems to be climbing, with the right foot on the foot 
of the &quot;Y&quot; and the left foot on the &quot;C.&quot;  Above, standing on the 
top left end of the &quot;Y,&quot; is a figure walking to the left.  Finally, the first bend in the vine 
growing from the right side of the final letter bears a seated 
figure facing right, with back slightly hunched over and right 
arm extended to the right knee.  This figure holds a book or 
tablet and is probably reading.  Two flames, or perhaps a
flame-like plant, spring from the foot of the &quot;Y&quot; on its right
side.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon's son</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon's daughter</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The human figures surrounding the heading, 
particularly the four largest figures, may be the &quot;sons &amp; 
daughters&quot; (line 8) of Enitharmon referred to on the 
plate.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>vegetating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Daphne</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Standing on the vine springing from the lower left 
of the letter &quot;A,&quot; near the left foot of the letter, is a human 
figure facing forward.  His or her arms, raised vertically, grow 
into limbs of a tree that bend downwards, as with a willow.  The 
motif suggests the classical myth of Daphne and her vegetating 
metamorphosis.  This parallel suggests that the figure is 
female.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below and left of the &quot;A&quot; in the title (line 2), a nude male(?), hovering in the air, embraces a female 
with his left arm around her waist.  We see him from behind, but 
his body is twisted into a curve.  His hair is long; his right 
leg is extended horizontally to the left.  He faces 
left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below and left of the &quot;A&quot; in the title (line 2), a nude female with long hair, facing down and to the 
left, hovers in the air.  She is embraced around the waist by the 
male(?) to the right.  We see her from behind, with her body twisted 
into a curve like the male's.  Although apparently nude from the 
waist up, a long, snake-like tail of drapery extends from her 
right leg.  Her arms are raised horizontally to the right.  This 
gesture, as well as her head position, suggest that she is trying 
to flee from the male.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Right of the &quot;A&quot; in the title (line 2), a nude male(?) hovers horizontally and reaches down, 
with his arms at 45 degrees, to embrace the female(?) below and to 
the left.  His large wings suggest he may be an angel.  He faces 
down and to the left and may be kissing the female.  His hair may 
be curly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Right of the &quot;A&quot; in the title (line 2), a nude female(?) hovers in the air.  Her large wings 
suggest she may be an angel.  She reaches up with her 
arms raised at 135 degrees to embrace the male(?) hovering horizontally to the right.  Her 
legs are slightly bent.  She faces up and to the right and may be 
kissing the male.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below the &quot;A&quot; (line 2) of the heading is a hunched over, and 
apparently gowned, figure facing to the left.  This extremely 
contracted figure, with his or her upper body and head bent down 
to touch the upper legs, sits on a cloud outline.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small figure holds the vertical of the first 
letter of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) in the heading.  The figure reaches up with 
both arms and may be climbing.  The figure probably faces forward 
or to the right.  </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dangling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure dangles below the &quot;P&quot; and grasps the base of the letter with vertically raised arms.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small figure stands, facing left, on the foot of 
the letter &quot;R&quot; in &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  The figure, probably male, has his 
arms raised vertically, perhaps to catch the small figure 
above.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>descending</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms reaching downward</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Just above the figure standing on the left foot of 
the letter &quot;R&quot; in &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) is a very small human form, probably 
a child or infant.  This tiny figure descends head-first toward 
the adult below, with arms reaching downward.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A very small figure sits on the right foot of the 
letter &quot;R&quot; in &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  The figure faces right and is slightly 
hunched over.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, stands within the &quot;O&quot; of 
&quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  He faces forward with his left arm raised 
horizontally.  He holds a shepherd's crook in his left hand.  
Given the crook and the flock of sheep to the right, the figure 
is almost certainly a shepherd.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male and seen from behind, climbs 
between the &quot;C&quot; and &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  His legs are spread, with 
his left foot poised on the &quot;C&quot; and his right foot just touching 
the foot of the &quot;Y.&quot;  He reaches up vertically with both arms to 
hold the left diagonal of the &quot;Y.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A very small figure, probably male, stands on top of 
the left diagonal of the &quot;Y&quot; in &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  He seems to be walking to the left. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>reading</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small figure, probably gowned and male, sits on 
the vine extending from the &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  He faces to the 
right, with his upper body hunched over and his right arm 
extended at 45 degrees to his knees.  He holds, and seems to be 
reading, a book or tablet.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="object">
            <characteristic>book</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tablet</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure sitting on the vine extending from the &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) appears to be holding a book or tablet.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two figures hover in, or fly through, the air above the &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  Both are nude; the upper figure appears to be male, while the lower figure seems to be female.  Both have their left arms raised horizontally and right arms raised at 135 degrees, and both may be holding something in their right hands.  The male’s body is twisted, and his left leg crossed in front of his right leg.  The female’s right leg is extended backward.  </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>sheep</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A flock of sheep rests within the &quot;O&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3), 
just to the right of their shepherd.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Flames, or perhaps flame-like plants, spring from 
the foot of the second &quot;P&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) on its right 
side.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="object">
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two flames, or perhaps flame-like plants, spring 
from the foot of the &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) on its right 
side.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The outlines of clouds extend above &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) from 
the &quot;O&quot; to the upper right corner of the plate; one cloud outline 
descends between the second &quot;P&quot; and &quot;H&quot; of the word and extends 
below the word to the &quot;R.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine, perhaps with leaves, extends to the left 
from the left foot of &quot;A&quot; (line 2) in the heading.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>willow</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The raised arms of the figure standing on the left 
foot of &quot;A&quot; (line 2) in the heading vegetate into branches that arch 
downward.  This may be a willow.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palm</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small tree with arching branches, perhaps a palm, 
grows from the right foot of &quot;A&quot; (line 2) in the heading.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine is intertwined with the first letter of 
&quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3) in the heading.  There are leaves or perhaps lily-like 
flowers at its left end; its right end curls behind the foot of 
the next letter (&quot;R&quot;).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with lily-like flowers is intertwined with 
the left side of the &quot;O&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).  A separate vine, or the 
other end of the same vine, grows up the right side of the same 
letter.  It too bears lily-like flowers.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop and a few leaves is intertwined 
with the letters &quot;HEC&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine, with a spiral upper right, grows from the 
right side of the foot of &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;PROPHECY&quot; (line 3).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>The cloud-like text panel containing lines 4-7 of 
the text includes three human figures, birds, and some vines.  A 
vine with two loops extends from the first word of line 4 and 
turns to the right over the line.  On it may be a single 
leaf or flower between the two loops.  To the right of the second loop sits 
a figure who is gowned and apparently female.  Her body faces to the 
left, but her head seems to be turned to the right so that we see 
her head and shoulders from behind.  Her left arm extends 
downward to her knee; her right arm is raised at about 135 
degrees and extended to the right.  Above her and to the left is a flock of five birds.  Two figures hover in the air right of line 4.  The gowned figure 
on the left is probably a female; we see her from behind with one 
arm raised horizontally and the other at 135 degrees.  To the right is a (probably nude and 
male) figure also hovering and seen from behind.  His left leg is 
extended, his right bent at the knee.  He holds, and apparently 
plays, a horn with one loop in it.  To the right of this figure, 
and above &quot;eternal&quot; in line 6, is a vine.  Another vine, with 
leaves at its lower end, extends from the last letter of the last 
word (&quot;abodes&quot;) in line 7.  To the right of this line are two 
birds, flying upward on extended wings.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure, gowned and probably female, sits on the vine above &quot;deep of&quot; in line 4 of the text.  Her body 
faces to the left, but her head seems to be turned to the right 
so that we see her head and shoulders from behind.  Her left arm 
extends downward to her knee; her right arm is raised at about 
135 degrees.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two figures hover in the air right of line 4 of the 
text.  The gowned figure on the left is probably a female; we see 
her from behind with one arm raised horizontally and the other at 135 degrees.  The hem of her gown forms a twisting tail.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>To the right of line 4, and right of the hovering 
female figure, is a (probably nude and male) figure also hovering 
and seen from behind.  His left leg is extended, his right bent 
at the knee.  He holds, and apparently plays, a horn with one 
loop in it.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure hovering above &quot;eternal&quot; (line 7) holds, and presumably plays, a horn with one loop in it.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A flock of five birds flies on extended wings above 
the vine extending horizontally above line 4 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two birds fly upwards on extended wings right of 
line 7 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with two loops extends from the first word 
of line 4 of the text and turns to the right over this line.  
On it may be a single leaf or flower between the two loops.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine curls above &quot;eternal&quot; in line 6 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine, perhaps with leaves at its lower end, 
extends from the last letter of the last word (&quot;abodes&quot;) in line 
7 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>Four figures, birds, a cloud outline, and a vine 
decorate the third cloud-like text panel containing lines 8-17 of 
the text.  A vine loops upward from the first letter of the first 
word in line 8 and extends above the line to the word &quot;her.&quot;  A 
much smaller vine or single leaf grows from the vertical of the last letter in 
this line.  Just above the first word (&quot;Then&quot;), a nude figure 
(probably male) lies supine on this vine.  One leg is extended, the other bent at the knee.  The figure faces up; his arms are raised at 135 degrees relative to his body.  The figure apparently rising into the air above, whose legs are spread and (left?) arm is raised vertically, is of uncertain gender.  To the right, above &quot;Enitharmon&quot; in line 8, is a flying bird.  
Another two birds fly on extended wings above the last word 
(&quot;come&quot;) in line 12.  A cloud outline (or perhaps the surface of 
the earth?) below and to the right of the birds bears a figure 
crawling to the right on all fours.  Further to the right, 
another figure, perhaps nude and female, stands and leans to the 
left against the cloud outline.  Her legs are 
crossed.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably male, lies supine on the 
vine above the first word (&quot;Then&quot;) in line 8 of the text.  One 
leg is extended, the other bent at the knee.  The figure faces 
up; his arms are raised at 135 degrees relative to his body.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure, facing left, hovers above the 
first letter of &quot;Enitharmon&quot; in line 8 of the text.  This figure, 
of uncertain gender, has his or her (left?) arm raised vertically 
and legs spread.  </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>crawling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure crawls to the right on all fours along the 
cloud outline (or surface of the earth?) above the last word 
(&quot;rest&quot;) in line 13 of the text.  The figure may be gowned.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably nude and female, stands and leans to the left against a cloud outline.  Her upper body, twisted to the left, is braced 
against the cloud with her left arm; her legs are 
crossed.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird flies upward on extended wings above the 
middle letters of &quot;Enitharmon&quot; (and above the vine), line 8 of 
the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two birds fly on extended wings above the last word 
(&quot;come&quot;) in line 12 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine loops upward from the first letter of the 
first word in line 8 and extends above the line to the word 
&quot;her.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The vertical of the final letter of &quot;around,&quot; the 
last word in line 8 of the text, becomes a vine arching over the 
word.  It may terminate in a leaf.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A cloud outline extends from the right margin of the 
plate and ends above the last word (&quot;come&quot;) in line 12 of the 
text.  Perhaps the segment of this line on the left, where a 
figure is crawling, is meant to represent the surface of the 
earth rather than a cloud.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="60" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">3</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="13" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.02">A</l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="8" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.03">PROPHECY</l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="6"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="7" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.04">The deep of winter came:</l>
          <l indent="7" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.05">What time the secret child,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.06">Descended thro' the orient gates of the eternal day;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.07">War ceas'd, &amp; all the troops like shadows fled </l>
          <l indent="7" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.08">to their abodes.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.09">Then Enitharmon saw her sons &amp; daughters rise around.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.10">Like pearly clouds they meet together in the crystal house:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.11">And Los. possessor of the moon, joy'd in the peaceful night;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.12">Thus speaking while his num'rous sons shook their bright fiery wings</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="3" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.13">Again the night is come</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.14">That strong Urthona takes his rest,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.15">And Urizen unloos'd from chains</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.16">Glows like a meteor in the distant north</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.17">Stretch forth your hands and strike the elemental strings!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.05.18">Awake the thunders of the deep,</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P6-7" id="europe.a.illbk.06">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.1 x 16.4 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1201" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The design below the text is dominated by two large 
figures and five smaller ones.  A nude and youthful male lies 
prone on the ground—or perhaps on a bed of straw.  He faces 
down, with his arms bent and his head resting on them.  Only part of his left arm and right hand are visible.  His hair 
is curly and a halo of fire surrounds his head.  This is probably 
the youthful Orc.  Above him, a nude female with long, flame-like 
hair kneels on a cloud and leans dramatically to the left.  Her 
left leg is extended and her right bent at the knee under her 
torso.  Her arms are extended horizontally and she holds, and 
apparently lifts with both hands, a cloak, blanket, or heavy 
drapery to uncover the youth below, at whom she is looking.  She 
is probably Enitharmon.  The five much smaller figures above may 
be her sons and daughters.  In the left corner of the design, 
just below the text, we see a nude figure lying supine on a cloud 
with legs bent and spread, body twisted to the left, head 
apparently down and resting on the left arm extended 
horizontally.  The gender of this figure is uncertain; his or her 
posture suggests erotic exhaustion.  Similar exhaustion is 
indicated by the nude figure to the right.  This figure is 
probably female and also lies supine on a cloud.  Her body is 
bent back, with her head, right arm, and right leg dangling 
downward.  Above and to the 
right is another nude female, sitting or lying supine on a cloud with her 
upper body propped up with her bent right arm.  She faces right 
and probably has long hair.  Her right leg is extended to the 
right and her left leg bent at the knee.  Further to the right is 
an embracing couple hovering in the air, with the woman on the 
right.  They may be kissing.  The nude male, facing right, has 
his legs spread and his right arm raised horizontally.  The 
female, facing left, is gowned and has a tail of drapery 
curling over her raised left leg.  Her legs are spread apart.  
Her long hair may be gathered into a bun.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>prone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head on arms</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand beside head</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude and youthful male lies prone on the ground— 
or perhaps on a bed of straw.  He faces down, with his arms bent 
and his head resting on them.  Only part of his left arm and right hand are visible.  His hair is curly and a halo of 
fire surrounds his head.  This is probably the youthful Orc.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lifting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
            <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>blanket</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Above the youthful male lying prone, a nude female 
with long, flame-like hair kneels on a cloud and leans 
dramatically to the left.  Her left leg is extended, her right bent at the knee and drawn up under her torso.  Her arms are raised 
horizontally and she holds, and apparently lifts with both hands, 
a cloak, blanket, or heavy drapery to uncover the youth below, at
whom she 
is looking.  She is probably Enitharmon.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon's sons</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Enitharmon's daughters</characteristic>
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Five nude figures fill the sky just below the text.  
These may be the sons and daughters of Enitharmon.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head on arm</characteristic>
            <characteristic>erotic</characteristic>
            <characteristic>exhausted</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In the left corner of the design, just below the 
text, we see a nude figure lying supine on a cloud with legs bent 
and spread, body twisted to the left, head apparently down and 
resting on the left arm extended horizontally.  The gender of 
this figure is uncertain; his or her posture suggests erotic 
exhaustion.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>erotic</characteristic>
            <characteristic>exhausted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, lies supine on a 
cloud.  Her posture suggests erotic exhaustion, with her head 
bent back and her right arm and right leg dangling 
downward.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude female sits or lies supine on a cloud with her upper 
body propped up with her bent right arm.  She faces right and 
probably has long hair.  Her right leg is extended to the right 
and her left leg bent at the knee.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude male, facing right, embraces a female and 
perhaps kisses her.  He hovers in the air, with legs spread.  His 
right arm is raised horizontally.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>partly nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A partly nude female, facing left, hovers in the air 
      and apparently embraces—and perhaps kisses—the male to the left.  Her legs 
are spread apart and a gown or piece of drapery curves over her 
left leg, forming a curling tail. Her long hair may be twisted 
into a bun.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>straw</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The youthful and nude male lies on the ground—or 
perhaps a bed of straw.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The large female figure, and the three smaller 
figures above her on the left, lie or kneel on 
clouds.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The text panel is shaped like, and may represent, a 
cloud floating in the sky.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The text panel is shaped like, and may represent, a 
cloud floating in the sky.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>The text is well decorated with vines, one fairly 
large human figure, and animals.  Right of lines 8-11 of the 
text, a nude male seems to be falling through the air.  His body 
is twisted dramatically at the waist, with his legs together, his 
head down, and his arms raised and wrapped around his head.  He 
appears to be bald.  Right of line 5 are four flying creatures.  
Reading left to right, these are a bird, a winged insect (perhaps 
a beetle or moth), a butterfly or moth, and a bird.  Another 
winged creature, perhaps an insect, flies right of lines 8-9.  Left 
and right of this creature are two vines; the vine on the right looks very worm-like.  A vine below line 10 
includes one loop and a grain tassel on its right end.  A 
grasshopper or locust stands on this vine, facing right.  Three 
winged insects fly above the grain tassel.  Another vine appears 
further to the right, with at least one leaf and three loops.  
Vines, or extensions of a cloud outline, extend below line 15.  A 
bird flies on extended wings above the first word (&quot;Then&quot;) in 
line 18 and a vine grows from the &quot;h&quot; of the next word 
(&quot;Enitharmon&quot;). </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="B" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Right of lines 8-11 of the text, a nude male seems 
to be falling through the air.  His body is twisted dramatically 
at the waist, with his legs together, his head down, and his arms 
bent upward and wrapped around his head.  He appears to be 
bald.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Right of line 5 of the text are four flying 
creatures.  Reading left to right, these are a bird, a winged 
insect (perhaps a beetle or moth), a butterfly or moth, and a 
bird.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A winged creature, perhaps an insect such as a moth or beetle, flies 
right of lines 8-9 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>grasshopper</characteristic>
            <characteristic>locust</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A grasshopper or locust sits, facing right, on the 
vine above line 11 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>moth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fly</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three flying insects, perhaps flies or moths, appear 
below &quot;nights of&quot; in line 10 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird flies on extended wings above the first word 
(&quot;Then&quot;) in line 18 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two vines appear right of lines 8-9 of the 
text.  The vine on the right is very worm-like.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop and a grain tassel at its right 
end appears between lines 10 and 11 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with three loops and one leaf wends its way 
between lines 10 and 11 of the text, left of the descending 
figure.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>An extension of a cloud outline between lines 15 and 
16 of the text takes on the appearance of a vine.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the &quot;t&quot; of &quot;Enitharmon,&quot; the 
second word in line 18 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="60" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">4</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.02">The shrill winds wake!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.03">Till all the sons of Urizen look out and envy Los;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.04">Sieze all the spirits of life and bind</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.05">Their warbling joys to our loud strings</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.06">Bind all the nourishing sweets of earth</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.07">To give us bliss, that we may drink the sparkling wine of Los</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.08">And let us laugh at war,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.09">Despising toil and care.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.10">Because the days and nights of joy. in lucky hours renew.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.11">Arise O Orc from thy deep den,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.12">First born of Enitharmon rise!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.13">And we will crown thy head with garlands of the ruddy vine;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.14">For now thou art bound;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.15">And I may see thee in the hour of bliss, my eldest born,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.16">The horrent Demon rose. surrounded with red stars of fire,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.17">Whirling about in furious circles round the immortal fiend.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.18">Then Enitharmon down descended into his red light,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.06.19">And thus her voice rose to her children, the distant heavens reply.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P7-8" id="europe.a.illbk.07">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B8">(Bentley 8, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E5">Erdman 5, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K5">Keynes 5)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.6 x 17.2 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1227" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Above the text, a scaly male stands between two 
female angels.  He stands in a slightly contrapposto posture, 
facing forward, with legs spread.  He wears a spiky crown with at least five points.  His right arm is slightly bent, with his right hand 
behind his right thigh.  He holds a large sword, with its point 
behind his left leg, in his left hand.  The scales may represent 
armor, although they extend over his face.  This may be Rintrah, 
as a personification of military wrath, referred to in the text 
on this plate.  Both angels have large wings.  The angel on the 
left has her arms folded over her chest and looks to the right.  
The angel on the right has her hands together, as if in prayer or 
supplication, and looks to the left.  Both wear long 
gowns.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Rintrah</characteristic>
            <characteristic>armor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Above the text, a scaly male stands between two 
female angels.  He stands in a slightly contrapposto posture, 
facing forward, legs spread.  He wears a spiky crown with at least five points.  His right arm is slightly bent, with his right hand 
behind his right thigh.  He holds a large sword, with its point 
behind his left leg, in his left hand.  His mouth is slightly open.  The scales may represent 
armor, although they extend over his face.  This may be Rintrah, 
as a personification of military wrath, referred to in the text 
on this plate.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="object">
            <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The central figure in the group of three holds a large sword in his left hand.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms folded</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hand on breast</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned, female angel stands on the left of the 
male figure.  She has large wings, looks to the right, and has 
her arms folded over her chest.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
            <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned, female angel stands on the right of the 
male figure.  She has large wings, looks to the left, and has her 
hands together as if in prayer or supplication.  Her mouth may be slightly open.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>The text area is decorated with vegetative motifs.  
A vine in two segments extends above the first line and luxuriates into large 
leaves in the right margin.  From these leaves a vine extends 
toward the end of line 10.  A vine grows upward from the first 
letter of the first word (&quot;Spread&quot;) of line 10; another vine grows 
from the last letter of &quot;every&quot; in the same line.  A long vine 
extends from the first letter of &quot;yet&quot; in line 11, extending to 
the word &quot;towards.&quot;  A small vine curls from the first letter of 
&quot;Arise&quot; in line 12.  A bird flies above the word &quot;race&quot; in line 6, and what may be insects fly over &quot;abode&quot; and &quot;where&quot; in line 8. </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine extends in two segments above line 2 and luxuriates into large leaves in the right margin.  From these 
leaves a vine extends toward the end of line 10.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows upward from the first letter of the 
first word (&quot;Spread&quot;) in line 10 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the descender of the last letter 
of &quot;every&quot; in line 10 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the descender of the first letter 
of &quot;yet,&quot; line 11 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows to the left of the first letter of 
&quot;Arise,&quot; line 12.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird flies above &quot;race&quot; in line 6, and what may be insects fly over &quot;abode&quot; and &quot;where&quot; in line 8.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="65" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">5</physnumber>
            <space extent="15"/>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="8"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.02">Now comes the night of Enitharmons joy,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.03">Who shall I call? Who shall I send?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.04">That Woman, lovely Woman! may have dominion?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.05">Arise O Rintrah thee I call! &amp; Palamabron thee!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.06">Go; tell the human race that Womans love is Sin:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.07">That an Eternal life awaits the worms of sixty winters</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.08">In an allegorical abode where existence hath never come:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.09">Forbid all Joy, &amp; from her childhood shall the little female</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.10">Spread nets in every secret path.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.11">My weary eyelids draw towards the evening, my bliss is yet but new!</l>
        </lg>
        <textfoot justify="left">
          <l indent="57" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.07.12">
            <catchword>Arise</catchword>
          </l>
        </textfoot>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P8-9" id="europe.a.illbk.08">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B9">(Bentley 9, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K6">Keynes 6)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.7 x 17.1 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1232" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The setting is an enclosed interior space with a 
floor and a stone back wall.  A fireplace with a grate and an 
arched top is at the center of the back wall and of the 
composition.  A coal fire burns on the grate.  Above is a large 
cooking pot with a handle suspended from the top of the fireplace 
by a chain or rod, possibly with a hook at its lower end.  Clouds of smoke or steam billow above the pot.  In 
the foreground are three figures.  On the left is a gowned woman, 
facing right and in an extremely contracted posture.  She sits or 
squats on the floor with her legs drawn up to her chest and her 
right arm wrapped around her right knee.  Her head is down 
between her knees; her long hair cascades to the ground.  The 
gowned woman on the right sits in an elegant, neoclassical chair. 
Her prominent knees are drawn up toward her chest, with legs 
crossed.  Her arms are apparently also crossed, with her left 
hand near her right breast and her right hand near her left 
breast.  She wears a necklace of beads and faces up with a 
worried or pained expression, perhaps looking at the pot.  Below 
the woman in the chair is a male child, nude, rigid, and lying 
supine on a white cloth spread on the floor.  His eyes are closed 
and he is probably dead.  His hair is curly.  A dark shadow slants 
across the upper half of the plate. The wall behind and to the 
right of the seated woman is also in shadow.  Some interpreters 
have described this design as a scene of famine, including the 
contemplation of cannibalism by the woman above the child's 
corpse.  </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms wrapped around knees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head on knees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman, facing right and in an extremely 
contracted posture, sits or squats on the floor with her legs 
drawn up to her chest and her right arm wrapped around her right 
knee.  Her head is down between her knees; her long hair 
cascades to the ground.  Her right foot is prominent.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>jewelry</characteristic>
            <characteristic>necklace</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beads</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman sits in an elegant, neoclassical 
chair.  Her prominent knees are drawn up toward her chest, with 
legs crossed.  Her arms are apparently also crossed, with her 
left hand near her right breast and her right hand near her left 
breast.  She wears a necklace of beads and faces up with her neck 
twisted to the left and with a pained or worried expression on 
her face.  She may be looking at the pot.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rigid</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
            <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cannibalism</characteristic>
            <characteristic>famine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cooking</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Below the woman in the chair is a male child, nude, 
rigid, and lying supine on a white cloth spread on the floor.  
His eyes are closed and he is probably dead.  His hair is curly.  
Some interpreters have described this design as a scene of 
famine, including the contemplation of cannibalism by the woman 
above the child's corpse.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="structure">
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fireplace</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>chamber</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coal</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The setting is an enclosed interior space with a 
floor and a stone back wall.  A fireplace with a grate and an 
arched top is at the center of the back wall and of the 
composition.  A coal fire burns on the grate.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>pot</characteristic>
            <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rod</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hook</characteristic>
            <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
            <characteristic>steam</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large cooking pot hangs by a chain or rod, possibly with a hook at its lower end. Smoke or steam billows above the pot. 
                  </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
            <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A dark shadow slants across the upper half of the plate. The wall behind and to the right of the seated woman is in shadow as well.  These areas may, alternatively, be darkened by smoke. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>blanket</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The apparently dead child lies on a blanket spread 
on the floor.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>classical art</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The woman sits in an elegant, neoclassical 
chair.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l justify="right" n="europe.a.illbk.08.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">6</physnumber>
            <space extent="15"/>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <!-- [Full-page design] -->
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P9-11" id="europe.a.illbk.09">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B11">(Bentley 11, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E8">Erdman 8, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K8">Keynes 8)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.6 x 16.7 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1227" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Below the text panel, shaped like a cloud, two 
figures stand before billowing storm clouds (or possibly smoke). This 
may be a night scene, with the suggestion of distant fires, or possibly a sunrise or sunset. A gowned 
and elderly male with long hair and beard stands on the right 
facing to the left.  His arms are raised horizontally, with palms 
outward (that is, facing to the left).  His worried expression, 
staring eyes, and arm gesture suggest that he is afraid of some 
unpictured presence to the left.  He may be Albion's Angel, 
frightened at the prospect of coming revolution.  A gowned woman 
kneels on the ground before the old man, with her right leg extended backward and left leg bent at the knee.  Her body is bent forward and her 
head down.  Her right arm is raised horizontally and she embraces 
the old man around his legs.  Her long hair cascades below her 
right upper arm.  She may be supplicating the man for help.  The 
background for the figures suggests dark clouds, but these are 
touched with red on their upper and left sides.  Perhaps the 
unpictured presence to the left is the fires of revolution.    
The ground below the figures may be covered with some sort of vegetation, perhaps grass or lichens.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>old</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Albion's Angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms vertical</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned and elderly male with long hair and beard 
stands on the right facing to the left.  His arms are raised 
horizontally, with palms outward (that is, facing to the left).  
His worried expression, staring eyes, and arm gesture suggest 
that he is afraid of some unpictured presence to the left.  He 
may be Albion's Angel, frightened by the coming 
revolution.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman kneels on the ground before the old 
man, with right leg extended backward and left leg bent at the knee.  Her 
body is bent forward and her head down.  Her right arm is raised 
horizontally and she embraces the old man around the legs.  Her 
long hair cascades below her right upper arm.  She may be 
supplicating the man for help.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>lichens</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The ground below the figures may be covered with 
some sort of vegetation, perhaps grass or lichens.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
            <characteristic>darkness</characteristic>
            <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>night</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The background for the figures suggests dark, stormy 
clouds, or possibly smoke.  The upper and left edges of the clouds are touched with red; perhaps the unpictured presence to the left is the fires of 
revolution or a sunrise or sunset.  This may be a night scene.  The text panel is shaped like a cloud.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>A vine, with a shape suggesting a spiral, extends horizontally below &quot;bring the lovely,&quot; line 8 of the text. The second letter of &quot;my&quot; 
                  in line 8 shows a vine-like extension of the descender, while a vine, or perhaps roots, dangle from the first letter of the first word (&quot;And&quot;) in line 13. </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine, with a shape suggesting a spiral, extends horizontally below &quot;bring the lovely,&quot; line 8 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>root</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The second letter of “my” in line 8 shows a vine-like extension of the descender, while a vine, or perhaps roots, dangle from the 
                     first letter of the first word (&quot;And&quot;) in line 13.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="60" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">7</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.02">Arise O Rintrah eldest born; second to none but Orc;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.03">O lion Rintrah raise thy fury from thy forests black;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.04">Bring Palamabron horned priest, skipping upon the mountains:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.05">And silent Elynittria the silver bowed queen:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.06">Rintrah where hast thou hid thy bride!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.07">Weeps she in desart shades?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.08">Alas my Rintrah! bring the lovely jealous Ocalythron,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.09">Arise my son! bring all thy brethren O thou king of fire.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.10">Prince of the sun I see thee with thy innumerable race;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.11">Thick as the summer stars:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.12">But each ramping his golden mane shakes,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.09.13">And thine eyes rejoice because of strength O Rintrah furious king.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P10-12" id="europe.a.illbk.10">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B12">(Bentley 12, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E9">Erdman 9, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K9">Keynes 9)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.4 x 16.6 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Grain stems grow from the lower left corner of the 
plate and coil upward into the large design above the text. Several vines, some of which form 
loops and at least one of which bears ivy-like leaves, are intertwined with the lower reaches of the stems, below and right of the text. The stems form a large &quot;C&quot; curve above the text and 
end near the right margin in grain tassels.  Two figures appear 
within this &quot;C&quot; curve.  The nude female, on the left, is seen 
from behind; her long hair is formed into a loose bun.  She 
hovers in the air, with her right leg extended and her left bent 
at the knee.  Her body and head are twisted to the right.  She 
holds in her raised right hand, and no doubt plays, a large, 
coiled horn or trumpet.  The black spots of blight covering the 
grain appear to emanate from the trumpet and the one her male 
companion plays.  He is also nude, seen from behind, and has his 
body twisted dramatically to the right.  His left leg is 
extended, his right bent at the knee as he hovers in the air.  He 
holds his coiled horn or trumpet with his left hand.  Both arms 
are raised horizontally.  His hair is curly.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude female is seen from behind; her long hair is 
formed into a loose bun with one strand of hair forming a vine-like tail left of the bun.  She hovers in the air, with her right 
leg extended and her left bent at the knee.  Her body and head 
are twisted to the right.  She holds in her raised right hand, 
and no doubt plays, a large, coiled horn or trumpet.  The black 
spots of blight covering the grain appear to emanate from the 
trumpet and the one her male companion plays.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A male nude, seen from behind, twists his body 
dramatically to the right.  His left leg is extended, his right 
bent at the knee as he hovers in the air.  He holds a coiled horn 
or trumpet with his left hand.  Both arms are raised 
horizontally.  His hair is curly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coil</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ivy</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Grain stems grow from the lower left corner of the 
plate and coil upward into the large design above the text.  
Several vines, at least one of which bears ivy-like leaves, are 
intertwined with the lower reaches of the stems, below and right 
of the text.  The stems form a large &quot;C&quot; curve above the text and 
end near the right margin in grain tassels.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>blight</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Black spots of grain blight cover the grain stems 
and tassels.  This blight seems to emanate from the horns or 
trumpets held by the two human figures.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>horn</characteristic>
            <characteristic>trumpet</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coil</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Both figures hold and play large, coiled horns or 
trumpets.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="CD" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>Vines, grain stems, and blight intrude into the text area. Splotches 
of blight appear right of lines 2-7 and below line 6.  A grain stem extends from the right margin 
between lines 6 and 7 of the text; it is intertwined with a looping and spiraling vine.  Another 
offshoot of the vine in the right margin extends between lines 9 and 13.  Three other vines, one with leaves, 
appear further to the left between lines 6 and 7. Vines with leaves grow from the first letter of &quot;years&quot; in line 
6 and &quot;Shadows&quot; in line 7.  A vine-like extension also grows from “by” in line 17.  More spots of blight appear right of 
lines 11, 12, and 14.  Two vines or leaves follow the last word of line 14. </illusobjdesc>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>blight</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Splotches of grain blight appear right of lines 2-7 
of the text, below line 6, and right of lines 11, 12, and 
14.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>grain stem</characteristic>
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A grain stem extends from the right margin between 
lines 6 and 7 of the text; it is intertwined with a looping and 
spiraling vine.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three vines appear between lines 6 and 7 of the 
text.  The middle vine bears leaves.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The descenders of the &quot;y&quot; in &quot;years&quot; (line 3) and &quot;by&quot; (last line [line 17]) have vine-like extensions.  A vine, perhaps with leaves, ascends from the first letter of line 7.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two vines or leaves follow the final word of line 14 of
the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="65" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">8</physnumber>
            <space extent="15"/>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="6"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.02">Enitharmon slept,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.03">Eighteen hundred years: Man was a Dream!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.04">The night of Nature and their harps unstrung:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.05">She slept in middle of her nightly song.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.06">Eighteen hundred years, a female dream!</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.07">Shadows of men in fleeting bands upon the winds:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.08">Divide the heavens of Europe;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.09">Till Albions Angel smitten with his own plagues fled with his bands</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.10">The cloud bears hard on Albions shore; </l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.11">Fill'd with immortal demons of futurity:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.12">In council gather the smitten Angels of Albion</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.13">The cloud bears hard upon the council house; down rushing</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.14">On the heads of Albions Angels.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.15">One hour they lay buried beneath the ruins of that hall;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.16">But as the stars rise from the salt lake they arise in pain,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.10.17">In troubled mists o'erclouded by the terrors of strugling times,</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P11-13" id="europe.a.illbk.11">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B13">(Bentley 13, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E10">Erdman 10, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K10">Keynes 10)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.4 x 16.7 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>A snake extends below the text, up the left margin, 
and above the text.  Its tail is in the lower margin; its body, 
in the left margin, has seven loops or coils suggesting, if not 
quite forming, a spiral; its head rises above the text.  Its 
mouth is open; its tongue merges with the halo of flames surrounding its 
crested head.  Mottling on the snake's body suggests 
scales.  This is probably the serpent-form of Orc, the spirit of 
revolution, although a more immediate textual context on this 
plate appears in line 18: &quot;Thought chang'd the infinite to a 
serpent.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="animal">
            <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coil</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>scales</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crest</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A snake extends below the text, up the left margin, 
and above the text.  Its tail is in the lower margin; its body, 
in the left margin, has seven loops or coils suggesting (if not 
quite forming) a spiral; its head rises above the text.  Its 
mouth is open; its tongue merges with the halo of flames surrounding its 
crested head.  Mottling on the snake's body suggests 
scales.  This is probably the serpent-form of Orc, the spirit of 
revolution, although a more immediate textual context on this 
plate appears in line 18: &quot;Thought chang'd the infinite to a 
serpent.&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="E" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>Several vines decorate the text: at the end of line 
3, descending from the first letter of the first word (&quot;There&quot;) 
in line 8, extending horizontally to the left from the first word 
(&quot;The&quot;) in line 15, extending from the first letter of the first 
word (&quot;Were&quot;) in line 16, descending from &quot;petrify'd&quot; in line 17, 
between lines 17 and 18, rising from the second letter of &quot;that&quot; 
in line 18, left and right of &quot;rush'd&quot; (line 22), descending from the second letter 
of &quot;tyrant&quot; in line 26, extending from both the beginning and 
termination of the first letter in line 27, growing from the 
first and fifth letter of &quot;Guardian&quot; in line 27, growing from the 
last letter of &quot;heavens&quot; in line 31, extending from the left foot 
of the first letter (&quot;A&quot;) in line 34, and extending in a loop 
from the last letter of &quot;dizzy&quot; in line 34.  A bird flies upward 
on extended wings above &quot;finite wall&quot; in line 23.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="BD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird flies upward on extended wings above &quot;finite 
wall&quot; in line 23 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine extends between &quot;following&quot; and &quot;silent&quot; at 
the end of lines 2-3 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop descends from the first letter 
of the first word (&quot;There&quot;) in line 8 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop extends horizontally from the 
first letter of the first word (&quot;The&quot;) in line 15.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop extends from the first letter 
of the first word (&quot;Were&quot;) in line 16 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop descends from the descender of 
&quot;y&quot; in &quot;petrify'd,&quot; line 17 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine extends horizontally between lines 17 and 18 
of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine ascends from the second letter of &quot;that&quot; in 
line 18 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Vines appear right and left of &quot;rush'd&quot; in line 22 of the text.  The 
vine right of &quot;rush'd&quot; bears leaves.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine descends from the second letter of &quot;tyrant,&quot; 
line 26 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Vines grow from the left and right terminations of 
the first letter in the first word (&quot;Now&quot;) in line 27 of the 
text.  The vine on the upper right contains two 
loops.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Vines grow from the first and fifth letters of 
&quot;Guardian,&quot; line 27 of the text.  The vine growing from the first 
letter includes a loop.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the final letter of &quot;heavens,&quot; 
line 31 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine descends from the left foot of &quot;A,&quot; the first 
word in line 34.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop descends from the last letter 
of &quot;dizzy,&quot; line 34 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="58" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">9</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="49" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.02">(following
               </l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.03">In thoughts perturb'd they rose from the bright ruins silent </l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.04">The fiery King, who sought his ancient temple serpent-form'd</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.05">That stretches out its shady length along the Island white.</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.06">Round him roll'd his clouds of war; silent the Angel went,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.07">Along the infinite shores of Thames to golden Verulam.</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.08">There stand the venerable porches that high-towering rear</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.09">Their oak-surrounded pillars, form'd of massy stones, uncut</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.10">With tool; stones precious; such eternal in the heavens,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.11">Of colours twelve. few known on earth, give light in the opake.</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.12">Plac'd in the order of the stars, when the five senses whelm'd </l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.13">In deluge o'er the earth-born man; then turn'd the fluxile eyes</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.14">Into two stationary orbs, concentrating all things.</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.15">The ever-varying spiral ascents to the heavens of heavens</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.16">Were bended downward; and the nostrils golden gates shut</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.17">Turn'd outward, barr'd and petrify'd against the infinite.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.18">Thought chang'd the infinite to a serpent; that which pitieth:</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.19">To a devouring flame; and man fled from its face and hid</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.20">In forests of night; then all the eternal forests were divided</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.21">Into earths rolling in circles of space, that like an ocean</l>
          <l indent="15" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.22">rush'd</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.23">And overwhelmed all except this finite wall of flesh.</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.24">Then was the serpent temple form'd, image of infinite</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.25">Shut up in finite revolutions, and man became an Angel;</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.26">Heaven a mighty circle turning; God a tyrant crown'd.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.27">Now arriv'd the ancient Guardian at the southern porch,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.28">That planted thick with trees of blackest leaf, &amp; in a vale</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.29">Obscure, inclos'd the Stone of Night; oblique it stood, o'erhung</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.30">With purple flowers and berries red; image of that sweet south,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.31">Once open to the heavens and elevated on the human neck,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.32">Now overgrown with hair and coverd with a stony roof, (feet</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.33">Downward 'tis sunk beneath th' attractive north, that round the</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.11.34">A raging whirlpool draws the dizzy enquirer to his grave.</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P12-14" id="europe.a.illbk.12">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A12">Object 12 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B14">(Bentley 14, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E11">Erdman 11, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K11">Keynes 11)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.4 x 16.9 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>A gowned male sits on a throne-like chair, the chair 
in turn resting on a cloud.  He faces forward and wears the 
triple-crown of a Pope.  His face, however, may be a caricature 
of George III.  He holds on his lap an open book.  Large, bat- 
like wings extend from behind his arms.  The back of his chair resembles the facade of a 
gothic church, with arches and spires right and left.  His gown 
between his legs seems to contain embroidered pictures of four 
gowned and standing figures.  Below this Pope, and below the 
cloud, are two female angels, right and left, with large wings.  
Both have long hair, are gowned, bow and look down, and have one 
arm extended at 45 degrees.  Each holds in her extended hand a 
scepter or staff with a fleur-de-lis point at its lower 
termination.  These two angels have small snake-like tails (or perhaps simply vines) projecting from the hems of their gowns.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>robe</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Pope</characteristic>
            <characteristic>George III</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bat-eared</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crown</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned male sits on a throne-like chair, the chair 
in turn resting on a cloud. He faces forward and wears the 
triple-crown of a Pope.  His face, however, may be a caricature 
of George III.  He holds on his lap an open book.  Large, bat- 
like wings extend from behind his arms.  His mouth is open; he may be speaking. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="figure">
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The seated figure's gown is decorated, between his 
legs, with four gowned and standing figures.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>book</characteristic>
            <characteristic>open</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The seated male holds an open book on his lap.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
            <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fleur-de-lis</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Each angel, right and left, holds a staff or scepter with a fleur-de-lis point at its lower end.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned, female angel with long hair and large 
wings with prominent feathers stands on the left side of the design.  She bows and looks down, with her right arm extended at 45 degrees.  She holds in her 
right hand a staff or scepter with a fleur-de-lis point at its 
lower termination.  A small, but perhaps snake-like, tail (or possibly just a vine) extends from the hem of her gown.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned, female angel with long hair and large 
wings with prominent feathers stands on the right side of the design.  She bows and looks down, with her left arm extended at 45 degrees.  She holds in her 
left hand a staff or scepter with a fleur-de-lis point at its 
lower termination.  A small, but perhaps snake-like, tail (or possibly just a vine) extends from the hem of her gown.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The wavy lines extending from the hems of the gowns 
      worn by both angels may be snake-like tails—or simply 
vines.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facade</characteristic>
            <characteristic>church</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The crowned male sits in a chair.  Its back 
resembles the facade of a Gothic church, with arches and spires 
right and left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The chair in which the male sits is placed on a 
cloud.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="55" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.12.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">10</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="10"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.12.02">Albions Angel rose upon the Stone of Night,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.12.03">He saw Urizen on the Atlantic:</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.12.04">And his brazen Book,</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.12.05">That Kings &amp; Priests had copied on Earth</l>
          <l indent="5" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.12.06">Expanded from North to South,</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P13-10" id="europe.a.illbk.13">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A13">Object 13 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B10">(Bentley 10, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K7">Keynes 7)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="full">
        <objnote>
          <p>The phrase inscribed on the wall is &quot;LORD HAVE MERCY ON US.&quot; The &quot;H&quot; of &quot;HAVE&quot; and &quot;Y&quot; of &quot;MERCY&quot; are hidden behind the arms of two of the figures.</p>
        </objnote>
        <objsize>23.4 x 17.0 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The background of the design is composed of a brick 
wall with a large wooden door.  The closed door is inscribed 
&quot;LORD [H]AVE MERC[Y] ON US&quot; with a cross below the inscription.  
Left of the door is a standing, and perhaps walking, figure 
wearing a heavy black coat.  He faces left, looks down with a 
worried expression, and wears a large and dark bicorn hat.  His 
left arm is at his side and he holds a large bell in his left 
hand.  This bellman, as well as the inscription on the door 
(typical of quarantined houses) can be associated with the theme 
of plague dominating the design.  Since his mouth is slightly 
open, he may be calling out, &quot;Bring out your dead!&quot;  Below the 
bellman on the left are a man and woman.  The man, wearing a gown 
or at least a shirt, appears against the left margin of the plate 
in profile, facing right and down, and perhaps holds the woman with his 
right arm.  His hair is curly.  The gowned woman sits on the 
ground, with her upper body propped up by the man.  Her hair is 
long and her arms are at her side.  Her face, with mouth open 
like her companion's, expresses despair and perhaps pain, and the limp posture of her body indicates that she may be weak from the plague.  To the right, a gowned woman with 
long hair seems to be falling on her knees.  Her arms are raised 
vertically as if in supplication, with the fingers of both hands 
spread apart.  She faces up, with her head bent back; like her 
companions, she has an expression of pain or 
despair indicative of the plague.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plague</characteristic>
            <characteristic>London</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The group of four figures—a bellman and three 
figures with expressions of pain or despair—— 
indicates that this is a picture of the plague.  This is 
confirmed by the inscription on the door in the background, 
typical of what was written on the doors of quarantined houses 
during the great plague of London in 1665.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bellman</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bell</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A standing, and perhaps walking, figure wears a 
heavy black coat.  He faces left, looks down with a worried 
expression, and wears a large and dark bicorn hat.  His left arm 
is at is side and he holds a large bell in his left hand.  This 
is a bellman, tolling the time.  Since his mouth is slightly 
open, he may be calling out during the plague, &quot;Bring out your 
dead!&quot;</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A male wearing a gown or shirt sits against the left 
margin of the plate in profile, facing right and down, and perhaps holds 
the woman to the right with his right arm.  His hair is curly and 
his mouth is open.  His facial expression indicates pain (from 
disease?) and despair.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>woman</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>limp</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman sits on the ground, with her upper 
body propped up by the man to the left.  Her hair is long and her 
arms are at her side.  Her face, with mouth open like her 
companion's, expresses despair and perhaps pain.  The limp posture of her body indicates disease.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman with long hair seems to be falling on 
her knees.  Her arms are raised vertically as if in supplication, 
with the fingers of both hands spread apart.  She faces up, with 
her head bent back; like her companions, she has an expression of pain or despair indicative of 
disease.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="structure">
            <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
            <characteristic>door</characteristic>
            <characteristic>brick</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cross</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The background of the design is composed of a brick 
wall with a large wooden door.  The closed door is inscribed 
&quot;LORD [H]AVE MERC[Y] ON US&quot; with a cross below the 
inscription.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="text">
            <transcription>
              <lg justify="left" type="prose">
                <l justify="left">LORD [H]AVE MERC[Y] ON US</l>
              </lg>
            </transcription>
            <illusobjdesc>The wooden door in the background wall is 
inscribed.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="70" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.13.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">11</physnumber>
            <space extent="15"/>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.13.02">LORD</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.13.03">AVE MERC</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="prose">
          <l justify="center" n="europe.a.illbk.13.04">ON US</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P14-15" id="europe.a.illbk.14">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A14">Object 14 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B15">(Bentley 15, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E12">Erdman 12, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K12">Keynes 12)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.4 x 17.3 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The illustration, dominated by spider webs, extends 
along the right margin, extends between lines 21 and 22 of the 
text, and fills the bottom margin of the plate.  Top right is a 
dense mass of lines that apparently represents a web; the other 
webs are more clearly pictured with finer lines.  At least five 
spiders appear on the web: right of lines 15-17, right of line 
20, in a dense web below the first word (&quot;Fled&quot;) in line 21, 
above &quot;wide&quot; in line 24, and right of lines 29-31 (dangling on a 
single thread).  What may be a sixth spider appears above &quot;&amp; 
louder&quot; at the end of line 15.  A great many insects appear in 
the design, although some are simply suggested by little more 
than dots.  The larger and more identifiable insects are a winged 
insect right of lines 11-13, a fly or butterfly further to the 
right and just below the mass of lines in the top right corner, a 
fly below this insect, four flies (two very small) right of lines 
15-17, a large winged insect (a beetle?) right of line 21 and 
half-way to the right margin, a caterpillar below and to the left 
of this last insect, another winged fly or beetle above and to 
the right of the spider between lines 21 and 22, and a large fly 
or beetle (and a cluster of very small insects) below &quot;he drag'd&quot; 
in line 21.  The landscape below the text is filled with heavy 
vegetation, including low plants with large leaves and a vine 
with one loop and three large leaves intertwined with the spider 
web in the lower right corner.  Just to the left is a nude figure, of uncertain gender, sitting on the ground and completely covered by a fine net or web.  The legs are bent at the knees and the body is twisted so that the figure faces forward.  The head is bent back and she or he looks up.  The upper body is braced up on the elbows.  The hands are held together in an attitude of supplication or prayer.  This figure may relate to the image of &quot;every man bound&quot; (line 27).</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms braced</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
            <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
            <characteristic>net</characteristic>
            <characteristic>web</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude figure, of uncertain gender, sits on the ground and is completely covered by a fine net or web.  The legs are bent at the knees and the body is twisted so that the figure faces forward.  The head is bent back and she or he looks up.  The upper body is braced up on the elbows.  The hands are held together in an attitude of supplication or prayer.  This figure may relate to the image of &quot;every man bound&quot; (line 27).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>web</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The design areas in the right margin and between 
lines 21 and 22 of the text are dominated by spider webs.  They 
are particularly dense and somewhat formless in the top right 
corner of the plate and between lines 21 and 22 near the left 
margin.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Several insects appear in this section of the 
design, including a large winged insect (a beetle?) right of 
lines 11-13 of the text, a fly or butterfly further to the right, 
and a small fly below the butterfly.  Dots in this area suggest 
other insects.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A small spider (although it has only six legs) 
appears above &quot;&amp; louder&quot; at the end of line 15 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two clearly defined, and two very small, flying 
insects appear right of lines 15-17 of the text.  Further to the 
right, a spider sits on its web.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A spider sits on a web just right of line 20 of the 
text.  Below and further to the right is a large flying insect, 
perhaps a beetle, with double wings.  A caterpillar rests on the 
web below and to the left of this winged insect.  Another flying 
insect is left of the caterpillar.  Other dots in this area may 
represent further insects.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large spider rests on 
the web between lines 21 and 22 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large flying insect with double wings, perhaps a fly or beetle, 
appears below &quot;he drag'd&quot; in line 21 of the text.  Other small 
flying insects hover in the same area; some are little more than 
dots.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A spider sits in a dense part of his web below the 
first word (&quot;Fled&quot;) in line 21 of the text. Below it are two indeterminate forms which may be insects caught in the web. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>thread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hanging</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large spider hangs head down from a single 
thread right of lines 28-32 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The lower margin of the plate is filled with 
vegetation, including some low plants with large 
leaves.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop and three or four large leaves 
grows from the lower right corner of the plate.  It is 
intertwined with the spider web above.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="E" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>Vines and insects decorate the text, continuing 
motifs appearing in the marginal designs.  In line 2, the first letter of the first word (&quot;And&quot;) 
grows into a vine with a loop.  The last letter of this word, the last letter of 
&quot;round,&quot; the second letter of &quot;the&quot; before &quot;night,&quot; and the final 
letter of &quot;of&quot; also grow into vines.  A vine with a loop grows from 
the first letter of the last word (&quot;Towers&quot;) in line 4.  A 
wavy vine grows from the last letter of the last word 
(&quot;Angel&quot;) in line 7.  Several vines appear below and to the right 
of line 14; the dots further to the right may represent insects.  
Vines grow horizontally above the last two words of line 20 and above &quot;Europe&quot; in line 22.  The winged 
creature above &quot;the&quot; in line 15 may be a bird.  At least two 
winged insects and a vine appear between lines 25 and 26.  At 
least three winged insects and a vine appear between lines 32 and 
33.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The dots on the right between lines 13 and 15 may 
represent insects.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>There may be a small bird flying on extended wings 
above &quot;the&quot; in line 15 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>At least two winged insects fly between lines 25 and 
26 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>At least three winged insects fly between lines 32 
and 33 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The first letter of the first word in line 2 (&quot;And&quot;) grows into a vine with a loop; 
the last letter of this word grows into a vine as well.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>In line 2, the final letter of 
&quot;round,&quot; the second letter of &quot;the,&quot; and the final letter of &quot;of&quot; 
grow into vines.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The first letter of the last word (&quot;Towers&quot;) in line 
4 of the text grows into a vine with one loop.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The last letter of the final word (&quot;Angel&quot;) in line 
7 of the text grows into a vine.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Several vines grow horizontally below and to the 
right of line 14 of the text.  The vine springing from &quot;louder&quot; 
in line 15 contains two loops.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows above the last two words of line 20.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows horizontally above &quot;Europe&quot; in line 22 
of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows horizontally between lines 25 and 26 of 
the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows horizontally below &quot;villagers,&quot; line 32 
of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="70" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">12</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.02">And the clouds &amp; fires pale rolld round in the night of Enitharmon</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.03">Round Albions cliffs &amp; Londons walls; still Enitharmon slept!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.04">Rolling volumes of grey mist involve Churches, Palaces, Towers;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.05">For Urizen unclaspd his Book! feeding his. soul with pity</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.06">The youth of England hid in gloom curse the paind heavens; compell'd</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.07">Into the deadly night to see the form of Albions Angel</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.08">Their parents brought them forth &amp; aged ignorance preaches canting,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.09">On a vast rock, perciev'd by those senses that are clos'd from thought:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.10">Bleak, dark, abrupt, it stands &amp; overshadows London city</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.11">They saw his boney feet on the rock, the flesh consum'd in flames;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.12">They saw the Serpent temple lifted above, shadowing the Island white:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.13">They heard the voice of Albions Angel howling in flames of Orc.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.14">Seeking the trump of the last doom</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.15">Above the rest the howl was heard from Westminster louder &amp; louder;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.16">The Guardian of the secret codes forsook his ancient mansion,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.17">Driven out by the flames of Orc; his furr'd robes &amp; false locks</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.18">Adhered and grew one with his flesh, and nerves &amp; veins shot thro' them</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.19">With dismal torment sick hanging upon the wind: he fled</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.20">Groveling along Great George Street thro' the Park gate; all the soldiers</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.21">Fled from his sight: he drag'd his torments to the wilderness.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.22">Thus was the howl thro Europe!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.23">For Orc rejoic'd to hear the howling shadows</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.24">But Palamabron shot his lightnings trenching down his wide back</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.25">And Rintrah hung with all his legions in the nether deep</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.26">Enitharmon laugh'd in her sleep to see (O womans triumph)</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.27">Every house a den, every man bound; the shadows are filld</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.28">With spectres, and the windows wove over with curses of iron:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.29">Over the doors Thou shalt not; &amp; over the chimneys Fear is written:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.30">With bands of iron round their necks, fasten'd into the walls</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.31">The citizens: in leaden gyves the inhabitants of suburbs</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.32">Walk heavy: soft and bent are the bones of villagers</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.33">Between the clouds of Urizen the flames of Orc roll heavy</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.34">Around the limbs of Albions Guardian. his flesh consuming,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.35">Howlings &amp; hissings. shrieks &amp; groans. &amp; voices of despair</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.36">Arise around him in the cloudy</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.14.37">Heavens of Albion, Furious</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P15-16" id="europe.a.illbk.15">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A15">Object 15 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B16">(Bentley 16, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E13">Erdman 13, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K13">Keynes 13)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.3 x 16.9 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1212" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>The setting is a stone prison cell with stone stairs 
rising on the right.  A prisoner, lower left, has shackles on 
both ankles; the shackles are in turn attached to the stone 
floor with two heavy chains.  The prisoner is a nude male with 
curly hair who sits on a stone ledge.  His prominent knees are 
drawn up to his chest and his legs crossed at the ankles.  His 
neck is twisted to the right; his head is back and he seems to 
look up at the figure on the right.  His arms are bent at the 
elbows with his hands raised, palms facing the viewer and fingers 
spread apart.  His gestures and open eye indicate fear and 
perhaps pain.  We see the male figure on the right from behind as 
he ascends the stairs (right leg extended backwards, left leg 
bent forward).  Except for what may be a belt around his waist, 
he is nude.  His hair is curly.  His right arm is at his side and 
he holds a large key (on a ring?) in his right hand.  This last object 
identifies him as a jailor.  The green coloring and mottled texture of his skin hints at a disease.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="C" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>prisoner</characteristic>
            <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
            <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
            <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A prisoner, lower left, has shackles on both ankles; 
the shackles are in turn attached to the stone floor with two 
heavy chains.  The prisoner is a nude male with curly hair who 
sits on a stone ledge.  His prominent knees are drawn up to his 
chest and his legs crossed at the ankles.  His neck is twisted to 
the right; his head is back and he seems to look up at the figure 
on the right.  His arms are bent at the elbows with his hands 
raised, palms facing the viewer and fingers spread apart.  His 
gestures and open eye indicate fear and perhaps 
pain.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="object">
            <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A prisoner, lower left, has shackles on both 
ankles; the shackles are in turn attached to the stone floor with two 
heavy chains.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>buttocks</characteristic>
            <characteristic>jailor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>hunched over</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>disease</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>We see from behind a male figure ascending the 
stairs (right leg extended backwards, left leg bent forward).  
Except for what may be a belt around his waist, he is nude.  His 
hair is curly.  His right arm is at his side and he holds a large 
key (on a ring?) in his right hand.  This last object identifies him as a 
jailor.  The green coloring and mottled texture of his skin hints at a disease.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>key</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ring</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The figure holds a key (on a ring?) in his right hand.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="structure">
            <characteristic>prison</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stairs</characteristic>
            <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The setting for the two figures is a prison cell 
with stairs on the right.  The walls, stairs, and floor appear to 
be built of stones.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>An insect (perhaps a fly) flies just below the last 
letter of &quot;presumptuous,&quot; line 4 of the text.  Vines extend into 
the left margin from the first letters of the first words in 
lines 5 and 6.  A spider sits on a web between lines 9 and 10.  
Further to the right, and extending up the right margin and then 
looping back toward the last word in line 5, is what may be a 
vine.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>An insect (perhaps a fly) flies just below the last 
letter of &quot;presumptuous,&quot; line 4 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A spider sits on a web between lines 9 and 10 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="object">
            <characteristic>web</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A spider web runs horizontally between lines 9 and 10 
of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Vines extend into the left margin from the first 
letters of the first words in lines 5 and 6 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine, and perhaps other sorts of vegetation, 
extends below the final word in line 9 of the text, grows upward 
in the right margin, and curls back to the left under the final 
word in line 4 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="63" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">13</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.02">The red limb'd Angel siez'd - in horror and torment;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.03">The Trump of the last doom; but he could not blow the iron tube!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.04">Thrice he assay'd presumptuous to awak
            <space extent="1"/>
            the dead to Judgment.
            <note>The &quot;e&quot; in &quot;awake&quot; did not print in this copy. </note></l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.05">A mighty Spirit leap'd from the land of Albion,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.06">Nam'd Newton; he siez'd the Trump, &amp; blow'd the enormous blast!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.07">Yellow as leaves of Autumn the myriads of Angelic hosts,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.08">Fell thro' the wintry skies seeking their graves;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.09">Rattling their hollow bones in howling and lamentation.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l indent="2" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.10">Then Enitharmon woke nor knew that she had slept</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.11">And eighteen hundred years were fled</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.12">As if they had not been</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.13">She calld her sons &amp; daughters</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.14">To the sports of night,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.15">Within her crystal house;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.16">And thus her song proceeds.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.17">Arise Ethinthus! tho' the earth-worm call;
               </l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.18">Let him call in vain;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.19">Till the night of holy shadows</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.15.20">And human solitude is past!</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P16-17" id="europe.a.illbk.16">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A16">Object 16 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B17">(Bentley 17, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E14">Erdman 14, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K14">Keynes 14)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.3 x 16.5 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1212" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>This text plate contains many interlinear vines, 
birds, insects, and three snakes.  Four or five 
butterflies appear right of lines 2-5.  A vine descends from the 
first letter of the first word in line 7.  Two vines grow from 
the first letter of the first word in line 10.  Vines, at least 
three birds, an insect(?) on a leaf, and flames decorate the space 
between lines 6 and 7.  A butterfly and two other winged insects, 
two vines (one may be a worm), and an odd shape that may be two 
moths flying close together appear between lines 9 and 10.  A vine 
with multiple branches and leaves wends its way through the 
margin right of lines 9-20.  A flower, shaped like a 
Meadia, grows close to the right margin of the plate, right of 
line 10.  Another such flower appears below and to the left of the 
first one, right of line 13.  On and around this large vine are an inch worm (below the last word in line 9),
caterpillars (above and to the right of line 15 and right of 
lines 10-11 and 16-17), a spider (right of line 15), and several flying 
insects.  Five flying insects (at least one a butterfly) follow 
line 12.  A vine descends left of the first word in line 16.  A 
vine with two loops grows from the descender of the last letter 
of &quot;thy&quot; in line 21.  A large bird, possibly an eagle, and three 
smaller birds or insects fly near the right margin of the plate 
right of lines 19-21.  A vine with many loops fills the 
considerable space between lines 21 and 22 and descends in the 
right margin to line 27.  On this vine are at least two large and 
two small caterpillars, an inch-worm, two snails, at least three 
spiders, at least two insects with wings folded, and a bird perched near the right margin with its mouth open (because it is singing?).  The odd shape within the loops of the vine to the left appears to be another bird, facing left with its beak open.  A large moth or butterfly appears below &quot;Antamon&quot; in line 21.  A flying insect is pictured far to the right of line 24.  Below and to the left is a large bird (possibly an 
eagle) soaring upwards, with a flock of five birds to the left.  
The form right of lines 27-31 probably represents the sky.  A 
vine descends from the second letter of &quot;my&quot; in line 26.  A vine 
with leaves and several branches appears right of lines 29-38.  Intertwined with this vine is a snake, facing to the left with its mouth open and its forked tongue clearly pictured.  Two other snakes, both facing left, appear in 
the bottom margin.  The right-most snake in the lower margin has 
a clearly pictured tongue.  The last letter of the last word in 
line 35 grows into a vine.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Four or five butterflies fly right of lines 2-5 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two, or perhaps three, birds fly below &quot;warble 
round&quot; in line 6 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A leaf or cluster of leaves is pictured below &quot;feet of,&quot; line 6 of the text.  The form just above the largest leaf is probably another leaf, but might be an insect.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="animal">
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two butterflies, and either a very small bird or 
another winged insect, appear below &quot;wings are my delight,&quot; line 
9 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>moth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The odd forms below &quot;flames&quot; in line 9 of the text 
may be two moths flying close together.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>An inch worm crawls on the vine below the last word in line 9.  A caterpillar climbs along the vine right of lines 
10-11 of the text.  Below this caterpillar is another 
insect on the vine.  A winged insect flies right of this last 
creature.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Five flying insects, perhaps butterflies, appear 
right of line 12 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A caterpillar appears above and to the right of the 
ending of line 15 of the text.  Further to the right are a spider 
and a flying insect.  Another caterpillar appears on the vine right of lines 16-17.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eagle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Right of line 18 of the text are two flying insects 
or birds.  Another such creature appears near the right margin.  
A large bird, perhaps an eagle, flies downward right of lines 19- 
20.  Two very small birds or winged insects appear below the 
bird, right of line 21.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="animal">
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>inch-worm</characteristic>
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snail</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The space between lines 21 and 22 of the text 
includes two large caterpillars, an inch-worm, a small spider, 
and a snail.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>spider</characteristic>
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>snail</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>perching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>singing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The space between lines 21 and 22, near the right 
margin, includes two spiders (one large, one small), at least two insects of 
uncertain species with wings folded, a caterpillar, a snail, and a bird perched on a vine, facing up and with its mouth open and probably singing.  
The form above the large snail may be another 
bird facing left, perhaps will its beak open.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="BD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>perching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>singing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird perches within the loops beneath &quot;love&quot; in line 21. This bird appears to be facing left, with its neck extended and beak open. It may be singing. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flock</characteristic>
            <characteristic>eagle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A flock of at least five birds flies right of line 
26.  Further to the right is a large bird, perhaps an eagle, 
soaring upwards.  Above and to the right of the bird is a flying 
insect, perhaps a beetle with four wings.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="animal">
            <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A snake is intertwined with the vine in the lower 
right corner of the plate.  It faces left, with mouth open and 
forked tongue clearly pictured.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="CD" type="animal">
            <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
            <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two snakes appear in the lower margin.  Both face 
left with mouths open.  The tongue of the right-most snake is 
clearly pictured.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="object">
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Several flames appear below and to the right of the 
last word (&quot;Enitharmon&quot;) in line 6 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two vines extend horizontally between lines 6 and 7 
of the text.  Both may bear slender leaves.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine descends from the first letter of the first 
word in line 7 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Two vines spring from the first letter of the first 
word in line 10 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine—or perhaps a worm—twists above &quot;Leutha,&quot; 
line 10 of the text.  A second vine extends horizontally above the 
last two words in the same line.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
            <characteristic>Meadia</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with multiple branches and leaves wends its 
way through the margin right of lines 9-20 of the text.  At least 
one flower, shaped like a Meadia, grows close to the right margin 
of the plate, right of line 10.  Another such flower appears below 
and to the left of the first one, right of line 13.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine descends from the first letter of the first 
word in line 16 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine descends from the first letter of the first word in line 21, 
and a vine with two loops grows from the descender of the last letter of &quot;thy&quot; in this line. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large vine with many loops extends between lines 
21 and 22 of the text.  Some tendrils, perhaps with leaves, 
descend in the right margin to line 27.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the first letter of the first word in line 23, and from the descender of the second letter of in line 26.  </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the first letter of the first word in line 33.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="object">
            <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
            <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The odd form right of lines 27-31 probably represents sky or the margins of clouds.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the last letter of the final word of line 35. </illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine or plant with leaves and several branches appears in 
the bottom margin and right of lines 29-38 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="65" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">14</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.02">Ethinthus queen of waters, how thou shinest in the sky:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.03">My daughter how do I rejoice! for thy children flock around</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.04">Like the gay fishes on the wave, when the cold moon drinks the dew.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.05">Ethinthus! thou art sweet as comforts to my fainting soul;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.06">For now thy waters warble round the feet of Enitharmon.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.07">Manathu-Varcyon! I behold thee flaming in my halls,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.08">Light of thy mothers soul! I see thy lovely eagles round:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.09">Thy golden wings are my delight, &amp; thy flames of soft delusion.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.10">Where is my lureing bird of Eden! Leutha silent love!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.11">Leutha. the many colourd bow delights upon thy wings;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.12">Soft soul of flowers Leutha!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.13">Sweet smiling pestilence! I see thy blushing light:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.14">Thy daughters many changing,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.15">Revolve like sweet perfumes ascending O Leutha silken queen!</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.16">Where is the youthful Antamon. prince of the pearly dew,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.17">O Antamon, why wilt thou leave thy mother Enitharmon?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.18">Alone I see thee crystal form.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.19">Floting upon the bosomd air:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.20">With lineaments of gratified desire.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.21">My Antamon the seven churches of Leutha seek thy love,</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="4"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.22">I hear the soft Oothoon in Enitharmons tents:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.23">Why wilt thou give up womans secrecy my melancholy child?</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.24">Between two moments bliss is ripe:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.25">O Theotormon robb'd of joy, I see thy salt tears flow</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.26">Down the steps of my crystal house.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.27">Sotha &amp; Thiralatha, secret dwellers of dreamful caves,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.28">Arise and please the horrent fiend with your melodious songs.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.29">Still all your thunders golden hoofd, &amp; bind your horses black.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.30">Orc! smile upon my children!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.31">Smile son of my afflictions.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.32">Arise O Orc and give our mountains joy of thy red light.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.33">She ceas'd, for All were forth at sport beneath the solemn moon
            <note>Line 33, as originally written, contained these words, &quot;and all went forth to sport,&quot; which were changed in the copper to &quot;for All were forth at sport&quot;.</note></l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.34">Waking the stars of Urizen with their immortal songs,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.35">That nature felt thro' all her pores the enormous revelry.</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.36">Till morning ope'd the eastern gate.
            <note>Line 36, as originally written, ended with &quot;and the angel trumpet blew!&quot; These five words were erased from the copper plate.</note></l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.37">Then every one fled to his station. &amp; Enitharmon wept.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.16.38">But terrible Orc, when he beheld the morning in the east,</l>
        </lg>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
    <desc dbi="europe.a.P17-18" id="europe.a.illbk.17">
      <objtitle>,

        <objid>
          <objnumber code="A17">Object 17 </objnumber>
          <objcode code="B18">(Bentley 18, </objcode>
          <objcode code="E15">Erdman 15, </objcode>
          <objcode code="K15">Keynes 15)</objcode></objid>
      </objtitle>
      <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>23.4 x 16.6 cm.</objsize>
        <windowsize height="1217" width="900"/>
      </physdesc>
      <illusdesc>
        <illustration location="E" type="plate">
          <illusobjdesc>Below the text, a nude, muscular male with curly 
hair stands with legs spread apart, his genitals clearly visible. 
His left leg is extended to the right, with his left foot on the 
ground.  His right leg is bent at the knee with his foot on one 
of at least two stone steps.  He may be striding to the left.  
His body faces forward, but his head is turned to the right.  His 
expression is fearful or pained.  He may be looking at the flames 
forming the background of the design or at the young girl whose 
left arm he grasps with his lowered left hand.  Perhaps the man 
is her father, attempting to rescue the child from the flames.  
She wears a gown and has long hair.  We see her from behind; her 
right arm is drawn back and raised at 135 degrees.  Her left leg is extended 
backward; she may be striding to the left.  The nude male 
carries, over his right shoulder, the limp body of a gowned 
woman—perhaps the child's mother.  The man's right arm is 
raised, bent at the elbow, and embraces the woman around the 
waist.  Her left arm and long hair dangle down toward the man's 
right knee.  Her gown, and presumably her legs, dangle behind the 
man's spread legs.  She may be dead or dying.  Lower left, on 
top of the steps, is a fluted and broken pillar.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
            <characteristic>family</characteristic>
            <characteristic>father</characteristic>
            <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The group of three figures may be a family of 
mother, father, and female child.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="figure">
            <characteristic>male</characteristic>
            <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
            <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
            <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
            <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>father</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
            <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>carrying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rescuing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A nude, muscular male with curly hair stands with 
legs spread apart, his genitals clearly visible.  His left leg is 
extended to the right, with his left foot on the ground.  His 
right leg is bent at the knee with his foot on one of at least 
two stone steps.  He may be striding to the left.  His body faces 
forward, but his head is turned to the right.  His expression is 
fearful or pained.  He may be looking at the flames forming the 
background of the design or at the young girl whose left arm he 
grasps with his lowered left hand.  Perhaps the man is her 
father, attempting to rescue the child from the flames.  He 
carries the limp body of a woman over his right 
shoulder.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="D" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>young</characteristic>
            <characteristic>child</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
            <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic>
            <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
            <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>We see a young female child from behind.  She wears 
a long gown.  Her left arm is held by the nude male; her right 
arm is drawn back and raised at 135 degrees.  Her left leg is extended backward; 
she may be striding to the left.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AC" type="figure">
            <characteristic>female</characteristic>
            <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
            <characteristic>limp</characteristic>
            <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
            <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
            <characteristic>legs dangling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
            <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
            <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The nude male carries, over his right shoulder, the 
limp body of a gowned woman—perhaps the child's mother.  The 
man's right arm is raised, bent at the elbow, and embraces the 
woman around the waist.  Her left arm and long hair dangle down 
toward the man's right knee.  Her gown, and presumably her legs, 
dangle behind the man's spread legs.  She may be dead or 
dying.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="E" type="object">
            <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>The background of the design below the text is 
composed mostly of a sheet of flames.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="C" type="structure">
            <characteristic>step</characteristic>
            <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>plinth</characteristic>
            <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ruin</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Three stone steps, or two steps and a plinth, and a fluted and broken classical pillar appear in the lower left corner of the 
design.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
        <illustration location="AB" type="interlinear">
          <illusobjdesc>The text area contains a good many vegetative motifs 
and animals.  Three vines extend horizontally between lines 3 and 
4.  The vine on the left includes a loop and one ivy-like leaf.  
The next vine to the right bears two oak or grape leaves.  The 
largest vine, furthest to the right, has long, slender leaves.  
At least four insects, most likely beetles and caterpillars, crawl on it.  Three winged 
insects (some little more than dots) and one butterfly (below 
&quot;fury&quot; in line 3) fly above the vine.  Below &quot;of his&quot; in line 3, 
a bird perches on the vine but spreads its 
wings as if about to fly into the air.  An oak or grape leaf grows into the left margin from the first letter of the first word of line 4.  A vine with ivy-like 
leaves extends horizontally between lines 9 and 10, divides into 
several branches in the right margin, and has one branch arching 
back to the left at line 7.  A branch bearing five oak leaves and 
one acorn extends into the right margin following the final line 
of text.  To the right of this branch, a bird flies upward on 
extended wings.  A vine with two loops grows from the first 
letter of &quot;FINIS&quot; (line 13) and extends horizontally above the 
word.</illusobjdesc>
          <component location="AB" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>beetle</characteristic>
            <characteristic>crawling</characteristic>
            <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>At least four insects, most likely beetles and caterpillars, crawl along 
the vine between lines 3 and 4 of the text.  There is an insect with folded wings on the vine near the right margin.  Three tiny creatures (one just a dot) fly below the vine just left of the right margin.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>insect</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>Four winged insects (some little more than 
dots) fly above the vine between lines 3 and 4 of the text.  The 
insect below &quot;fury&quot; at the end of line 3 is probably a 
butterfly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>perching</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird perches on the vine between lines 3 and 4 of 
the text, just below &quot;of his&quot; in line 3.  Its wings spread as though it were about to 
fly.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="animal">
            <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
            <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
            <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
            <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A bird flies upward and to the left on extended 
wings near the right margin of the plate, right of the branch 
following the final line of text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ivy</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop and an ivy-like leaf grows from 
the first letter of the first word (&quot;The&quot;) in line 4 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="A" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>grape</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with two oak or grape leaves extends 
horizontally below &quot;the vineyards&quot; in line 3 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large vine with slender leaves extends 
horizontally beneath line 3 of the text and descends, in the 
right margin, to line 11.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>ivy</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A large vine with ivy-like leaves extends 
horizontally between lines 9 and 10 of the text and divides into 
several branches in the right margin.  One branch extends back to 
the left at line 7.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="B" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
            <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
            <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
            <characteristic>acorn</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A branch bearing five oak leaves and one acorn 
extends into the right margin following the final line of 
text (line 13).</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
          <component location="AB" type="vegetation">
            <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
            <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
            <illusobjdesc>A vine with two loops grows from the first letter of 
&quot;FINIS&quot; (line 13) and extends horizontally above the word.</illusobjdesc>
          </component>
        </illustration>
      </illusdesc>
      <phystext>
        <texthead justify="left">
          <l indent="60" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.01">
            <physnumber type="pen-and-ink">15</physnumber>
          </l>
        </texthead>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.02">Shot from the heights of Enitharmon,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.03">And in the vineyards of red France appear'd the light of his fury.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.04">The sun glow'd fiery red;</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.05">The furious terrors flew around!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.06">On golden chariots raging, with red wheels dropping with blood; </l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.07">The Lions lash their wrathful tails!</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.08">The Tigers couch upon the prey &amp; suck the ruddy tide:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.09">And Enitharmon groans &amp; cries in anguish and dismay</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="1"/>
        <lg justify="left" type="verse">
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.10">Then Los arose his head he reard in snaky thunders clad:</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.11">And with a cry that shook all nature to the utmost pole,</l>
          <l justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.12">Call'd all his sons to the strife of blood.</l>
        </lg>
        <vspace extent="2"/>
        <textfoot justify="left">
          <l indent="23" justify="left" n="europe.a.illbk.17.13">FINIS</l>
        </textfoot>
      </phystext>
    </desc>
  </objdesc>
</bad>