<bad id="gates-sexes.k" type="illbk" work="For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise" copy="K" copyid="K"
        institution="lc" catalog="bentley" catid="K" hidden="false">
        <header>
                <filedesc>
                        <titlestmt>
                                <title reg="For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise"><main>For the
                                                Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</main><copy> Copy
                                                K</copy> : electronic edition </title>
                                <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,
                                        </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,
                                        </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                                                Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at
                                        Chapel Hill</principal>
                                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina
                                        at Chapel Hill, and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                                <funder/>
                        </titlestmt>
                        <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
                        <extent>1 XML file approx. 112KB; 28 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in
                                size from 14KB to 380KB</extent>
                        <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC
                                Libraries</publicationstmt>
                        <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
                        <updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the
                                publication of digital editions of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The
                                        Gates of Paradise</hi> Copies B, F, and K. They join Copy D
                                of <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi> and Copy D
                                of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>-the
                                revised and augmented version of <hi rend="i">For
                                Children</hi>-already available in the Archive. The Archive is also
                                publishing color printed impressions of Plates 1 and 7 of <hi
                                        rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>. <lb/>
                                <lb/> In 1793, Blake etched and published <hi rend="i">For
                                        Children</hi>, an emblem book comprising eighteen small
                                intaglio plates. Through a numbered series of designs with
                                inscriptions ranging from single words to brief aphorisms, Blake
                                puts the course of human life in psychological perspective. Some of
                                the emblems form narrative sequences; others exemplify mental states
                                and their reification in the external world. <hi rend="i">For
                                        Children</hi> is extant in five copies (A-E), with the
                                plates in their second states in all copies except Copy A. <lb/>
                                <lb/> In about 1818 Blake revised <hi rend="i">For Children: The
                                        Gates of Paradise</hi>, giving the work the new title of <hi
                                        rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> and
                                adding three new text plates at the end (Plates 19-21). Plates 19-20
                                contain brief interpretive statements keyed by number to the
                                preceding designs. The final plate is addressed to Satan as the "God
                                of This [fallen] World." <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> Copy B,
                                from the British Museum, Department of Prints and Drawings, was
                                printed c. 1818, with Plates 1-10 and 12-18 in their third state,
                                Plate 11 in its second state, and Plates 19-21 in their first state.
                                Copy B joins Copy D, from the Morgan Library and Museum, with Plates
                                1-10 and 13-18 in their fourth state, Plate 12 in its third state,
                                Plates 11, 19, and 21 in their second state, and Plate 20 in its
                                first state. <lb/>
                                <lb/> All the plates in <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> Copies F and
                                K are in their final states; Copy F lacks Plates 19 and 20 and Copy
                                K lacks 4-7, 10, 12, and 17. Both Copies F and K were once thought
                                to have been printed posthumously, possibly by Frederick Tatham, c.
                                1831. Recent studies of the states and the manner in which these
                                copies were produced indicate that Copy F, along with Copies G, H,
                                and I, were printed by Catherine Blake in late 1827 or early 1828,
                                when she was staying at John Linnell's studio in Fitzroy Square.
                                They also indicate that Copies J and N were once a single copy (now
                                referred to as J/N) and printed by Blake along with Copies E, K, and
                                L, c. 1826-27 (see Viscomi, “Posthumous Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake /
                                        An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 53.2 [fall 2019]). <lb/>
                                <lb/> The addition to the Archive of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>
                                Copies B, K, and F enables students of Blake to trace the evolution
                                of the designs, from their second states in 1793 through Blake's
                                revisions in c. 1818, 1825, and c. 1826-27, and to examine the
                                printing of Catherine Blake. <lb/>
                                <lb/> In 1796, Blake color printed an assortment of twenty-three
                                illuminated plates without their texts to form the <hi rend="i"
                                        >Small Book of Designs</hi>. He printed the plates twice
                                without replenishing the colors between pulls, using the first pulls
                                to form the <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> Copy A and the
                                second pulls to form Copy B, which he compiled after 1818. He also
                                printed first and second pulls of eight etchings and relief etchings
                                to form the <hi rend="i">Large Book of Designs</hi>. He did not,
                                however, compile the second pulls to form a Copy B. The
                                color-printed impressions of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
                                        of Albion</hi> Plates 1 and 7 are two of those second pulls,
                                which were acquired by Blake's patron, John Linnell, late in Blake's
                                life. They join three other plates from <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> in
                                our new category of graphic works, referred to in the index of
                                copies as “MPI,” an abbreviation for Miscellaneous Plates and
                                Impressions. <lb/>
                                <lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing
                                no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site
                                is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                                with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the
                                Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array
                                of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to
                                reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
                        <notesstmt/>
                </filedesc>
                <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
                        Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
                        Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
                        express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                        publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
                        only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © 2019 William Blake
                        Archive.</userestrict>
                <encodingdesc/>
                <profiledesc/>
                <revisiondesc>
                        <changestmt>
                                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                                <date>September 2019</date>
                                <respstmt>
                                        <resp>Editors:</resp>
                                        <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester;
                                                <name>Robert Essick,</name> University of
                                        California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                                        University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant
                                                Editor:</resp>
                                        <name>Michael Fox</name>
                                        <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                                        <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                                        <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                                        <name>Grant Glass</name>
                                        <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                                        <name>Eric Loy</name>
                                        <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                                        <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                                        <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                                        <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                                        <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                                        <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                                        <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                                        <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                                        <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                                        <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                                        <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                                        <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                                        <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                                        <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                                        <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                                        <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                                        <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                                        <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                                        <name>Kendall DeBoer</name>
                                        <name>Helen Davies</name>
                                </respstmt>
                        </changestmt>
                        <changestmt>
                                <change>BAD created</change>
                                <date>February 2008</date>
                                <respstmt>
                                        <resp>Editors: </resp>
                                        <name>Morris Eaves, </name> University of Rochester;
                                                <name>Robert Essick, </name> University of
                                        California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                                        University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Project
                                                Manager: </resp>
                                        <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                                        <name>William Shaw</name>
                                        <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                                        <name>Kate Attkisson, </name>
                                        <name>Kit Curtin, </name>
                                        <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                                        <name>Sarah Jones, </name>
                                        <name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name>
                                        <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                                        <name>Rachel Lee, </name>
                                        <name>Ali McGhee, </name>
                                        <name>Sarah Tolf, </name>
                                        <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                                        <name>Adair Rispoli </name>
                                </respstmt>
                        </changestmt>
                        <changestmt>
                                <change>Images acquired</change>
                                <date>October 1997</date>
                                <respstmt>
                                        <resp>Editors:</resp>
                                        <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester;
                                                <name>Robert Essick,</name> University of
                                        California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                                        University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                                                <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                                        <name>David Cosca, </name>
                                        <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                                        <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                                        <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                                        <resp>Project Assistant: </resp>
                                        <name>Greg Murray</name>
                                </respstmt>
                        </changestmt>
                </revisiondesc>
        </header>
        <objdesc>
                <source>
                        <objdescid>
                                <objtitle>
                                        <title> *For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise* </title>
                                </objtitle>
                                <origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor,
                                                </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher,
                                                </role><role>printer</role></origination>
                                <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role><note>Blake is
                                                recorded only as the publisher in the book, but
                                                there can be no question that he designed the images
                                                and authored their captions.</note></origination>
                                <imprint>
                                        <publisher>William Blake</publisher>
                                        <pubplace>London<note>"Lambeth" (a suburb of London) is
                                                  given as the place of publication on Objects 5, 7,
                                                  8, and 10 (Bentley Plates 9, 13, 14, and 16). This
                                                  refers to the place of publication of *For
                                                  Children: The Gates of Paradise* in 1793. Blake
                                                  lived in London during the revisions to Objects
                                                  1-11 (Bentley Plates 1-3, 8, 9, 11, 13-16, 18),
                                                  the etching and engraving of Objects 12-14
                                                  (Bentley Plates 19-21), and the printing of this
                                                  copy.</note></pubplace>
                                        <date>1793</date>
                                </imprint>
                                <compdate value="1793.B">1793, c. 1818<note>Objects 1-11 (Bentley
                                                Plates 1-3, 8, 9, 11, 13-16, 18) first etched and
                                                engraved in 1793; Objects 12-14 (Bentley plates
                                                19-21) etched and engraved c. 1818. The work is
                                                based on designs Blake drew in his Notebook; some of
                                                these sketches may have been executed c. 1790-93.
                                                The states of Bentley Plates 1-10, 13-18 were
                                                revised c. 1818, c. 1825, and c. 1826-27. Bentley
                                                Plate 11 was revised c. 1826-27. Bentley Plate 12
                                                was revised c. 1818 and c. 1826-27. Bentley Plates
                                                19 and 21 were revised c. 1825 and c. 1826-27.
                                                Bentley Plate 20 was revised c. 1826-27. This copy
                                                lacks Bentley Plates 4-7, 10, 12, and
                                        17.</note></compdate>
                        </objdescid>
                        <objinfo>
                                <printdate value="1826.C">c. 1826-27</printdate>
                                <numberobj>14</numberobj>
                                <objorder>Bentley Plates 1-3, 8, 9, 11, 13-16, 18-21</objorder>
                                <objsize>platemarks ranging in size between 10.5 x 7.2 cm. and 6.1 x
                                        4.2 cm.</objsize>
                                <numberleaves>14</numberleaves>
                                <leafsize>37.5 x 26.5 cm.</leafsize>
                                <medium>intaglio etching/engraving<note>All Objects are in their
                                                final states. Objects 1-5, 7-11 (Bentley Plates 1-3,
                                                8, 9, 13-16, and 18) are in the fifth state (of
                                                five); Objects 6, 12, and 14 (Bentley Plates 11, 19,
                                                and 21) are in the third state (of three); Object 13
                                                (Bentley Plate 20) is in the second state (of two).
                                                The first two states of Bentley Plates 1-18 appear
                                                in copies of *For Children: The Gates of Paradise*.
                                                Bentley Plates 19-21 appear only in copies of *For
                                                the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise*. This copy lacks
                                                Bentley Plates 4-7, 10, 12, and 17.</note></medium>
                                <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
                                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                                <support>wove paper</support>
                                <watermark>none</watermark>
                                <etchednumbers>1, 6, 7, 9, 11-14, 16 lower left on Objects 3-11
                                        (Bentley Plates 3, 8, 9, 11, 13-16, 18)</etchednumbers>
                                <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                                <framelines>none</framelines>
                                <binding>loose</binding>
                                <stabholes>none</stabholes>
                        </objinfo>
                        <provenance n="1">
                                <name>Library of Congress</name>
                                <date>1945</date>
                                <dealer>gift</dealer>
                                <price>gift</price>
                                <note>John Linnell, probably acquired directly from Blake or his
                                        wife, Catherine; John Linnell's grandson, Herbert Linnell,
                                        probably by inheritance; sold through the dealer Lionel
                                        Robinson to Lessing J. Rosenwald in July 1937; given by
                                        Rosenwald to the Library of Congress in 1945.</note>
                        </provenance>
                        <repository>
                                <institution>Library of Congress</institution>

                                <department>Rare Book and Special Collections Division</department>
                                <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection>
                                <repositoryid label="Call number">PR4144.F65 1810</repositoryid>
                                <repositoryid label="Call number">1814</repositoryid>
                        </repository>
                </source>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.01" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P1" compwith="gates-child.B1">
                        <objtitle><title type="transcribed">For the Sexes: The Gates of
                                        Paradise</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1
                                                </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1,
                                                </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i,
                                                </objcode><objcode code="Ki">Keynes
                                        i)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>9.4 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="489" width="328"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>We see two large leaves, perhaps oak leaves,
                                                growing from a branch. The veins on the lower leaf
                                                are particularly prominent. The upper leaf bears a
                                                large caterpillar which may be eating the edge of
                                                the leaf. The lower leaf cradles an infant or at
                                                least the head of an infant with closed eyeswhose
                                                body suggests both swaddling bands and a chrysalis.
                                                There are slight indications of curly hair on the
                                                infant's head.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>veins</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>We see two large leaves, perhaps oak
                                                  leaves, growing from a branch. The veins on the
                                                  lower leaf are particularly
                                                  prominent.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="animal" location="AB">
                                                <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A large caterpillar rests on the edge
                                                  of, and may be eating, a leaf.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>swaddled</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>chrysalis</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A leaf cradles an infant--or at least
                                                  the head of an infant with closed eyes--whose body
                                                  suggests both swaddling bands and a chrysalis.
                                                  There are slight indications of curly hair on the
                                                  infant's head.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <texthead justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.01.01" justify="center"
                                                >Frontispiece</l>
                                </texthead>
                                <vspace extent="4"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.01.02" justify="center">What is
                                                Man!</l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.01.03" justify="center">The Suns
                                                Light when he unfolds it</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.01.04" justify="center">Depends on
                                                the Organ that beholds it</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.01.05" justify="center">Publishd
                                                by WBlake 17 May 1793</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P2" compwith="gates-child.B2">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">object 2 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="Eii"
                                                >Erdman ii, </objcode><objcode code="Kii">Keynes
                                                ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>6.8 x 4.2 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize width="315" height="430"/>
                                <objnote>
                                        <p>This impression is in the second state for <hi
                                                  rend="italic">For the Sexes</hi>. The first state
                                                lacks the disc (apparently of the sun) and lines of
                                                radiance appearing above line 5 of the text
                                                ("Paradise").</p>
                                </objnote>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="interlinear" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>Two figures, both probably gowned and with
                                                arms extended horizontally, hover below the first
                                                line of text. Their directional orientation is
                                                uncertain; we may be seeing them from behind. Below
                                                the figure on the left in this pair are three very
                                                small hovering figures. The right-most figure in
                                                this group appear to have her or his arms raised at
                                                135 degrees. The central figure may have one arm
                                                raised at 45 degrees. The companion group on the
                                                right includes three (gowned?) and hovering figures,
                                                with the head of a fourth figure just visible above
                                                and to the left of the central figure in this group.
                                                The left-most figure has one arm raised horizontally
                                                and the other vertically. Below "Gates" (line 3) in
                                                the title, and on each side of the word "of" (line
                                                4), are two hovering angels with large wings. Both
                                                have their arms bent with their hands together in an
                                                attitude of prayer. The angel on the left faces
                                                right; the angel on the right faces left. There are
                                                slight indications of a gown worn by the angel on
                                                the left. They may be looking down at a portion of
                                                the circumference of sun arcing between "of" and
                                                "Paradise" (line 5) in the title. Lines of radiance
                                                emanate from the arc, suggesting a sunrise or
                                                sunset.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="object" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A portion of the circumference of sun
                                                  arcing between "of" and "Paradise" (line 5) in the
                                                  title. Lines of radiance emanate from the arc,
                                                  suggesting a sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="A">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A figure with arms raised horizontally
                                                  hovers below "For" in the first line of the title
                                                  inscription (line 1). The figure may be gowned.
                                                  The figure's directional orientation is uncertain;
                                                  we may be seeing him or her from
                                                  behind.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A figure with arms raised horizontally
                                                  hovers below "Sexes" in the first line of the
                                                  title inscription (line 1). The figure may be
                                                  gowned. The figure's directional orientation is
                                                  uncertain; we may be seeing him or her from
                                                  behind.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="A">
                                                <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised at 135
                                                  degrees</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A group of three small figures hovers
                                                  left of "The" in the second line of text. The
                                                  right-most figure may have her or his arms raised
                                                  at 135 degrees.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  vertically</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A group of three small (gowned?)
                                                  figures hovers right of "The" in the second line
                                                  of text. There may be the head of a fourth figure
                                                  above and to the left of the center figure in the
                                                  group. The left-most figure in the group has one
                                                  arm raised horizontally and the other
                                                  vertically.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="A">
                                                <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A gowned angel with large wings
                                                  hovers, facing right, left of "of" in the title
                                                  inscription (line 4). The angel's arms are bent
                                                  with hands raised together in an attitude of
                                                  prayer.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>An angel with large wings hovers,
                                                  facing left, right of "of" in the title
                                                  inscription (line 4). The angel's arms are bent
                                                  with hands raised together in an attitude of
                                                  prayer.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <texthead justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.01" justify="center">For the
                                                Sexes</l>
                                </texthead>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.02" justify="center">The</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.03" justify="center">Gates</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.04" justify="center">of</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.05" justify="center"
                                                >Paradise</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.06" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Mutual Forgiveness of each Vice</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.07" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Such are the Gates of Paradise</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.08" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Against the Accusers chief desire</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.09" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Who walkd among the Stones of Fire</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.10" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Jehovahs Finger Wrote the Law</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.11" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Then Wept! then rose in Zeal &amp; Awe</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.12" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >And the Dead Corpse from Sinais heat</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.13" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >Buried beneath his Mercy Seat</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.14" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >O Christians Christians! tell me Why</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.02.15" justify="left" indent="31"
                                                >You rear it on your Altars high</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.03" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P3" compwith="gates-child.B3">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A3">object 3 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B3">(Bentley 3, </objcode><objcode code="E1"
                                                >Erdman 1, </objcode><objcode code="K1">Keynes
                                                1)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>7.8 x 6.4 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="406" width="333"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>A large tree grows up the left margin, with
                                                branches arching toward the left in the top third of
                                                the image. Its long, dangling branches and/or leaves
                                                suggest it may be a willow. A few small plants with
                                                large leaves cover the ground below the trunk. To
                                                the right, below the tree's largest branch, is a
                                                gowned woman striding to the left with legs spread
                                                apart. Her hair is drawn into a bun on the back of
                                                her head. Her left arm is bent at the elbow and she
                                                holds in her left hand two small children or
                                                infants. We see only one child's head and the right
                                                eye and cheek of the other; a part of the woman's
                                                gown, or a separate blanket, covers the children's
                                                bodies. The woman, perhaps the children's mother or
                                                a nurse, leans over and faces down. She reaches down
                                                with her right arm and hand and appears to be
                                                pulling a third child or infant out of the earth. We
                                                see this child only from the chest up; his or her
                                                hair stands on end. The position of the child
                                                suggests that it is the anthropomorphic form of a
                                                vegetable, perhaps a mandrake, traditionally thought
                                                to be shaped like a human body. Perhaps the woman
                                                has "harvested" the other two children, held in her
                                                left arm, in a similar fashion. Plants or trees fill
                                                the middle distance right of the woman; trees and a
                                                low hill fill the middle distance left of the woman.
                                                A few clouds fill the sky behind the tree's limbs
                                                and leaves.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Plants or trees fill the middle
                                                  distance right of the woman; trees and a low hill
                                                  fill the middle distance left of the
                                                  woman.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>willow</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A large tree grows up the left margin,
                                                  with branches arching toward the left in the top
                                                  third of the image. Its long, dangling branches
                                                  and/or leaves suggest it may be a
                                                  willow.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A few small plants with large leaves
                                                  cover the ground below the trunk of the
                                                  tree.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                                                <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A few clouds fill the sky behind the
                                                  tree's limbs and leaves.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nurse</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm reaching
                                                  downward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>finger's spread</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman strides to the left
                                                  with legs spread apart. Her hair is drawn into a
                                                  bun on the back of her head. Her left arm is bent
                                                  at the elbow and she holds in her left hand two
                                                  small children or infants. The woman, perhaps the
                                                  children's mother or a nurse, leans over and faces
                                                  down. She reaches down with her right arm and hand
                                                  and appears to be pulling a third child or infant
                                                  out of the earth. The fingers of her right hand
                                                  are spread over the child's
                                                  forehead.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>blanket</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The woman holds two small children or
                                                  infants in her left arm and hand. We see only the
                                                  head of one child, facing forward; the second
                                                  child, above and to the right of the more
                                                  prominent one, is indicated only by the left eye
                                                  and cheek, facing up. The bodies of both children
                                                  are covered with a portion of the woman's gown or
                                                  a separate blanket.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hair standing on
                                                  end</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mandrake</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The woman reaches down with her right
                                                  arm and hand and appears to be pulling a child or
                                                  infant out of the earth. We see this child only
                                                  from the chest up; his or her hair stands on end.
                                                  The position of the child suggests that it is the
                                                  anthropomorphic form of a plant--perhaps a
                                                  mandrake, traditionally thought to be shaped like
                                                  a human body. Perhaps the woman has "harvested"
                                                  the other two children, held in her left arm, in a
                                                  similar fashion.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.03.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">1</physnumber><space extent="5"/>I
                                                found him beneath a Tree</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.03.02" justify="left" indent="9"
                                                >Publishd 17 May 1793 by W Blake</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.04" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P4-8" compwith="gates-child.B8">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A4">object 4 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B8">(Bentley 8, </objcode><objcode code="E6"
                                                >Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes
                                                6)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>6.1 x 5.0 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize width="315" height="430"/>
                                <objnote>
                                        <p>This impression is in the second state for <hi
                                                  rend="italic">For the Sexes</hi>. In the first
                                                state, there are only two broken pieces of egg in
                                                the lower foreground; the piece farthest to the
                                                right was added here in the second state.</p>
                                </objnote>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>An infant or young child, nude and probably
                                                male, emerges like a hatchling from a broken egg.
                                                Given his wings, he may be a putto, cherub, or
                                                angel. His legs are crossed at the ankles; his left
                                                arm is bent, with his left hand placed on the shell
                                                as though he were pushing against it to rise. He
                                                faces forward, with his head up and eyes raised. His
                                                hair is curly. Clouds fill the sky behind the figure
                                                and the egg; three broken pieces of the latter rest
                                                in the foreground.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="object" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>egg</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A child emerges from a broken egg,
                                                  three pieces of which lie in the foreground.
                                                  Clouds fill the sky.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cherub</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>pushing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>breaking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>An infant or young child, nude and
                                                  probably male, emerges like a hatchling from a
                                                  broken egg. Given his wings, he may be a putto,
                                                  cherub, or angel. His legs are crossed at the
                                                  ankles; his left arm is bent, with his left hand
                                                  placed on the shell as though he were pushing
                                                  against it to rise. He faces forward, with his
                                                  head up and eyes raised. His hair is curly.
                                                </illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="5"
                                                >At length for hatching ripe</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="2"
                                                  ><physnumber type="etched">6</physnumber><space
                                                  extent="9"/>he breaks the shell</l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.04.03" justify="left" indent="6"
                                                >Publishd by WBlake 17 May 1793</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.05" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P5-9" compwith="gates-child.B9">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A5">object 5 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B9">(Bentley 9, </objcode><objcode code="E7"
                                                >Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes
                                                7)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>7.5 x 5.0 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize width="315" height="430"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>A young male strides, with legs spread, from
                                                left to right. He wears tights or a combination of
                                                breeches and a shirt. His hair is curly. He faces to
                                                the right, with a look of surprise or excitement on
                                                his face. His left arm is at his side; his right arm
                                                is raised vertically but slightly bent at the elbow.
                                                He holds a hat in his raised right hand. To the
                                                right of his face is a (nude and male?) human
                                                figure, perhaps an infant or child, hovering
                                                (flying?) in mid-air. We see this figure, also with
                                                curly hair, from the back, but facing to the left
                                                (toward the large figure). His legs are spread, as
                                                though fleeing from the youth with a hat, who may be
                                                pursuing him. The hovering figure has his arms
                                                extended horizontally. Below, on the ground in the
                                                lower right corner of the design, is a second
                                                diminutive figure of uncertain gender. He or she may
                                                be dead and lies face-down, with the right leg
                                                extended and arms extended horizontally in a
                                                cruciform position. His or her hair is long. Given
                                                the positioning of these two small figures and the
                                                iconographic tradition from which this design may
                                                have been developed, the two small human forms may
                                                be personifications of birds or butterflies; the
                                                inscription below the image suggests a more specific
                                                identification within the context of Blake's own
                                                mythic creations. The middle distance is dominated
                                                by leafy plants or trees. Clouds fill the sky in the
                                                upper portions of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                                                <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Clouds fill the sky in the upper
                                                  portions of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Leafy plants or trees fill the middle
                                                  distance of the design.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  vertically</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A young male strides, with legs
                                                  spread, from left to right. He wears tights--or a
                                                  combination of breeches and a shirt. He may also
                                                  wear shoes. His hair is curly. He faces to the
                                                  right, with a look of surprise or excitement on
                                                  his face. His left arm is at his side; his right
                                                  arm is raised vertically but slightly bent at the
                                                  elbow. He holds a hat in his raised right hand. He
                                                  may be pursuing, and attempting to kill or
                                                  capture, the flying figure to the
                                                  right.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>To the right of the large figure's
                                                  face is a (nude and male?) human figure, perhaps
                                                  an infant or child, hovering (flying?) in mid-air.
                                                  We see this figure with curly hair from the back,
                                                  but facing to the left (toward the large figure).
                                                  His legs are spread, as though fleeing from the
                                                  youth with a hat, who may be pursuing him. The
                                                  hovering figure has his arms extended
                                                  horizontally. Given the iconographic tradition
                                                  from which this design may have been developed,
                                                  this figure may be the anthropomorphic form of a
                                                  bird or butterfly.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A diminutive figure of uncertain
                                                  gender lies on the ground, lower right. He or she
                                                  may be dead and lies face-down, with the right leg
                                                  extended and arms extended horizontally in a
                                                  cruciform position. His or her hair is long. Given
                                                  the positioning of the two small figures and the
                                                  iconographic tradition from which this design may
                                                  have been developed, the two small human forms may
                                                  be personifications of birds or
                                                  butterflies.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.05.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">7</physnumber><space extent="2"
                                                />What are these? Alas! the Female Martyr</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.05.02" justify="left" indent="9"
                                                >Is She also the Divine Image</l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.05.03" justify="left" indent="6"
                                                >Publishd 17 May 1793 by WBlake Lambeth</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.06" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P6-11"
                        compwith="gates-child.B11">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A6">object 6 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B11">(Bentley 11, </objcode><objcode code="E9"
                                                >Erdman 9, </objcode><objcode code="K9">Keynes
                                                9)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>7.1 x 4.8 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize width="315" height="430"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>The design is dominated by the night sky,
                                                complete with seven stars and a thin, crescent moon.
                                                A long ladder reaches from the surface of the earth,
                                                lower right, to the moon. A small figure has just
                                                begun to climb the ladder, with the left leg bent at
                                                the knee so as to place the left foot on the third
                                                rung of the ladder, and the right foot still on the
                                                earth. This figure's arms are raised horizontally,
                                                with his hands apparently holding the vertical sides
                                                of the ladder. The figure is probably male; he wears
                                                a hat and may be looking to the right. In the far
                                                right corner is a group of two figures, probably a
                                                woman on the left (wearing a dress or skirt) and a
                                                man on the right. The man has at least his left arm
                                                raised horizontally; he may be embracing the woman
                                                around her waist. The woman's right arm is bent at
                                                the elbow, with her forearm raised horizontally.
                                                Both these figures appear to be facing to the left
                                                and looking at the man climbing the ladder; the
                                                woman may be pointing at him.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="object" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>ladder</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The night sky shows seven stars. A
                                                  ladder extends from the earth, lower right, to a
                                                  crescent moon, top left.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="A">
                                                <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A crescent moon appears in the night
                                                  sky, top left.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A small figure has just begun to climb
                                                  the ladder, with the left leg bent at the knee so
                                                  as to place the left foot on the third rung of the
                                                  ladder, and the right foot still on the earth.
                                                  This figure's arms are raised horizontally, with
                                                  his hands apparently holding the vertical sides of
                                                  the ladder. The figure is probably male; he wears
                                                  a hat and may be looking to the
                                                  right.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>In the far right corner of the image
                                                  is a group of two figures, probably a woman on the
                                                  left (wearing a dress or skirt) and a man on the
                                                  right. The man has at least his left arm raised
                                                  horizontally; he may be embracing the woman around
                                                  her waist. The woman's right arm is bent at the
                                                  elbow, with her forearm raised horizontally. Both
                                                  these figures appear to be facing to the left and
                                                  looking at the man climbing the ladder; the woman
                                                  may be pointing at him.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.06.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">9</physnumber><space extent="15"/>I
                                                want! I want!</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.06.02" justify="left" indent="8"
                                                  >Pub<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> by WBlake 17 May
                                                1793</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.07" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P7-13"
                        compwith="gates-child.B13">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A7">object 7 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B13">(Bentley 13, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E11">Erdman 11, </objcode><objcode code="K11"
                                                >Keynes 11)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>7.1 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="369" width="328"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>The design is based on a traditional emblem of
                                                Age clipping the wings of Love. On the left sits a
                                                gowned old man wearing spectacles (an indication of
                                                limited vision). He has a long beard and probably
                                                long hair. His eyes are closed or looking down; he
                                                may be blind or almost blind. His mouth is open
                                                slightly. His legs, with prominent knees, are
                                                crossed at the ankles. His left arm is raised
                                                horizontally, with the left hand grasping the wing
                                                of the youthful figure to the right. His right arm
                                                is bent at the elbow; he holds in his right hand a
                                                pair of scissors with which he is about to cut the
                                                tip of the youth's right wing. This winged and
                                                youthful male figure, nude and striding
                                                energetically to the right, is a winged Cupid,
                                                cherub, or angel. His legs are spread apart, as
                                                though running to the right; he may be fleeing from
                                                the old man. The youth's hair is curly. His right
                                                arm is bent upward at the elbow, with the fingers of
                                                his raised right hand spread apart. His body faces
                                                to the right, but we see only the back of his head
                                                as he looks back to the sun rising or setting on the
                                                distant horizon. Lines of radiance emanate from the
                                                sun. A tree, its branches arching over both figures,
                                                grows up the left margin. The leaves of a tree or
                                                large plant fill the background above the old man.
                                                There may be grass on the slight hill or mound on
                                                which the two figures are placed.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cutting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>spectacles</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>blind</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>scissors</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>On the left sits a gowned old man
                                                  wearing spectacles (an indication of limited
                                                  vision). He has a long beard and probably long
                                                  hair. His eyes are closed or looking down; he may
                                                  be blind are almost blind. His mouth is open
                                                  slightly. His legs, with prominent knees, are
                                                  crossed at the ankles. His left arm is raised
                                                  horizontally, with the left hand grasping the wing
                                                  of the youthful figure to the right. His right arm
                                                  is bent at the elbow; he holds in his right hand a
                                                  pair of scissors with which he is about to cut the
                                                  tip of the youth's right wing.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>genitals</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cherub</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>Cupid</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A winged and youthful male figure,
                                                  nude and striding energetically to the right, is a
                                                  winged Cupid, cherub, or angel. His legs are
                                                  spread apart, as though running to the right; he
                                                  may be fleeing from the old man. The youth's hair
                                                  is curly. His right arm is bent upward at the
                                                  elbow, with the fingers of his raised right hand
                                                  spread apart. A few lines indicate the youth's
                                                  genitals. His body faces to the right, but we see
                                                  only the back of his head as he looks back to the
                                                  sun rising or setting on the distant
                                                  horizon.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="BD">
                                                <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>We see about half the sun rising or
                                                  setting. Radiant beams of light emanate from
                                                  it.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>limb</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A tree, its branches arching over both
                                                  figures, grows up the left margin. The leaves of a
                                                  tree or large plant fill the background above the
                                                  old man. There may be grass on the slight hill or
                                                  mound on which the two figures are
                                                  placed.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.07.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">11</physnumber><space extent="13"
                                                />Aged Ignorance</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.07.02" justify="left" indent="2"
                                                >Perceptive Organs closed their Objects close</l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.07.03" justify="left" indent="4"
                                                >Publishd 17 May 1793 by WBlake Lambeth</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.08" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P8-14"
                        compwith="gates-child.B14">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A8">object 8 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B14">(Bentley 14, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E12">Erdman 12, </objcode><objcode code="K12"
                                                >Keynes 12)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>6.4 x 6.1 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="333" width="317"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>Within a small room, probably a prison cell
                                                built of stone, we see five seated male figures, all
                                                apparently nude (with the possible exceptions of the
                                                figures lower left and right). The central figure,
                                                facing forward, is old and bearded with hair
                                                standing on end; the others are much younger. He,
                                                and the two figures next to him, appear to be
                                                sitting on a low stone step. There may be three
                                                small windows above them. The larger, older central
                                                figure has his legs drawn up; his knees are very
                                                prominent. His face suggests despair or worse.
                                                Immediately to the left, very close to the old man,
                                                is a young man with legs drawn up and crossed at the
                                                ankles. His knees are also prominent. His body faces
                                                forward, but his head is turned up and to the right;
                                                he may be looking at the face of the old man.
                                                Although we see only his right shoulder and upper
                                                arm, his right arm may be extended horizontally; he
                                                may be embracing the old man. On the right is
                                                another young male close to the old man. His legs
                                                are drawn up and crossed at the ankles, with
                                                prominent knees. His body faces forward, but his
                                                head is turned to the left, with his face pressed
                                                against the body or left leg of the old man. This
                                                figure's hair seems to be long. Another youthful
                                                male sits in the right foreground. His legs are
                                                extended but slightly bent at the knees. Although
                                                probably nude, like his companions, lines just below
                                                his knees suggest that he might be wearing breeches.
                                                His left arm is at his side, with his left hand on
                                                the ground (or, rather, on the floor), fingers
                                                spread apart. He faces left, with his head bent back
                                                and looking up; his mouth is slightly open. His hair
                                                is probably long. In the left foreground is the
                                                final youthful figure, seated and with legs
                                                extended. Though he may be nude, lines just below
                                                his knees suggest that he, too, may be wearing
                                                breeches. He faces to the right, with his head down.
                                                His right arm is at is side, with his right hand on
                                                the ground (or, rather, on the floor), fingers
                                                spread. His hair is curly. Given the configuration
                                                of the males, the setting, and the compositional
                                                relationship to several drawings by Blake, this
                                                design would seem to be inspired by Dante's
                                                description of Count Ugolino and his sons in
                                                prison.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="structure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>prison</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Within a small room, probably a prison
                                                  cell built of stone, we see five seated figures.
                                                  The central, older figure and the two younger
                                                  figures next to him appear to be sitting on a low
                                                  stone step. There might be three small windows
                                                  above them.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>Ugolino</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Within a small room, probably a prison
                                                  cell built of stone, we see five seated male
                                                  figures, all apparently nude (with the possible
                                                  exception of the figures lower left and right, who
                                                  may wear breeches). Given the configuration of
                                                  these figures, the setting, and the compositional
                                                  relationship to several drawings by Blake, this
                                                  design would seem to be inspired by Dante's
                                                  description of Count Ugolino and his sons in
                                                  prison. All appear to be dying in pain and
                                                  despair.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>Ugolino</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hair standing on
                                                  end</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The central seated figure, male and
                                                  apparently nude, in this group of five faces
                                                  forward. He is old and bearded with hair standing
                                                  on end. He has his legs drawn up; his knees are
                                                  very prominent. His face suggests despair or
                                                  worse. He may be Ugolino.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="AC">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A youthful male nude sits next to the
                                                  old man in the center of the design. His hair is
                                                  long and perhaps drawn into a bun. His legs are
                                                  drawn up and crossed at the ankles. His knees are
                                                  prominent. His body faces forward, but his head is
                                                  turned up and to the right; he may be looking at
                                                  the face of the old man. Although we see only his
                                                  right shoulder and upper arm, his right arm may be
                                                  extended horizontally; he may be embracing the old
                                                  man.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="BD">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A youthful male nude sits to the right
                                                  of the old man in the center of the design. His
                                                  legs are drawn up and crossed at the ankles, with
                                                  prominent knees. His body faces forward, but his
                                                  head is turned to the left, with his face pressed
                                                  against the body or left leg of the old man. This
                                                  figure's hair seems to be long.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A youthful male sits in the lower
                                                  right corner of the cell. He is probably nude, but
                                                  lines just below his knees suggest that he may be
                                                  wearing breeches. His legs are extended but
                                                  slightly bent at the knees. His left arm is at his
                                                  side, with his left hand on the ground (or,
                                                  rather, on the floor), fingers spread apart. He
                                                  faces left, with his head bent back and looking
                                                  up; his mouth is slightly open. His hair is
                                                  probably long.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A youthful male sits in the lower left
                                                  corner of the cell. He is probably nude, but lines
                                                  just below his knees suggest that he may be
                                                  wearing breeches. He faces to the right, with his
                                                  head down. His right arm is at is side, with his
                                                  right hand on the ground (or, rather, on the
                                                  floor), fingers spread. His hair is
                                                  curly.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.08.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">12</physnumber><space extent="4"
                                                />Does thy God O Priest take such vengeance</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.08.02" justify="left" indent="22"
                                                >as this?</l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.08.03" justify="left" indent="7"
                                                >Publishd 17 May 1793 by WBlake Lambeth</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.09" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P9-15"
                        compwith="gates-child.B15">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A9">object 9 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B15">(Bentley 15, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E13">Erdman 13, </objcode><objcode code="K13"
                                                >Keynes 13)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>8.1 x 7.2 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="421" width="374"/>
                                <objnote>
                                        <p>This impression is in the second state for <hi
                                                  rend="italic">For the Sexes</hi>, with the head of
                                                the child immediately right of the woman turned
                                                toward the viewer. In the first state, the child's
                                                head is in right profile.</p>
                                </objnote>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>We see the corner of a featureless chamber or
                                                cell, perhaps with stone walls and a wooden floor.
                                                The only furniture is a bed (or possibly a bier),
                                                probably made of wood. A bodyvery probably deadlies
                                                supine and rigid on the bed, legs together and at
                                                least the right arm at his side. This gowned figure
                                                is very probably an old man, as indicated by his
                                                long beard. His face is hidden by another figure. At
                                                his feet, rising into the air at a 45 degree angle
                                                from lower right to upper left, is another gowned
                                                and bearded old man. We can see the supine figure's
                                                feet through the lower leg of the rising figure, and
                                                thus he is almost certainly the ghost or spirit of
                                                the dead man. His hair is long and he faces to the
                                                left. His right arm is bent at the elbow with the
                                                forearm raised horizontally across his body. The
                                                index finger of his right hand is extended and
                                                points to the right. His left arm is bent at the
                                                elbow with the forearm raised vertically. One finger
                                                of his left hand points upward. A radiant light
                                                surrounds his head and body, extending down to his
                                                lower legs. The effect is particularly prominent
                                                around his head and strongly suggests and halo.
                                                Beams of light radiate from his aura on the left. In
                                                the foreground on the left is a young man with curly
                                                hair. He squats or sits on his left leg, bent under
                                                his body; his right leg is extended to the right and
                                                bent slightly at the knee. He may be wearing tights,
                                                or at least a belt around his waist. His right arm
                                                is at his side, with the fingers of his right hand
                                                spread apart. His mouth is slightly open and he
                                                appears to be looking up and to the right in fear or
                                                surprise at the ghostly figure above and to the
                                                right. He may be the son of the dead man. Behind the
                                                bed and its corpse we see the head and upper body of
                                                a gowned woman wearing a scarf over her head. Her
                                                left arm is extended at 45 degrees. She also looks
                                                up and to the right at the ghost, perhaps with an
                                                expression of fear or surprise. She may be the wife
                                                or daughter of the dead man. Behind her and to the
                                                right are two small figures, probably children or
                                                grandchildren of the dead man. Of the child closest
                                                to the woman we see only the face. The child faces
                                                toward the viewer. The child farthest to the right
                                                in this group is probably a male with curly hair. We
                                                see only his face and upper chest. He is probably
                                                looking up and to the right at the
                                                ghost.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="structure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>chamber</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>We see the corner of a featureless
                                                  chamber or cell, perhaps with stone walls and a
                                                  wooden floor.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bier</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The only piece of furniture in the
                                                  room is a bed or bier, probably made of
                                                  wood.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The group of figures in the design may
                                                  be a family--a dead father on the bed, his wife,
                                                  and three children.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>rigid</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A body--very probably dead--lies
                                                  supine and rigid on the bed, legs together and at
                                                  least the right arm at his side. This gowned
                                                  figure is very probably an old man, as indicated
                                                  by his long beard. His face is hidden by another
                                                  figure.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="BD">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm wrapped around
                                                  body</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  vertically</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>light</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>At the feet of the body on the bed or
                                                  bier, rising into the air at a 45 degree angle
                                                  from lower right to upper left, is another gowned
                                                  and bearded old man. We can see the supine
                                                  figure's feet through the lower leg of the rising
                                                  figure, and thus the latter is almost certainly
                                                  the ghost or spirit of the dead man. His hair is
                                                  long and he faces to the left. His right arm is
                                                  bent at the elbow with the forearm raised
                                                  horizontally across his body. The index finger of
                                                  his right hand is extended and points to the
                                                  right. His left arm is bent at the elbow with the
                                                  forearm raised vertically. One finger of his left
                                                  hand points upward. A radiant light surrounds his
                                                  head and body, extending down to his lower legs.
                                                  The effect is particularly prominent around his
                                                  head and strongly suggests and halo. Beams of
                                                  light radiate from his aura on the
                                                  left.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>In the foreground on the left is a
                                                  young man with curly hair. He squats or sits on
                                                  his left leg, bent under his body; his right leg
                                                  is extended to the right and bent slightly at the
                                                  knee. He may be wearing tights, or at least a belt
                                                  around his waist. His right arm is at his side,
                                                  with the fingers of his right hand spread apart.
                                                  His mouth is slightly open and he appears to be
                                                  looking up and to the right in fear or surprise at
                                                  the ghostly figure above and to the right. He may
                                                  be the son of the dead man.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="AC">
                                                <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised at 45
                                                  degrees</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Behind the bed and its corpse we see
                                                  the head and upper body of a gowned woman wearing
                                                  a scarf over her head. Her left arm is raised at
                                                  45 degrees. She looks up and to the right at the
                                                  ghost, perhaps with an expression of fear or
                                                  surprise. She may be the wife or daughter of the
                                                  dead man.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Behind the prominent female figure and
                                                  to the right are two small figures, probably
                                                  children or grandchildren of the dead man. Of the
                                                  child closest to the woman we see only the face.
                                                  The child faces toward the viewer. The child
                                                  farthest to the right in this group is probably a
                                                  male with curly hair. We see only his face and
                                                  upper chest. He is probably looking up and to the
                                                  right at the ghost. Both children's mouths appear
                                                  to be open.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.09.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">13</physnumber><space extent="10"
                                                />Fear &amp; Hope are  Vision</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.10" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P10-16"
                        compwith="gates-child.B16">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A10">object 10 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B16">(Bentley 16, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E14">Erdman 14, </objcode><objcode code="K14"
                                                >Keynes 14)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>6.7 x 4.7 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize width="315" height="430"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>A male traveler strides boldly to the right.
                                                He wears a coat, breeches, shoes, and a hat; he
                                                holds a walking-stick in his right hand. His right
                                                arm is bent at the elbow, with his forearm raised
                                                horizontally. His hair would appear to be long. A
                                                long shadow extends from his left foot; another may
                                                form the dark triangle lower right. The ground
                                                beneath his feet may be covered with grass; leafy
                                                trees or large plants form the background. A few
                                                clouds fill the sky above.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="object" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A long shadow extends from the
                                                  figure's left foot; another may form the dark
                                                  triangle lower right.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>walking-stick</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A male traveler strides boldly to the
                                                  right. He wears a coat, breeches, shoes, and a
                                                  hat; he holds a walking-stick in his right hand.
                                                  His right arm is bent at the elbow, with his
                                                  forearm raised horizontally. His hair would appear
                                                  to be long.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The ground beneath the walking man's
                                                  feet may be covered with grass; leafy trees or
                                                  large plants form the background.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="AB">
                                                <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A few clouds fill the sky above the
                                                  trees.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-child.d.illbk.10.01" justify="left" indent="3"
                                                >The Traveller hasteth in the</l>
                                        <l n="gates-child.d.illbk.10.02" justify="left"><space
                                                  extent="13"/>Evening</l>
                                        <l n="gates-child.d.illbk.10.03" justify="left">
                                                <physnumber type="etched">14</physnumber>
                                        </l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-child.d.illbk.10.04" justify="left" indent="4"
                                                >Publishd 17 May 1793 by WBlake Lambeth</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.11" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P11-18"
                        compwith="gates-child.B18">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A11">object 11 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B18">(Bentley 18, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E16">Erdman 16, </objcode><objcode code="K16"
                                                >Keynes 16)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>6.4 x 5.2 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize width="315" height="430"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure of uncertain gender squats or
                                                sits, with legs drawn up and prominent knees, upon
                                                the earth. The figure, who faces forward, has a
                                                scarf or hood over the head. Arms at side, the
                                                figure holds a slender staff in the right hand. The
                                                left hand is on the ground. The figure appears to be
                                                looking, with open eyes, directly at the viewer. A
                                                worm lies on the ground, encircling the figure and
                                                reaching upward in a loop on the right side of the
                                                figure. Further to the lower right are two or three
                                                heads partly buried in the earth. These may be
                                                severed heads, or the heads of corpses whose bodies
                                                are buried in graves below the seated figure. The
                                                front-most figure, probably male and bearded, has
                                                his eyes closed. The dark background is filled with
                                                the leafless limbs, trunks, and roots of trees.
                                                There may also be a small plant, lower left, large
                                                stones (particularly on the left), and a cave behind
                                                and above the seated figure.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="figure" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure of uncertain gender
                                                  squats or sits, with legs drawn up and prominent
                                                  knees, upon the earth. The figure, who faces
                                                  forward, has a scarf or hood over the head. Arms
                                                  at side, the figure holds a slender staff in the
                                                  right hand. The left hand is on the ground. The
                                                  figure appears to be looking, with open eyes,
                                                  directly at the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="animal" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>encircling</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A worm lies on the ground, encircling
                                                  the seated figure and reaching upward in a loop on
                                                  the right side of the figure.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>buried</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>severed head</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>grave</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner of the image
                                                  are two or three heads partly buried in the earth.
                                                  These may be severed heads, or the heads of
                                                  corpses whose bodies are buried in graves below
                                                  the seated figure. The front-most figure, probably
                                                  male and bearded, has his eyes
                                                  closed.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>root</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>limb</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The dark background is filled with the
                                                  leafless limbs, trunks, and roots of trees. There
                                                  may be a small plant growing in the lower left
                                                  corner of the image.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="E">
                                                <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The background of the image may
                                                  include large stones, particularly on the right,
                                                  and a cave behind and above the seated
                                                  figure.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <vspace extent="8"/>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.11.01" justify="left"><physnumber
                                                  type="etched">16</physnumber><space extent="2"/>I
                                                have said to the Worm: Thou</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.11.02" justify="left" indent="6"
                                                >art my mother &amp; my sister</l>
                                </lg>
                                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.11.03" justify="left" indent="5"
                                                >Publishd by WBlake 17 May 1793</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P12-19">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A12">object 12 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B19">(Bentley 19, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E17">Erdman 17, </objcode><objcode code="K17"
                                                >Keynes 17)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>10.5 x 6.8 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="546" width="354"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="interlinear" location="A">
                                        <illusobjdesc>Just left of the first letter of the first
                                                word of the heading ("The Keys" [line 1]), two
                                                standing or hovering figures embrace. Both are
                                                probably gowned. The figure on the left, perhaps
                                                female, may have one arm raised at 135 degrees. She
                                                faces right; her companion, presumably male, faces
                                                left. Between the words "The" and "Keys," a gowned
                                                and hovering figure has her or his arms raised
                                                vertically and holds a triangular object over her or
                                                his head.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="figure" location="A">
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised at 135
                                                  degrees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Just left of the first letter of the
                                                  first word of the heading ("The Keys" [line 1]),
                                                  two standing or hovering figures embrace. Both are
                                                  probably gowned. The figure on the left, perhaps
                                                  female, may have one arm raised at 135 degrees.
                                                  She faces right; her companion, presumably male,
                                                  faces left.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="A">
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  vertically</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>triangle</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Between the words "The" and "Keys" in
                                                  the first line of the text, a gowned and hovering
                                                  figure has her or his arms raised vertically and
                                                  holds a triangular object over her or his
                                                  head.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <texthead justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.01" justify="left" indent="9"
                                                >The Keys</l>
                                </texthead>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.02" justify="left">The
                                                Catterpiller on the Leaf</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.03" justify="left">Reminds thee
                                                of thy Mothers Grief</l>
                                </lg>
                                <texthead justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.04" justify="left" indent="9"
                                                >of the Gates</l>
                                </texthead>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.05" justify="left">1 My Eternal
                                                Man set in Repose</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.06" justify="left">The Female
                                                from his darkness rose</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.07" justify="left">And She
                                                found me beneath a Tree</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.08" justify="left">A Mandrake
                                                &amp; in her Veil hid me</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.09" justify="left">Serpent
                                                Reasonings us entice</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.10" justify="left">Of Good
                                                &amp; Evil: Virtue &amp; Vice</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.11" justify="left">2 Doubt Self
                                                Jealous Watry folly</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.12" justify="left">3 Struggling
                                                thro Earths Melancholy</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.13" justify="left" indent="1">4
                                                Naked in Air in Shame &amp; Fear</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.14" justify="left" indent="1">5
                                                Blind in Fire with shield &amp; spear</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.15" justify="left">Two Horn'd
                                                Reasoning Cloven Fiction</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.16" justify="left">In Doubt
                                                which is Self contradiction</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.17" justify="left">A dark
                                                Hermaphrodite We stood<note>In copy B, the line
                                                  reads "A dark Hermaphrodite I stood". In the
                                                  second and third states of the plate, found in all
                                                  other traced impressions, "We" follows
                                                  "Hermaphrodite".</note></l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.18" justify="left">Rational
                                                Truth Root of Evil &amp; Good</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.19" justify="left" indent="1"
                                                >Round me flew the Flaming Sword</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.20" justify="left">Round her
                                                snowy Whirlwinds roard</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.21" justify="left">Freezing her
                                                Veil the Mundane Shell</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.22" justify="left">6 I rent the
                                                Veil where the Dead dwell</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.12.23" justify="left" indent="1"
                                                >When weary Man enters his Cave</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P13-20">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A13">object 13 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B20">(Bentley 20, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E18">Erdman 18, </objcode><objcode code="K18"
                                                >Keynes 18)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>10.4 x 6.8 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="541" width="354"/>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="interlinear" location="AC">
                                        <illusobjdesc>Several forms decorate the left margin of the
                                                text. A figure, probably winged and facing right,
                                                hovers left of line 15. Another hovering figure
                                                proceeds line 17. Line 21 is introduced by another
                                                hovering figure, probably facing forward and arms
                                                raised at approximately 135 degrees. Twisting vines
                                                grow left of lines 25 and 27-29.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="figure" location="AC">
                                                <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably winged and facing
                                                  right, hovers left of line 15 of the
                                                  text.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A hovering figure proceeds line 17 of
                                                  the text.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised at 135
                                                  degrees</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Line 21 of the text is introduced by a
                                                  hovering figure, probably facing forward and arms
                                                  raised at approximately 135
                                                  degrees.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Twisting vines grow left of lines 25
                                                  and 27-29 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                                <illustration type="interlinear" location="BD">
                                        <illusobjdesc>Several images decorate the right margin of
                                                the text. Those following lines 2 and 3 may simply
                                                be leaves or flowers. Right of line 7 are two
                                                hovering figures, apparently facing each other. The
                                                figure on the left has her or his arms raised at 45
                                                degrees; the figure on the right has his or her arms
                                                raised horizontally. Another hovering figure, arms
                                                raised at 45 degrees, follows lines 11-12. Two
                                                hovering figures follow line 15. A larger hovering
                                                figure, probably gowned, follows line 17. This
                                                figure, probably female and facing forward, has one
                                                arm raised horizontally and the other raised
                                                vertically. An embracing and hovering couple follows
                                                lines 19-20. Behind them are slight indications of
                                                steps and a building and doorway (possibly one of
                                                the "Dungeons" referenced in line 18). Vines spiral
                                                in loops right of lines 22-23, 26-28, and 29. A wavy
                                                line, perhaps a vine, appears below "over the Web"
                                                in the last line of text.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The slight forms following lines 2 and
                                                  3 of the text may be leaves or
                                                  flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised at 45
                                                  degrees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised at
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Right of line 7 are two hovering
                                                  figures, apparently facing each other. The figure
                                                  on the left has her or his arms raised at 45
                                                  degrees; the figure on the right has his or her
                                                  arms raised horizontally.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="B">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised at 45
                                                  degrees</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Another hovering figure, arms raised
                                                  at 45 degrees, follows lines 11-12 of the text.
                                                  The figure's legs are bent.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="BD">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Two hovering figures follow line 15 of
                                                  the text. The figure on the far right seems
                                                  twisted with legs bent.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm raised
                                                  vertically</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A hovering figure, probably gowned,
                                                  follows line 17 of the text. This figure, probably
                                                  female and facing forward, has one arm raised
                                                  horizontally and the other raised
                                                  vertically.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>An embracing and hovering couple
                                                  follows lines 19-20 of the text.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="structure" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>step</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>prison</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Behind the figures following lines
                                                  19-20 of the text are slight indications of steps
                                                  and doorway of a building (possibly one of the
                                                  "Dungeons" referenced in line 18).</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Vines spiral in loops right of lines
                                                  22-23, 26-28, and 29 of the text. A wavy line,
                                                  perhaps a vine, appears below "over the Web" in
                                                  the last line of text.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.01" justify="left">He meets his
                                                Saviour in the Grave</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.02" justify="left">Some find a
                                                Female Garment there</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.03" justify="left">And some a
                                                Male. woven with care</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.04" justify="left">Lest the
                                                Sexual Garments sweet</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.05" justify="left">Should grow
                                                a devouring Winding sheet</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.06" justify="left">7 One Dies!
                                                Alas! the Living &amp; Dead</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.07" justify="left">One is slain
                                                &amp; One is fled</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.08" justify="left">8 In
                                                Vain-glory hatcht &amp; nurst</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.09" justify="left">By double
                                                Spectres Self Accurst</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.10" justify="left">My Son! my
                                                Son! thou treatest me</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.11" justify="left">But as I
                                                have instructed thee</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.12" justify="left">9 On the
                                                shadows of the Moon</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.13" justify="left">Climbing
                                                thro Nights highest noon</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.14" justify="left">10 In Times
                                                Ocean falling drownd</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.15" justify="left">In Aged
                                                Ignorance profound</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.16" justify="left">11 Holy
                                                &amp; cold I clipd the Wings</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.17" justify="left">Of all
                                                Sublunary Things</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.18" justify="left">12 And in
                                                depths of my Dungeons</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.19" justify="left">Closed the
                                                Father &amp; the Sons</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.20" justify="left">13 But when
                                                once I did descry</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.21" justify="left">The Immortal
                                                Man that cannot Die</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.22" justify="left">14 Thro
                                                evening shades I haste away</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.23" justify="left">To close the
                                                Labours of my Day</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.24" justify="left">15 The Door
                                                of Death I open found</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.25" justify="left">And the Worm
                                                Weaving in the Ground</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.26" justify="left">16 Thou'rt
                                                my Mother from the Womb</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.27" justify="left">Wife.
                                                Sister. Daughter to the Tomb</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.28" justify="left">Weaving to
                                                Dreams the Sexual strife</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.13.29" justify="left">And weeping
                                                over the Web of Life</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
                <desc id="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14" dbi="gates-sexes.k.P14-21">
                        <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A14">object 14 </objnumber><objcode
                                                code="B21">(Bentley 21, </objcode><objcode
                                                code="E19">Erdman 19, </objcode><objcode code="K19"
                                                >Keynes 19)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                        <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                                <objsize>9.5 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
                                <windowsize height="494" width="328"/>
                                <objnote>
                                        <p>This impression is in the second state for <hi
                                                  rend="italic">For the Sexes</hi>. In the first
                                                state, the figure's body and wings are engraved
                                                principally in outline and lack the dark hatching
                                                strokes of the second state.</p>
                                </objnote>
                        </physdesc>
                        <illusdesc>
                                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                                        <illusobjdesc>We see from behind a bat-winged figure, almost
                                                certainly male, flying or hovering in the air. He
                                                faces away from the viewer and is dark-skinned, nude
                                                and bald. His arms are apparently raised
                                                horizontally, for we can see his hands, fingers
                                                spread apart, extending beyond each wing. His right
                                                leg is drawn up behind him, his left bent slightly
                                                at the knee but extended to the left. At least ten
                                                stars and two circles decorate his wings. The circle
                                                on the left is probably the moon (note the slight
                                                indications of a crescent within the circle); the
                                                circle on the right may be the sun (note the
                                                radiance just outside the circumference). This
                                                figure is no doubt Satan, "The Accuser who is The
                                                God of This World," named in the first three lines
                                                of the text on this plate. He can also be associated
                                                with Blake's concept of the spectre. Lying supine on
                                                the ground beneath the winged figure is the "lost
                                                Traveller" named in line 10. He is a muscular male
                                                and would appear to be nude; his hair is long. His
                                                eyes are closed, for he is very probably asleep and
                                                dreaming (see line 10). His neck is twisted so that
                                                he faces forward. His head may be resting on a stone
                                                or mound of earth and his legs may be crossed at the
                                                ankles. His right arm is at his side, with his right
                                                arm holding (or at least resting on) a staff or
                                                walking-stick. The background landscape on the right
                                                is filled with a hill (see the last word on this
                                                plate) and radiant beams of light (a sunrise or
                                                sunset?) rising above the hill. On the left, the
                                                beams of light may be issuing from the background
                                                horizon, but they also form a halo-like radiance
                                                above the traveler's head.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bald</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arms raised
                                                  horizontally</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>accuser</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>spectre</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>We see from behind a bat-winged
                                                  figure, almost certainly male, flying or hovering
                                                  in the air. He faces away from the viewer and is
                                                  dark-skinned, nude and bald. His arms are
                                                  apparently raised horizontally, for we can see his
                                                  hands, fingers spread apart, extending beyond each
                                                  wing. His right leg is drawn up behind him, his
                                                  left bent slightly at the knee but extended to the
                                                  left. At least ten stars and two circles decorate
                                                  his wings. The circle on the left is probably the
                                                  moon (note the slight indications of a crescent
                                                  within the circle); the circle on the right may be
                                                  the sun (note the radiance just outside the
                                                  circumference). This figure is no doubt Satan,
                                                  "The Accuser who is The God of This World," named
                                                  in the first three lines of the text on this
                                                  plate. He can also be associated with Blake's
                                                  concept of the spectre.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                                <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>dreaming</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>walking-stick</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>Lying supine on the ground beneath the
                                                  winged figure is the "lost Traveller" named in
                                                  line 10. He is a muscular male and would appear to
                                                  be nude; his hair is long. His eyes are closed,
                                                  for he is very probably asleep and dreaming (see
                                                  line 10). His neck is twisted so that he faces
                                                  forward. His head may be resting on a stone and
                                                  his legs may be crossed at the ankles. His right
                                                  arm is at his side, with his right arm holding (or
                                                  at least resting on) a staff or walking-
                                                  stick.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="C">
                                                <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The sleeping figure's head may be
                                                  resting on a stone or mound of
                                                  earth.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>The background on the right is
                                                  dominated by a hill (see the final word of line
                                                  10) and, just above it, radiance and beams of
                                                  light that may indicate a sunrise or
                                                  sunset.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="object" location="D">
                                                <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>halo</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>On the left and just above the
                                                  sleeping figure's head, the beams of light may
                                                  indicate a sunrise or sunset, but they also form a
                                                  halo-like radiance above the sleeping figure's
                                                  head.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                                <illustration type="interlinear" location="AB">
                                        <illusobjdesc>A snake with open mouth and a prominent tongue
                                                faces to the right between the second and third
                                                lines of text. The snake's body forms a spiral and
                                                his head bears a small crest. At least the first
                                                nine loops, reading back from the snake's head, are
                                                numbered consecutively 1-9.</illusobjdesc>
                                        <component type="animal" location="AB">
                                                <characteristic>snake</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                                                <characteristic>crest</characteristic>
                                                <illusobjdesc>A snake with open mouth and a
                                                  prominent tongue faces to the right between the
                                                  second and third lines of text. The snake's body
                                                  forms a spiral. His head bears a small crest. At
                                                  least the first nine loops, reading back from the
                                                  snake's head, are numbered consecutively
                                                  1-9.</illusobjdesc>
                                        </component>
                                        <component type="text" location="AB">
                                                <illusobjdesc>At least the first nine loops of the
                                                  snake's body are numbered 1-9, reading back from
                                                  his head.</illusobjdesc>
                                                <transcription>
                                                  <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                                  <l justify="left">1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</l>
                                                  </lg>
                                                </transcription>
                                        </component>
                                </illustration>
                        </illusdesc>
                        <phystext>
                                <texthead justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.01" justify="left" indent="6"
                                                >To The Accuser who is</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.02" justify="left" indent="6"
                                                >The God of This World</l>
                                </texthead>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.03" justify="left">Truly My
                                                Satan thou art but a Dunce</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.04" justify="left">And dost not
                                                know the Garment from the Man</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.05" justify="left">Every Harlot
                                                was a Virgin once</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.06" justify="left">Nor canst
                                                thou ever change Kate into Nan</l>
                                </lg>
                                <vspace extent="1"/>
                                <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.07" justify="left">Tho thou art
                                                Worshipd by the Names Divine</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.08" justify="left">Of Jesus
                                                &amp; Jehovah: thou art still</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.09" justify="left">The Son of
                                                Morn in weary Nights decline</l>
                                        <l n="gates-sexes.k.illbk.14.10" justify="left">The lost
                                                Travellers Dream under the Hill</l>
                                </lg>
                        </phystext>
                </desc>
        </objdesc>
</bad>
