<bad id="gates-child.a" type="illbk" work="For Children: The Gates of Paradise" copy="A" copyid="A" institution="lc" catalog="bentley" catid="A">
   <header>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <title reg="For Children: The Gates of Paradise"><main>For Children: The Gates of
                  Paradise</main><copy> Copy A</copy> : electronic edition </title>
            <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                  <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                  Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
            <respstmt/>
            <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the University of
                    Rochester, and the Library of Congress</sponsor>
            <funder/>
         </titlestmt>
         <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
         <extent>1 XML file approx. 200KB; 36 JPEG
            (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 500KB to 1800KB.</extent>
         <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries <date>August
                    2024</date></publicationstmt>
         <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
             The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi> Copy A, from the Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress. In 1793, Blake etched and published <hi rend="i">For Children</hi>, an emblem book comprising eighteen small intaglio plates. Through a numbered series of designs with inscriptions ranging from single words to brief aphorisms, Blake puts the course of human life in psychological perspective. Some of the emblems form narrative sequences; others exemplify mental states and their reification in the external world. Though the first of five copies printed in 1793, Copy A is unique in that all of its 18 plates are in their first states, whereas the other copies printed in 1793, including Copy D, which is in the Archive, are in their second states.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
Copy A is a proof copy, that is, it was printed to proof the designs and prepare them for the subsequent copies. It also joins <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> Copies B, D, F, and K, already in the Archive. <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> is the revised version of <hi rend="i">For Children</hi>, augmented with three new plates, 19, 20, and 21. Copy B was printed c. 1818 with all but one of its first 18 plates in their third state; Copy D was printed c. 1825 with all but two of its first 18 plates in their fourth state; Copy K was printed c. 1826–27 with nearly all the core plates in their fifth and final state; Copy F, with all plates in their final states, was one of four copies posthumously printed by Catherine Blake, c. 1828–29.
<lb/>
<lb/>
With this publication of <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi> Copy A, combined with our earlier publications of Copy D of <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> and four copies of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>, the Archive now presents all known states of all the plates Blake used for both works. Thus, the Archive enables students of Blake, using our compare feature (Objects from the Same Matrix) located below the image, to trace the evolution of every design from its first and second states in 1793 through Blake’s revisions in c. 1818, 1825, and c. 1826-27. The original plate numbers etched lower left corner below the designs were erased and repositioned in the plate’s second state, which included an imprint, “Publishd by WBlake 17 May 1793” or a variant thereof, sometimes including the name of Blake’s London neighborhood, “Lambeth.” The second state of Plate 2, the title plate, reads “Published by W Blake No 13 Hercules Buildings Lambeth and J. Johnson St. Pauls' Church Yard.” In Copy A the title page is a proof that bears fragments of an erased imprint that may refer to J. Dodsley as the publisher or co-publisher. There is no other evidence that either Johnson (a bookseller for whom Blake executed many engravings) or Dodsley actually participated in the publication of the book. Johnson, however, may have been involved in selling, or at least displaying copies, of the book, for in a letter of 25 Sept. 1794 to Francis Douce, Richard Twiss states that “Blakes Paradise…. You will see” along with “several more of Blakes books” at “Johnsons” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Records</hi>, page 65).
<lb/>
<lb/>
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt>                  
         <notesstmt/>
      </filedesc>
      <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2024</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
         Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
         Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms,
         in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification
         of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
         granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/> This work
         copyright © 2024 William Blake Archive.</userestrict>
      <encodingdesc/>
      <profiledesc/>
      <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>August 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
                     <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created</change>
                <date>May 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed, </name>
                    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
                    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                        <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
         <changestmt>
            <change>Images acquired and catalogued</change>
            <date>1997</date>
            <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp>
<name>Morris Eaves, </name>
University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>
University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
<name>David Cosca </name>
and
<name>Robert Bingler</name>
<resp>Project Manager: </resp>
<name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
<resp>Project Assistant: </resp>
<name>Greg Murray</name>
</respstmt>
         </changestmt>
      </revisiondesc>
   </header>
   <objdesc>
      <source>
         <objdescid>
            <objtitle>
               <title>For Children: The Gates of Paradise</title>
            </objtitle>
            <origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator,
                  </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer</role></origination>
            <origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role></origination>
            <imprint>
               <publisher>William Blake and Joseph Johnson <note>There is no imprint in the first state impression of Object 2, the title page, in Copy A.  Johnson's name appears in the
                     imprint on Object 2, the title page, in its second state, but the extent of his involvement in the publication of the work is not known. He may have been involved in the selling, or at least displaying copies, of the book, for in a letter of 25 Sept. 1794 to Francis Douce, Richard Twiss states that “Blakes Paradise…. You will see” along with “several more of Blakes books” at “Johnsons” (Bentley, *Records*, page 65).</note></publisher>
               <pubplace>Lambeth <note>The London suburb of "Lambeth" is recorded as the place of
                     publication on Objects 2, 6, 9, 10, 13, 14, 16, and 17 in their second states. Object 2, the title page, in its second state also gives Joseph Johnson's London address.</note></pubplace>
               <date>1793<note>The date does not appear in Copy A but was added to Object 2, the title page, in its second state.  The imprints on other plates in their second states include the date "17 May 1793".  There is no imprint on Object 15 (Bentley Plate 15) in its second state.</note></date>
            </imprint>
            <compdate value="1793.A">1793<note>The work is based on designs Blake drew in his
                  Notebook; some of these sketches may have been executed c.
               1790-92.</note></compdate>
         </objdescid>
         <objinfo>
            <printdate value="1793.A">1793</printdate>
            <numberobj>18</numberobj>
            <objorder>Bentley Plates 1-18 <note>Object 1, the frontispiece, is bound facing Object
                  2, the title page.</note></objorder>
            <objsize>Platemarks range in size between 9.4 x 7.4 cm. and 6.1 x 4.2 cm.</objsize>
            <numberleaves>18</numberleaves>
            <leafsize>13.9 x 9.6 cm.</leafsize>
            <medium>intaglio etching/engraving<note>All plates are in their first state.  Copy A can be considered a proof or pre-publication copy because of the absence of the imprints added to all but Object 15 (Bentley Plate 15) in their second states. There are
                  five states of Objects 1-10, 13-18 (Bentley Plates 1-10, 13-18), three states of
                  Object 11 (Bentley Plate 11), and four states of Object 12 (Bentley Plate 12). The
                  first two states appear in copies of *For Children: The Gates of Paradise* and
                  states three through five in copies of *For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise*. The
                  only recorded copy with the plates in their first states is Copy A of *For Children*. See Bentley pages 187-91 for brief descriptions of the differences between the first and second states. Blake added three plates, Bentley Plates 19-21, when he transformed *For Children* into *For the Sexes* c. 1818.</note></medium>
            <printingstyle>intaglio</printingstyle>
            <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
            <support>wove paper</support>
            <watermark>MAFRINS<note>This (probably fragmentary) watermark appears only on Objects 13 and 15.  Bentley page 186, note 2, states that the watermark is "almost illegible" and that Object 2, the title page, in Copy A is "on clearly different paper" from the other objects.</note></watermark>
            <etchednumbers>1 lower left on Object 1; 2-16 lower left on Objects 4-18</etchednumbers>
            <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
            <framelines>none</framelines>
            <binding>red morocco<note>Bentley page 191 notes that the binding probably dates from c. 1805.</note></binding>
            <stabholes>Originally stabbed through three holes, 3.2 cm. from the top edge of the leaves and 3.9 cm. and 3.8 cm. apart.</stabholes>
         </objinfo>
         <provenance n="1">
            <name>Library of Congress</name>
            <date>1945</date>
            <dealer>none</dealer>
            <price>gift</price>
            <note>Acquired by Rebekah Bliss, probably directly from Blake no later than c. 1805; sold from her collection, Saunders and Hodgson auction, London, 26 April 1826, lot 10 (8s.); P. A. Hanrott, sold from his collection, Evans auction, London, 26 April 1833, lot 894 (&#163;1.16s. to "Thorpe," probably a dealer possibly acting for "Clarke," also probably a dealer); William Beckford, sold from his collection Sotheby's, 4 July 1882, lot 953 (&#163;16 to the dealer James Bain); acquired by Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge, possibly at the 1882 Beckford auction but no later than 1892; sold from the Macgeorge collection, Sotheby's, 1 July 1924, lot 112 (&#163;174 to the dealer Maggs Bros.); offered by Maggs, 1924 catalogue 456, item 55 (&#163;275); W. E. Moss by no later than 1927; sold from his collection, Sotheby's, 2 March 1937, lot 176 (&#163;460 to the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach, probably acting for Lessing J. Rosenwald); given by Rosenwald to the Library of Congress in 1945.</note>
         </provenance>
         <repository>
            <institution>Library of Congress</institution>
            <department>Rare Book and Special Collections</department>
            <collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection>
            <repositoryid label="Call number">PR4144.F6 1793a</repositoryid>
            <repositoryid label="Catalog number">1813A</repositoryid>
         </repository>
      </source>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.01" dbi="gates-child.A.P1">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1,
                  </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode><objcode code="Ki">Keynes
                  i)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>9.4 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="489" width="328"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>We see two large leaves, perhaps oak leaves, growing from a branch. The
                  veins on the lower leaf are particularly prominent. The upper leaf bears a large
                  caterpillar which may be eating the edge of the leaf. The lower leaf cradles an
                  infant or at least the head of an infant with closed eyes whose body suggests both
                  swaddling bands and a chrysalis. There are slight indications of curly hair on the
                  infant's head.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>oak</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>veins</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>We see two large leaves, perhaps oak leaves, growing from a branch.
                     The veins on the lower leaf are particularly prominent.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="animal" location="AB">
                  <characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eating</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A large caterpillar rests on the edge of, and may be eating, a
                     leaf.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>swaddled</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>chrysalis</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A leaf cradles an infant—or at least the head of an infant with
                     closed eyes—whose body suggests both swaddling bands and a chrysalis. There are
                     slight indications of curly hair on the infant's head.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.01.01" justify="center">What is Man!</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.01.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >1</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.02" dbi="gates-child.A.P2">
         <objtitle><title type="transcribed">For Children The Gates of Paradise</title>,
                  <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2,
                  </objcode><objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii, </objcode><objcode code="Kii">Keynes
                  ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objnote><p>The abraded condition of the paper below "Paradise" and above the ruled line, as well as the ghostly and fragmentary printing of an inscription beginning with the letter "P" and ending with the letters "ey", indicate that text was erased from this impression. The inscription must have also been removed from the copperplate because no such inscription appears in the next (second) state of the plate. Bentley, *Writings*, volume 1, page 165, suggests that the deleted inscription might be a reference to the publisher James Dodsley: “P[ublishd by J. Dodsl]ey.” There is, however, no other evidence that Dodsley was involved in the publication or sale of *For Children*.</p></objnote>
            <objsize>6.8 x 4.2 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="489" height="328"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="interlinear" location="AB">
               <illusobjdesc>A figure hovers in the air with arms extended horizontally. We
                  apparently see this figure from behind, at least in part. The figure may be facing
                  right. A few lines near the feet and legs suggest the hem of a
                  gown.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="figure" location="AB">
                  <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A figure hovers in the air with arms extended horizontally. We
                     apparently see this figure from behind, at least in part. The figure may be
                     facing right. A few lines near the feet and legs suggest the hem of a
                     gown.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <texthead justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.02.01" justify="center">For Children</l>
            </texthead>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.02.02" justify="center">The</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.02.03" justify="center">Gates</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.02.04" justify="center">of</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.02.05" justify="center">Paradise</l>
            </lg>  
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.03" dbi="gates-child.A.P3">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E1">Erdman 1, </objcode><objcode code="K1">Keynes
                  1)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objnote><p>A few very light lines lower left look like the number 17, but we suspect that these are just accidental scratches on the copperplate.</p></objnote>
            <objsize>7.8 x 6.4 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="406" width="333"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A large tree grows up the left margin, with branches arching toward the
                  left in the top third of the image. Its long, dangling branches and/or leaves
                  suggest it may be a willow. A few small plants with large leaves cover the ground
                  below the trunk. To the right, below the tree's largest branch, is a gowned woman
                  striding to the left with legs spread apart. Her hair is drawn into a bun on the
                  back of her head. Her left arm is bent at the elbow and she holds in her left hand
                  two small children or infants. We see only one child's head and the right eye and
                  cheek of the other; a part of the woman's gown, or a separate blanket, covers the
                  children's bodies. The woman, perhaps the children's mother or a nurse, leans over
                  and faces down. She reaches down with her right arm and hand and appears to be
                  pulling a third child or infant out of the earth. We see this child only from the
                  chest up; his or her hair stands on end. The position of the child suggests that
                  it is the anthropomorphic form of a vegetable, perhaps a mandrake, traditionally
                  thought to be shaped like a human body. Perhaps the woman has "harvested" the
                  other two children, held in her left arm, in a similar fashion. A few clouds fill
                  the sky behind the tree's limbs and leaves.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>willow</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A large tree grows up the left margin, with branches arching toward
                     the left in the top third of the image. Its long, dangling branches and/or
                     leaves suggest it may be a willow.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                  <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A few small plants with large leaves cover the ground below the
                     trunk of the tree.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="AB">
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A few clouds fill the sky behind the tree's limbs and
                     leaves.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nurse</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pulling</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>finger's spread</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A gowned woman strides to the left with legs spread apart. Her hair
                     is drawn into a bun on the back of her head. Her left arm is bent at the elbow
                     and she holds in her left hand two small children or infants. The woman,
                     perhaps the children's mother or a nurse, leans over and faces down. She
                     reaches down with her right arm and hand and appears to be pulling a third
                     child or infant out of the earth. The fingers of her right hand are spread over
                     the child's forehead.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>blanket</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The woman holds two small children or infants in her left arm and
                     hand. We see only the head of one child, facing forward; the second child,
                     above and two the right of the more prominent one, is indicated only by the
                     left eye and cheek, facing up. The bodies of both children are covered with a
                     portion of the woman's gown or a separate blanket.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="C">
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mandrake</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The woman reaches down with her right arm and hand and appears to be
                     pulling a child or infant out of the earth. We see this child only from the
                     chest up; his or her hair stands on end. The position of the child suggests
                     that it is the anthropomorphic form of a plant—perhaps a mandrake,
                     traditionally thought to be shaped like a human body. Perhaps the woman has
                     "harvested" the other two children, held in her left arm, in a similar
                     fashion.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.03.01" justify="center">I found him beneath a Tree</l>
            </lg>  
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.04" dbi="gates-child.A.P4">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 4,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E2">Erdman 2, </objcode><objcode code="K2">Keynes
                  2)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>8.2 x 7.3 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="426" width="380"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A nude male, apparently with long hair, sits on the bank of a river or
                  lake with legs crossed at the ankles. He faces down, with eyes closed or partly
                  closed. His arms reach down, and his hands rest on his knees; his palms are open
                  and facing down with fingers spread. The lines on his face and his general
                  expression suggest despair or melancholy. To the right is a tree, the barren
                  branches of which arch over the figure. A few lines beneath its trunk may be
                  roots. Other lines, almost vertical but slightly angled from right to left, cover
                  most of the image and very probably represent rain. A river or lake appears lower
                  left and below the man's feet. As the caption (line 1) indicates, "Water" is the
                  subject, both literal and metaphoric, of the design.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms resting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>palms down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A nude male, apparently with long hair, sits on the bank of a river
                     or lake with legs crossed at the ankles. He faces down, with eyes closed or
                     partly closed. His arms reach down, and his hands rest on his knees; his palms
                     are open and facing down with fingers spread. His mouth is slightly open. The
                     lines on his face and his general expression suggest despair or melancholy. He
                     may be a personification of water as both a substance and a psychological state
                     within a Blakean version of humoral theory.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>root</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A leafless tree grows up the right margin of the design, with a
                     prominent limb arching over the seated man. Lines below the trunk of the tree
                     suggest roots.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>bank</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>peninsula</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The man sits on a bank of earth above a river or lake. This body of
                     water would seem to extend around the left end of the bank, thus making it a
                     diminutive peninsula. Lines, almost vertical but angling slightly to the lower
                     left, indicate heavy rain.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.04.01" justify="center">Water</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.04.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >2</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.05" dbi="gates-child.A.P5">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 5,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E3">Erdman 3, </objcode><objcode code="K3">Keynes
                  3)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>8.2 x 7.4 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="426" width="385"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A nude male struggles within a cleft or cavern formed by dark and
                  massive stones. He is bearded; his hair is slightly curly. He squats or crouches,
                  with legs spread apart. His left leg is bent sharply at the knee and the right,
                  slightly bent, is extended toward the lower margin of the image. He faces forward,
                  with his arms raised, elbows bent. His hands are above his head; he may be
                  grasping the top of his head with his left hand. The general expression is one of
                  conflict, grief, and pain. He may be a personification of "Earth" (line 1) within
                  a Blakean version of humoral theory.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A man struggles within a cleft or cavern formed by dark and massive
                     stones.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grief</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A nude male struggles within a cleft or cavern formed by dark and
                     massive stones. He is bearded; his hair is slightly curly. He squats or
                     crouches, with legs spread apart. His left leg is bent sharply at the knee and
                     the right, slightly bent, is extended toward the lower margin of the image. He
                     faces forward, with his arms raised, elbows bent. His hands are above his head;
                     he may be grasping the top of his head with his left hand. The general
                     expression is one of conflict, grief, and pain. He may be a personification of
                     "Earth" (line 1) within a Blakean version of humoral theory.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.05.01" justify="center">Earth</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.05.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >3</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.06" dbi="gates-child.A.P6">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 6,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode><objcode code="K4">Keynes
                  4)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>8.2 x 7.2 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="426" width="374"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A youthful, nude male sits, in a crouch-like posture, on a cloud. Parts
                  of this cloud, or perhaps other clouds, extend behind him and in front of him,
                  covering his feet. Fourteen stars fill the night sky. His legs are bent sharply at
                  his prominent knees. His hair is curly. His arms are bent at the elbows and
                  extended upward, with both hands clasped over, and perhaps clutching, his
                  forehead. His chin rests on his right knee. He faces forward, with a lined visage
                  suggesting despair or melancholy. Given the caption, he may be a personification
                  of "air" (line 1) within a Blakean version of humoral theory.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Clouds and fourteen stars fill the night sky.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>crouching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head on knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>air</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A youthful, nude male sits, in a crouch-like posture, on a cloud.
                     His legs are bent sharply at his prominent knees. His hair is curly. His arms
                     are bent at the elbows and extended upward, with both hands clasped over, and
                     perhaps clutching, his forehead. His chin rests on his right knee. He faces
                     forward, with a lined visage suggesting despair or melancholy. Given the
                     caption, he may be a personification of "air" (line 1) within a Blakean version
                     of humoral theory.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.06.01" justify="center">Air</l>
               <vspace extent="1"/>
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.06.02" justify="left">
                  <physnumber type="etched">4</physnumber>
               </l>
            </lg>          
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.07" dbi="gates-child.A.P7">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E5">Erdman 5, </objcode><objcode code="K5">Keynes
                  5)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>9.1 x 7.3 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="473" width="380"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A young and muscular nude male, with curly (almost snake-like) hair,
                  stands facing forward. His legs are spread apart, and his arms are raised at
                  approximately 135 degrees. His right arm is slightly bent. He holds a spear in his
                  right hand; a large shield is buckled to his left arm and hand. His posture
                  suggests triumph or challenge, but his visage expresses fear or pain. His mouth is
                  slightly open, and his eyes are raised. Flames fill the background of the design
                  and rise over the figure's right lower leg. The figure and his setting suggest
                  both Blake's Orc (frequently associated with fire) and Milton's Satan in hell. The
                  caption (line 1) indicates that he is, at the very least, a personification of
                  "Fire."</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hell</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Flames fill the background and foreground of the design. There may
                     be smoke on each side of the figure's head. The fire and the character of the
                     figure suggest this may be a vision of hell.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>snake-like</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shield</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Satan</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A young and muscular nude male, with curly (almost snake-like) hair,
                     stands facing forward. His legs are spread apart, and his arms raised at
                     approximately 135 degrees. His right arm is slightly bent. He holds a spear in
                     his right hand; a large shield is buckled to his left arm and hand. His posture
                     suggests triumph or challenge, but his lined visage expresses fear or pain. His
                     mouth is slightly open, and his eyes are raised. The figure and his fiery
                     setting suggest both Blake's Orc (frequently associated with fire) and Milton's
                     Satan in hell. The caption (line 1) indicates that he is, at the very least, a
                     personification of "Fire."</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.07.01" justify="center">Fire</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.07.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >5</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.08" dbi="gates-child.A.P8">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 8,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes
                  6)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>6.1 x 5.0 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>An infant or young child, nude and probably male, emerges like a
                  hatchling from a broken egg. Given his wings, he may be a putto, cherub, or angel.
                  His legs are crossed at the ankles; his left arm is bent, with his left hand
                  placed on the shell as though he were pushing against it to rise. He faces
                  forward, with his head up and eyes raised. His hair is curly. Clouds fill the sky
                  behind the figure and the egg; two broken pieces of the latter rest in the
                  foreground.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>egg</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A child emerges from a broken egg, two pieces of which lie in the
                     foreground. Clouds fill the sky.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cherub</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pushing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breaking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>An infant or young child, nude and probably male, emerges like a
                     hatchling from a broken egg. Given his wings, he may be a putto, cherub, or
                     angel. His legs are crossed at the ankles; his left arm is bent, with his left
                     hand placed on the shell as though he were pushing against it to rise. He faces
                     forward, with his head up and eyes raised. His hair is curly. </illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.08.01" justify="left" indent="5">At length for hatching
                  ripe</l>
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.08.02" justify="left" indent="11">he breaks the shell</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.08.03" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >6</physnumber>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.09" dbi="gates-child.A.P9">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber><objcode code="B9">(Bentley 9,
                  </objcode><objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes
                  7)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>7.5 x 5.0 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A young male strides, with legs spread, from left to right. He wears
                  tights or a combination of breeches and a shirt. His hair is curly. He faces to
                  the right, with a look of surprise or excitement on his face. His left arm is at
                  his side; his right arm is raised vertically but slightly bent at the elbow. He
                  holds a hat in his raised right hand. To the right of his face is a (nude and
                  male?) human figure, perhaps an infant or child, hovering (flying?) in mid-air. We
                  see this figure, also with curly hair, from the back, but facing to the left
                  (toward the large figure). His legs are spread, as though fleeing from the youth
                  with a hat, who may be pursuing him. The hovering figure has his arms extended
                  horizontally. Below, on the ground and in the lower right corner of the design, is
                  a second diminutive figure of uncertain gender. He or she may be dead and lies
                  face-down, with the right leg extended and arms extended horizontally in a
                  cruciform position. His or her hair is long. Given the positioning of these two
                  small figures and the iconographic tradition from which this design may have been
                  developed, the two small human forms may be personifications of birds or
                  butterflies. The middle distance is dominated by leafy plants or trees. Clouds
                  fill the sky in the upper portions of the design.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="AB">
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Clouds fill the sky in the upper portions of the
                     design.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Leafy plants or trees fill the middle distance of the
                     design.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A young male strides, with legs spread, from left to right. He wears
                     tights—or a combination of breeches and a shirt. He may also wear shoes. His
                     hair is curly. He faces to the right, with a look of surprise or excitement on
                     his face. His left arm is at his side; his right arm is raised vertically but
                     slightly bent at the elbow. He holds a hat in his raised right hand. He may be
                     pursuing, and attempting to kill or capture, the flying figure to the
                     right.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="B">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>To the right of the large figure's face is a (nude and male?) human
                     figure, perhaps an infant or child, hovering (flying?) in mid-air. We see this
                     figure with curly hair from the back, but facing to the left (toward the large
                     figure). His legs are spread, as though fleeing from the youth with a hat, who
                     may be pursuing him. The hovering figure has his arms extended horizontally.
                     Given the iconographic tradition from which this design may have been
                     developed, this figure may be the anthropomorphic form of a bird or
                     butterfly.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="D">
                  <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>butterfly</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>crucified</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A diminutive figure of uncertain gender lies on the ground, lower
                     right. He or she may be dead and lies face-down, with the right leg extended
                     and arms extended horizontally in a cruciform position. His or her hair is
                     long. Given the positioning of the two small figures and the iconographic
                     tradition from which this design may have been developed, the two small human
                     forms may be personifications of birds or butterflies.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.09.01" justify="center">Alas!</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.09.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >7</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.10" dbi="gates-child.A.P10">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber><objcode code="B10">(Bentley
                  10, </objcode><objcode code="E8">Erdman 8, </objcode><objcode code="K8">Keynes
                  8)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>9.3 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="484" width="328"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>On the left, a youthful male with curly hair strides to the left.
                  Although basically pictured as a nude, a small piece of drapery seems to extend to
                  the right of his left thigh. His body is twisted, and he faces to the right,
                  toward a bearded man. The youth's right arm is raised horizontally, and he may be
                  pointing toward this older man. His left arm is raised vertically; he grasps a
                  spear or dart in his raised left hand. He may be about to throw his weapon at the
                  old man. To the right sits a nude old man with long hair and a long beard. His
                  left leg is bent at the knee, his right extended to the left. His left arm is bent
                  at the elbow, and he props his head on his left hand, a posture traditionally
                  indicative of melancholy. His body is twisted, and he looks down and to the right.
                  His right arm is raised horizontally, and he grasps a large sword in his right
                  hand. The positioning of the two figures and their relative ages suggest that the
                  youth is an Orc-like figure and the old man is his father, as well as a king or
                  Urizen figure. The caption (line 1), if spoken by the old man, indicates that the
                  youth is his child. The old man's chair (a primitive throne?) is constructed of
                  large stones. The back of the chair is also constructed of stones. Alternatively,
                  if the perspective is distorted, this may be a ruined wall and the "chair" part of
                  the wall or building. A large tree with several leafy branches arches above the
                  old man. We see a low hill, a mountain behind and to the right, and clouds in the
                  sky on the left. The earth in the foreground may be covered with
                  grass.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="figure" location="AC">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>throwing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>spear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dart</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Orc</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A youthful male with curly hair strides to the left. Although
                     basically pictured as a nude, a small piece of drapery seems to extend to the
                     right of his left thigh. His body is twisted and he faces to the right, toward
                     an old, bearded man. The youth's right arm is raised horizontally, and he may
                     be pointing toward the bearded man. His left arm is raised vertically; he
                     grasps a spear or dart in his raised left hand. He may be about to throw his
                     weapon at the old man. The relative positions and ages of the figures suggest
                     that the youth is an Orc figure. If the caption (line 1) is spoken by the old
                     man, then the youth is his child.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="BD">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sword</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>king</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Urizen</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>To the right of the young man sits a nude old man with long hair and
                     a long beard. His left leg is bent at the knee, his right extended to the left.
                     His left arm is bent at the elbow, and he props his head on his left hand—a
                     posture traditionally indicative of melancholy. His body is twisted, and he
                     looks down and to the right. His right arm is raised horizontally, and he
                     grasps a large sword in his right hand. The positioning of the two figures and
                     their relative ages suggest that the youth is an Orc- like figure and the old
                     man is his father, as well as a king or Urizen figure</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The earth in the foreground of the design may be covered with
                     grass.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>limb</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A large tree with several leafy branches arches through the upper
                     part of the design.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="BD">
                  <characteristic>chair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ruin</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The bearded old man sits on a chair composed of large cut stones.
                     The high back of the chair is also stony. Alternatively, if the perspective is
                     distorted, this may be a ruined wall and the man's "chair" simply more stones
                     from the wall or building.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="AC">
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A low hill fills the middle distance, with a mountain behind and to
                     the right. Clouds fill the sky above.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.10.01" justify="center">My Son! my Son!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.10.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >8</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.11" dbi="gates-child.A.P11">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber><objcode code="B11">(Bentley
                  11, </objcode><objcode code="E9">Erdman 9, </objcode><objcode code="K9">Keynes
                  9)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>7.1 x 4.8 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>The design is dominated by the night sky, complete with seven stars and
                  a thin, crescent moon. A long ladder reaches from the surface of the earth, lower
                  right, to the moon. A small figure has just begun to climb the ladder, with the
                  left leg bent at the knee so as to place the left foot on the third rung of the
                  ladder, and the right foot still on the earth. This figure's arms are raised
                  horizontally, with his hands apparently holding the vertical sides of the ladder.
                  The figure is probably male: he wears a hat and may be looking to the right. In
                  the far right corner is a group of two figures, probably a woman on the left
                  (wearing a dress or skirt) and a man on the right. The man has at least his left
                  arm raised horizontally; he may be embracing the woman around her waist. The
                  woman's right arm is bent at the elbow, with her forearm raised horizontally. Both
                  these figures appear to be facing to the left and looking at the man climbing the
                  ladder; the woman may be pointing at him.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>star</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>night</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ladder</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The night sky shows seven stars. A ladder extends from the earth,
                     lower right, to a crescent moon, top left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="A">
                  <characteristic>moon</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A crescent moon appears in the night sky, top left.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="D">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>climbing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A small figure has just begun to climb the ladder, with the left leg
                     bent at the knee so as to place the left foot on the third rung of the ladder,
                     and the right foot still on the earth. This figure's arms are raised
                     horizontally, with his hands apparently holding the vertical sides of the
                     ladder. The figure is probably male: he wears a hat and may be looking to the
                     right.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="D">
                  <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>skirt</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the far right corner of the image is a group of two figures,
                     probably a woman on the left (wearing a dress or skirt) and a man on the right.
                     The man has at least his left arm raised horizontally; he may be embracing the
                     woman around her waist. The woman's right arm is bent at the elbow, with her
                     forearm raised horizontally. Both these figures appear to be facing to the left
                     and looking at the man climbing the ladder; the woman may be pointing at
                     him.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.11.01" justify="center">I want! I want!</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.d.illbk.11.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >9</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.12" dbi="gates-child.A.P12">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A12">Object 12 </objnumber><objcode code="B12">(Bentley
                  12, </objcode><objcode code="E10">Erdman 10, </objcode><objcode code="K10">Keynes
                  10)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>6.7 x 5.0 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>The design is dominated by a stormy sky and sea, the former filled with
                  clouds and the latter fraught with two large waves. Near one wave crest we see a
                  human arm raised vertically, fingers spread apart. This figure's head (just to the
                  left of the arm) is bent back and facing up. The figure is probably male and,
                  given the caption, trying to swim but drowning in the attempt. He may be looking
                  to the heavens for help but is in despair.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The design is dominated by a stormy sky and sea, the former filled
                     with clouds and the latter fraught with two large waves.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>swimming</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>drowning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Near one wave crest we see a human arm raised vertically, fingers
                     spread apart. This figure's head (just to the left of the arm) is bent back and
                     facing up. The figure is probably male and, given the caption, trying to swim
                     but drowning in the attempt. He may be looking to the heavens for help but is
                     in despair.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.12.01" justify="center">Help! Help!</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.12.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >10</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.13" dbi="gates-child.A.P13">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A13">Object 13 </objnumber><objcode code="B13">(Bentley
                  13, </objcode><objcode code="E11">Erdman 11, </objcode><objcode code="K11">Keynes
                  11)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>7.1 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="369" width="328"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>The design is based on a traditional emblem of Age clipping the wings
                  of Love. On the left sits a gowned old man wearing spectacles (an indication of
                  limited vision). He has a long beard and probably long hair. His eyes are closed
                  or looking down; he may be blind or almost blind. His legs, with prominent knees,
                  are crossed at the ankles. His left arm is raised horizontally, with the left hand
                  grasping the wing of the youthful figure to the right. His right arm is bent at
                  the elbow; he holds in his right hand a pair of scissors with which he is about to
                  cut the tip of the youth's right wing. This winged and youthful male figure, nude
                  and striding energetically to the right, is a winged Cupid, cherub, or angel. His
                  legs are spread apart, as though running to the right; he may be fleeing from the
                  old man. The youth's hair is curly. His right arm is bent upward at the elbow,
                  with the fingers of his raised right hand spread apart. His body faces to the
                  right, but we see only the back of his head as he looks back to the sun rising or
                  setting on the distant horizon. Lines of radiance emanate from the sun. A tree,
                  its branches arching over both figures, grows up the left margin. The leaves of a
                  tree or large plant fill the background above the old man. There may be grass on
                  the slight hill or mound on which the two figures are placed.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cutting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>spectacles</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>blind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>scissors</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>On the left sits a gowned old man wearing spectacles (an indication
                     of limited vision). He has a long bear and probably long hair. His eyes are
                     closed or looking down; he may be blind are almost blind. His legs, with
                     prominent knees, are crossed at the ankles. His left arm is raised
                     horizontally, with the left hand grasping the wing of the youthful figure to
                     the right. His right arm is bent at the elbow; he holds in his right hand a
                     pair of scissors with which he is about to cut the tip of the youth's right
                     wing.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fleeing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cherub</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Cupid</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A winged and youthful male figure, nude and striding energetically
                     to the right, is a winged Cupid, cherub, or angel. His legs are spread apart,
                     as though running to the right; he may be fleeing from the old man. The youth's
                     hair is curly. His right arm is bent upward at the elbow, with the fingers of
                     his raised right hand spread apart. His body faces to the right, but we see
                     only the back of his head as he looks back to the sun rising or setting on the
                     distant horizon.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="BD">
                  <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>We see about half the sun rising or setting. Radiant beams of light
                     emanate from it.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>limb</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mound</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A tree, its branches arching over both figures, grows up the left
                     margin. The leaves of a tree or large plant fill the background above the old
                     man. There may be grass on the slight hill or mound on which the two figures
                     are placed.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.13.01" justify="center">Aged Ignorance</l>
            </lg>
            <vspace extent="1"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.13.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >11</physnumber><note>The number “11” is only faintly visible.</note></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.14" dbi="gates-child.A.P14">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A14">Object 14 </objnumber><objcode code="B14">(Bentley
                  14, </objcode><objcode code="E12">Erdman 12, </objcode><objcode code="K12">Keynes
                  12)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>6.4 x 6.1 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="333" width="317"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>Within a small room, probably a prison cell built of stone, we see five
                  seated male figures, all apparently nude (with the possible exceptions of the
                  figures lower left and right). The central figure, facing forward, is old and
                  bearded with hair standing on end; the others are much younger. This central
                  figure has his legs drawn up; his knees are very prominent. His face suggests
                  despair or worse. Immediately to the left, very close to the old man, is a young
                  man with legs drawn up and crossed at the ankles. His knees are also prominent.
                  His body faces forward, but his head is turned up and to the right; he may be
                  looking at the face of the old man. Although we see only his right shoulder and
                  upper arm, his right arm may be extended horizontally; he may be embracing the old
                  man. On the right is another young male close to the old man. His legs are drawn
                  up and crossed at the ankles, with prominent knees. His body faces forward, but
                  his head is turned to the left, with his face pressed against the body or left leg
                  of the old man. This figure's hair seems to be long. Another youthful male sits in
                  the right foreground. His legs are extended but slightly bent at the knees.
                  Although probably nude, like his companions, lines just below his knees suggest
                  that he might be wearing breeches. His left arm is at his side, with his left hand
                  on the ground (or, rather, on the floor), fingers spread apart. He faces left,
                  with his head bent back and looking up; his mouth is slightly open. His hair is
                  probably long. In the left foreground is the final youthful figure, seated and
                  with legs extended. Though he may be nude, lines just below his knees suggest that
                  he, too, may be wearing breeches. He faces to the right, with his head down. His
                  right arm is at is side, with his right hand on the ground (or, rather, on the
                  floor), fingers spread. His hair is curly. Given the configuration of the males,
                  the setting, and the compositional relationship to several drawings by Blake, this
                  design would seem to be inspired by Dante's description of Count Ugolino and his
                  sons in prison.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="structure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>prison</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Within a small room, probably a prison cell built of stone, we see
                     five seated figures.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Ugolino</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>despair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pain</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Within a small room, probably a prison cell built of stone, we see
                     five seated male figures, all apparently nude (with the possible exception of
                     the figures lower left and right, who may wear breeches). Given the
                     configuration of these figures, the setting, and the compositional relationship
                     to several drawings by Blake, this design would seem to be inspired by Dante's
                     description of Count Ugolino and his sons in prison. All appear to be dying in
                     pain and despair.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>Ugolino</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The central seated figure, male and apparently nude, in this group
                     of five faces forward. He is old and bearded with hair standing on end. He has
                     his legs drawn up; his knees are very prominent. His face suggests despair or
                     worse. He may be Ugolino.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="AC">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>embracing</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A youthful male nude sits next to the old man in the center of the
                     design. His hair is long and perhaps drawn into a bun. His legs are drawn up
                     and crossed at the ankles. His knees are prominent. His body faces forward, but
                     his head is turned up and to the right; he may be looking at the face of the
                     old man. Although we see only his right shoulder and upper arm, his right arm
                     may be extended horizontally; he may be embracing the old man.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="BD">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A youthful male nude sits next to the old man in the center of the
                     design. His legs are drawn up and crossed at the ankles, with prominent knees.
                     His body faces forward, but his head is turned to the left, with his face
                     pressed against the body or left leg of the old man. This figure's hair seems
                     to be long.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="D">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A youthful male sits in the lower right corner of the cell. He is
                     probably nude, but lines just below his knees suggest that he may be wearing
                     breeches. His legs are extended but slightly bent at the knees. His left arm is
                     at his side, with his left hand on the ground (or, rather, on the floor),
                     fingers spread apart. He faces left, with his head bent back and looking up;
                     his mouth is slightly open. His hair is probably long.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="C">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A youthful male sits in the lower left corner of the cell. He is
                     probably nude, but lines just below his knees suggest that he may be wearing
                     breeches. He faces to the right, with his head down. His right arm is at is
                     side, with his right hand on the ground (or, rather, on the floor), fingers
                     spread. His hair is curly.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.14.01" justify="center">Does thy God O Priest take such
                  vengeance</l>
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.14.02" justify="center">as this?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.14.03" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >12</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.15" dbi="gates-child.A.P15">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A15">Object 15 </objnumber><objcode code="B15">(Bentley
                  15, </objcode><objcode code="E13">Erdman 13, </objcode><objcode code="K13">Keynes
                  13)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>8.1 x 7.2 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize height="421" width="374"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>We see the corner of a featureless chamber or cell, perhaps with stone
                  walls and a wooden floor. The only furniture is a bed (or possibly a bier),
                  probably made of wood. A body very probably dead lies supine and rigid on the bed,
                  legs together and at least the right arm at his side. The fingers of his right
                  hand are long and prominent. This gowned figure is very probably an old man, as
                  indicated by his long beard. His face is hidden by another figure. At his feet,
                  rising into the air at a 45 degree angle from lower right to upper left, is
                  another gowned and bearded old man. We can see the supine figure's feet through
                  the lower leg of the rising figure, and thus he is almost certainly the ghost or
                  spirit of the dead man. His hair is long and he faces to the left. His right arm
                  is bent at the elbow with the forearm raised horizontally across his body. The
                  index finger of his right hand is extended and points to the right. His left arm
                  is bent at the elbow with the forearm raised vertically. One finger of his left
                  hand points upward. In the foreground on the left is a young man with curly hair.
                  He squats or sits on his left leg, bent under his body; his right leg is extended
                  to the right and bent slightly at the knee. He may be wearing tights, or at least
                  a belt around his waist. His right arm is at his side, with the fingers of his
                  right hand spread apart. His mouth is slightly open, and he appears to be looking
                  up and to the right in fear or surprise at the ghostly figure above and to the
                  right. He may be the son of the dead man. Behind the bed and its corpse we see the
                  head and upper body of a gowned woman wearing a scarf over her head. Her left arm
                  is extended at 45 degrees. Her mouth may be slightly open, and she also looks up
                  and to the right at the ghost with an expression of fear or surprise. She may be
                  the wife or daughter of the dead man. Behind her and to the right are two small
                  figures, probably children or grandchildren of the dead man. Of the child closest
                  to the woman we see only the face, which is in right profile. The child farthest
                  to the right in this group is probably a male with curly hair. We see only his
                  face and upper chest. He is probably looking up and to the right at the
                  ghost.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="structure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>chamber</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cell</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>We see the corner of a featureless chamber or cell, perhaps with
                     stone walls and a wooden floor.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>bier</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The only piece of furniture in the room is a bed or bier, probably
                     made of wood.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>family</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>father</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mother</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The group of figures in the design may be a family—a dead father on
                     the bed, his wife, and three children.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>rigid</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs together</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A body—very probably dead—lies supine and rigid on the bed, legs
                     together and at least the right arm at his side. The fingers of his right hand
                     are long and prominent. This gowned figure is very probably an old man, as
                     indicated by his long beard. His face is hidden by another
                     figure.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="BD">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>ghost</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>spirit</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm wrapped around body</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>At the feet of the body on the bed or bier, rising into the air at a
                     45 degree angle from lower right to upper left, is another gowned and bearded
                     old man. We can see the supine figure's feet through the lower leg of the
                     rising figure, and thus the latter is almost certainly the ghost or spirit of
                     the dead man. His hair is long, and he faces to the left. His right arm is bent
                     at the elbow with the forearm raised horizontally across his body. The index
                     finger of his right hand is extended and points to the right. His left arm is
                     bent at the elbow with the forearm raised vertically. One finger of his left
                     hand points upward.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>belt</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the foreground on the left is a young man with curly hair. He
                     squats or sits on his left leg, bent under his body; his right leg is extended
                     to the right and bent slightly at the knee. He may be wearing tights, or at
                     least a belt around his waist. His right arm is at his side, with the fingers
                     of his right hand spread apart. His mouth is slightly open, and he appears to
                     be looking up and to the right in fear or surprise at the ghostly figure above
                     and to the right. He may be the son of the dead man.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="AC">
                  <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>surprise</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Behind the bed and its corpse we see the head and upper body of a
                     gowned woman wearing a scarf over her head. Her left arm is raised at 45
                     degrees. Her mouth may be slightly open, and she looks up and to the right at
                     the ghost with an expression of fear or surprise. She may be the wife or
                     daughter of the dead man.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="D">
                  <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>Behind the prominent female figure and to the right are two small
                     figures, probably children or grandchildren of the dead man. Of the child
                     closest to the woman we see only the face, which is in right profile. The child
                     farthest to the right in this group is probably a male with curly hair. We see
                     only his face and upper chest. He is probably looking up and to the right at
                     the ghost.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.d.illbk.15.01" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                     >13</physnumber><space extent="10"/>Fear or Hope are  Vision<note>In the second state of this plate, the word "or" is changed to an ampersand.</note></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.16" dbi="gates-child.A.P16">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A16">Object 16 </objnumber><objcode code="B16">(Bentley
                  16, </objcode><objcode code="E14">Erdman 14, </objcode><objcode code="K14">Keynes
                  14)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>6.7 x 4.7 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A male traveler strides boldly to the right. He wears a coat, breeches,
                  shoes, and a hat; he holds a walking-stick in his right hand. His right arm is
                  bent at the elbow, with his forearm raised horizontally. His hair would appear to
                  be long. A long shadow extends from his left foot; another may form the dark
                  triangle lower right. The ground beneath his feet may be covered with grass; leafy
                  trees or large plants form the background. A few clouds fill the sky
                  above.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>traveler</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking-stick</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>coat</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>shoes</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A male traveler strides boldly to the right. He wears a coat,
                     breeches, shoes, and a hat; he holds a walking-stick in his right hand. His
                     right arm is bent at the elbow, with his forearm raised horizontally. His hair
                     would appear to be long.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                  <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The ground beneath the walking man's feet may be covered with grass;
                     leafy trees or large plants form the background.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A long shadow extends from the figure's left foot; another may form
                     the dark triangle lower right.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="AB">
                  <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A few clouds fill the sky above the trees.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
    <vspace extent="8"/>
    <lg type="prose" justify="center">
        <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.16.01" justify="center" indent="3">The Traveller hasteth in the</l>
        <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.16.02" justify="center">Evening</l>
    </lg>
    <vspace extent="1"/>
    <lg>
        <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.16.03" justify="left">
            <physnumber type="etched">14</physnumber></l>
    </lg>
</phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.17" dbi="gates-child.A.P17">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A17">Object 17 </objnumber><objcode code="B17">(Bentley
                  17, </objcode><objcode code="E15">Erdman 15, </objcode><objcode code="K15">Keynes
                  15)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>7.2 x 5.2 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>The entire image is filled with a door in a building, wall, or tomb.
                  The posts and lintel of this structure are made of stone; the partly-opened door
                  into the dark chamber is made of wood. Into this doorway steps an old man leaning
                  on a single crutch under his left arm. He apparently holds the crutch with his
                  left hand. His beard is long; his long hair streams out to the left, the direction
                  in which he is facing, as though shaped by a wind blowing from right to left and
                  into the tomb or chamber. His left foot is on tiptoe; his right foot and leg are
                  not pictured beneath his long gown. Given the caption, the man is entering his
                  tomb and thus dying.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="structure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>building</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>post</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>lintel</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tomb</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>chamber</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wall</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wood</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The entire image is filled with a door in a building, wall, or tomb.
                     The posts and lintel of this structure are made of stone; the partly-opened
                     door into the dark chamber is made of wood.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>crutch</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dying</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>An old man leaning on a single crutch under his left arm steps into
                     a doorway. He apparently holds the crutch with his left hand. His beard is
                     long; his long hair streams out to the left, the direction in which he is
                     facing, as though shaped by a wind blowing from right to left and into the tomb
                     or chamber. His left foot is on tiptoe; his right foot and leg are not pictured
                     beneath his long gown. Given the caption, the man is entering his tomb and thus
                     dying.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="center">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.17.01" justify="center">Death's Door</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.17.02" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >15</physnumber></l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
      <desc id="gates-child.a.illbk.18" dbi="gates-child.A.P18">
         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A18">Object 18 </objnumber><objcode code="B18">(Bentley
                  18, </objcode><objcode code="E16">Erdman 16, </objcode><objcode code="K16">Keynes
                  16)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
            <objsize>6.4 x 5.2 cm.</objsize>
            <windowsize width="315" height="472"/>
         </physdesc>
         <illusdesc>
            <illustration type="plate" location="E">
               <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure of uncertain gender squats or sits, with legs drawn up
                  and prominent knees, upon the earth. The figure, who faces forward, has a scarf or
                  hood over the head. Arms at side, the figure holds a slender staff in the right
                  hand. The left hand is on the ground. The figure appears to be looking, with open
                  eyes, directly at the viewer. A worm lies on the ground, encircling the figure and
                  reaching upward in a loop on the right side of the figure. Further to the lower
                  right are two or three heads partly buried in the earth. These may be severed
                  heads, or they may be the heads of corpses whose bodies are buried in graves below
                  the seated figure. The front-most figure, probably male, has his eyes closed. The
                  dark background is filled with the leafless limbs, trunks, and perhaps roots of
                  trees. There may also be a small plant, lower left, large stones (particularly on
                  the left), and a cave behind and above the seated figure.</illusobjdesc>
               <component type="figure" location="E">
                  <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hood</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>staff</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure of uncertain gender squats or sits, with legs drawn
                     up and prominent knees, upon the earth. The figure, who faces forward, has a
                     scarf or hood over the head. Arms at side, the figure holds a slender staff in
                     the right hand. The left hand is on the ground. The figure appears to be
                     looking, with open eyes, directly at the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="animal" location="CD">
                  <characteristic>worm</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>encircling</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>A worm lies on the ground, encircling the seated figure and reaching
                     upward in a loop on the right side of the figure.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="figure" location="D">
                  <characteristic>group of figures</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>buried</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>severed head</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>corpse</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>grave</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>In the lower right corner of the image are two or three heads partly
                     buried in the earth. These may be severed heads, or the heads of corpses whose
                     bodies are buried in graves below the seated figure. The front-most figure,
                     probably male, has his eyes closed.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                  <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>trunk</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>root</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>limb</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The dark background is filled with the leafless limbs, trunks, and
                     perhaps roots of trees. There may be a small plant growing in the lower left
                     corner of the image.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
               <component type="object" location="E">
                  <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                  <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                  <illusobjdesc>The background of the image may include large stones, particularly
                     on the right, and a cave behind and above the seated figure.</illusobjdesc>
               </component>
            </illustration>
         </illusdesc>
         <phystext>
            <vspace extent="8"/>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.18.01" justify="left" indent="4">I have said to the Worm, Thou</l>
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.18.02" justify="left" indent="6">art my mother &amp; my
                  sister</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
               <l n="gates-child.a.illbk.18.03" justify="left"><physnumber type="etched"
                  >16</physnumber>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </phystext>
      </desc>
   </objdesc>
</bad>
