<tei.2 n="illum"><teiheader><filedesc><titlestmt><title>Illuminated Printing</title></titlestmt><editionstmt><edition>Electronic edition</edition></editionstmt><publicationstmt><pubplace>University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia</pubplace><publisher>Institute for Advance Technology for the Humanities and
			 William Blake Archive</publisher><date>2003</date><availability><p>Available from: The William Blake Archive</p><p>URL: http://www.blakearchive.org</p></availability><date>February 2004</date></publicationstmt><sourcedesc><biblfull><titlestmt><title level="a">Illuminated Printing</title></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><pubplace>New York</pubplace><date>2003</date><availability><p>Available from: The William Blake Archive</p><p>URL: http://www.blakearchive.org</p></availability><date>©2003</date></publicationstmt><notesstmt><note>Illuminated Printing was first published in The
				  Cambridge Companion to William Blake, edited by Morris Eaves, 2003. It is
				  republished here by permission of Cambridge University Press. While the text
				  remains the same, the electronic version has a slightly different structure and
				  90 illustrations versus 9 in the printed version.</note></notesstmt></biblfull></sourcedesc></filedesc></teiheader><text><front><titlepage><doctitle><titlepart>Illuminated Printing</titlepart></doctitle></titlepage><div1 id="d0"><p>Illuminated Printing was first published in <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to William Blake</title>, edited by Morris Eaves, 2003. It is republished here by permission of Cambridge University Press. While the text remains the same, the electronic version has 95 illustrations versus 9 in the printed version. The illustrations demonstrate in detail the stages of both Blakes relief etching (illuminated printing) and conventional intaglio etching according to the six Chambers in the Printing house in Hell, from Blakes <title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>. The comparison of these two methods of etching will help reveal what was borrowed, altered, invented, and radical in Blakes new mode of graphic production. The illustrations, which are linked to enlargements that have detailed captions, supplement the text but also function autonomously as slide shows on the technical and aesthetic contexts in which illuminated printing was invented, and as
tutorials in the production of engravings, etchings, and relief etchings.
</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section" id="d1"><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">If a method of Printing which combines the
	  Painter and the Poet is a phenomenon worthy of public attention, provided that
	  it exceeds in elegance all former methods, the Author is sure of his
	  reward.</hi></q><bibl> Blake, 
	  <title level="m">Prospectus</title>, October 1793</bibl></cit></epigraph><head>Engraving</head><p>On 12 April 1827, shortly before he died, Blake wrote to George
 Cumberland thanking him for trying to sell copies of Blakes illuminated books
 and his recently published engraved illustrations to the Book of Job. Blake had
 first executed the Job illustrations as watercolor drawings for Thomas Butts
 around 1805, followed by a duplicate set for John Linnell, who commissioned him
 to engrave the series in 1823.</p><p>Three years later, Blake had 22 line engravings that looked very
 different from the tonal prints then popular. Indeed, they even looked
 different from engravings, his own included, for they were not executed in the
 standard mixed method technique, in which designs were first
 etched and then finished as engravings. In this technique, which Blake mastered
 as an apprentice, the designs outline was traced with a needle through
 an acid-resistant ground covering the copper plate and then
 etched with acid. The engraver went over these slightly incised lines with
 burins (metal tools with square or lozenge-shaped tips used to cut lines into
 the plate) and engraved the plates entire surface, uniting all parts in a web
 of crosshatched lines. <ptr target="d1.1"/><ptr target="d1.2"/><ptr target="d1.3"/><ptr target="d1.4"/><ptr target="d1.5"/><ptr target="d1.6"/><ptr target="d1.7"/> These advances in technique enabled modern
 engravers to represent mass and tone more convincingly than the more linear
 style of such ancient engravers as Blakes heroes, Durer
 and Raimondi, whose works were often dismissed as Hard Stiff &amp; Dry
 Unfinishd Works of Art (anno. Reynolds, E 639). The Job engravings were
 executed entirely with burins and without preliminary etching, with tone
 subordinate to line and texture and with lines amassed in parallel strokes
 rather than in the conventional dot and lozenge pattern (dots incised in the
 interstices of crosshatched lines, the linear system characteristic of
 bank-note engraving; see <ptr target="d1.8"/><ptr target="d1.9"/><ptr target="d1.10"/>. Blakes emulation of the ancient engravers produced a
 modern result: original artistic expression in a graphic medium whose
 materiality and natural language were fully exploited. <ptr target="d1.11"/><ptr target="d1.12"/> It was the masterpiece of his lifetime as an engraver,
 but it would be a tough sell, as Blake and Linnell, who had 315 sets printed in
 early 1826, must both have realized. 
 <note type="foot" id="I.1">215 proof sets were printed on special
	papers for connoisseurs and sold at L6.6s., and 100 sets were printed on
	regular paper, at L3.3s. For Blakes apprenticeship and lifelong development as
	a graphic artist, see Essick, <title level="m">William Blake, Printmaker</title>.</note></p><p>Works that Blake had in stock were not selling well. Even if the
 illuminated books might do better, as Cumberland supposed, the prospect of
 printing new copies did not excite their maker: 
 <q rend="block">…having none remaining of all that I had Printed
	I cannot Print more Except at a great loss for at the time I printed those
	things I had a whole House to range in now I am shut up in a Corner therefore
	am forced to ask a Price for them that I scarce expect to get from a Stranger.
	I am now Printing a Set of the Songs of Innocence &amp; Experience for a Friend
	at Ten Guineas which I cannot do under Six Months consistent with my other
	Work, so that I have little hope of doing any more of such things. the Last
	Work I produced is a Poem Entitled Jerusalem the Emanation of the Giant Albion,
	but find that to Print it will Cost my Time the amount of Twenty Guineas One I
	have Finishd It contains 100 Plates but it is not likely that I shall get a
	Customer for it (letter of 12 April 1827, E 783-84)</q> Though dubious about
 their prospects, Blake listed six books he was willing to reprintat
 about twenty times the prices advertised in his 1793 Prospectus (E 693).</p><p>Producing new copies of any illuminated book had become far more
 labor intensive, with each illuminated page now printed on one side of the leaf
 and elaborately colored, framed with lines, and often touched with gold leaf.
 Impressions now looked more like miniature paintings, a far cry from those
 produced in the 1790s, when plates were usually printed on both sides of the
 paper and lightly colored to look more like pages than prints or paintings. But
 six months?</p><p>Blakes Corner was two fair-sized rooms in the
 Strandmuch less space than the eight or ten rooms (BR 560)
 in Lambeth, where from 1790 to 1800 he had written, designed, etched, printed,
 and colored <title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title> (1790),
 <title level="m">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>, <title level="m">America a Prophecy</title>, <title level="m">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</title> (all 1793), <title level="m">Europe a Prophecy</title>,
 <title level="m">Songs of Experience</title>, the combined <title level="m">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>, <title level="m">The First Book of Urizen</title> (all 1794), <title level="m">The
 Book of Los</title>, <title level="m">The Song of Los</title>, and <title level="m">The Book of Ahania</title> (all 1795), and where he also reprinted
 copies of his earlier works, <title level="m">All Religions are One</title> and
 <title level="m">There is No Natural Religion</title> (1788), <title level="m">Songs of Innocence</title> (1789), and <title level="m">The Book
 of Thel</title> (1789-90). By 1795, Blake had produced over 125 copies of the 168
 surviving copies of illuminated books.
		  <note type="foot" id="I.2">This total omits the works of one plate,
 <title level="m">On Homers Poetry</title> and <title level="m">Laocoön</title>,
 and two plates, <title level="m">The Ghost of Abel</title>.</note></p><p>Clearly, six months was a lot of time to devote to an illuminated
 book. Of the 111 engravings that Blake had produced between 1789 and 1795, he
 had executed 80 between 1790 and 1793, which suggests that he concentrated on
 illuminated printing during 1789-90 and 1793-95, intervals that correspond
 exactly with the books dates, and that he underwrote the cost of his
 original productions with his commercial work. From one medium-sized engraving,
 Blake could earn L15-30 (E 703) or as much as L80 (<title level="m">BR</title>
 569). Had he sold his entire stock of illuminated books at their initial
 prices, he would have made less than L50, barely enough to pay for the copper
 and paper, let alone his labor (Bentley, Price of Experience
 628-29). By 1795, with a stock of illuminated books, he began to redirect his
 considerable energies toward other projects. These included twelve large
 color-print drawings, 537 watercolor illustrations to Edward Youngs
 <title level="m">Night Thoughts</title>, 43 of which he engraved, 117
 illustrations to Grays <title level="m">Poems</title>, the
 <title level="m">Four Zoas</title> manuscript, and a series of tempera paintings
 for Butts. The 1790s were his most successful period financially, not from the
 sale of illuminated books but from the steady employment by the book and print
 publishers and his patron. After the intense early periods of illuminated
 printing, the books never again commanded center stage in his life; even the
 150 plates of the major prophecies <title level="m">Milton</title> (c. 1811) and
 <title level="m">Jerusalem</title> (c. 1820) were written and etched over many
 years consistent with his other Work.</p><p>In 1800 the Blakes left London to spend three years in Felpham. On
 their return they took a first-floor apartment in South Molton Street. Their
 living quarters became smaller with each move, more suitable for engraving and
 painting than printing. At Felpham, Blake may have printed a few separate
 copies of <title level="m">Innocence</title> and <title level="m">Experience</title>; at South Molton Street, he wrote and printed
 <title level="m">Milton</title> and <title level="m">Jerusalem</title>, probably
 revised <title level="m">For Children</title>, and reprinted nine other
 illuminated booksabout 29 copies altogether. These were the years of
 Blakes 1809 exhibition, illustrations to Blairs <title level="m">Grave</title>, illustrations to Milton, most of the Bible
 illustrations, and the Canterbury Pilgrims engraving. By contrast, when
 Cumberland wrote him at Fountain Court, he had etched only three illuminated
 plates, for <title level="m">On Homers Poetry</title> (c. 1822) and
 <title level="m">The Ghost of Abel</title> (1822), and had printed only four
 copies of <title level="m">Songs</title> (Copies W and Y in 1825, Z and AA in
 1826). But, as implied in his letter to Cumberland, he remained as busy as
 ever. </p><p>Blake had been illustrating Dantes <title level="m">Divine
 Comedy</title> for over two years. <ptr target="d1.13"/><ptr target="d1.14"/> When he wrote Cumberland, he had 102 designs and was
 engraving seven of them. As he told Linnell, I am too much attachd to
 Dante to think much of any thing elseI have Proved the Six Plates &amp;
 reduced the Fighting Devils ready for the Copper I count myself sufficiently
 Paid If I live as I now do (letter of 25 April 1827, E 784). The other
 work was a copy of <title level="m">Marriage</title> (I) and one of
 <title level="m">Songs</title> (X), the Set of the Songs he was
 now Printing. Both were highly finished in gold, watercolors, and
 pen and ink. His very last book, though, was uncolored Copy F of
 <title level="m">Jerusalem</title>, a commission secured by Linnell a few weeks
 after he wrote Cumberland. Its 100 Plates did not, however, sell
 for Twenty Guineas; Blake completed it on his deathbed, and its £5.5s.
 sale price helped to pay for his burial.
		  <note type="foot" id="I.3">Blake died of liver failure; for a possible connection
 between that and chronic copper intoxication, see Viscomi and Robson, Blakes
 Death.</note></p><p>Three books in six months. Printing illuminated books was still
 possible, but more difficult than before because they demanded greater artistic
 attention, disrupted other work, and required more space. The place they
 occupied in Blakes life had changed. How different things had been with
 a whole House to range in, where he could spread out and move
 through the stages of illuminated printing, from preparing plates and designing
 pages, to etching and printing designs, to coloring and collating impressions,
 as though moving through the six days of creationor the six chambers
 of the Printing house in Hell (<title level="m">MHH</title> 15, E
 40).</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d2"><head>New Printing Technologies</head><p>Fifteen of Blakes 19 illuminated works were executed in a
 relief-etching technique he had invented in 1788. In his prospectus of 1793 he
 called it Illuminated Printing and announced that he had
 invented a method of Printing both Letter-press and Engraving in a style
 more ornamental, uniform, and grand, than any before discovered, while it
 produces works at less than one fourth of the expense; he defined it as
 a method of Printing which combines the Painter and the Poet
 (Prospectus, E 692-93). Though he never explained the technique, he did
 describe his infernal method as melting apparent surfaces
 away, and displaying the infinite which was hid (<title level="m">MHH
</title> 14, E 39). In a Printing house in Hell, he saw the
 method in which knowledge is transmitted from generation to generation,
 and allegorized its major stages as fantastic acts in six chambers, where a
 cave, symbolizing the copper plate, was made
 infinite and cast into the expanse
 (<title level="m">MHH</title> 15, E 40). </p><p>In practice, Blake wrote texts and drew illustrations with pens and
 brushes on copper plates in acid-resistant ink and, with nitric acid, etched
 away the unprotected metal to bring the composite design into printable relief.
 He printed the plates in colored inks on a rolling press and tinted most
 impressions in watercolors. While the combination of word and image is a
 prominent feature of illuminated printing, it appears not to have been the
 impetus for the invention. He credited the method to a vision of his recently
 deceased brother Robert, and first used it for <title level="m">The Approach
 of Doom</title> (Viscomi, <title level="m">Idea</title> 172; see also Essick,
 <title level="m">Separate Plates</title>, III), a print in imitation of Roberts
 wash drawing. <ptr target="d2.1"/><ptr target="d2.2"/> The first works to incorporate text were
 <title level="m">All Religions are One</title> and <title level="m">No Natural
 Religion</title>, small philosophical tractates on perception and the
 Poetic Genius. The following year he used the technique to
 publish poetry, beginning with <title level="m">Innocence</title> and
 <title level="m">Thel</title>.</p><p>Illuminated printing was not mysterious, complex, or difficult. The
 pens, brushes, and liquid medium enabled Blake to design directly on copper
 plates as though he were drawing on paper, which in turn encouraged him to
 integrate text and illustration on the same page. Technically, such integration
 was possible in conventional (intaglio) etching (as in <title level="m">Ahania</title>), but the economics of publishing had long defined
 etching as image reproduction and letterpress as text reproduction, so that the
 conventional illustrated book was the product of much divided labor, with
 illustrations produced and printed in one medium and shop and separately
 inserted into leaves printed elsewhere in letterpress on a different kind of
 press. Even when words and images were brought together on the same leaf,
 divisions in production were maintained.</p><p>Whether Blake used relief or intaglio, as author illustrating and
 printing himself, he would have united the various stages of book production,
 obtaining control over the production of his illustrated text the same way he
 did as a graphic artist over his own images. The tools of drawing and
 sketching, though, freed him to think in new ways, to unite invention and
 execution in ways defeated by conventional printmaking. Moreover, the idea that
 an artists first and spontaneous thoughts are most valuable because they
 are closest to the original creative spark, often obliterated by high
 finishing, had become very popular in the late eighteenth century, creating a
 taste for drawings and sketches and motivating printmakers to invent techniques
 to reproduce them in facsimile and to simulate their various textures (e.g.,
 chalk, crayon, pen and wash; see <ptr target="d2.3"/><ptr target="d2.4"/><ptr target="d2.5"/><ptr target="d2.6"/><ptr target="d2.7"/><ptr target="d2.8"/><ptr target="d2.9"/><ptr target="d2.10"/><ptr target="d2.11"/><ptr target="d2.12"/>. Such prints, however, were carefully executed with
 needles, roulettes (a textured wheel used to roughen the plates surface
 to produce tonalities), and other metal tools, their spontaneity a crafted
 illusion. Blake, on the other hand, by actually using the tools and techniques
 of writing and drawing, had solved the technical problem of reproducing pen and
 brush marks in metal. He created a multi-media site where poetry, painting, and
 printmaking came together in ways both original and characteristic of
 Romanticisms fascination with spontaneity and the idea of the
 sketch.
		  <note type="foot" id="I.4">For the origins of illuminated printing, see Viscomi,
 <title level="m">Blake and the Idea of the Book</title>, chapters 4 and
 18.</note></p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d3"><head>Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</head><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">In the first chamber was a Dragon-Man, clearing
	away the rubbish from a caves mouth; within, a number of Dragons were hollowing
	the cave</hi></q></cit></epigraph><p>No printmaker before Blake had incorporated the tools and techniques
 of writing, drawing, and painting in a graphic medium, though the materials and
 tools were commonplace. The varnishes, acid, inks, dabbers, brushes, quills,
 oils, colors, and paper were in every engravers workshopalong
 with the main ingredient, the copper plate. Plates were purchased from
 coppersmiths, usually cut to size. Because intaglio etchings and engravings had
 to be printed with pressure great enough to force paper into the incised lines,
 which resulted in a platemark or embossment that revealed the plates
 shape, engravers neatly squared the plate and bevelled the sides to prevent
 them from cutting the paper. For relief etching, Blake cut small plates out of
 larger sheets himself, cutting them roughly equal size but not uniformly, using
 either a hammer and chisel or scoring the sheet deeply with a burin and
 snapping it between boards <ptr target="d3.1"/>. Because he printed from raised surfaces rather than
 incised lines, he used less pressure and avoided pronounced platemarks, and
 consequently he dispersed with squaring and bevelling. Equally unorthodox, he
 etched both sides of plates (e.g., <title level="m">Experience</title>,
 <title level="m">Europe</title>, and <title level="m">Urizen</title> were etched
 on the backs of <title level="m">Innocence</title>, <title level="m">America</title>, and <title level="m">Marriage</title> plates).
 Cutting the cost of copper, his most expensive material, the
 verso books were the only ones to turn a profit at the time
 (Bentley, <title level="a">Price of Experience</title> 635).</p><p>Blake prepared plates for relief etching as he did for intaglio
 etching. He planed plates on an anvil with a hammer (the tools of Los in
 Blakes mythology), and then, with water, oil, and various grinding
 stones, polished the surface to a mirror-like finish <ptr target="d3.2"/><ptr target="d3.3"/><ptr target="d3.4"/>. Polishing made plates easier to cut with burins or
 needles and easier to wipe clean of ink, but it deposited a greasy film that
 had to be removed, otherwise either the etching ground or Blakes ink would
 have adhered to the film rather than metal and could have flaked from the plate
 in the acid bath <ptr target="d3.5"/>. Because relief etchings required a long bite in strong
 acid, thorough and correct degreasing with chalk or breadcrumbs
 was of the utmost importance<ptr target="d3.6"/><ptr target="d3.7"/>.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d4"><head>Chamber Two: Executing the Design</head><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">In the second chamber was a Viper folding round
	the rock &amp; the cave, and others adorning it with gold, silver and precious
	stones</hi></q></cit></epigraph><p>In intaglio etching, Blake melted a ball of ground consisting of wax
 and resins and spread it over a warm degreased plate <ptr target="d4.1"/><ptr target="d4.2"/><ptr target="d4.3"/>. He smoked the ground to darken and harden it, transferred
 the design onto it, and cut through the design with a needle <ptr target="d4.4"/><ptr target="d4.5"/><ptr target="d4.6"/><ptr target="d4.7"/><ptr target="d4.8"/><ptr target="d4.9"/>. The metal thus exposed was bitten below the surface with
 acid. In relief etching, though, he drew the design directly on a clean copper
 plate with pens and brushes using a liquid medium. Like the etching ground,
 this medium had to be acid resistant but it also had to flow easily, adhere
 when dry, not spread or blot on the plate, and be usable in pens and brushes.
 In short, it had to behave like writing ink. Linnell identified Blakes
 impervious liquid (<title level="m">BR</title> 460n1) as being the
 usual stop-out varnish that etchers used to paint over lines sufficiently
 etched to stop the acid from biting them deeper <ptr target="d4.10"/>. By stopping out lines and biting plates in successive
 stages, etchers varied the depth and width of linesmuch as engravers did
 by cutting them deeper with their diamond-shaped burins. Varying the amount of
 ink that lines held altered their tone, making possible the modeling of forms
 and the illusion of aerial perspective.</p><p>Blake did not invent his writing medium; he merely adapted one of
 the brown asphaltum-based stop-out varnishes. With plate, acid-resistant
 ink, pens, and brushes, he entered the second chamber and, like
a Viper folding round the rock &amp; the cave, he rewrote his text, first
 drafted on paper, and illustrated it in a sinuous, calligraphic hand <ptr target="d4.11"/><ptr target="d4.12"/>. By cutting into broad areas painted in stop-out, he
 created fine white and black parallel lines <ptr target="d4.13"/>; by cutting the nib of his quill, he varied the strokes of
 his letters.</p><p>Because the printed image mirrors the plate image, Blake rewrote his
 text backwards, an art his friends acknowledged he
 excel[led] in (<title level="m">BR</title> 212n1)and which
 he pictures himself doing in Jerusalem plate 37 <ptr target="d4.14"/>. He usually started with text and illustrated around it,
 visually composing the page design while executing it <ptr target="d4.15"/>. How different this was from the way he worked as an
 etcher and engraverfrom all etchers and engraverseven when
 executing original designs. Their methods and objectives prevented designing
 directly in the metal; the image they reproduced was first worked up on paper
 and then transferred to the plate as a guide for the needle. Likewise, the
 engraver needed the lightly etched outline because the burin cuts rather than
 draws lines, translating them into three-dimensional lines of varying depth and
 width. But the methods used by engravers to transfer designs did not work in
 relief etching, and there was no technical need for Blake to transfer the page
 design or any of its parts, since he was engaged neither in cutting it into the
 plate nor in translating it into different kinds of lines. The tools and
 Blakes twenty years of drawing experience enabled him to design his
 pages as he rewrote his texts on the plates, as though creating an illuminated
 manuscript.</p><p>No illuminated designs that might have been transferred or even
 redrawn are extant, nor are there any mockups of designs except for two roughly
 composed, textless pencil sketches for <title level="m">Thel</title> plates 6
 and 7 <ptr target="d4.16"/>, and both differ considerably from the printed designs 
 <ptr target="d4.17"/>. Blake realized very early that his new mediums
 autographic nature made the poem the only prerequisite for executing plates,
 that rewriting texts was also an act of visual invention, and thus that the
 medium could be used for production rather than reproduction. With no designs
 to transfer or reproduce, the placement and extent of text, letter size, line
 spacing, as well as placement and extent of illustration, were invented only
 during execution.
 <note type="foot" id="I.5">After 1800, Blake invented two variations on relief
	etching (E 694). These required outlines to be transferred on etching grounds
	and the whites scraped or scratched through with oval and pointed
	needles to create images loosely resembling woodcuts or wood engravings (e.g.,
	<title level="m">Jerusalem</title> plates 14 and 33). Accompanying text was
	still written backwards and the page designed when executed. </note> This
 method of designing meant that Blake did not know what lines or stanza would go
 on what plate, or how many plates a poem/book would need. Working without
 models allowed each illuminated print and book to evolve through its production
 in ways impossible in conventional book making. Blake could begin working on a
 book before it was completely written.
<note type="foot" id="I.6">See Viscomi, The Evolution of William Blakes
 <title level="m">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>.</note></p><p>While writing backwards was not difficult, mastering the
 ink and giving small letters the proper slant were, at least
 initially. Blake could dip brushes directly in the ink, but probably loaded the
 quill pens used for text with a small brush, a method illuminators used to keep
 quills from clogging <ptr target="d4.11"/>. And like illuminators of manuscripts, he may have slanted
 his plates to keep his quill as horizontal as possible. Blake could write texts
 in roman or italic letteringhe used both in <title level="m">No
 Natural Religion</title>but he quickly favored the latter, which was easier
 to write and, with fewer letter ends to coordinate, to keep straight and
 uniform. Italic script also facilitated the next stage: with fewer letter ends
 exposed to acid, words were better protected against problems caused by the
 acid pitting and lifting the ground. Tight designs also exemplified
 Blakes thinking in terms of his medium: to be printable, they do not
 need to be bitten as deeply as designs with open spaces, and thus require less
 time in acid. Their dense line systems also facilitated inking by keeping the
 ink dabber on the surface and clear of the shallows, the areas bitten below
 the surface meant to print white.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d5"><head>Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</head><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">In the third chamber was an Eagle with wings
	and feathers of air, he caused the inside of the cave to be infinite, around
	were numbers of Eagle like men, who built palaces in the immense
	cliffs</hi></q></cit></epigraph><p>Blake had to etch accurately to retain the autographic quality of
 his designs. The acidor aquafortiscommonly employed
 in his day was diluted nitric. Acid is unpredictable, affected by age,
 temperature, humidity, and the metals purityespecially in relief
 etching, because the large amount of exposed metal heats it and makes it bite
 more viciously. Such corrosives may be salutary and
 medicinal…in Hell (<title level="m">MHH</title> 14, E 39), but on
 earth they emit noxious orange fumes and require good ventilation. Blake
 embedded the plates edges in strips of wax to create a self-contained
 tray and poured the acid about a quarter inch deep <ptr target="d5.10"/>
 . He watched it turn blue and gas bubbles form along the
 designmore bubbles than he had ever seen before, signs of trouble 
 <ptr target="d5.2"/><ptr target="d5.11"/>. He passed a featherthe conventional tool to
 agitate the acidover the design 
 <ptr target="d5.12"/><ptr target="d5.13"/>
, doing so every few minutes as bubbles began to reform, to
 keep the acid from undercutting or lifting the design: an Eagle with
 wings and feathers of air…caused the inside of the cave to be
 infinite. Looking down on the flat, dark-brown design on reddish copper
 in its cloudy blue-tinted bath, he was like Rintrah, shaking his fires
 in the burdend air, watching hungry clouds swag on the
 deep (<title level="m">MHH</title> 2, E 33). Indeed, he was the Spirit of
 God that was upon the face of the deep…divid[ing] the light from the
 darkness (Gen. 1.1-4).</p><p>Hours, not days, later, unetched surfaces were divided from shallows
 and a relief plate was created. Like a god brooding over
 creationpictured on <title level="m">Marriage</title> plate 14Blake was Melting
 apparent surfaces away, and displaying the infinite which was hid (E
 39). Displayed, of course, was the composite design now visible in relief,
 metaphorically materialized as immense cliffs large enough to
 house palaces built by Eagle like men, assistants
 in the image and likeness of the Eagle, as signs of their
 dominion (Gen. 1.26). The cliffs and valleys of this small copper
 plate were indeed a minute particular manifesting Creation itself.</p><p>Under the watchful eyes of Blake or his trusted devil,
 or printers assistant, his wife Catherine, etching could take much of
 the day, and no doubt a few plates were etched at the same timebut not
 in one long continuous bite of the acid. In intaglio etching, he stopped out
 selected areas and etched the plate in successive stages to vary line depth and
 tone <ptr target="d5.4"/><ptr target="d5.5"/><ptr target="d5.6"/><ptr target="d5.7"/><ptr target="d5.8"/><ptr target="d5.9"/>
. But relief lines are all on the same level and thus
 receive equal amounts of ink; like woodcuts, they are essentially
 two-dimensional, boldly contrasting black and white forms incapable of
 producing tonal gradation. Nevertheless, Blake stopped out his plates at least
 once. (A two-stage etch is indicated by steps around the relief plateaus of
 Blakes only surviving relief-etched copperplate, a fragment from a
 rejected <title level="m">America</title> plate. <ptr target="d5.18"/> After 45 to 90
 minutes of etching, his design was in slight relief. He poured off the acid,
 dried the plate, and then carefully painted over words with stop out to protect
 details from lifting during a longer second bite, which was necessary to deepen
 the areas around words and lines. <ptr target="d5.14"/><ptr target="d5.15"/> Only if the ink started to
 lift would there be additional stopping out.</p><p>A long day, but at the end, a printable image was created many times
 more quickly than by engraving, where a square inch of close crosshatching
 could take a full day or more. After etching the design into printable relief,
 pouring off the acid, and removing the wax walls <ptr target="d5.16"/>, Blake erased the
 ink with turpentine and polished the plate <ptr target="d5.17"/>
). He was now ready to
 make printing ink.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d6"><head>Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</head><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">In the fourth chamber were Lions of flaming
	fire raging around &amp; melting the metals into living fluids.</hi></q></cit></epigraph><p>Ink for relief and intaglio printing was made by grinding powdered
 pigment with different grades of walnut or linseed oil. <ptr target="d6.1"/><ptr target="d6.2"/><ptr target="d6.3"/> Intaglio
 ink is tackier and stiffer <ptr target="d6.4"/> than relief because it must stay in
 incised lines when the plates surface is wiped clean <ptr target="d6.5"/><ptr target="d6.6"/><ptr target="d6.7"/> and
 requires more pressure to transfer evenly. Nevertheless, Blake used it to print
 relief plates, as is evinced by the slightly reticulated surfaces of his
 prints, especially noticeable in solid areas. He inked plates on the intaglio
 printers conventional charcoal brazier, whose low heat made stiff ink
 thinner and more fluid and thus easier to manipulate and spread. Like a
 Lion[] of flaming fire raging around &amp; melting the metals into
 living fluids, he spread glistening, warm ink with a linen dabber,
 moving its slightly convex bottom across the plates surface and off the
 shallows. <ptr target="d6.8"/><ptr target="d6.9"/> Plates with wide shallows he inked locally with small
 dabbers or brushes. Even so, inking relief plates was quicker than intaglio
 plates, which required a two-step process of rubbing ink into the lines and
 wiping the surface clean with rags and the palm of the hand. <ptr target="d6.5"/><ptr target="d6.6"/><ptr target="d6.7"/></p><p>Blake wiped the ink from any relief surfaces he did not wish to
 print. He routinely wiped the thin line bordering the plate created by the wax
 dike used to hold the acid. <ptr target="d6.10"/> The borders formed part of the
 plates relief line system and acted as runners for the dabber. Wiping
 them was similar to wiping the bevelled edges of intaglio plates to prevent
 them from blemishing the platemark. The result, however, was very different.
 Platemarks, clean or not, always reveal a plates shape and hence the
 images origin and medium. Because relief etchings produce no pronounced
 platemark, wiping the borders erased overt signs of the graphic medium. The
 unframed text and image looked written and drawn rather than printed, a unique
 rather than a repeatable image, an illusion further enhanced by colored inks
 and watercolor finishing.</p><p>The books were Printed in Colours (Prospectus, E 693). The first
 printing of <title level="m">Thel</title>, for example, yielded thirteen
 (surviving) copies in five different colors. Changing inks during a print run
 diversified stock but also required more time, but it was not as labor
 intensive as color printing, in which a few thick opaque colors were applied to
 the plates surfaces and shallows, sometimes heavily, sometimes lightly,
 and printed with the inked design. Blake had adapted the <hi rend="italic">á
 la poupée</hi> technique English printers used for color printing, and used it
 for nearly everything he printed in 1794-95.
 <note type="foot" id="I.7">French printers favored the multi-plate mode of color
	printing: a key plate prints the outline and separate plates, registered
	exactly onto the key plate, carry one or more colors. For a detailed
	examination of Blakes color printing method and others of his day, see
	Essick and Viscomi, Inquiry and Blakes
	Method.</note> In effect, he painted plates with small dabbers (<hi rend="italic">poupées</hi>)
 to produce opaque colors and textures resembling oil sketches <ptr target="d6.11"/><ptr target="d6.12"/>),
 which he enriched and finished in watercolors and pen and ink. <ptr target="d6.13"/> In
 1795, he brilliantly extended color printing more fully into painting,
 executing 12 Large Prints…Printed in Colours…unaccompanied by any
 writing. <ptr target="d6.14"/> He rarely used the technique for books after that, though
 in 1796 he created the Large and Small Books of Designs for, appropriately
 enough, a miniaturist painter, by color printing a selection of plates from
 the different Books of such as could be Printed without the Writing (letter of
 9 June 1818, E 771).</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d7"><head>Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</head><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">In the fifth chamber were Unnamd forms,
	which cast the metals into the expanse.</hi></q></cit></epigraph><p>From the inking station, Blake went to the press, where he again met
 Mrs. Blake, his printing devil. Simultaneously the dirtiest and
 cleanest of arts, involving oily inks and pristine paper, printing was best
 performed by two people. Printers, though, went unnamed in inscriptions on
 reproductive prints, which recorded date, title, artist, publisher, and
 engraver. Blake signed most illuminated works Author &amp; Printer W.
 Blake or Printed by W. Blake, taking pride in his manual as well as
 mental labor. The fifth chambers unpictureable image also puns on
 form, which is type set into pages in a metal frame for printing.
 Cast, another printing pun, refers to a stereotype (a solid body of type), as
 well as to the mold in which molten metals are poured; here, the mold shaping
 the living…metals is the expanse of blank
 sheets of paper, which now embody the relief plates immense cliffs,
 valleys, and palaces.</p><p>Blake printed on the most beautiful wove paper that could be
 procured (Prospectus, E 693)the kind used by engravers. And he
 prepared it as a printmaker rather than a book printer, tearing large sheets of
 paper into quarters, eights, or twelves, instead of printing the sheet and then
 folding it into pages. Depending on the size of the sheet and how he cut it,
 the resulting leaves were basically big, medium, and small, or, according to
 Blake, folio, quarto, and octavo,
 because they roughly corresponded with those standard book sizes (he advertised
 <title level="m">Songs</title>, for example, as octavo). Like all
 intaglio and relief printers of the day, he dampened the paper for printing.
 <ptr target="d7.1"/></p><p>Blake had taught his wife how to print, draw, and color, and was
 especially proud of her printing abilities. She proofed and printed both his
 relief and intaglio plates (<title level="m">BR</title> 459; <ptr target="d7.2"/><ptr target="d7.3"/>). For
 relief plates, they decreased the pressure on their rolling press (a machine
 with two large cylinders between which a board passes when the top cylinder is
 turned) by slightly raising the roller and probably removing one of three felt
 blankets placed between plate and roller. Blake laid the inked plate on the bed
 of the press, face up. Mrs. Blake held top and bottom of a damp sheet of paper
 and lowered it onto the plate, being careful not to let it sag in the middle
 and touch the ink, or to move it once it touched the plate, otherwise some
 lines would print double or slightly out of focus. She covered the leaf
 registered to the plate with a backing sheet and blankets and turned the
 presss handle to pull the bed smoothly between two heavy rollers. <ptr target="d7.4"/> After the marriage of inked plate and paper, she removed the
 printed impression <ptr target="d7.5"/> to dry and brought another leaf to the press as
 Blake brought another plate, returning the printed plate to the brazier to be
 reinked.</p><p>Printing impressions without pronounced platemarks meant Blake could
 print on both sides of leaves to create facing pages. This conventional book
 format used less paper, which was Blakes largest expense other than
 metal, but could present difficulties. Mrs. Blake registered the clean side of
 the paper just printed onto the newly inked plate, and covered the printed side
 with a stiff backing sheet or thin metal plate (which she could wipe of offset
 ink and reuse). Offset was minimal, as in letterpress printing, because the ink
 was slightly pressed into the paper, and thus below the surface. Alternatively,
 Blake could print a stack of leaves and then print the versos (kept damp) once
 the ink was dry to the touch. In 1794, when Blake began color printing his
 plates <ptr target="d7.6"/>
), he also began routinely printing on only one side of the
 paper, which, though easier, changed the dynamic between book and reader: with
 no competing image, the solo design dominated the page spread, demanding full
 attention and, in this format, came to demand more of Blake as it became
 increasingly more painterly. </p><p>By alternating plates, the Blakes kept the press in action and could
 efficiently print a dozen impressions in an hour. Printing eleven copies of an
 eleven-plate book like <title level="m">Visions</title> (121 impressions) would
 take less than two full days. Normally, they printed one plate at a time, but
 for small plates, such as <title level="m">Songs</title>, they could print two,
 each onto a separate leaf, halving their printing time. Registration of paper
 to plate was sometimes off, resulting in designs hanging low or high, slanted
 left or right. Blake did not mind; he appears to have rarely discarded
 impressions, since the quality of inking, printing, and registration varies
 within copies of books. Creating pages with uniform margins was impossible with
 plates only roughly equal in size, and given how they were cut, it is not
 likely that Blake was very exacting about registration. He did not abhor
 accidents, but saw them as part of the creative process, as revealing the
 makers hand and production process.</p><p>Hells Printing house has no chamber explicitly
 designated for coloring impressions. The infernal printmakers, however,
 incorporated ornamentation and color into the second and fourth chambers: the
 brushes illustrating text were also adorning it with gold, silver, and
 precious stones, and the living fluids of colored inks
 were inherently illuminating. Blakes 1793 prospectus does not explicitly
 state that impressions were hand colored, only that they were Printed in
 Colours. But illuminated implies coloring, specifically of
 manuscripts, and a method of Printing which combines the Painter and the Poet
 implies the same.</p><p>As with quills, inks, and varnishes, Blake made his own watercolors.
 He ground many of the same pigments used to make ink in water and gum arabic
 <ptr target="d7.8"/>
 instead of oil, and, to make the thicker, more opaque colors, in
 a thin carpenters glue, diluting the paste with water to vary the paint
 layers consistency. <ptr target="d7.9"/> In the early days, when he printed in
 earth tones (yellow ochre and raw sienna mostly), he applied broad, delicate
 washes in only a few colors, and usually left texts unwashed. <ptr target="d7.10"/> He
 printed late works in red and orange inks, bright colors that invited a more
 extensive palette and elaborate coloring <ptr target="d7.11"/>. He applied colors in thin
 washes and translucent layers with detailed brushwork, adding blues, pinks, or
 yellows behind text and often outlining texts and illustrations in pen and ink.
 The result was a beautiful, strongly linear miniature, with legibility
 sometimes compromised. </p><p>He and his wife shared the task of illuminating the prints, at least
 in the first productions, perhaps adapting the method print publishers used
 when coloring prints, with each colorist using one or two colors and then
 passing the impression to the next colorist to add another color or two. For
 some books, Blake may have finished an impression from each stack of pages as a
 model, but neither he nor Mrs. Blake copied the other exactly. Making each
 impression exactly repeatable (as one would expect of books and prints) was not
 really possible when working by hand with an assistant. While each copy
 produced was a unique work of art, most impressions printed and colored at the
 same time do not differ very much; they share printing style, colors, coloring
 style, and even placement of colors. Making each impression <hi rend="italic">very</hi> different would have required more labor and time,
 and, given the objective of producing multiple copies of books at less than
 one fourth of the expense, would have been inefficient. Books printed in
 different periods, though, were also printed and colored in different styles
 and are visually very different. Overt differences among copies, in other
 words, usually reveal different periods and styles of production and not
 revision of the particular work.</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d8"><head>Chamber Six: Prints into Books</head><epigraph><cit><q><hi rend="italic">There they were recievd by Men who
	occupied the sixth chamber, and took the forms of books &amp; were arranged in
	libraries</hi></q></cit></epigraph><p>The sixth chamber conflates two actions, collating leaves to form
 copies of books and distributing them. It also implicitly questions the
 receptionand perceptionof the book.</p><p>Like other book publishers of the day, the Blakes knew purchasers
 would have their books professionally bound. They merely fastened the leaves
 between two sheets of laid paper by tying string through three or more stab
 holes. <ptr target="d8.1"/><ptr target="d8.2"/> They varied the plate order for many of the early books,
 most notably for <title level="m">Songs</title> and <title level="m">Urizen</title>. And like the publishers, they warehoused or
 arranged their copies in the printing house. But the sixth
 chamber is also <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> the printing house, in the
 expanse into which the metals were cast. The expanse is, ironically, the
 private space defined by the blank paper in the studio, but it is also the
 public space occupied by that paper as it moves from production to reception.
 After its gloriously sublime journey, touched by Dragons, Vipers, Eagles,
 Lions, Unnamd forms, and now Men, the illuminated print shelved in a
 library seems anticlimactic. But is it? As a cast of the original plate, it
 extends Hells Printing house to the place of reading. Do the fires of
 hell…look like torment and insanity or an immense world of
 delight? Is the reader an Angel…whose works are only
 Analytics, or an Angel, who is now become a Devil, reading in the
 infernal or diabolical sense (<title level="m">MHH</title> 6, 7,
 20, 24, E 35, 42, 44)? Does the reader participate in or resist the creative
 process embodied in the book?</p><p>In 1795, Blake produced a deluxe set of the books on large paper,
 possibly to display at the shop of his friend and sometimes employer, the
 publisher Joseph Johnson. Blake had by this time printed and colored with Mrs.
 Blake about 125 copies of his illuminated books in small editions very much on
 his own terms: No Subscriptions for the numerous great works now in hand are
 asked, for none are wanted; but the Author will produce his works, and offer
 them to sale at a fair price (Prospectus, E 693). Except for
 <title level="m">Songs</title>, most copies of illuminated books executed by
 1795 were also printed by 1795: fourteen of the sixteen extant copies of
 <title level="m">Thel</title>; seven of the nine copies of  <title level="m">Marriage</title>; fourteen of seventeen copies of
 <title level="m">Visions</title>, twelve of fourteen copies of
 <title level="m">America</title>; eight of the nine copies of <title level="m">Europe</title>; seven of the eight copies of  <title level="m">Urizen</title>; unique copies of <title level="m">The Book of
 Los</title> and <title level="m">Ahania</title>, and the six copies of
 <title level="m">The Song of Los</title>.</p><p>For years he relied on stock, which, for <title level="m">Songs</title>, his most popular work, lasted till around 1802, when
 he reprinted a few copies of <title level="m">Innocence</title> and
 <title level="m">Experience</title>, adding a few more in 1804 or 1805. One from
 the latter printing (Q) he sold to the Rev. Joseph Thomas, who paid ten
 guineas (10 pounds, 10 shillings)the price Blake feared in 1827
 he could scarce expect to get from a Strangeras a way of giving
 this proud artist a monetary gift. This was far more than Blake had ever
 received for an illuminated book, and for such a sum he
 could hardly do enough, finishing the plates like miniatures
 (Gilchrist, I.124). Indeed, Blakes fair price for the
 <title level="m">Songs</title> was originally 6 shillings, 6 pence (Prospectus,
 E 693). Initially, all his books were sold in shillings, not pounds, priced as
 poetry rather than as colored prints or small paintings. The following year, in
 1806, when Butts requested a copy, Blakes stock of <title level="m">Songs</title> was again depleted, so he created Copy E by salvaging
 poorly printed impressions from various 1789, 1794, and 1795 printings of
 <title level="m">Innocence</title> and <title level="m">Experience</title> still
 in the studio, recoloring them and strengthening text and designs in pen and
 ink. A lot of work but easier than making ink and colors, preparing paper and
 press, inking plates and printing, which were not worth doing for just one copy
 of one bookor, at that time, even for a complete set of books.</p><p>In December 1808, Cumberland wrote on behalf of a friend who
 was so charmed with Blakes incomparable etchings…that he requested…a compleat Set of all you have published in the way
 of <hi rend="italic">Books</hi> coloured as mine are. If none were
 to be had, he was willing to wait your own time in order
 to have them as those of mine are (<title level="m">BR</title> 211).
 Blake refused this generous offer, fearing to disrupt his present
 course of Designing &amp; Painting:  
		  <q rend="block">I am very much obliged by your kind ardour in my cause
 &amp; should immediately Engage in reviving my former pursuits of printing if I
 had not now so long been turned out of the old channel into a new one that it
 is impossible for me to return to it without destroying my present course New
 Vanities or rather new pleasures occupy my thoughts New profits seem to arise
 before me so tempting that I have already involved myself in engagements that
 preclude all possibility of promising any thing…my time…in future
 must alone be devoted to Designing &amp; Painting. (letter of 19 December 1808,
 E 769-70)</q></p><p>Blake was working on his 1809 exhibition, which netted a scurrilous
 review but no profits. For the next decade, with his stock of books depleted,
 Blake continued to work primarily as a painter and engraver, executing temperas
 (what he called fresco), illustrating Miltons major poems,
 and engraving designs after Flaxman. He finished his <title level="m">Milton</title>, printing three copies about 1811, and he continued
 to etch plates for <title level="m">Jerusalem</title>though, according to
 Cumberland, he had already etched 60 Plates of a new Prophecy by
 summer 1807 (<title level="m">BR</title> 187).</p><p>Only fourteen copies of four books (<title level="m">Innocence</title>, <title level="m">Experience</title>,
 <title level="m">America</title>, and <title level="m">Milton</title>) were
 produced between ca. 1796 and 1818, which means that most illuminated books lay
 untouched for over twenty years. Blake did not replenish his stock until around
 1818, motivated possibly by Linnell, whom he met that summer, and/or an inquiry
 about the books from Dawson Turner. He sent Turner a list of eight books (<title level="m">Innocence</title> and <title level="m">Experience</title> were still
 listed separately) and 12 Large Prints that he was willing to reprint and
 their prices, telling him that any Person wishing to have any or all of them
 should send me their Order to Print them on the above terms &amp; I will take
 care that they shall be done at least as well as any I have yet Produced
 (letter of 9 June 1818, E 771). For the first time since 1795, he printed
 copies of <title level="m">Thel</title> (N, O), <title level="m">Marriage</title>
 (G), <title level="m">Visions</title> (N, O, P), and <title level="m">Urizen</title> (G), along with <title level="m">Milton</title> (D)
 and <title level="m">Songs</title> (U, T), all in the same orange-red ink,
 paper, and coloring style. Of these, only <title level="m">Marriage</title>,
 which he did not include in the list for Turner, and <title level="m">Songs</title> would he print again. 
 <note type="foot" id="I.8">There are no surviving post-1795 copies of
	<title level="m">All Religions</title>, <title level="m">No Natural
	Religion</title>, <title level="m">Book of Los</title>, <title level="m">Ahania</title>, or <title level="m">Song of Los</title>.</note> Nor
 did he list <title level="m">Jerusalem</title>, which was still in progress and
 not printed till c. 1820, in three copies in black ink, one of which Linnell
 purchased. He did list <title level="m">America</title> and <title level="m">Europe</title>, but did not print them till 1821, when he produced
 matching copies (O and K, respectively) for Linnell and began printing and
 coloring <title level="m">Jerusalem</title> Copy E in the same style. </p><p>The books he offered to Cumberland in 1827 were the same as those he
 had offered Turner (minus <title level="m">Milton</title> and with
 <title level="m">Innocence</title> and <title level="m">Experience</title>
 combined), and the prices were L1-2 higher. Though nothing on the list was
 printed, he wasconsistent with [his] other Work printing copies
 of <title level="m">Songs</title> and <title level="m">Marriage</title> (again,
 conspicuously missing from his list), and ended his days printing a copy of
 <title level="m">Jerusalem</title>. When he said he had none remaining of all
 that [he] had Printed, he meant it. He had even sold his personal copies:
 Songs Copy R (the model for the plate order of the last seven copies), printed
 ca. 1795, to Linnell in 1819, for L1.19.6 (more than four pounds less than he
 offered <title level="m">Songs</title> to Turner) and <title level="m">Marriage</title> Copy H, printed in 1790, to Linnell in 1821, for
 £2.2s. (less than half the then price of <title level="m">Urizen</title>which was etched on its versos). As with
 <title level="m">Songs</title> Copy E, he reworked both books before selling
 them. For <title level="m">Songs</title> Copy R, he added wide frames around
 each image and strengthened the coloring. For <title level="m">Marriage</title>
 Copy H, initially uncolored but printed in various red, olive, and green inks
 on both sides of the leaves, Blake elaborately colored the pages, adding gold
 leaf and, what is most unusual, going over the texts in various colored inks,
 word by word. </p><p>When he died, Blake had the only complete colored copy of
 <title level="m">Jerusalem</title> (E), which he feared would not find a
 Customer, and <title level="m">Songs</title> Copy W. His wife inherited both
 but could sell only the Songs. All of Blakes illuminated plates, prints,
 drawings, and manuscripts ended up in the hands of Frederick Tatham, one of the
 young artists who gathered around Blake in the last years of his life. In the
 1830s, Tatham printed uncolored copies of <title level="m">Songs</title>,
 <title level="m">America</title>, <title level="m">Europe</title>, and
 <title level="m">Jerusalem</title> from Blakes plates. The plates disappeared
 while in Tathams possession, reputedly sold for scrap metal (BR 417n3).</p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d9"><head>Conclusion</head><p>From the perspective of book publishing, Blakes illuminated books
 were produced as fine limited editions. They were not invented to
 secure financial independence, and they didnt. And though Blake stated
 that his method cut production costs (primarily by his not paying for labor,
 manuscript, or design), it was a labor intensive, and not cost effective, means
 of production, mostly underwritten by his commercial work. Printing
 relief-etched plates was not difficult, but slow compared to printing books in
 the standard way. Considering how few Copies Blake could produce during the
 run, we can see why he felt that he was never…able
 to produce a Sufficient number for a general Sale by means of a regular
 Publisher, and why the books proved unprofitable enough to [him]
 tho Expensive to the Buyer. But from the perspective of an artist
 accustomed to producing unique works, illuminated books provided wider
 audiences and greater opportunities to make his reputation, which he also
 admitted to Turner: The Few I have Printed and Sold are sufficient to
 have gained me great reputation as an Artist which was the chief thing
 Intended. He also insisted, though, referring to the Large and Small Books of
 Designs, that printing illuminated plates without the Writing was
 at the Loss of some of the best things For they when Printed perfect
 accompany Poetical Personifications &amp; Acts without which Poems they never
 could have been Executed (letter of 9 June 1818, E 771).</p><p>Looking back from the last year of his life, Blake could see the
 great contrast between his early and late illuminated books. The first six
 years of production progressed through a series of three formats: leaves
 printed on both sides and lightly washed (1789-93), color printing (1794-95),
 and single-sided printing with borders and richer coloring (c. 1795). After
 1795, the format remained the same, though the coloring style continued to
 become more elaborate. Late practice differed from early in that far fewer
 copies per book were produced, various titles were produced in the same
 session, and printing sessions appear to have been motivated by at least one
 commission, which made printing other titles viable. Late copies cost far more
 than early ones. The dramatic increase in price reflects a change in
 Blakes idea of the bookfrom books of poems to series of
 hand-colored prints, from prints as pages to prints as paintings. The latter
 demanded more from him and the reader, but, early or late, his books always had
 the power to illuminate, to open eyes and convert angels into
 devils. The apocalyptic role of his infernal method
 was always clear: The whole creation will be consumed, and appear
 infinite. and holy…by an improvement of sensual enjoyment (<title level="m">MHH</title> 14, E 39)and with that, the Author is sure of
 his reward. </p></div1><div1 type="section" id="d10"><head>Works Cited</head><listbibl><bibl> Bentley, G. E., Jr. 
 <title level="m">Blake Records</title>. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
 1969. Cited as BR. </bibl><bibl> . 
 <title level="a">What is the Price of Experience: William Blake and
	the Economics of Illuminated Painting [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>
	Printing].</title><title level="j">University of Toronto Quarterly</title> 68 (1999):
 617-41. </bibl><bibl> Erdman, David V., ed. with commentary by Harold Bloom. 
 <title level="m">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
	Blake</title>. (1965) Rev. edn. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of
 California Press, 1988. Cited as E. </bibl><bibl> Essick, Robert N. 
 <title level="m">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
	Catalogue</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1983. </bibl><bibl> . 
 <title level="m">William Blake, Printmaker</title>. Princeton:
 Princeton University Press, 1980. </bibl><bibl> Essick, Robert N., and Joseph Viscomi. An Inquiry into
 Blakes Method of Color Printing. 
 <title level="m">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title> 35 (Winter
 2001/02): 73-102. &lt;www.blakequarterly.org&gt; </bibl><bibl> . Blakes Method of Color Printing: Some
 Responses and Further Observations. 
 <title level="m">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title> (Fall 2002):
 49-64. &lt;www.blakequarterly.org&gt; </bibl><bibl> Gilchrist, Alexander. 
 <title level="m">Life of William Blake</title>. 2 vols. London:
 Macmillan, 1863. </bibl><bibl> Viscomi, Joseph. 
 <title level="m">Blake and the Idea of the Book</title>. Princeton:
 Princeton University Press, 1993. </bibl><bibl> . 
 The Evolution of William Blakes <title level="m">The Marriage of
	Heaven and Hell.</title><title level="j">Huntington Library Quarterly</title> 58.3&amp;4
 (1997): 281-344. </bibl><bibl> . 
 William Blake, Illuminated Books, and the Concept of
	Difference. 
 <title level="m">Essays on Romanticism</title>. Ed. Karl Kroeber and
 Gene Ruoff. New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 1993. 63-87. </bibl><bibl> Viscomi, Joseph, and Lane Robson. 
 Blakes Death. 
 <title level="j">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title> 30 (1996):
 36-49. </bibl></listbibl></div1><div1 type="illustration"><div2 id="i1" corresp="d1"><list><head>Engraving</head><item><figure entity="illum.1.1" id="d1.1" n="1"><head>Tools of engraving</head><figdesc>The two kinds of reproductive prints in the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century were relief and intaglio. In the former, the design
	  is put into relief by cutting what is not part of the design below the surface,
	  and in the latter, designs are incised into metal plates. Woodcut, an example
	  of the former, was the first printing technique, in use by the late 14th
	  century. Engraving, invented in the 15th century, was the first of the intaglio
	  techniques. It requires gravers or burins (figs. 1, 2, C) with
	  wedge-shaped tips for gouging lines into the surface of metal plates, scrapers
	  (figs. 4, 5) to remove the metal forced up by the burin (the
	  burr), and burnishers (figs. 6, 7) to polish lines smooth. A
	  whetstone (fig. D) is used to sharpen the burins. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.2" id="d1.2" n="2"><head>Tools and materials of engraving</head><figdesc>Engravers also used a leather pad (fig. 9) upon which
	  the plate is engraved and turned, a hammer and anvil (figs. 12, 13) to plane
	  and repair plates, a tightly rolled piece of felt and oil (figs. 16, 19) for
	  polishing the plates surface, a compass (fig. 17) for measurements, and
	  calipers (fig. 18) to mark the point on the plates verso that needed to
	  be hammered up when lines on the surface had been scraped down to erase a
	  mistake. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.3" id="d1.3" n="3"><head>Holding the burin</head><figdesc>Burins are held in the palm of the hand (fig. 4) and
	  pushed into the plate and away from the body (fig. 5). To make a curved line,
	  the plate is turned on its leather pad while the burin ploughs straight. Unlike
	  drawing, writing, painting, and etching, engraving is nonautographic and a
	  skill requiring years of training. This is why most painters interested in
	  making prints learned etching, a technique in which one uses a needle like a
	  pen and thus drawing skills already acquired, rather than engraving.
	  <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.4" id="d1.4" n="4"><head>Kinds of engraved lines and their combinations</head><figdesc>Lines cut deeper into the plate will be wider, hold
	  more ink, and print darker than those cut slightly (figs. 12, 13). By varying
	  the depths and widths of lines, the engraver creates lines that taper and swell
	  (fig. 10), and by combining and hatching them in various ways (figs. 6, 7),
	  creates the illusion of tone and mass. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.5" id="d1.5" n="5"><head>Engraving in practice</head><figdesc>Engraving fine lines in the background of a recreation
	  of Blakes Marriage plate 10, executed on a zinc plate.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.6" id="d1.6" n="6"><head>Engraving and Etching</head><figdesc>The first engravers practiced pure
	  engraving: an outline of the design was transferred from paper onto a thin wax
	  ground covering the plates surface and the lines were cut directly into
	  the metal with burins. By the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, this practice had been replaced by
	  mixed method engraving, a combination of etching and engraving,
	  in which the design was first scratched through the ground with a needle and
	  bitten into the plate with acid and then finished with burins (see series of
	  illustrations demonstrating etching). </figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.7" id="d1.7" n="7"><head>“Mixed method” engraving of the 18th century</head><figdesc>Mixed-method engraving had become the economic and
	  aesthetic norms, because it greatly shortened the amount of time required to
	  produce a print and because the resulting line systems were believed (though
	  not by Blake) to be more supple, versatile, and grand than either engraving or
	  etching alone and hence superior to the works of the ancient
	  engravers. As an apprentice to James Basire, a master engraver, Blake learned
	  the arts of etching and engraving and excelled in the commercial styles then
	  popular, and though he felt spiritually aligned with the ancient engravers, he
	  did not emulate their practice until late in the last decade of his
	  life.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.8" id="d1.8" n="8"><head>Dot-and-lozenge line system</head><figdesc>The complex hatching system seen here was known as
	  dot and lozenge and came to define 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century engraving, for small book illustrations as well as
	  the larger, separately sold, reproductions of paintings, and lives today in
	  bank-note engraving. Whereas renaissance engravers had drawing as their
	  paradigm, which guided how they made and combined lines and used the white of
	  the paper, the modern engravers had engraving, now centuries old,
	  as their paradigm, which had evolved into a highly artificial, albeit virtuoso,
	  performance in metal in which every part of the design, even the highlights,
	  were enmeshed in a unifying line system. Detail of <title level="m">Orlando Uprooting a Pine</title>, engraved by Blake after Stothard. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.9" id="d1.9" n="9"><head>Engravers as copyists</head><figdesc>Despite their remarkable graphic language and skill,
	  engravers were considered more copyist and craftsman than artist because they
	  were not the inventors of the designs. The muse inspires the artist, pointing
	  to his head as the true origin of the design, which moves from concept to work
	  on paper or canvas and through the reproductive process, through etching (boy
	  agitating the acid) to engraving, a move symbolizing the distance between
	  original and copy. The dismissal of craft or execution as less significant than
	  invention deeply bothered Blake; philosophically, in a platonic aesthetic, this
	  hierarchy and separation extended to the artist as well, since the material
	  artifact could not realize perfectly the idea as originally conceived in the
	  mind. While Blake stated that he copied imagination as others copied nature, he
	  countered this received hierarchy and separation by arguing that invention can
	  only be known as it is executed and that execution generates invention.
	  <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1751-52. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.10" id="d1.10" n="10"><head>Printing intaglio plates on the rolling press</head><figdesc>Engravings, like all intaglio plates, are printed on
	  rolling presses. A printer operates a rolling press, another inks a plate on a
	  brassier, and another wipes a plates surfaces of ink in preparation for
	  the press. The intaglio plate is placed face up on the long plank
	  (bed) of the press, dampened paper is placed on top of it, and
	  three or four felt blankets cover them as the bed passes through heavy top and
	  bottom rollers. The top roller exerts great pressure to force the paper into
	  the incised lines of the plate. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767.
	  Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.11" id="d1.11" n="11"><head>Blake, <title level="m">Illustrations of the Book of Job</title>, Plate 12</head><figdesc>In his 22 <title level="m">Illustrations of the Book of Job</title> engravings, published in 1826, Blake reproduced his own designs
	  and, hence, as artist and engraver produced what was understood as
	  original rather than reproductive prints. He
	  returned to the earliest style of engraving, to the pure engraving practiced by
	  his heroes, Albrecht Durer and Marcantonio Raimondi. The lines, engraved
	  directly into the plate without preliminary etching, are densely laid in a
	  parallel rather than cross-hatched style, as evinced by the detail of plate
	  12. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.12" id="d1.12" n="12"><head>Albrecht Durer, <title level="m">Meloncholia</title>, 1514</head><figdesc>The detail of Durers <title level="m">Meloncholia I</title>, a pure engraving from 1514, reveals lines,
	  flicks, untouched highlights, and sharp contrasts similar to those used in the
	  Job engravings. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,  National Gallery of Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.13" id="d1.13" n="13"><head>Blake, <title level="m">Illustrations of Dante</title>, Plate 4</head><figdesc>During 1827, the last year of his life, Blake engraved
	  seven of his 101 watercolor designs of Dantes <title level="m">Divine
	  Comedy</title>. These are all unfinished, but it seems that he was again emulating
	  renaissance models, as evinced by this detail of plate 4, in which form is
	  defined in a more open, less dense manner than the Job, showing more of the
	  white of the paper. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.1.14" id="d1.14" n="14"><head>Andrea Mantegna, <title level="m">Madonna and Child</title>, c. 1485-91</head><figdesc>The detail of Andrea Mantegnas Madonna and
	  Child, a pure engraving, c. 1485-91, reveals a manner of laying in lines and
	  modeling form similar to that used by Blake in the Dante engravings. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,  National Gallery of Art.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i2" corresp="d2"><list><head>New Printing Technologies</head><item><figure entity="illum.2.1" id="d2.1" n="1"><head>Blake, <title level="m">The Approach of Doom</title></head><figdesc>By the last quarter of the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
	  century, with new printing technologies capable of reproducing tone and the
	  appearances of pencil, chalk, pen, and brush, prints in imitation of drawings
	  and watercolors became very popular. Blakes first experiment in relief
	  etching appears to have been <title level="m">The Approach of Doom</title>,
	  1788, after his brothers drawing. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.2" id="d2.2" n="2"><head>Robert Blake, <title level="m">The Approach of Doom</title></head><figdesc><title level="m">The Approach of Doom</title>, pen and
	  wash drawing by Robert Blake, c. 1786. British Museum.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.3" id="d2.3" n="3"><head>Chiaroscuro woodcut</head><figdesc>The first tonal printmaking process, dating from the
	  mid-16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, was invented to imitate drawings on
	  colored paper in several monochromatic washes. It consisted of multiple
	  woodcuts, with a key block for outline and one or two for tones, printed on top
	  of one another. This technique, called chiaroscuro woodcut, was revived in the
	  18th century by John Baptist Jackson, whose <title level="m">Descent from the
	  Cross</title>, after Rembrandt, was executed in 1738 as part of a series of prints
	  in imitation of old master paintings. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.4" id="d2.4" n="4"><head>Tools of Mezzotint</head><figdesc>The first intaglio tonal method was mezzotint,
	  developed in the late 17th century to reproduce the tonal gradations of oil
	  paint. Mezzotinters work from black to white, rather than on a white ground
	  with black line. The plate is roughened with a rocker, a tool
	  with serrated edges (fig. 1) that incised the entire plate with thousands of
	  overlapping lines to create, when printed, a solid black ground. Working with
	  scrapers and burnishers, the mezzotinter reduces the ground and thus the amount
	  of ink printed to create grays and whites (fig. 9). <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.5" id="d2.5" n="5"><head>Mezzotint print</head><figdesc>A detail of Richard Earloms mezzotint of
	  flowers, after Jan Van Huysum, 1778, reveals a wide range of blacks, grays, and
	  whites used to define forms without lines. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.6" id="d2.6" n="6"><head>Tools of Stipple and Chalk engraving</head><figdesc>Using multi-pointed needles (figs. 1-3), punches (figs.
	  4-7), and roulettes (figs. 8, 9), engravers could create stipple
	  and chalk engravings that imitated the appearance of chalk,
	  pencil, and conté crayon (figs. 11-13). Abraham Bosse, <title level="m">De la
	  Manière de graver a leauforte et au burin</title>. 1758. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.7" id="d2.7" n="7"><head>Stipple engraving</head><figdesc>A detail of a stipple engraving printed in reddish
	  brown ink in imitation of conté crayon, by Francesco Bartolozzi, a master of
	  the technique. Stipples and mezzotints were often printed in colors and
	  finished in watercolors. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.8" id="d2.8" n="8"><head>Pure etching</head><figdesc>The etched line is freer, more spontaneous and pen like
	  than the engraved line, as is demonstrated by Paul Sandbys
	  <title level="m">Sketch of Tree with House in the Background</title>, c. 1760.
	  Etching as a fine art, though, had a much smaller share of the English print
	  market than engraving. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.9" id="d2.9" n="9"><head>Etching with roulette imitating marks of a brush</head><figdesc>A facsimile of Van Dykes pen and ink drawing of
	  <title level="m">Jacob Sending Benjamin with his Brethren into Egypt</title>,
	  executed by William Ryland in 1762 for Charles Rogers 2 volume
	  <title level="m">A Collection of Prints in Imitations of Drawings</title>, 1778.
	  Ryland used etching needles and roulettes to carefully reconstruct the
	  appearance of pen and brush marks made spontaneously, imitating the look rather
	  than the process of drawing. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.10" id="d2.10" n="10"><head>Etching with mezzotint imitating pen and wash</head><figdesc>A facsimile by Charles Knapton, c. 1760, of a wash
	  drawing by Giovani Pannini, combining mezzotint rockers for tone and etching
	  needles for outlines. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.11" id="d2.11" n="11"><head>Aquatints, monochrome and colored</head><figdesc>By 1775, the new technique of aquatint was used to
	  reproduce wash drawings (detail, top) and watercolor drawings (detail, bottom),
	  the latter often printed in two inks and hand colored.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.2.12" id="d2.12" n="12"><head>Pen and ink sketch and facsimile reproduction</head><figdesc>By the 1780s, prints in imitation of drawings were
	  very popular, reflecting the taste for the autographic or spontaneous gesture
	  of an artists first thoughts. The popularity of the sketch is evinced by
	  the hundreds of rough drawings Cipriani (detail, top) provided Bartolozzi for
	  reproduction (detail, bottom).</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i3" corresp="d3"><list><item><figure entity="illum.3.1" id="d3.1" n="1"><head>Cutting plates from sheet of copper</head><figdesc>Scoring the sheet of copper deeply with a needle,
	  clamping it at the edge of a table under a second plate or steel ruler, and
	  snapping it into smaller plates; alternatively, the plates could be cut out
	  with a hammer and chisel on an anvil.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.3.2" id="d3.2" n="2"><head>Planing the copper plate with charcoal</head><figdesc>Copper sheets were hand-hammered and thus had fine, densely textured surfaces that could interfere with burins and needles. The plates were planed smooth first with charcoal.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.3.3" id="d3.3" n="3"><head>Planing the copper plate with pumice</head><figdesc>Planing the hand-hammered copper plate with pumice, or “snakestone” and water.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.3.4" id="d3.4" n="4"><head>Polishing the copper plate</head><figdesc>Polishing the copper plate with tightly rolled felt, powdered pumice, and oil, to remove scratches from the planing process.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.3.5" id="d3.5" n="5"><head>Testing the plate’s surface for oil</head><figdesc>Oily film on the copper plate, evinced by water not
	  spreading across the plate, will prevent the waxy layer of acid-resistant
	  varnish, called an etching ground, from adhering to the metal and
	  cause it to lift off during the acid bath.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.3.6" id="d3.6" n="6"><head>Degreasing the plate with whiting and water</head><figdesc>The plate is cleaned or degreased of the
	  oil with a paste of whiting and water.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.3.7" id="d3.7" n="7"><head>Testing the plate’s surface for oil</head><figdesc>Oily film on the plates surface is removed, as
	  evinced by the water spreading evenly over the plate. The plate is now ready to
	  receive its etching ground.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i4" corresp="d4"><list><head>Intaglio Etching</head><item><figure entity="illum.4.1" id="d4.1" n="1"><head>Tools of etching</head><figdesc>Tools of etching, showing taper for smoking the plate
	  (fig. 4), dabber for spreading the etching ground (fig. 3), ball of etching
	  ground (fig. 1 bis), copper plate with ground melted on its surface and spread
	  into a film (figs. 1, 2), brassier (fig. 5), needles (figs. 6-9), brushes (fig.
	  10), and stop-out varnish (fig. 11). <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>,
	  1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. </figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.2" id="d4.2" n="2"><head>Melting the etching ground</head><figdesc>Melting etching ground onto a copper plate over
	  electric heater.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.3" id="d4.3" n="3"><head>Spreading the etching ground</head><figdesc>Spreading etching ground into a thin film with a linen
	  dabber.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.4" id="d4.4" n="4"><head>Blackening the ground</head><figdesc>Blackening the ground with soot from a flaming taper so
	  that lines scratched into it will show up with maximum contrast.
	  <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1751-52. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.5" id="d4.5" n="5"><head>Technique for transferring drawing to plate</head><figdesc>Transferring a design onto an etching ground using the
	  calking or carbon paper method. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.6" id="d4.6" n="6"><head>Transferring a drawing</head><figdesc>Design is traced with a stylus onto the ground through
	  a sheet of thin paper with red chalk on the verso.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.7" id="d4.7" n="7"><head>The transferred drawing</head><figdesc>Designs calked onto the plate are the
	  same direction as the original and thus reversed in the impressions.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.8" id="d4.8" n="8"><head>Counterproofing a design onto plate</head><figdesc>Transferring a pencil design onto the ground using the
	  counterproof method, in which a dampened outline drawing is placed faced down
	  on the plate and passed through the press. The outline is reversed onto the
	  plate, which means that it will be the same direction as the original drawing.
	  This technique was often used for text.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.9" id="d4.9" n="9"><head>Scratching the design through the ground</head><figdesc>With the design transferred onto the copper plate, the
	  etcher knows what to copy and, with the etching needle, scratches through the
	  lines and darkened ground to expose the metal to acid, which, in the next
	  stage, will etch the design into the metal.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Relief Etching</head><item><figure entity="illum.4.10" id="d4.10" n="10"><head>Stop-out varnish</head><figdesc>Standard tools in etching include stop-out varnish
	  (fig. 11), which is a liquid ground made of resin dissolved in turpentine,
	  stored in bottles, and applied with brushes from sea shells (figs. 12, 13).
	  <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.17" id="d4.11" n="11"><head>Loading the quill with a brush</head><figdesc>The stop-out varnish mixed with lampblack for color is
	  loaded into the quill by a brush, a technique used by illuminators. Blake used
	  stop-out varnish as an acid-resistant ink, writing and drawing
	  with both quills and brushes as he would if he were working on paper. The
	  printed results look like drawings not out of imitation but because Blake was
	  actually drawing and writing with similar tools.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.11" id="d4.12" n="12"><head>Writing with stop-out varnish as an ink</head><figdesc>Writing with a quill in stop-out varnish directly on
	  the plate in reverse so that it will print correctly.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.12" id="d4.13" n="13"><head>Creating fine white and black lines</head><figdesc>To create fine white and black lines, Blake could cut
	  into the varnish with a needle as though it were an etching ground, as is
	  evinced by the white lines in the vegetation in The Divine Image
	  from <title level="m">Songs of Innocence</title>, Copy U (1789). Houghton Library, Harvard University.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.13" id="d4.14" n="14"><head>Blake writing backwards</head><figdesc>Blake picturing himself writing backwards with a quill
	  in <title level="m">Jerusalem</title> Copy E, plate 41, detail. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.15" id="d4.15" n="15"><head>Executing a design in stop-out varnish</head><figdesc>Design of text and illustration drawn directly on the
	  plate <hi rend="italic">without</hi> the aid of transfers. The lettering
	  style, letter size, spacing between word and line, number of lines, the
	  texts shape, the vignettes placement are all determined when the
	  text is rewritten on the plate, which means that the parts that form the
	  <hi rend="italic">page design</hi> are visually composed when executed.
	  Because the page design as such does not pre-exist its execution, relief
	  etching produces rather than reproduces its designs. </figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.15" id="d4.16" n="16"><head>Sketches for <title level="m">Thel</title> plates 6 and 7</head><figdesc>Pencil sketches for <title level="m">Thel</title>
	  plates 6 and 7, roughly blocking out space for text and vignette. British Museum.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.4.16" id="d4.17" n="17"><head><title level="m">Thel</title>, Copy H, plates 6 and 7</head><figdesc><title level="m">Thel</title> Copy H, plates 6 and 7;
	  the prints differ considerably from the sketches. The vignette beginning
	  section III (plate 6) was used to conclude the section on plate 7, and the
	  vignette used to conclude the section (plate 7) was completely redrawn and
	  placed at the beginning of plate 6. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i5" corresp="d5"><list><head>Intaglio Etching</head><item><figure entity="illum.5.1" id="d5.1" n="1"><head>Diking the plate</head><figdesc>Walling in the plate with wax to create a dike to hold
	  acid.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.2" id="d5.2" n="2"><head>Feathering the acid</head><figdesc>Copper plate diked with wax walls to hold acid and an
	  engravers assistant, or printmakers devil,
	  agitating the acid with a feather. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>,
	  1751-52. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.3" id="d5.3" n="3"><head>Feathering gas bubbles from the lines</head><figdesc>The acid attacks the exposed metal and bites the lines
	  into the plate; the gas bubbles are removed from the etched lines with a
	  feather to protect the ground from pitting or lifting.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.4" id="d5.4" n="4"><head>Drying the plate</head><figdesc>Removing the acid and drying the plate in preparation
	  for stopping out portions of the design.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.5" id="d5.5" n="5"><head>Stopping out areas of the design</head><figdesc>Painting over areas of the design in stop-out varnish
	  to protect them from the acid in subsequent bites; these lines will be the
	  least deep and will print lightest.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.6" id="d5.6" n="6"><head>Diagram explaining effects of stopping out</head><figdesc>Lines bitten longest are deepest and print
	  darkestand vice versa; by varying the time different areas of the design
	  is in acid, the etcher varies tone and creates the illusion of aerial
	  perspective and roundness. <title level="m">Sculptura Historico-Technica</title>,
	  1760. </figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.7" id="d5.7" n="7"><head>Re-etching the plate</head><figdesc>With the lightest lines stopped out, the plate is
	  etched again, a stage that can be repeated many times, with new lines stopped
	  out each time the plate is etched.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.8" id="d5.8" n="8"><head>Removing the etching ground</head><figdesc>The etching ground is removed with turpentine.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.9" id="d5.9" n="9"><head>Design incised into the metal and edges beveled</head><figdesc>The design has been bitten into the metal by the acid;
	  the sides of intaglio plates must be beveled with a file so they do not tear
	  the paper when the plate is printed with the great pressure required to force
	  paper into the incised line.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Relief Etching</head><item><figure entity="illum.5.10" id="d5.10" n="10"><head>Pouring acid on the plate</head><figdesc>Pouring nitric acid onto a recreation of
	  <title level="m">Marriage</title> plate 10 diked with wax walls; the acid etches
	  the bare metal so that it will become lower than the design, the areas drawn in
	  the acid-resist, thereby putting the design into relief. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.11" id="d5.11" n="11"><head>Feathering the acid</head><figdesc>Agitating the acid with a feather to remove gas
	  bubbles, which helps to protect the design from lifting, pitting, or being
	  uncut.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.12" id="d5.12" n="12"><head>Feathering gas bubbles, detail</head><figdesc>Gas bubbles forming along lines of the design.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.13" id="d5.13" n="13"><head>Feathering gas bubbles, detail</head><figdesc>Removing the gas bubbles with a feather.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.14" id="d5.14" n="14"><head>Stopping out delicate areas to protect them</head><figdesc>After an initial bite to put the design into low relief, the acid is poured out and the plate is dried. The more delicate parts of the design are painted over with stop-out varnish to protect them from the acid in a second, longer bite. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.15" id="d5.15" n="15"><head>Re-etching the plate</head><figdesc>The plate is rebitten for a second, longer time that will put the design into printable relief; stopping out is for protecting lines and not, as it is in etching, to create tone. All the lines in a relief etching are on the same surface, which creates a two-tone print, like a woodcut.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.16" id="d5.16" n="16"><head>Removing the wax walls</head><figdesc>After the plate is etched into printable relief, the wax walls are removed.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.17" id="d5.17" n="17"><head>Removing the acid-resist</head><figdesc>The acid resist is removed with turpentine and the plate is ready to be printed; the sides do not need to be beveled because the relief plate will be printed with relatively light pressure, unlike intaglio plates.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.5.18" id="d5.18" n="18"><head>Fragment of an illuminated plate</head><figdesc>A fragment of the only extant illuminated plate, a rejected plate from <title level="m">America</title> (1793). It reveals a two-step biting process in the plateaus around the lettering, evidence that the letters were stopped out after a short initial bite.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i6" corresp="d6"><list><head>Making Ink</head><item><figure entity="illum.6.1" id="d6.1" n="1"><head>Pigments for ink</head><figdesc>Intaglio ink is made with powered pigments mixed with various grades of burnt linseed oil.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.2" id="d6.2" n="2"><head>Grinding pigment in oil</head><figdesc>The pigment is ground on a marble slab with a heavy grinder.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.3" id="d6.3" n="3"><head>Mixing pigment in oil with palette knife</head><figdesc>Mixing the ink with a broad palette knife.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.4" id="d6.4" n="4"><head>Intaglio ink</head><figdesc>The resulting intaglio ink is tacky and buttery.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Inking Intaglio Etchings</head><item><figure entity="illum.6.5" id="d6.5" n="5"><head>Rubbing ink into incised lines</head><figdesc>Using a tightly rolled piece of felt, the etcher rubs ink into the incised lines of the plate; this is usually done over a brassier, which warms the ink and makes it easier to spread.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.6" id="d6.6" n="6"><head>Wiping the surface of ink with muslin rag</head><figdesc>The plate’s surface is wiped of excess ink with a muslin rag.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.7" id="d6.7" n="7"><head>Wiping the surface clean with palm of the hand</head><figdesc>The plate’s surface and edges are given their finishing touches by being wiped clean of all ink and plate tone with the palm of the hand and a little whiting.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Inking Relief Etchings</head><item><figure entity="illum.6.8" id="d6.8" n="8"><head>Inking with a dabber</head><figdesc>The relief-etched plate was inked with tacky intaglio ink, the kind Blake was used to making, rather than relief ink, as is evinced by the reticulated textures on impressions. The linen dabber, with a bottom flat and stiff with dried ink, spreads the ink and is supported by the dense line system and the plate borders created by the wax walls, which help the dabber avoid touching the shallows.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.9" id="d6.9" n="9"><head>The inked design</head><figdesc>The design etched in relief is inked in black and the shallows of the plate are left untouched.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.10" id="d6.10" n="10"><head>Wiping ink to erase lines</head><figdesc>The thin borders along the sides of the plate and the cave forms at the bottom of the plate are wiped of ink, which erases these design elements since without ink they will not print.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Inking à la poupée</head><item><figure entity="illum.6.11" id="d6.11" n="11"><head>Adding colors to the plate’s shallows</head><figdesc>Colors can be added to inked plates and printed with ink simultaneously to produce a “color print.” The colors can be oil based inks or, in the case of Blake’s illuminated plates, water-based, pigments mixed with glue or gum Arabic. The water-based colors, should they dry on the plate, are reconstituted when printed onto damp paper.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.12" id="d6.12" n="12"><head>Painting the plate’s illustration</head><figdesc>The plate is painted in various colors with small brushes or dabbers in the standard color printing technique known as “à la poupée,” which was commonly used to print stipples, chalk engravings, and mezzotints.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.13" id="d6.13" n="13"><head>The color-printed impression</head><figdesc><title level="m">Marriage</title> Copy F plate 10, color printed c. 1794; visually, its colors are opaque and roughly textured, more like a la prima oil sketches than watercolors. The Pierpont Morgan Library.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.6.14" id="d6.14" n="14"><head>Blake, <title level="m">The House of Death</title></head><figdesc><title level="m">The House of Death</title>, color-print drawing, 1795, from a series of twelve. These color prints, approximately 40 x 60 cm., brilliantly combine printmaking and painting. Most of the plates were printed twice, with the second impression a little lighter than the first because it was taken from the plate without it being recolored. Most of the plates were reprinted c. 1805. Fitzwilliam Museum.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i7" corresp="d7"><list><head>Intaglio Etching</head><item><figure entity="illum.7.1" id="d7.1" n="1"><head>Preparing paper for printing</head><figdesc>For intaglio printing, paper is cut to size and dampened.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.2" id="d7.2" n="2"><head>The rolling press</head><figdesc>The intaglio plate is placed face up on the long plank (“bed”) of the rolling press, paper is placed on top of it, and three or four felt blankets cover them as they pass under the heavy top roller. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.3" id="d7.3" n="3"><head>The intaglio impression</head><figdesc>After the intaglio print is pulled through the press, the paper is lifted off the plate and hung or laid flat to dry. Impressions from intaglio plates have pronounced platemarks, the embossment of the plate, because of the pressure necessary to force paper into the plate’s incised lines.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Relief Etchings</head><item><figure entity="illum.7.4" id="d7.4" n="4"><head>The rolling press and division of labor</head><figdesc>Blake used his rolling press to print relief-etchings, adjusting it so it printed with less pressure. Whereas commercial printers of intaglio plates could use three people in the printing processone handling the press and paper, one for inking the plate, another for wiping ink from the surface of the plateBlake needed only two, since he did not have to wipe the surface of his plates clean of ink. He and his wife probably worked as a team, with Mrs. Blake handling the paper and press and Blake inking the plates and placing them on the bed of the press. Abraham Bosse, <title level="m">Traicté des manières e graveur en taille douce</title>. 1645. Essick Collection.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.5" id="d7.5" n="5"><head>The relief-etched impression</head><figdesc>The printed sheet is registered to the sheet under the plate or marks on that bottom sheet. Because the design is in relief and not below the surface, Blake printed his relief etchings with less pressure, which eliminated overt platemarks and enabled him to print on both sides of the sheet and thereby create books with facing pages, a style of printing he used till 1794, when he began printing on one side of the sheet only.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.6" id="d7.6" n="6"><head>Printing in colors</head><figdesc>In 1794 and 1795, Blake routinely printed his illuminated plates in colors, by painting the plate after inking it and printing ink and colors simultaneously. The color-printed impression was then finished in watercolors and pen and ink.</figdesc></figure></item></list><list><head>Illuminating Prints</head><item><figure entity="illum.7.7" id="d7.7" n="7"><head>Making watercolors</head><figdesc>Blake usually printed in colored inks and then finished his impressions in watercolors. He made his colors by mixing pigments into its vehicle, gum Arabic or glue.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.8" id="d7.8" n="8"><head>Grinding pigments</head><figdesc>Pigments are ground very finely into the vehicle on a slab with a flat pestle.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.9" id="d7.9" n="9"><head>Diluting watercolor</head><figdesc>The watercolor paint can be diluted with water to produce stains or translucency, or used undiluted or with whiting to produce a paint film and more opaque tones.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.10" id="d7.10" n="10"><head>Blake’s early style of coloring prints</head><figdesc>Jacqueline  Marshall hand coloring the master copy of “The Ecchoing Green” for the Manchester  Etching Workshop’s facsimile of <title level="m">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title> Copy B. The coloring is in Blake’s early style of illumination.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.7.11" id="d7.11" n="11"><head>Blake’s late style of coloring prints</head><figdesc>“The Ecchoing Green,” <title level="m">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>, Copy Z, 1826, printed in orange-red ink and finished in watercolors, pen and ink, and gold, and given frame lines like a miniature painting. This was Blake’s late coloring style, used for nearly all works printed after 1800. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2><div2 id="i8" corresp="d8"><list><item><figure entity="illum.8.1" id="d8.1" n="1"><head><title level="m">Songs of Innocence</title>, Copy E, 1789, in original wrappers</head><figdesc><title level="m">Songs of Innocence</title> Copy E, 1789, as it left Blake’s printshop: the impressions were stabbed through three holes between sheets of wove paper (“wrappers”). In the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, books were sold in uncut sheets, with binding the responsibility of the buyer. Blake knew that purchasers would have the books rebound to fit the style of the other books in their libraries. Berg Collection, New York Public Library.</figdesc></figure></item><item><figure entity="illum.8.2" id="d8.2" n="2"><head><title level="m">The Book of Thel</title>, Copy R, c. 1790, in original stitching</head><figdesc><title level="m">The Book of Thel</title>, Copy R, c. 1790; impressions stabbed through three holes and bound with string. Yale Center for British Art.</figdesc></figure></item></list></div2></div1></body></text></tei.2>