<bad id="lt11sept1801.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to Thomas Butts, 11 September 1801" copy="1"
     copyid="1" institution="westminster" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-11sept1801">
     <header>
          <filedesc>
               <titlestmt>
                    <title reg="Letter to Thomas Butts, 11 September 1801">
                         <main>Letter to Thomas Butts, 11 September 1801</main> : electronic edition </title>
                    <principal>
                         <resp>Editors: </resp>
                         <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                              Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                              Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                         Hill</principal>
                    <respstmt> </respstmt>
                    <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel
                         Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                    <funder/>
               </titlestmt>
               <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
               <extent>1 XML file approx. 27.4KB; 8 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from
                    approx. 157KB to 1.5MB</extent>
               <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>August 2019</date></publicationstmt>
               <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
               <updatestmt> 
                    The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of digital editions of our third installment of Blake's 95 known letters. The latest 28, drawn from nine collections, span nearly the entire chronological range of Blake’s correspondence from 1791 to 1827, the year of his death. Three of this group are by Blake’s correspondents&#8212;included here because of especially tight connections with their associated documents. (Those pairs are 18 October [Reveley] and October 1791 [Blake]; 23 September [Blake] and September 1800 [Butts]; 18 December [Cumberland] and 19 December 1808 [Blake].)                
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    A sample of the many highlights from the 28 new letters might feature
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    --2 October 1800 (to Blake’s London patron Thomas Butts): fresh with optimism after his recent arrival in Felpham, Blake’s awkward amalgam of down to earth excuse-making with 78 lines of visionary verses:
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    To my Friend Butts I write<lb/>
                    My First Vision of Light<lb/>
                    . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
                    I saw you and your wife<lb/>
                    By the fountains of Life<lb/>
                    Such the Vision to me<lb/>
                    Appeard on the Sea<lb/>
                    Mrs Butts will I hope Excuse my not having finishd the Portrait.<lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    --16 August 1803 (to Thomas Butts): Blake’s “whole outline” of his dangerous and distressing encounter with the soldier Private John Scolfield in Blake’s garden, which resulted in a “very unwarrantable warrant,” a charge of sedition against Blake, depositions, a lawyer, a trial, and, finally, acquittal: a “perilous adventure” for sure. Its imaginative afterlife was the appearance of Scolfield and his companion Private John Cock as shady Sons of Albion in Blake’s illuminated epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>.  
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    --18 January 1808 (to Ozias Humphry): Blake’s detailed description of his intricate 1808 watercolor <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> (Petworth House, Sussex), commissioned by the Countess of Egremont on Humphry’s recommendation. (We reproduce one of the three copies that Blake made of his description; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Records</hi>, pages 249-50.)  
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    --25 November 1825 (to John Linnell): sometimes called the kitchen letter for Blake’s brief contention that his flat at 3 Fountain Court would be the optimal place (the press is already assembled there, the lighting is better) for printing a copy of his engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>. For details of the unearthing of the letter—which turned up in a box of autograph scraps in the archives of publisher John Murray&#8212;and its surprisingly rich contexts in Blake’s workaday life, see Angus Whitehead, “The Uncollected Letters of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 80.3: 423-35.
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake's hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    Once again, special thanks to the City of Westminster Archives Centre for courteous assistance, excellent digital images, and willingness to share Kerrison Preston’s Blake library with the world. 
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
               </updatestmt>
               <notesstmt/>
          </filedesc>
          <userestrict>Copyright &#169; <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
               Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
               with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication
               on other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
               advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
               this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
               <lb/>This image copyright &#169; 2019 City of Westminster Archives Centre. </userestrict>
          <encodingdesc/>
          <profiledesc/>
          <revisiondesc>
               <changestmt>
                    <change>Final proofing and publication of 28 letters written between 1791 and 1827</change>
                    <date>April 2019-August 2019</date>
                    <respstmt>
                         <resp>Editors:</resp>
                         <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                         University of Rochester;
                         <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                         University of California, Riverside; and
                         <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                         University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                         <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                         <name>Michael Fox</name>
                         <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                         <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                         <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                         <name>Grant Glass</name>
                         <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                         <name>Eric Loy</name>
                         <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                         <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                         <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                         <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                         <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                         <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                         <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                         <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                         <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                         <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                         <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                         <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                         <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                         <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                         <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                         <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                         <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                         <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                         <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                         <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                         <name>Kendall DeBoer</name>
                         <name>Helen Davies</name>
                    </respstmt>
               </changestmt>
          </revisiondesc>
     </header>
     <objdesc>
          <source>
               <objdescid>
                    <objtitle>
                         <title>Letter to Thomas Butts, 11 September 1801</title>
                    </objtitle>
                    <origination>William Blake<role>author,</role>
                         <role>inventor,</role>
                         <role>delineator</role>
                    </origination>
                    <compdate value="1801.B">1801</compdate>
               </objdescid>
               <objinfo>
                    <numberobj>4</numberobj>
                    <objorder>1-4</objorder>
                    <objsize>full sheet 19.1 x 30.7 cm. <note>Full sheet and Leaf Size dimensions (height x width) are given according to the vertical orientation of the body of Blake's letter; see the note on Number of Leaves, below. Object 1 has been reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as would be customary when reading the address.</note></objsize>
                    <numberleaves>2<note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3) and second recto (Object 4). This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object 1).</note>
                    </numberleaves>
                    <leafsize>19.1 x 15.3 cm.</leafsize>
                    <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                    <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                    <support>laid paper</support>
                    <watermark>F HAYES / 1798</watermark>
                    <binding>none</binding>
                    <postmark>none</postmark>
                    <sealDesc>red wafer</sealDesc>
                    <addressee>Thomas Butts</addressee>
                    <placeLet>Felpham</placeLet>
               </objinfo>
               <provenance n="1">
                    <name>City of Westminster Archives Centre</name>
                    <date>1967</date>
                    <dealer>none</dealer>
                    <price>gift</price>
                   <note>Captain Frederick Butts (the grandson of the recipient) sold (c. 1906) this
                         letter along with several other letters to W. Graham Robertson, who allowed them 
                         to be reproduced (1926) and bequeathed them in 1948 to Mr. Kerrison Preston, who 
                         gave them in 1967 to The Westminster Public Library, which has since been 
                         incorporated into the City of Westminster Archives Centre.</note>
               </provenance>
               <repository>
                    <institution>City of Westminster Archives Centre</institution>
                    <addressline>10 St Ann's Street</addressline>
                    <addressline>London SW1P 2DE</addressline>
                    <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                    <addressline>Telephone:044 020 7641 5189</addressline>
                    <addressline>E-mail: archives@westminster.gov.uk</addressline>
                    <addressline>URL: https://www.westminster.gov.uk/contact-archives</addressline>
                    <department>Local Studies</department>
                    <repositoryid label="Call Number">Preston Blake Collection: Blake-Butts Letters
                         &#38; Receipts (5)</repositoryid>
               </repository>
          </source>
          <desc id="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt11sept1801.1.1.LT">
               <objtitle>
                    <title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid>
                         <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                    </objid>
               </objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objsize>15.3 x 19.1 cm.</objsize>
                    <objnote>
                         <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on
                              the first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3) and second recto
                              (Object 4). This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed
                              packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object
                              1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.</p> 
                         <p>The number “5” is written upside down (as the object is reoriented for reading the address) in the lower left corner in an unknown hand.</p>
                         <p>A tear appears on the bottom of the object, presumably where the wafer was torn away upon opening the letter.</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
               </physdesc>
               <phystext>
                    <vspace extent="10"/>
                    <lg justify="left">
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Butts</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left">Great Marlborough Street</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="5">London&#8212;</l>
                    </lg>
               </phystext>
          </desc>
          <desc id="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt11sept1801.1.2.LT">
               <objtitle>
                    <title type="transcribed">I hope you will continue to excuse my want</title>, <objid>
                         <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
                    </objid>
               </objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objsize>19.1 x 15.3 cm.</objsize>
                    <objnote>
                         <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on
                              the first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3) and second recto
                              (Object 4). This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed
                              packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object
                              1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
               </physdesc>
               <phystext>
                    <vspace extent="2"/>
                    <lg justify="left">
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">My Dear Sir</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="9">I hope you will
                              continue to excuse my want of s<subst><del type="overwrite">p</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">t</add></subst><choice>
                                   <orig>eady</orig>
                                   <reg>steady</reg>
                              </choice> perseverance </l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">by which want I am still so
                              much your debtor &#38; you so much my Credit-er</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">but such as I can be I will:
                              I can be grateful &#38; I can soon Send</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">you some of your designs
                              which I have nearly completed. In the mean</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">time by my
                                        <choice><orig>Sisters</orig><reg>Sister's</reg></choice>
                              hands I transmit to <choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                                        >rs</hi></orig><reg>Mrs</reg></choice> Butts an attempt <del
                                   type="overstrike">to</del> at </l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">your likeness which I hope
                              She who is the best judge will think like</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">Time flies faster, (as seems
                              to me), here than in London I
                                        <choice><orig>labour</orig><reg>labor</reg></choice></l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">incessantly &#38; accomplish
                              not one half of what I intend because my</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">Abstract folly hurries me
                              often away while I am at work, carrying</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">me over Mountains &#38;
                              Valleys which are not Real in a Land of</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">Abstraction where Spectres
                              of the Dead wander. This I
                                        <choice><orig>endeavour</orig><reg>endeavor</reg></choice>
                              to</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">prevent &#38; with my whole
                              might chain my feet to the world of Duty</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left">&#38; Reality. but in vain!
                              the faster I bind the better is the Ballast</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left">for I so far from being
                              bound down take the world with me in my</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left">flights &#38; often it seems
                              lighter than a ball of wool rolled by the wind<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 34) reads "wool" as
                                   "Wool".</note></l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left">Bacon &#38; Newton would
                              prescribe ways of making the world heavier</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left">to me &#38; Pitt would
                              prescribe distress for a medicinal potion. but</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.19" justify="left">as none on Earth can give me
                              Mental Distress. &#38; I know that all</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.20" justify="left">Distress inflicted by Heaven
                              is a Mercy. a Fig for all Corporeal</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.21" justify="left">Such Distress is my mock
                              &#38; scorn. Alas wretched happy ineffectual</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.22" justify="left"
                                        ><choice><orig>labourer</orig><reg>laborer</reg></choice> of
                                        <choice><orig>times</orig><reg>time's</reg></choice> moments
                              that I am! who shall deliver me from</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.23" justify="left">this Spirit of Abstraction
                              &#38; Improvidence. Such my Dear Sir</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.24" justify="left">Is the truth of my state
                              &#38; I tell it you in palliation of my</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.25" justify="left">seeming neglect of your most
                              pleasant orders. but I have</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.26" justify="left">not neglected them &#38; yet
                              a Year is rolled over &#38; only now<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1552) reads "now" as
                                   "nhw".</note></l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.27" justify="left">I approach the prospect of
                              sending you some which you may expect</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.28" justify="left">soon. I should have sent
                              them by My Sister but as the Coach</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.29" justify="left">goes three times a week to
                              London &#38; they <del type="overstrike">shall</del> will arrive as
                              safe</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.30" justify="left">as with her. I shall have an
                              opportunity of
                                   <choice><orig>inclosing</orig><reg>enclosing</reg></choice>
                              several together</l>

                    </lg>
               </phystext>
          </desc>
          <desc id="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03" dbi="lt11sept1801.1.3.LT">
               <objtitle>
                    <title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid>
                         <objnumber code="A3">Object 3</objnumber>
                    </objid>
               </objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objsize>19.1 x 15.3 cm.</objsize>
                    <objnote>
                         <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on
                              the first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3) and second recto
                              (Object 4). This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed
                              packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object
                              1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
               </physdesc>
               <phystext>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg justify="left">
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.01" justify="left">which are not yet completed.
                              I thank you again &#38; again for your</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.02" justify="left">generous forbearance of
                              which I have need_ &#38; now I must express</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.03" justify="left">my wishes to see you at
                              Felpham &#38; to <choice><orig>shew</orig><reg>show</reg></choice> you
                                             <choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                                        >r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                              <choice><orig>Hayleys</orig><reg>Hayley's</reg></choice></l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.04" justify="left">Library. which is still
                                        <choice><orig>unfinishd</orig><reg>unfinished</reg></choice>
                              but is <gap reason="cancellation" extent="2" unit="character"/> in a
                              finishing way</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.05" justify="left">&#38; looks well. I ought
                              also to mention my Extreme disappointment</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.06" justify="left">at <choice><orig>M<hi
                                             rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                              <choice><orig>Johnsons</orig><reg>Johnson's</reg></choice>
                              forgetfulness, who appointed to call on you but</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.07" justify="left">did Not. He is also a happy
                              Abstract known by all his</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.08" justify="left">Friends as the most innocent
                              forgetter of his own Interests. He is</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.09" justify="left" indent="7">
                              <add place="supralinear">the late</add>
                         </l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.10" justify="left">nephew to <add
                                   type="insertion" place="inline" symbol="caret"><hi
                                        rend="subscript">^</hi></add>
                              <choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                                   >r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice> Cowper the Poet you would
                              like him much</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.11" justify="left">I continue painting
                              Miniatures &#38; Improve more &#38; more as all</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.12" justify="left">my friends tell me. but my
                              Principal <choice><orig>labour</orig><reg>labor</reg></choice> at this
                              time is</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.13" justify="left">Engraving Plates for
                                        <choice><orig>Cowpers</orig><reg>Cowper's</reg></choice>
                              Life a Work of Magnitude</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.14" justify="left">which <choice><orig>M<hi
                                             rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                              Hayley is now
                                   <choice><orig>Labouring</orig><reg>Laboring</reg></choice> with
                              all his matchless</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.15" justify="left">industry &#38; which will be
                              a most valuable acquisition to</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.16" justify="left">Literature not only on
                              account of <choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                                        >r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                              <choice><orig>Hayleys</orig><reg>Hayley's</reg></choice>
                              composition</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.17" justify="left">but also as it will contain
                              Letters of Cowper to his friends<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1553) reads "Friends" for
                                   "friends".</note></l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.18" justify="left">Perhaps or rather Certainly
                              the very best letters that ever</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.19" justify="left">were published</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.20" justify="left" indent="6"> My wife joins
                              with me in Love to you &#38; <choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                                             >rs</hi></orig><reg>Mrs</reg></choice> Butts</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.21" justify="left">hoping that her joy is now
                              increased &#38; yours also in an</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.22" justify="left">increase of family &#38; of
                              health &#38; happiness</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.03.23" justify="left" indent="14">I remain Dear
                              Sir</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.24" justify="left" indent="19">Ever Yours
                              Sincerely</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.25" justify="left">Felpham Cottage</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.26" justify="left">of Cottages the prettiest
                                   <space extent="6"/> William Blake</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.27" justify="left">September 11. 1801</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg justify="left">
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.28" justify="left" indent="4">Next time I have
                              the happiness to see you I am determined</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.29" justify="left">to paint another Portrait of
                              you from Life in my best manner</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.02.30" justify="left">for Memory will not do in
                              such minute operations, for I have</l>
                    </lg>
               </phystext>
          </desc>
          <desc id="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04" dbi="lt11sept1801.1.4.LT">
               <objtitle>
                    <title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid>
                         <objnumber code="A4">Object 4</objnumber>
                    </objid>
               </objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objsize>19.1 x 15.3 cm.</objsize>
                    <objnote>
                         <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on
                              the first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3) and second recto
                              (Object 4). This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed
                              packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object
                              1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
               </physdesc>
               <phystext>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.01" justify="left">now
                                        <choice><orig>discoverd</orig><reg>discovered</reg></choice>
                              that without Nature before the
                                        <choice><orig>painters</orig><reg>painter's</reg></choice>
                              Eye he can</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.02" justify="left">never produce
                                        <choice><orig>any thing</orig><reg>anything</reg></choice>
                              in the walks of Natural Painting</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.03" justify="left">Historical Designing is one
                              thing &#38; Portrait Painting another</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.04" justify="left">&#38; they are as Distinct
                              as any two Arts can be Happy would</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.05" justify="left">that Man be who could unite
                              them</l>
                    </lg>
                    <vspace extent="5"/>
                    <lg>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.06" justify="left" indent="1">P.S. Please to Remember our
                              best respects</l>
                         <l n="lt11seot1801.1.ltr.04.07" justify="left" indent="3">to <choice><orig>M<hi
                                             rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                                        B<subst><gap reason="overwrite" extent="1" unit="character"
                                   /><add type="overwrite" place="inline">i</add></subst><choice><orig>rch</orig><reg>John
                                        Birch</reg></choice> &#38; tell him that Felpham</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.08" justify="left" indent="3">Men are the mildest of the
                              human race if</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.09" justify="left" indent="3">it is the will of Providence
                              they shall be the wisest</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.10" justify="left" indent="3">We hope that he will next
                              Summer joke us</l>
                         <l n="lt11sept1801.1.ltr.04.11" justify="left" indent="3">face to face&#8212; &#8212;God bless
                              you all</l>
                    </lg>
               </phystext>
          </desc>
     </objdesc>
</bad>
