<bad id="lt12april1827.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to George Cumberland, 12 April 1827" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-12apr1827"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to George Cumberland, 12 April 1827"><main>Letter to George Cumberland, 12 April 1827</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 28KB; 6 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 310KB
                to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died.
                <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”  <lb/><lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London.  His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.  Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite extraordinary thing.  If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/>
                In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.  We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/>
                Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2013 Fitzwilliam Museum. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to George Cumberland, 12 April 1827</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role> inventor, </role><role>
                        delineator</role></origination><origination>George Cumberland<role>author, </role><role> inventor, </role><role>
                        delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1827.G">1827</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>4</numberobj><objorder>1-4</objorder><objsize>full sheet 16.5 x 20.9 cm.<note>Unfolded full sheet and Leaf Size
                        dimensions (height x width) are given according to the vertical orientation
                        of the body of Blake's letter; see the note on Number of Leaves, below.
                        Object 1 has been reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as would be
                        customary when reading the address.</note></objsize><numberleaves>2<note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter
                        appears on the first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3). This
                        folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed letter packet. The address
                        appears on the second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior
                        of the sealed packet. Notes in another hand, identified as George
                        Cumberland's by Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1668) and
                        Keynes (*Letters*, page 169n3), appear on the second recto
                        (Object 4), to which is attached a copy of the calling card produced by
                        Blake for Cumberland and mentioned in both Blake's letter and Cumberland's
                        notes. Images of the fully unfolded letter and a copy of George Cumberland's
                        card are available under Related Works in the Archive.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>16.5 x 10.45 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper</support><watermark>RUSE &amp; TURNERS / 1810</watermark><binding>none<note>Remnants of a fabric strip, probably silk, used as some form of
                        binding or album attachment are visible along edges of Objects 1 and
                        4.</note></binding><postmark>none</postmark><sealDesc>wafer</sealDesc><addressee>George Cumberland</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name><date>1935</date><dealer>Maggs Brothers</dealer><price>£150, price including letter and attached card</price><note>Sold with attached card by T.G. Arthur at Sotheby's, 11 April 1893, lot 188
                    (£5.5s to Pearson); sold posthumously from Charles Fairfax Murray
                    Collection at Sotheby's, 5 Feb. 1920, lot 21, to Morton; Maggs Bros. advertised
                    letter with card in Summer 1934 catalogue 597, lot 287; sold by Maggs Bros.
                    (£150) to Fitzwilliam Museum, 17 October 1935, through the T.H. Riches
                    Fund.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution><addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline><addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 44-1223-332900</addressline><addressline>Fax: 44-1223-332923</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Department of Manuscripts and Printed Books</department><collection>Fitzwilliam Museum</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">MS 9-1935</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt12april1827.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt12april1827.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber></Objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>10.45 x 16.5 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3). This folded sheet was
                        folded further to form a sealed letter packet. The address appears on the
                        second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed
                        packet. Notes in another hand, identified as George Cumberland's by Bentley
                            (*Writings* volume 2, page 1668) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 169n3), appear on the second recto (object
                        4), to which is attached a copy of the calling card produced by Blake for
                        Cumberland and mentioned in both Blake's letter and Cumberland's notes.
                        Images of the fully unfolded letter and a copy of George Cumberland's card
                        are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p><p>In the bottom right corner near the "FITZWILLIAM MUSEUM" stamp, a library
                        inscription in pencil in an unknown hand includes illegible text in brackets
                        followed by the accession number "9-1935".</p></objnote><windowsize width="1010" height="850"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">George Cumberland <choice><sic>Esq</sic><reg>Esquire</reg></choice><hi rend="superscript">re</hi></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="5">Culver Street</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="11">Bristol</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt12april1827.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I have been very near the Gates of Death &amp; have
                    returned</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </Objnumber></Objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.5 x 10.45 cm</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3). This folded sheet was
                        folded further to form a sealed letter packet. The address appears on the
                        second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed
                        packet. Notes in another hand, identified as George Cumberland's by Bentley
                            (*Writings* volume 2, page 1668) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 169n3), appear on the second recto (object
                        4), to which is attached a copy of the calling card produced by Blake for
                        Cumberland and mentioned in both Blake's letter and Cumberland's notes.
                        Images of the fully unfolded letter and a copy of George Cumberland's card
                        are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p></objnote><windowsize width="840" height="1050"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left" indent="5">Dear Cumberland</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="19">I have been very
                        near the Gates of Death &amp; have returned</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left" indent="5">very weak &amp; an
                        Old Man feeble &amp; tottering. but not in Spirit &amp; Life</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left" indent="5">not in The Real Man
                        The Imagination which Liveth for Ever. In that</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left" indent="5">I am stronger &amp;
                        stronger as this Foolish Body decays. I thank you</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left" indent="5">for the Pains you
                        have taken with Poor Job. I know too well that a</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left" indent="5">great majority of
                        Englishmen are fond of The Indefinite which they</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left" indent="5">Measure by Newton's
                        doctrine of the Fluxions of an Atom. A Thing<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1667), Erdman (page 783) and Keynes
                                (*Letters*, page 168) read "doctrine" as
                            "Doctrine".</note></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left" indent="5">that does not Exist.
                        These are Politicians &amp; think that Republican Art</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left" indent="5">is Inimical to their
                        Atom. For a Line or Lineament is not formed by</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left" indent="5">Chance a Line is a
                        Line in its Minutest Subdivisions <choice><orig>Strait</orig><reg>Straight</reg></choice> or Crooked It</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left" indent="5">is Itself &amp; Not
                        Intermeasurable with or by any Thing Else Such is Job</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left" indent="5">but since the French
                        Revolution Englishmen are all Intermeasurable</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left" indent="5">One by Another
                        Certainly a happy state of Agreement to which I for</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left" indent="5">One do not Agree God
                        keep me from the Divinity of Yes &amp; No too</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left" indent="5">The Yea <subst><del type="overwrite">&amp;</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">N</add></subst><choice><sic>ay</sic><reg>Nay</reg></choice> Creeping Jesus from supposing Up &amp; Down to be the
                            same<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1667),
                            Erdman (page 783), and Keynes (*Letters*, page 168) read
                            "Yea Nay".</note></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left" indent="5">Thing as all
                        Experimentalists must suppose</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left" indent="11">You are desirous I
                        know to dispose of some of my Works &amp; to make</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.19" justify="left"><add type="insertion" place="marginleft">them </add><choice><orig>Pleasin</orig><reg>Pleasing</reg></choice> I am obliged to you &amp; to all who do so But having none
                            remaining<note>The word "them" appears as a probable marginal insertion
                            to the left of the main body of the text.</note></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.20" justify="left" indent="5">of all that I had
                        Printed I cannot Print more Except at a great loss</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.21" justify="left" indent="5">for at the time I
                        printed those things I had a whole House to range in</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.22" justify="left" indent="5">now I am shut up in a
                        Corner therefore am forced to ask a Price for</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.23" justify="left" indent="5">them that I scarce
                        expect to get from a Stranger. I am now Printing</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.24" justify="left" indent="5">a Set of the Songs of
                        Innocence &amp; Experience for a Friend at Ten Guineas</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.25" justify="left" indent="5">which I cannot do
                        under Six Months consistent with my other Work,</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.26" justify="left" indent="5">so that I have little
                        hope of doing any more of such things. the Last<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1667) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 169) read "the" as "The".</note></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.27" justify="left" indent="5">Work I produced is a
                        Poem Entitled Jerusalem the Emanation of the Giant</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.02.28" justify="left" indent="5">Albion. but find that
                        to Print it will Cost my Time the amount of</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03" dbi="lt12april1827.1.3.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </Objnumber></Objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.5 x 10.45 cm</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3). This folded sheet was
                        folded further to form a sealed letter packet. The address appears on the
                        second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed
                        packet. Notes in another hand, identified as George Cumberland's by Bentley
                            (*Writings* volume 2, page 1668) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 169n3), appear on the second recto (object
                        4), to which is attached a copy of the calling card produced by Blake for
                        Cumberland and mentioned in both Blake's letter and Cumberland's notes.
                        Images of the fully unfolded letter and a copy of George Cumberland's card
                        are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p></objnote><windowsize width="940" height="1050"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.01" justify="left">Twenty Guineas One I have <choice><sic>Finishd</sic><reg>Finished</reg></choice> It contains 100 Plates but it is</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.02" justify="left">not likely that I shall get a
                        Customer for it</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.03" justify="left" indent="6">As you wish me to
                        send you a list with the Prices of these things</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.04" justify="left">they are as follows<space extent="27"/>£<space extent="3"/>s<space extent="1"/>d</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.06" justify="left" indent="17">America<space extent="16"/>— 6 . 6 . 0</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.07" justify="left" indent="17">Europe<space extent="20"/>6 . 6 . 0</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.08" justify="left" indent="17">Visions &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c</hi><space extent="16.5"/>5 . 5 . 0</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.09" justify="left" indent="17">Thel<space extent="22"/>3 . 3 . 0</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.10" justify="left" indent="17">Songs of <choice><orig>Inn.</orig><reg>Innocence</reg></choice> &amp; <choice><orig>Exp.</orig><reg>Experience</reg></choice><space extent="6"/>10 .10 . 0</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.11" justify="left" indent="17">Urizen<space extent="20"/>6 . 6 . 0</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.12" justify="left" indent="4">The Little Card I
                        will do as soon as Possible but when you Consider that</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.13" justify="left">I have been reduced to a
                        Skeleton from which I am slowly recovering you</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.14" justify="left">will I hope have Patience with
                        me</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.15" justify="left" indent="7">Flaxman is Gone &amp;
                        we must All soon follow every one to his Own</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.16" justify="left">Eternal House Leaving the
                        Delusive Goddess Nature &amp; her Laws to get</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.17" justify="left">into Freedom from all Law of the
                        Members into The Mind in which every</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.18" justify="left">one is King &amp; Priest in his
                        own House God send it so on Earth as it is<note>Erdman (page 784) reads
                            "send" as "Send".</note></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.19" justify="left">in Heaven</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.20" justify="left" indent="25">I am Dear Sir Yours
                        Affectionately</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.21" justify="left" indent="30">William Blake</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.22" justify="left" indent="2">12 April 1827</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.03.22" justify="left" indent="2">N 3 Fountain Court
                        Strand</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04" dbi="lt12april1827.1.4.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Notes by George Cumberland and George Cumberland's
                    card</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </Objnumber></Objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.5 x 10.45 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) and first verso (Object 3). This folded sheet was
                        folded further to form a sealed letter packet. The address appears on the
                        second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed
                        packet. Notes in another hand, identified as George Cumberland's by Bentley
                            (*Writings* volume 2, page 1668) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 169n3), appear on the second recto (object
                        4), to which is attached a copy of the calling card produced by Blake for
                        Cumberland and mentioned in both Blake's letter and Cumberland's notes.
                        Images of the fully unfolded letter and a copy of George Cumberland's card
                        are available under Related Works in the Archive.</p><p>Cumberland's notes on Object 4, lines 1-12, are transcribed along with the
                        text from the card by Blake.</p></objnote><windowsize width="940" height="1050"/></physdesc><related objectid="esxxi.1.spb.01" ovp="noindex"/><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.01" justify="left" indent="1">He died on <choice><orig>aug</orig><reg>August</reg></choice> 12. 1827 in the back room of the first floor</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.02" justify="left" indent="2">of N 3 Fountain Court
                        in the Strand, and was buried</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.03" justify="left" indent="3">in Bunhill fields
                        burying ground on the 17 <choice><orig>aug</orig><reg>August</reg></choice> 25 feet</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.04" justify="left" indent="4">from the North wall N
                        80..</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.05" justify="left"><hi rend="underline">T.
                            Smith</hi>, says his disease was the bile mixing with his</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.06" justify="left" indent="1">blood — in his random
                        way of writing —and considering the</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.07" justify="left" indent="2">malignity of this
                        Smith in his infamous biography of Nollekens</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.08" justify="left" indent="3">it is fortunate the
                        he speaks no ill of him.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.09" justify="left" indent="4">My little Message
                        card was the last thing he executed<note>Bentley (*Writings*
                            volume 2, page 1669n9) reads "My" as "my" and "Message" as
                            "message".</note></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.10" justify="left" indent="4">and he dated it thus
                        — <choice><orig>W.</orig><reg>William</reg></choice> Blake inv &amp; sc.</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.11" justify="left" indent="26">A Æ 70
                        1827.</l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.12" justify="left" indent="4">The widow charged me
                        3.3 for it and £3.3.– for the Job</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.13" justify="left" indent="20">M.<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Cumberland.<note><illus filename="lt12april1827.4.13.note.jpg"/>The text of the attached,
                            engraved card produced by Blake for Cumberland is transcribed on lines
                            13-15. A copy of George Cumberland's card is available as a separate
                            work through the Index of Works in the Archive and as a Related Work on
                            the Object View Page.</note></l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.14" justify="left" indent="37"><hi rend="subscript">W Blake inv &amp; sc.</hi></l><l n="lt12april1827.1.ltr.04.15" justify="left" indent="37"><hi rend="superscript">A Æ 70 1827</hi></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>