<bad id="lt12march1804.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to William Hayley, 12 March 1804" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="morgan" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-12april1804"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to William Hayley, 12 March 1804"><main>Letter to William Hayley, 12 March 1804</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 14.1KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 218KB
                to 1100KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to his trial for sedition.
                <lb/>
                The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the next stage of Blake’s life.  <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;    <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.   <lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.   <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.  
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2014 Morgan Library. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>December 2013-January 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to William Hayley, 12 March 1804</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1804.D">1804</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>full sheet 23.0 x 37.0 cm.<note>Full sheet and Leaf Size dimensions (height
                        x width) are given according to the vertical orientation of the body of
                        Blake's letter; see the note on Number of Leaves, below. Object 1 has been
                        reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as would be customary when
                        reading the address.</note></objsize><numberleaves>2<note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter
                        appears on the first recto (Object 2) of the folded sheet. This folded sheet
                        was folded further to form a sealed packet for posting. The address appears
                        on the second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the
                        sealed packet. The interior pages of the folded packet, the reverse sides of
                        Objects 1 and 2, are not photographed.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>23.0 x 18.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper</support><watermark>design</watermark><binding>none</binding><postmark>"6", "M . R / B 12 / [1]804"</postmark><sealDesc>none</sealDesc><addressee>William Hayley</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Morgan Library and Museum</name><note>William Hayley; sold from the Hayley Correspondence, Sotheby's, 20 May 1878,
                    lot 7 (£2.15s. to Waller); sold from the collection of Joseph Mayer of
                    Liverpool, Sotheby's, 19 July 1887 in lot 189, which included an unspecified
                    copy of *Nollekens*, with 450 portraits and 200 letters
                    including Blake’s letters of 12 March 1804, 31 March 1804, 27 April 1804, 28
                    September 1804 (£10.5s. to Robson); acquired by H. Buxton Forman; sold from
                    the Buxton Forman collection at the Anderson Galleries in New York, 15 March
                    1920, lot 69 ($125); in 1925 in the possession of Arthur F. Egner, New Jersey;
                    acquired by Mary E. Malone; purchased in 1976 by Charles A. Ryskamp, Princeton,
                    N.J.; given to Morgan Library and Museum by Ryskamp in memory of Grace Lansing
                    Lambert, 2005; Morgan Library and Museum.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Morgan Library and Museum</institution><addressline>29 East 36th Street</addressline><addressline>New York, NY 10016</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 212-685-0610</addressline><addressline>Fax: 212-481-3484</addressline><addressline>E-mail: media@morganlibrary.org</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.morganlibrary.org</addressline><department>Department of Literary and Historical Manuscripts</department><collection>Morgan Library and Museum</collection><repositoryid label="Accession Number">MA 6334</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt12march1804.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt12march1804.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>18.5 x 23.0 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) of the folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded
                        further to form a sealed packet for posting. The address appears on the
                        second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed
                        packet. The interior pages of the folded packet, the reverse sides of
                        Objects 1 and 2, are not photographed.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">To</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="4">William Hayley Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="5">Felpham<space extent="3"/>near</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left" indent="12">Chichester</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left" indent="14">Sussex</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt12march1804.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I begin with the latter end of your letter</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.0 x 18.5 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) of the folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded
                        further to form a sealed packet for posting. The address appears on the
                        second verso (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed
                        packet. The interior pages of the folded packet, the reverse sides of
                        Objects 1 and 2, are not photographed.</p><p>In the upper left corner of Object 2 what appears to be an empty set symbol,
                        "∅", or a slashed zero, has been inscribed in pencil, followed by
                        "[72?] / see Gilchrist / vol 1 [p. 180?]", in the same unknown hand. Blake's
                        letter of 12 March 1804 appears on page 205 of Alexander Gilchrist's *Life Of William Blake* volume 1 (London: Macmillan, 1880),
                        the volume this note appears to be referencing. In the upper right corner of
                        Object 2 the unclear characters "b q E 0 5 2" are inscribed in pencil in an
                        unknown hand.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">Dear Sir</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="8">I begin with the
                        latter end of your letter &amp;</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">grieve more for Miss Pooles i<subst><del type="overstrike"><gap reason="overwrite" extent="2"/></del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">ll</add></subst> health than for my</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">failure in sending proofs tho I
                        am verry sorry that</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">I cannot send before Saturdays
                        Coach. Engr<add type="overwrite" place="inline">avin</add>g</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">is Eternal work. the two plates
                        are almost finishd <del type="overstrike">You</del></l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">You will recieve proofs of them
                        for Lady Hesketh. whose</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left"><unclear resp="nw">c</unclear>opy of Cowpers letters ought to be printed in<note><illus filename="lt12march1804.2.8.note.jpg"/>Part of the "c" of "copy" is
                            obscured by the gap caused by the remnant of the seal along the left
                            edge of Object 2.</note></l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left"><gap agent="cutaway" extent="2"/>tters of Gold &amp; ornamented with Jewels of Heaven<note><illus filename="lt12march1804.2.9.note.jpg"/>The first letters of line 9,
                            ostensibly the "le" of "[le]tters" are obscured by the gap caused by the
                            remnant of the seal along the left edge of Object 2.</note></l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">Havilah Eden &amp; all the
                        countries where Jewels abound</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">I curse &amp; bless Engraving
                        alternately because it</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">takes so much time &amp; is so
                        untractable. <choice><sic>tho</sic><reg>though</reg></choice></l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">capable of such beauty &amp;
                        perfection.</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left" indent="5">My wife desires with
                        me to Express her</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left">Love to you Praying for Miss Po<subst><del type="overwrite">l</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">o</add></subst>les perfect</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left">recovery &amp; we both
                        remain</l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left">March 12<space extent="9"/>Your
                            Affecti<unclear resp="nw">onate</unclear></l><l n="lt12march1804.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left" indent="5">1804<space extent="15"/><hi rend="underscore">Will Blake</hi></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>