<bad id="lt14july1826.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, 14 July 1826" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="morgan" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-14july1826"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to John Linnell, 14 July 1826"><main>Letter to John Linnell, 14 July 1826</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 13KB; 6 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 140KB
                to 520KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died.
                <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”  <lb/><lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London.  His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.  Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite extraordinary thing.  If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/>
                In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.  We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/>
                Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2013 Morgan Library and Museum. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to John Linnell, 14 July 1826</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1826.F">1826</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>3</numberobj><objorder>1-3</objorder><objsize>full sheet 20.9 x 33.2 cm.<note>Unfolded full sheet and Leaf Size
                        dimensions (height x width) are given according to the vertical orientation
                        of the body of Blake's letter; see the note on Number of Leaves, below.
                        Object 1 has been reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as would be
                        customary when reading the address.</note></objsize><numberleaves>2<note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with a witnessed
                        statement on the first recto (object 3) and a personal message on the second
                        recto (object 2), both signed by Blake. This folded sheet was folded further
                        to form a packet. The address appears on the second verso (object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the folded packet. The blank first recto is
                        not pictured.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>20.9 x 16.6 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper</support><watermark>SMITH &amp; ALLNUTT / 1815</watermark><binding>loose</binding><postmark>none</postmark><sealDesc>none</sealDesc><addressee>John Linnell</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Morgan Library and Museum</name><date>1960</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>$400</price><note>John Linnell; lent with other Linnell papers to A.H. Palmer; found by Palmer's
                    son, Bryan Palmer, in 1959; purchased through the Fellows Fund on 15 February
                    1960 by the Morgan Library.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Morgan Library and Museum</institution><addressline>225 Madison Avenue</addressline><addressline>New York, NY 10016</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 212-685-0008</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 212-590-0315</addressline><addressline>Fax, Reader Sevices: 212-768-5615</addressline><addressline>Email, Reader Services: readingroom@themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>URL, Reading Room:
                    http://www.themorgan.org/research/reading.asp</addressline><department>Literary and Historical Manuscripts</department><collection>Morgan Library and Museum</collection><repositoryid label="Accession number">MA 2021</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt14july1826.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt14july1826.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.6 x 20.9 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with a witnessed statement on
                        the first recto (object 3) and a personal message on the second recto
                        (object 2), both signed by Blake. This folded sheet was folded further to
                        form a packet. The address appears on the second verso (object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the folded packet. The blank first recto is
                        not pictured.</p></objnote><windowsize width="975" height="805"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">To</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="4">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Linnell</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="5">Cirencester Place</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left" indent="9"><choice><orig>Fitz Roy</orig><reg>Fitzroy</reg></choice>. Square</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt14july1826.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I am so much better</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">object 2 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.9 x 16.6 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with a witnessed statement on
                        the first recto (object 3) and a personal message on the second recto
                        (object 2), both signed by Blake. This folded sheet was folded further to
                        form a packet. The address appears on the second verso (object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the folded packet. The blank first recto is
                        not pictured.</p></objnote><windowsize width="777" height="1000"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left" indent="2">Dear Sir</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="10">I am so much better
                        that I have hopes of</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">fulfilling my expectation &amp;
                        desire of Visiting Hampstead</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">I am nevertheless very
                        considerably <choice><orig>weakend</orig><reg>weakened</reg></choice> by the Last<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2,
                            page 1659) reads "nevertheless" as "never the less". Erdman (page 779)
                            reads "Last" as "last".</note></l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">severe attacks Pray remember me
                        with Kind Love to<note>Erdman (page 779) reads "Kind" as "kind".</note></l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>
                        Linnell &amp; her lovely Family</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left" indent="23">Yours Sincerely</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left" indent="1">July 14:1826 <space extent="17"/>William Blake</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03" dbi="lt14july1826.1.3.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Witnessed Statement to John Linnell</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A3">object 3 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.9 x 16.6 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with a witnessed statement on
                        the first recto (object 3) and a personal message on the second recto
                        (object 2), both signed by Blake. This folded sheet was folded further to
                        form a packet. The address appears on the second verso (object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the folded packet. The blank first recto is
                        not pictured.</p><p>Near the bottom right corner "<hi rend="u">See over</hi>" is inscribed in
                        pencil in an unknown hand.</p></objnote><windowsize width="795" height="1005"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03.01" justify="left" indent="1">To M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Linnell _ July 14: 1826</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03.02" justify="left" indent="2">I hereby Declare. That
                            M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John Linnell<note>Keynes (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, page 161) reads "Declare" as "declare".</note></l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03.03" justify="left">has Purchased of Me. The Plates
                        &amp; <choice><orig>Copy-right</orig><reg>Copyright</reg></choice></l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03.04" justify="left">of Job; &amp; the same is his
                        sole Property</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03.05" justify="left" indent="3">Witness <space extent="10"/>William Blake</l><l n="lt14july1826.1.ltr.03.06" justify="left" indent="14"><choice><orig><hi rend="u">Edw<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Jno
                                Chance</hi></orig><reg>Edward John Chance</reg></choice><note>The second signature, signed by the witness to this statement, is not
                            in Blake's hand. Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page
                            1659n2) identifies this signature and witness as Edward John Chance,
                            Linnell's nephew.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>