<bad id="lt16july1826.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, 16 July 1826" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-16july1826"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to John Linnell, 16 July 1826"><main>Letter to John Linnell, 16 July 1826</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 17KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 145KB
                to 550KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died.
                <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”  <lb/><lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London.  His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.  Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite extraordinary thing.  If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/>
                In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.  We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/>
                Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2013 Huntington Library and Art Gallery. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to John Linnell, 16 July 1826</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1826.G">1826</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>full sheet 21 x 16.7 cm.<note>Full sheet and Leaf Size dimensions (height x
                        width) are given according to the vertical orientation of the body of
                        Blake's letter (Object 2). Object 1 has been reoriented vertically in the
                        Object View Page, as would be customary when reading the address.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1<note>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the
                        other side (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed
                        packet for posting. The address appears on what would have been the exterior
                        of the sealed packet (Object 1). Material, probably glued paper or tape,
                        used to repair the tear caused by the seal is visible along one edge of the
                        letter.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>21 x 16.7 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper</support><watermark>RUSE &amp; TURNERS / 1810</watermark><binding>loose</binding><postmark>"T.P / StrandCO" and "[number obscured].NOON.10 / 17.JY / 1826"</postmark><sealDesc>remnant present</sealDesc><addressee>John Linnell</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</name><date>1918</date><dealer>George D. Smith</dealer><price>£84<note>This price includes all items in lot 214 in the 1918 Linnell sale;
                        see the note on provenance below.</note></price><note>John Linnell; sold from Linnell's estate, Christie's, 15 March 1918, in lot
                    214 with 12 (?) other letters by Blake (£84 to the dealer George D. Smith acting
                    for Henry E. Huntington) including 9 (?) letters by Blake to John Linnell of 10
                    November 1825, 19 May 1826, 5 July 1826, 29 July 1826, 1 August 1826, 27 January
                    1827, 2 undated letters (one probably of March 1825, inscribed "12 O Clock /
                    Wednesday" with an 1818 watermark, and the other probably of February 1827), and
                    probably 3 July 1827; 2 letters by Blake to Mrs. Linnell, one of 11 October 1825
                    and one undated (inscribed "Sunday Morning", probably of 5 February 1826); and
                    probably a draft of Blake's letter to Willey Reveley, undated, written on
                    Reveley's letter of 18 October 1791 to Blake.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</institution><addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline><addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2100</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 626-405-2191</addressline><addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 626-405-3477</addressline><addressline>E-mail, Reader Services:
                    readerregistration@huntington.org</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline><department>Manuscripts</department><repositoryid label="Call number">HM 20010</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt16july1826.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt16july1826.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.7 x 21 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet for
                        posting. The address appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        sealed packet (Object 1). Material, probably glued paper or tape, used to
                        repair the tear caused by the seal is visible along the top edge of object
                        1.</p><p>In the margin to the left of the address an "X" is inscribed in an unknown
                        hand.</p></objnote><windowsize width="1025" height="830"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="1">To</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="6">John Linnell <choice><orig>Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></orig><reg>Esquire</reg></choice></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left">Cirencester Place</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left" indent="12">FitzRoy
                            Square<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1660),
                            Erdman (page 779), and Keynes (*Letters*, page 222) read
                            "FitzRoy" as "Fitzroy".</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt16july1826.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I have been ever since taking Dr Youngs
                    Addition</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>21 x 16.7 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet for
                        posting. The address appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        sealed packet (Object 1). Material, probably glued paper or tape, used to
                        repair the tear caused by the seal is visible along the left edge of object
                        2, near line 14.</p><p> In the bottom left corner "(9)" is inscribed in pencil in an unknown
                        hand.</p></objnote><windowsize width="800" height="1055"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">Dear Sir</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="7">I have been ever since
                        taking <choice><orig>D <hi rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Doctor</reg></choice><choice><orig>Youngs </orig><reg>Young</reg></choice><subst><del type="overwrite">a</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">A</add></subst>ddition to</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left" indent="26"><substSpan spanto="B1"/><add type="insertion" place="supralinear" symbol="caret">The Addition</add><note><illus filename="lt16july1826.2.3.note.jpg"/>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1660) and Keynes (*Letters*, page 162) read "The" as "the".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">M<hi rend="superscript">r </hi><choice><orig>Finchams</orig><reg>Fincham</reg></choice> Practise with me (<del type="overstrike">it</del><anchor xml:id="B1"/><add type="insertion" place="inline"><hi rend="subscript">^</hi></add> is dandelion) In a Species of <note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 162) reads "Species" as "species".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">Delirium &amp; in Pain too much
                        for Thought It is now passed as I hope<note>Erdman (page 779) reads
                            "Delirium" as "Delireum"; Keynes (*Letters*, page 162)
                            reads "delirium".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">But the moment I got ease of
                        Body. began Pain of Mind <gap reason="cancellation" extent="5" unit="character"/><note><illus filename="lt16july1826.2.6.note.jpg"/>Keynes (*Letters*, page 162) does not include the deletion in his
                            transcription; Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1660)
                            reads the deletion uncertainly as "it is".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">&amp; that not a Small one It is
                        about The Name of the Child which<note>Keynes (*Letters*,
                            page 162) reads "Small" as "small".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">Certainly ought to be Thomas.
                        after M<hi rend="superscript">rs </hi><choice><orig>Linnells</orig><reg>Linnell</reg></choice> Father It will</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left" indent="39"><add type="insertion" place="supralinear" symbol="caret">&amp; on my
                            Part</add></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">be brutal not to say Worse for it
                        is worse In my opinion<add type="insertion" place="inline" symbol="caret"><hi rend="subscript">^</hi></add>. Pray <note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 162) reads the
                            first instance of "Worse" as "worse".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">Reconsider it if it is not too
                        late It very much troubles Me as a</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left" indent="18"><substSpan spanto="leafmonster"/><add type="insertion" place="inline">The</add></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">Crime in which I shall <del type="overstrike">a</del><anchor xml:id="leafmonster"/> Principal. Pray Excuse this hearty<note><illus filename="lt16july1826.2.13.note.jpg"/>Erdman (page 780) and
                            Keynes (*Letters*, page 162) read "hearty" as
                            "hasty".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left"><gap agent="cutaway" extent="1"/><choice><sic>xpostulation</sic><reg>Expostulation</reg></choice> &amp; believe me to be Yours Sincerely<note><illus filename="lt16july1826.2.14.note.jpg"/>A tear in the page
                            partially removed the first letter of line 14. Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1660), Erdman (page 780), and Keynes
                                (*Letters*, page 162) read "Expostulation".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left" indent="6">Sunday Afternoon
                            <space extent="16"/> William Blake</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left" indent="6">July 16 —1826</l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left" indent="9">P.S.<space extent="3"/>Fincham is a Pupil of <choice><orig>Abernethy's</orig><reg>Abernethy</reg></choice> this is what<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2,
                            page 1660) reads "Abernethy's" as "Abernathy's".</note></l><l n="lt16july1826.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left" indent="6">gives me great
                        pleasure I did not know it before yesterday from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fincham</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>