<bad id="lt18oct1791.1" type="ltr" work="Letter from Willey Reveley, c. 18 October 1791" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-18oct1791">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter from Willey Reveley, c. 18 October 1791">
                    <main>Letter from Willey Reveley, c. 18 October 1791</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                        Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                            Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 17.6KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from approx. 500KB
                to 1.5MB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>August 2019</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of digital editions of our third installment of Blake's 95 known letters. The latest 28, drawn from nine collections, span nearly the entire chronological range of Blake’s correspondence from 1791 to 1827, the year of his death. Three of this group are by Blake’s correspondents&#8212;included here because of especially tight connections with their associated documents. (Those pairs are 18 October [Reveley] and October 1791 [Blake]; 23 September [Blake] and September 1800 [Butts]; 18 December [Cumberland] and 19 December 1808 [Blake].)                
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                A sample of the many highlights from the 28 new letters might feature
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --2 October 1800 (to Blake’s London patron Thomas Butts): fresh with optimism after his recent arrival in Felpham, Blake’s awkward amalgam of down to earth excuse-making with 78 lines of visionary verses:
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                To my Friend Butts I write<lb/>
                My First Vision of Light<lb/>
                . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
                I saw you and your wife<lb/>
                By the fountains of Life<lb/>
                Such the Vision to me<lb/>
                Appeard on the Sea<lb/>
                Mrs Butts will I hope Excuse my not having finishd the Portrait.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                --16 August 1803 (to Thomas Butts): Blake’s “whole outline” of his dangerous and distressing encounter with the soldier Private John Scolfield in Blake’s garden, which resulted in a “very unwarrantable warrant,” a charge of sedition against Blake, depositions, a lawyer, a trial, and, finally, acquittal: a “perilous adventure” for sure. Its imaginative afterlife was the appearance of Scolfield and his companion Private John Cock as shady Sons of Albion in Blake’s illuminated epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --18 January 1808 (to Ozias Humphry): Blake’s detailed description of his intricate 1808 watercolor <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> (Petworth House, Sussex), commissioned by the Countess of Egremont on Humphry’s recommendation. (We reproduce one of the three copies that Blake made of his description; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Records</hi>, pages 249-50.)  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --25 November 1825 (to John Linnell): sometimes called the kitchen letter for Blake’s brief contention that his flat at 3 Fountain Court would be the optimal place (the press is already assembled there, the lighting is better) for printing a copy of his engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>. For details of the unearthing of the letter—which turned up in a box of autograph scraps in the archives of publisher John Murray&#8212;and its surprisingly rich contexts in Blake’s workaday life, see Angus Whitehead, “The Uncollected Letters of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 80.3: 423-35.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake's hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Once again, special thanks to the City of Westminster Archives Centre for courteous assistance, excellent digital images, and willingness to share Kerrison Preston’s Blake library with the world. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>This image copyright © 2019 Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication of 28 letters written between 1791 and 1827</change>
                <date>April 2019-August 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter from Willey Reveley, c. 18 October 1791</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>Willey Reveley<role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1791.A">1791<note>Willey Reveley's letter to Blake is dated "Oct
                    18" in Reveley's hand, but the partial postmark stamp, "C OCT / 7", suggests
                    it may have actually been posted by [1]7 October 1791. Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1521) notes "The date of the letter is in
                    some doubt [...] for though Reveley clearly dated the letter 'Oct 18', the
                    numeral in the postmark is equally clearly a '7'. I cannot reconcile these
                    facts." Blake's undated reply to Reveley was written on the back of the
                    letter he received by post from Reveley. According to Essick (*Huntington*, page 185), "Blake refers to his willingness to engrave
                    for Reveley 'by the end of January' some illustrations for James Stuart and
                    Nicholas Revett, *The Antiquities of Athens*. Volume 3
                    (1794) of that work [...] includes 4 plates by
                    Blake dated 3 April 1792 in the imprints. Thus, Blake must have written his
                    note, a direct reply to Reveley's letter, shortly after 18 October 1791."
                    See also the note on Number of Leaves, below. </note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>2</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-2</objorder>
                <objsize>Full sheet 15.0-18.9 x 23.2 cm.<note>Unfolded full sheet and Leaf Size
                    dimensions (height x width) are given according to the vertical orientation
                    of the body of Reveley's letter to Blake; see the note on Number of Leaves,
                    below. Object 1 has been reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as
                    would be customary when reading the address.</note>
                </objsize>
                <numberleaves>2<note>The full sheet bearing Reveley's letter (Object 2) was folded
                    into two leaves, which were folded further to form a packet for posting.
                    Blake's address (Object 1) appears on what would have been the exterior of
                    the folded packet. The leaf bearing Object 1 is torn and the postmark partially missing.
                    Blake's undated response to Reveley, not pictured, is written on the reverse
                    side of the leaf bearing Blake's address (Object 1); see the note on
                    Composition Date, above. Blake's letter to Reveley, dated
                    c. October 1791, is also available as a separate work through the Index
                    of Letters.</note>
                </numberleaves>
                <leafsize>15.0-18.9 cm x 11.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>CURTEIS &amp; SON</watermark>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <postmark>C OCT / 7 / [remainder torn away]</postmark>
                <sealDesc>none</sealDesc>
                <addressee>William Blake</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</name>
                <date>1918</date>
                <dealer>George D. Smith</dealer>
                <price>£84<note>This price includes all items in lot 214 in the 1918 Linnell sale;
                    see the note on provenance below.</note>
                </price>
                <note>Reveley's letter to Blake and Blake's response are written on the same sheet of paper and </note>
                <note>John Linnell; sold from Linnell's estate, Christie's, 15 March 1918, not listed in the Linell auction catalogue but probably
                    included with lot 214 with 12 other letters (not counting Blake's response written on the same sheet of paper) (Essick *Huntington*, pages 184 and 190; Keynes *Bibliography*, page 68; Keynes *Letters*, page 183); although Blake's letter to Reveley
                    appears to be an unsent draft, no fair copy has been located.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</institution>
                <addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline>
                <addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline>
                <addressline>United States</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2100</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Readers Services: 626-405-2191</addressline>
                <addressline>E-mail, Readers Services:
                    readerregistration@huntington.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline>
                <department>Manuscripts</department>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">HM 20020</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt18oct1791.1.1.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>15.0-18.9 x 11.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet bearing Reveley's letter (Object 2) was folded into two
                        leaves, which were folded further to form a packet for posting. Blake's
                        address (Object 1) appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        folded packet. The leaf bearing Object 1 is torn and the postmark is partially missing.
                        Blake's undated response to Reveley, not pictured, is written on the reverse
                        side of the leaf bearing Blake's address (Object 1); see the note on
                        Composition Date in the Work Information. Blake's letter to
                        Reveley, dated c. October 1791, is available as a separate work
                        through the Index of Letters.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="7"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left"><choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                        Blake Engraver</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left">Hercules Buildings</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="2">Westminster Bridge</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt18oct1791.1.2.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">Mr Reveleys Compts to Mr Blake</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2</objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>18.9 x 11.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet bearing Reveley's letter (Object 2) was folded into two
                        leaves, which were folded further to form a packet for posting. Blake's
                        address (Object 1) appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        folded packet. The leaf bearing Object 1 is torn and the postmark is partially missing.
                        Blake's undated response to Reveley, not pictured, is written on the reverse
                        side of the leaf bearing Blake's address (Object 1); see the note on
                        Composition Date in the Work Information. Blake's letter to
                        Reveley, dated c. October 1791, is available as a separate work
                        through the Index of Letters.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="5"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left" indent="2"><choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice> <choice><orig>Reveleys</orig><reg>Reveley's</reg></choice> <choice><orig>Comp<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></orig><reg>Compliments</reg></choice> to <choice><orig>M<hi
                            rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice> Blake</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left">if he wishes to engrave any</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">of Mr Pars's drawings for the</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">Antiquities of Athens, &amp;
                        can</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">do them by the end of January</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left"><choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice>
                        Reveley will be glad to Some<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 4)
                            reads "Some" as "some".</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">to him.</l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left" indent="2">Great Titchfield <choice><orig>St</orig><reg>Street</reg></choice></l>
                    <l n="lt18oct1791.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left" indent="4"><choice><orig>Oct</orig><reg>October</reg></choice> 18</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>     
    </objdesc>
</bad>
