<bad id="lt1827.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, c. February 1827" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="lc" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-1827"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to John Linnell, c. February 1827"><main>Letter to John Linnell, c. February 1827</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 15KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 165KB
                to 750KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died.
                <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”  <lb/><lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London.  His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.  Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite extraordinary thing.  If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/>
                In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.  We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/>
                Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2013 William Blake Archive. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to John Linnell, c. February 1827</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1827.B">1827<note>Undated; Blake writes to John Linnell that he
                        "shall Soon get Proofs of these Four [engravings of Dante] which I have
                        &amp; beg the favor of you to send me the two Plates of Dante which you have
                        that I may finish them sufficiently" (Object 2, lines 7-9). These engravings
                        of <hi rend="i">Blake's Illustrations of Dante</hi>, six of seven eventual
                        plates chosen for engraving from Blake's 102 drawings illustrating Dante's
                            <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi> commissioned by John Linnell, were begun
                        by 1826 and left incomplete at Blake's death on 12 August 1827. <hi rend="i">Blake's Illustrations of Dante</hi> and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to
                            Dante's "Divine Comedy"</hi> are available as separate works through the
                        Index of Works. Blake's reference to "the Removal" suggests Blake is
                        responding to Linnell's attempt to persuade the Blakes to move to
                        Cirencester Place, which Linnell refers to in his journal entry for 7
                        February 1827: "To M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Blake to speak to him
                        [about] living at C[irencester] P[lace]" (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
                        pages 338, 592). See also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page
                        1664n1.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>full sheet 20.8 x 16.5 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1<note>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the
                        other side (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed
                        packet. The address appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        sealed packet (Object 1).</note></numberleaves><leafsize>20.8 x 16.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1759)
                        notes that similarly spaced chain lines may indicate that Blake used the
                        same stock in this letter as that bearing the "RUSE &amp; TURNERS / 1810"
                        watermark present in his letters of 31 January 1826, 16 July 1826, and 12
                        April 1827.</note></support><watermark>none</watermark><binding>loose</binding><postmark>none</postmark><sealDesc>wafer</sealDesc><addressee>John Linnell</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Library of Congress</name><date>1918</date><dealer>Swayne</dealer><price>29 guineas<note>lot 211 in the 1918 Linnell sale; see the note on provenance
                        below.</note></price><note>John Linnell; sold from Linnell's estate, Christie's, 15 March 1918, lot 211
                    (29 guineas to Swayne); sold posthumously by Willis Vickery at Anderson
                    Galleries, American Art Association, 1 March 1933, lot 22; resold by Anderson
                    Galleries, American Art Association, 25 May 1938, lot 74; Lessing J. Rosenwald
                    Collection, Library of Congress, Washington D.C.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Library of Congress</institution><addressline>101 Independence Ave SE</addressline><addressline>Washington, DC 20540</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 202-707-5000</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/</addressline><department>Rare Book and Special Collections Division</department><repositoryid label="call number">Rosenwald Coll. ms. no. 6</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt1827.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt1827.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.8 x 16.5 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet. The
                        address appears on what would have been the exterior of the sealed packet
                        (Object 1).</p><p>Two inscriptions in an unknown hand appear on Object 1: an "X" in the margin
                        above the address and "38.76" along the bottom edge.</p></objnote><windowsize width="800" height="1045"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="2">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Linnell</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left">Cirencester Place</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="5">Fitzroy Square</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt1827.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt1827.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I thank you for the Five Pounds</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.8 x 16.5 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet. The
                        address appears on what would have been the exterior of the sealed packet
                        (Object 1).</p><p>Two inscriptions in pencil in an unknown hand appear on Object 2: near the
                        top right corner "[( 13 ) ?", with the "3" appearing to be written over a
                        "2", and near the bottom right corner "[1827] (Feb ?)".</p></objnote><windowsize width="790" height="1025"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left" indent="4">Dear Sir</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="12">I thank you for the Five
                        Pounds <choice><sic>recievd</sic><reg>received</reg></choice> to day<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page
                            1664) and Erdman (page 781) read "to day" as "to Day".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">am getting better every Morning but
                        slowly. as I am still feeble</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">&amp; tottering. tho all the symptoms
                        of my complaint seem almost<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume
                            2, page 1664), Erdman (page 782), and Keynes (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>,
                            page 166) read "symptoms" as "Symptoms".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">gone as the fine weather is very
                        beneficial &amp; comfortable to me</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">I go on as I think improving my
                        Engravings of Dante more &amp; more</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">&amp; shall soon get Proofs of these
                        Four which I have &amp; beg the favor<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1664) reads "soon" as
                        "Soon".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">of you to send me the two Plates of
                        Dante which you have that I</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">may finish them sufficiently to make
                        some Shew of Colour &amp; Strength</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left" indent="4">I have Thought &amp; Thought
                        of the Removal. &amp; cannot get my Mind<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1664) reads "Thought &amp; Thought" as
                            "Thought &amp; thought".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">out of a state of terrible fear at such
                        a step. the more I think the<note>Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume
                            2, page 1665) and Erdman (page 782) read "state" as "State". Bentley
                                (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1665) reads "step" as
                            "Step".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">more I feel terror at what I <choice><sic>wishd</sic><reg>wished</reg></choice> at first <subst><del><gap reason="overwrite" extent="1"/></del><add type="overwrite" place="inline">&amp;</add></subst> thought it a thing<note><illus filename="lt1827.2.12.note.jpg"/>The
                            ampersand appears to be written over another illegible character or
                            letter.</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">of benefit &amp; Good hope you will
                        attribute it to <unclear resp="nw">the</unclear> right Cause</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left">Intellectual Peculiarity that must be
                        Myself alone shut up in</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left">Myself or Reduced to Nothing. I could
                        tell you of Visions &amp;</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left">d<unclear resp="NW">reams</unclear>
                        upon the Subject I have asked &amp; <choice><sic>intreated</sic><reg>entreated</reg></choice> divine help<note><illus filename="lt1827.2.16a.note.jpg"/><illus filename="lt1827.2.16b.note.jpg"/>The first word of line 16
                            is unclear. Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2, page 1665)
                            reads "Dreams". Erdman (page 782) and Keynes (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>
                            page 166) read "dreams". Bentley (<hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume 2,
                            page 1665), Erdman (page 782), and Keynes (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>,
                            page 166) read "divine" as "Divine".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left">but fear continues upon me &amp; I must
                        relinquish the step that</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left">I had wished to take &amp; still wish
                        but in vain<note>Keynes (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, page 166) reads "wished"
                            as "wish'd".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.19" justify="left" indent="9">Your Success in your
                        Profession is above all things to<note>Erdman (page 782) reads "Success" as
                            "success".</note></l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.20" justify="left">me most gratifying. may it go on to the
                        Perfection you wish</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.21" justify="left">&amp; more <space extent="12"/>So
                        wishes also Yours Sincerely</l><l n="lt1827.1.ltr.02.22" justify="left" indent="34">William Blake</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>