<bad id="lt18jan1808.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="spademan" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-18jan1808">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808">
                    <main>Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                        Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                            Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 19.4KB; 8 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from approx. 148KB
                to 3.7MB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>August 2019</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of digital editions of our third installment of Blake's 95 known letters. The latest 28, drawn from nine collections, span nearly the entire chronological range of Blake’s correspondence from 1791 to 1827, the year of his death. Three of this group are by Blake’s correspondents&#8212;included here because of especially tight connections with their associated documents. (Those pairs are 18 October [Reveley] and October 1791 [Blake]; 23 September [Blake] and September 1800 [Butts]; 18 December [Cumberland] and 19 December 1808 [Blake].)                
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                A sample of the many highlights from the 28 new letters might feature
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --2 October 1800 (to Blake’s London patron Thomas Butts): fresh with optimism after his recent arrival in Felpham, Blake’s awkward amalgam of down to earth excuse-making with 78 lines of visionary verses:
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                To my Friend Butts I write<lb/>
                My First Vision of Light<lb/>
                . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
                I saw you and your wife<lb/>
                By the fountains of Life<lb/>
                Such the Vision to me<lb/>
                Appeard on the Sea<lb/>
                Mrs Butts will I hope Excuse my not having finishd the Portrait.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                --16 August 1803 (to Thomas Butts): Blake’s “whole outline” of his dangerous and distressing encounter with the soldier Private John Scolfield in Blake’s garden, which resulted in a “very unwarrantable warrant,” a charge of sedition against Blake, depositions, a lawyer, a trial, and, finally, acquittal: a “perilous adventure” for sure. Its imaginative afterlife was the appearance of Scolfield and his companion Private John Cock as shady Sons of Albion in Blake’s illuminated epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --18 January 1808 (to Ozias Humphry): Blake’s detailed description of his intricate 1808 watercolor <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> (Petworth House, Sussex), commissioned by the Countess of Egremont on Humphry’s recommendation. (We reproduce one of the three copies that Blake made of his description; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Records</hi>, pages 249-50.)  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --25 November 1825 (to John Linnell): sometimes called the kitchen letter for Blake’s brief contention that his flat at 3 Fountain Court would be the optimal place (the press is already assembled there, the lighting is better) for printing a copy of his engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>. For details of the unearthing of the letter—which turned up in a box of autograph scraps in the archives of publisher John Murray&#8212;and its surprisingly rich contexts in Blake’s workaday life, see Angus Whitehead, “The Uncollected Letters of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 80.3: 423-35.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake's hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Once again, special thanks to the City of Westminster Archives Centre for courteous assistance, excellent digital images, and willingness to share Kerrison Preston’s Blake library with the world. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright &#169; <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>This work copyright &#169; 2019 Benjamin Spademan: Rare Books. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication of 28 letters written between 1791 and 1827</change>
                <date>April 2019-August 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>author,</role>
                    <role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1808">1808
                    <note>According to Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1637), "Blake copied this letter (A) twice, once (B) evidently for the Earl of Egremont or his wife [...], and the second time (C) in February for Ozias Humphry to send to the Earl of Buchan". In *Blake Books Supplement* (page 95), Bentley updates this ordering by referring to John Wilson who "argues plausibly that the first version of the letter was B (sent to the Earl of Egremont), that A (sent to Ozias Humphry) was copied from B, and that C (sent by Humphry to the Earl of Buchan) was copied from A". In any event, the letter copy presented here is what has been historically labeled "A" by scholars.</note>
                </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>4</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-4</objorder>
                <objsize>22 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>2<note>A double leaf written on four sides.</note>
                </numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22 x 18.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>Ivy Mill / 1806</watermark>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <postmark>none</postmark>
                <sealDesc>none</sealDesc>
                <addressee>Ozias Humphry</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Benjamin Spademan</name>
                <date>2015</date>
                <price>&#163;43,750</price>          
                <note>Ozias Humphry; likely passed to his son William Upcott; acquired by J. R. Smith no later than 1828; ownership unknown after 1829 until offered for sale by Thomas Thorp in 1837 for 15s; later in the collection of Major C. H. Simpson of Bath; sold at Sotheby's, 15 March 1916, lot 33 to G. D. Smith for &#163;51; acquired by Oliver R. Barrett; passed to his son Roger W. Barrett; sold at Sotheby's New York, 14 December 1988, lot 58 for &#36;24,000; sold by John Wilson Autographs Ltd at Sotheby's London 14 December 1992, lot 16 for &#163;18,000; Roy Davids Collection; sold at Bonham's 18 March 2015 for &#163;43,750 to dealer Benjamin Spademan.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Benjamin Spademan: Rare Books</institution>
                <addressline>14 Masons Yard - London SW1Y 6BU</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +4420 7930 8499</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: www.benjaminspademan.com/</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>       
<desc id="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt18jan1808.1.1.LT">
    <objtitle>
        <title type="transcribed">The Design of The Last Judgment</title>
        <title type="alt">Letter to Ozias Humphrey</title>, <objid>
            <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
        </objid>
    </objtitle>
    <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>22 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
    </physdesc>
    <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="6">To Ozias Humphry <choice><orig>Esq:<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></orig><reg>Esquire</reg></choice></l>
        </lg>
        <lg justify="left">
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="4">The Design of The Last Judgment, which I have</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left">completed by your recommendation for The Countess of Egremont.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left">it is necessary to give some account of: &#38; its various parts</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left">ought to be described, for the accomodation of those who give it</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.06" justify="left">the <choice><orig>honor</orig><reg>honour</reg></choice> of attention.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.07" justify="left" indent="9">Christ seated on the Throne of Judgment:</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.08" justify="left">The Heavens in Clouds rolling before him &#38; around him, like</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.09" justify="left">a Scroll ready to be consumed in the fires of the Angels; who<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 132) reads "scroll" for "Scroll".</note></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.10" justify="left">descend before his feet with their four trumpets sounding to the</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.11" justify="left">four Winds.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.12" justify="left" indent="9">Beneath; the Earth is <choice><reg>convulsed</reg><orig>convuls'd</orig></choice> with the <choice><orig>labours</orig><reg>labors</reg></choice></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.13" justify="left">of the Resurrection; In the caverns of the Earth is the Dragon</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.14" justify="left">with seven heads &#38; ten horns, Chained by two Angels &#38; above</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.15" justify="left">his Cavern on the Earths Surface, is the Harlot also siezed<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 132) reads "surface" for "Surface".</note></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.16" justify="left">&#38; bound by two Angels with Chains while her Palaces are falling</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.17" justify="left">into ruins &#38; her <choice><reg>Counselor's</reg><orig>Counsellors</orig></choice> &#38; Warriors are descending into the</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.18" justify="left">Abyss in wailings &#38; despair</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.19" justify="left" indent="8">Hell opens beneath the Harlots seat on the left hand</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.01.20" justify="left">into which the Wicked are descending</l>
        </lg>
    </phystext>
</desc>
<desc id="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt18jan1808.1.2.LT">
    <objtitle>
        <title type="editorial">cont.</title>
        <title type="alt">Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808</title>, <objid>
            <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
        </objid>
    </objtitle>
    <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>22 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
    </physdesc>
    <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left" indent="5">The right hand of the Design is appropriated to the <choice><orig>Re-</orig><reg type="split_word">Resurrection</reg></choice></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left"><choice><orig>-surrection</orig><reg>Resurrection</reg></choice> of The Just; the left hand of the Design is <choice><orig>appro-</orig><reg type="split_word">appropriated</reg></choice></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left"><choice><orig>-priated</orig><reg>appropriated</reg></choice> to the Resurrection &#38; Fall of the Wicked</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left" indent="7">Immediately before the Throne of Christ is Adam &#38;</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">Eve, kneeling in humiliation, as representitives of the whole Human</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">Race; Abraham &#38; Moses kneel on each side beneath them; from</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">the Cloud on which Eve kneels &#38; beneath Moses &#38; from the Tables</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">of Stone which utter lightnings; is seen Satan wound round</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">by the Serpent &#38; falling headlong; the Pharisees appear on</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">the left hand pleading their own righteousness before the Throne</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">of Christ: The Book of Death is <choice><orig>opend</orig><reg>opened</reg></choice> on Clouds by two Angels;</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">many groupes of Figures are falling from before the Throne &#38;</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">from the Sea of Fire which flows before the Steps of the Throne;<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 132) reads "steps" for "Steps".</note></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left">on which are seen the Seven Lamps of the Almighty. burning</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left">before the Throne. many Figures <choice><orig>Chaind</orig><reg>chained</reg></choice> &#38; bound together fall <choice><orig>thro'</orig><reg>through</reg></choice></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left">the air, &#38; some are scourged by Spirits with flames of fire into the</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left">Abyss of Hell which opens to recieve them beneath, on the left hand</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left">of the Harlot's seat; where others are howling &#38; descending into the</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.19" justify="left">flames. &#38; in the act of dragging each other into Hell &#38; of <choice><orig>con-</orig><reg type="split_word">contending</reg></choice></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.20" justify="left"><choice><orig>tending</orig><reg>contending</reg></choice> in fighting with each other on the brink of Perdition</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.21" justify="left" indent="9">Before the Throne of Christ on the right hand</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.02.22" justify="left">the Just in humiliation &#38; in exultation, rise <choice><orig>thro'</orig><reg>through</reg></choice> the air,</l>
        </lg>
    </phystext>
</desc>
<desc id="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03" dbi="lt18jan1808.1.3.LT">
    <objtitle>
        <title type="editorial">cont.</title>
        <title type="alt">Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808</title>, <objid>
            <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
        </objid>
    </objtitle>
    <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>22 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
    </physdesc>
    <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.01" justify="left">with their Children &#38; Families; some of whom are bowing before</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.02" justify="left">the Book of Life which is <choice><orig>opend</orig><reg>opened</reg></choice> by two Angels on Clouds; many</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.03" justify="left"><choice><orig>Groupes</orig><reg>Groups</reg></choice> arise with Exultation; among them ins a Figure crowned</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.04" justify="left">with Stars &#38; the moon beneath her feet with six infants around her</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.05" justify="left">She represents the Christian Church; The Green Hills appear</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.06" justify="left">beneath: with the Graves of the Blessed, which are seen bursting</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.07" justify="left">with their births of immortality; Parents &#38; Children embrace</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.08" justify="left">&#38; arise together &#38; in exulting attitudes tell each other, that The</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.09" justify="left">New Jerusalem is ready to descend upon Earth; they arise upon</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.10" justify="left">the air rejoicing! others newly <choice><orig>awakend</orig><reg>awakened</reg></choice> from the Grave stand</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.11" justify="left">upon the Earth embracing &#38; shouting to the Lamb who cometh</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.12" justify="left">in the Clouds with Power &#38; great Glory.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.13" justify="left" indent="8">The whole upper part of the Design is a view of Heaven</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.14" justify="left">opened; around the Throne of Christ, Four Living Creatures filled</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.15" justify="left">with Eyes, attended by seven Angles with the Seven Vials of the</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.16" justify="left">Wrath of God, &#38; above these Seven Angles with the Seven Trumpets</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.17" justify="left">compose the Cloud, which by its rolling away displays the opening</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.18" justify="left">Seats of the Blessed, on the right &#38; the left of which are seen the</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.19" justify="left">Four &#38; Twenty Elders seated on Thrones to Judge the Dead.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.20" justify="left" indent="8">Behind the Seat and Throne of Christ appears the Tabernacle</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.21" justify="left">with its Veil opened; the Candlestick on the right; the Table with</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.22" justify="left"><choice><orig>Shew Bread</orig><reg>Showbread</reg><reg>Shewbread</reg></choice>, on the left; &#38; in the midst, the Cross in place of</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.03.23" justify="left">the Ark, with the two Cherubim bowing over it.</l>
        </lg>
    </phystext>
</desc>
<desc id="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04" dbi="lt18jan1808.1.4.LT">
    <objtitle>
        <title type="editorial">cont.</title>
        <title type="alt">Letter to Ozias Humphry, 18 January 1808</title>, <objid>
            <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
        </objid>
    </objtitle>
    <physdesc desclevel="brief">
        <objsize>22 x 18.5 cm.</objsize>
        <objnote>
        </objnote>
        <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
    </physdesc>
    <phystext>
        <lg justify="left">
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.01" justify="left" indent="3">On the right hand of the Throne of Christ is Baptism.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.02" justify="left">On his left is the <choice><orig>Lords</orig><reg>Lord's</reg></choice> Supper; the two introducers into</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.03" justify="left">Eternal Life. Women with Infants approach the Figure of</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.04" justify="left">an aged apostle which represents Baptism; &#38; on the left hand</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.05" justify="left">the Lords Supper is <choice><orig>administerd</orig><reg>administered</reg></choice> by Angels, from the hands of</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.06" justify="left">another aged Apostle; these kneel on each side of the Throne<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 133) reads "Kneel" for "kneel".</note></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.07" justify="left">which is surrounded by a glory, in the glory many Infants</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.08" justify="left">appear, representing Eternal Creation flowing from The</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.09" justify="left">Divine Humanity in Jesus; who opens the Scroll of Judgment</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.10" justify="left">upon his knees before the Living &#38; the Dead.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.11" justify="left" indent="8">Such is the Design which you my Dear Sir</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.12" justify="left">have been the cause of my producing &#38; which; but</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.13" justify="left">for you might have slept till the Last Judgment.</l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.14" justify="left" indent="23">William Blake<hi rend="u"><space extent="2"/></hi></l>
            <l n="lt18jan1808.1.ltr.04.15" justify="left">18 January 1808.</l>
        </lg>
    </phystext>
</desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
