<bad id="lt18feb1800.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to William Hayley, 18 February 1800" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="wilson" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-18feb1800"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to William Hayley, 18 February 1800"><main>Letter to William Hayley, 18 February 1800</main> :
                                        electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
                                                <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California,
                                        Riverside; and <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of
                                        North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina
                                        at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 18.2KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in
                                size from 278KB to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to his trial for sedition.
                <lb/>
                The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the next stage of Blake’s life.  <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;    <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.   <lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.   <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.                
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
                        and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared
                        in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
                        Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
                        express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                        publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2014 Wilson Library. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>December 2013-January 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to William Hayley, 18 February 1800</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1800.A">1800</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>1</numberobj><objorder>1</objorder><objsize>full page 20.1 x 11.9 cm.<note>Dimensions unknown from
                                                original manuscript; given dimensions refer to the
                                                photographed page of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
                                                  of William Blake</hi> volume 1; see the note on
                                                Provenance in the Work Information.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1<note>Object 1 includes a transcribed fragment of a
                                                manuscript letter by Blake, now lost. The fragment
                                                of Blake's letter appears at the end of the second
                                                paragraph on page 143 (Object 1) of the revised 1880
                                                edition of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life
                                                  of William Blake</hi> volume 1, described in the
                                                note on Provenance in the Work Information. The
                                                Textual Transcription includes only the text
                                                attributed to Blake in his letter to Hayley of 18
                                                February 1800, which is surrounded by biographical
                                                text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors,
                                                possibly including the hands of Anne Gilchrist,
                                                Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also
                                                Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages
                                                24-27). The text not attributed to Blake can be
                                                viewed directly on the Object View Page.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink manuscript lost; <hi rend="i">Life of William
                                                Blake</hi> volume 1 is a letterpress book</medium><inkcolor>unknown from original manuscript; <hi rend="i">Life of
                                                William Blake</hi> volume 1 is printed in black
                                        ink</inkcolor><support>unknown from original manuscript; <hi rend="i">Life of
                                                William Blake</hi> volume 1 is printed on laid
                                        paper</support><watermark>unknown from original manuscript; page 143 (Object 1)
                                        includes the countermark “VanG”, oriented upside down, at
                                        the top left of the page; <hi rend="i">Life of William
                                                Blake</hi> volume 1 printed on paper with a large
                                        central watermark depicting a crown on top of a fleur-de-lis
                                        with illegible cursive script at the bottom of the
                                        fleur-de-lis; countermarks appearing in the volume include
                                        “TDEB”, “LDER”, and “VanG”</watermark><binding>bound in publisher's dark blue-green cloth, elaborately
                                        gilt stamped; a small sticker on the recto of the last
                                        endpaper states "Bound by Burn &amp; Co.”; the front cover
                                        design is based on a drawing in Blake's <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> that is now attributed to Blake's
                                        brother Robert (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> volume
                                        1, page 13); the design on the spine is a modified version
                                        of one of the angels in Blake's engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, Object 16</binding><postmark>unknown</postmark><sealDesc>unknown</sealDesc><addressee>William Hayley</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Rare Book Collection, Wilson Library, University of North
                                        Carolina at Chapel Hill</name><note>William Hayley; original manuscript untraced; letter only
                                        known from printed transcription appearing in <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> volume 1 (London:
                                        Macmillan, 1880). Bentley suggests this letter may have been
                                        "The unidentified letter in the 1880 [Quaritch's General
                                        Catalogue]", but he does not provide further information
                                        (see Bentley, "A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries
                                        in 1995," <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                                        (Summer 2010), page 137n31).<lb/><lb/>The transcribed
                                        fragment from Blake’s letter to William Hayley, 18 February
                                        1800, was among the materials added in the revised and
                                        expanded second edition (1880) of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, "Pictor
                                                Ignotus"</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863). Blake's
                                        posthumous biographer Alexander Gilchrist died in 1861
                                        before completing his biography of Blake, which was finished
                                        by his wife, Anne Gilchrist, with assistance from Dante
                                        Gabriel Rossetti and others (see also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages 24-27).<lb/><lb/> The title
                                        page of the 1880 volume containing the letter reads: "LIFE /
                                        OF / WILLIAM BLAKE / WITH SELECTIONS FROM HIS POEMS AND
                                        OTHER WRITINGS / BY / ALEXANDER GILCHRIST / OF THE MIDDLE
                                        TEMPLE, BARRISTER-AT-LAW / AUTHOR OF "THE LIFE OF WILLIAM
                                        ETTY, R.A." // A NEW AND ENLARGED EDITION / ILLUSTRATED FROM
                                        BLAKE'S OWN WORKS / WITH ADDITIONAL LETTERS AND A MEMOIR OF
                                        THE AUTHOR // IN TWO VOLUMES / VOL. 1 // LONDON / MACMILLAN
                                        AND CO. / 1880 // The Right of Translation is Reserved". The
                                        book was printed by R. Clay, Sons, and Taylor, Bread Street
                                        Hill, London.<lb/><lb/>Images, object notes, and
                                        transcriptions are from a copy in the Rare Book Collection
                                        of the Wilson Library at the University of North Carolina at
                                        Chapel Hill. The copy photographed was owned by Annie G.
                                        Holden, and is inscribed "Annie G. Holden / Xmas 1880" in
                                        brown ink on the recto of the first flyleaf; later in the
                                        library of Tatton Henry Bower of Yorkshire (1867-1931),
                                        whose armorial bookplate is also attached; the Wilson
                                        Library purchased this copy from the dealer Claude Cox in
                                        1978.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Wilson Library</institution><addressline>CB#3936 Wilson Library</addressline><addressline>University of North Carolina at Chapel
                                        Hill</addressline><addressline>Chapel Hill, NC 27514-8890</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 919-962-1143</addressline><addressline>E-mail, Reader Services:
                                        rbcref@email.unc.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.lib.unc.edu/rbc/</addressline><department>Rare Books, Special Collections</department><repositoryid label="Call number">PR4146 .G5 1880 C.1
                                        V.1</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt18feb1800.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt18feb1800.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">has been approved [...] by Mr.
                                        Flaxman</title><objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Object 1 includes a transcribed fragment of a manuscript
                                                letter by Blake, now lost. The fragment of Blake's
                                                letter appears at the end of the second paragraph on
                                                page 143 (Object 1) of the revised 1880 edition of
                                                Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William
                                                  Blake</hi> volume 1, described in the note on
                                                Provenance in the Work Information.</p><p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text
                                                attributed to Blake in his letter to Hayley of 18
                                                February 1800, which is surrounded by biographical
                                                text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors,
                                                possibly including the hands of Anne Gilchrist,
                                                Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also
                                                Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pages
                                                24-27). The text not attributed to Blake can be
                                                viewed directly on the Object View Page.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="21"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt18feb1800.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left"><space extent="28"/>has been approved,<note>The full
                                                  sentence surrounding the quotes from Blake's
                                                  letter on lines 1-5 reads "This was the occasion
                                                  of / Blake's first coming into direct personal
                                                  communication with / Hayley, to whom he submitted
                                                  an impression of the plate / of <hi rend="i">The
                                                  Death of Demosthenes</hi>, which 'has been
                                                  approved,' he / writes, February 18th, 1800, 'by
                                                  Mr. Flaxman;' adding his / hopes that the young
                                                  sculptor 'will soon be well enough to / 'make
                                                  hundreds of designs both for the engraver and the
                                                  / sculptor.' "</note></l><l n="lt18feb1800.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left"><space extent="22"/>by Mr. Flaxman;<space extent="8"/></l><l n="lt18feb1800.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left"><space extent="23"/>will soon be well enough to</l><l n="lt18feb1800.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left">make hundreds
                                                of designs both for the engraver and the</l><l n="lt18feb1800.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left">sculptor.</l></lg><vspace extent="12"/></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>