<bad id="lt22jan1805.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to William Hayley, 22 January 1805" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="wilson" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-22jan1805"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to William Hayley, 22 January 1805"><main>Letter to William Hayley, 22 January 1805</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 22.8KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 280KB
                to 1300KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to his trial for sedition.
                <lb/>
                The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the next stage of Blake’s life.  <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;    <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.   <lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.   <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.  
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2014 Wilson Library, University of North Carolina. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>December 2013-January 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to William Hayley, 22 January 1805</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1805.A">1805</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.<note>Dimensions unknown from original manuscript; given
                        dimensions refer to the photographed page of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
                            of William Blake</hi> volume 1; see note on Provenance in the Work
                        Information.</note></objsize><numberleaves>1<note>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript
                        letter by Blake, now lost. The letter begins in the top third of page 219
                        (Object 1) and ends near the middle of page 220 (Object 2) of the revised
                        1880 edition of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William
                            Blake</hi> volume 1, described in the note on Provenance in the Work
                        Information. The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to
                        Blake in his letter to Hayley of 22 January 1805, which is surrounded by
                        biographical text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly
                        including the hands of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others
                        (see also Bentley, *Blake Books*, pages 24-27). The text not
                        attributed to Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page. Page 219
                        (Object 1) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to Hayley,
                        18 December 1804, which is also untraced beyond the transcription in
                        Gilchrist’s *Life of William Blake* volume 1. Page 220
                        (Object 2) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to Hayley
                        of c. 22 March 1805, misdated in Gilchrist as "*April *25*th*, 1805", which is now in the Houghton Library, Harvard
                        University (see the note on Composition Date in the Work Information for the
                        letter of c. 22 March 1805). The letters of both 18 December 1804 and c. 22
                        March 1805 can be accessed through the Index of Letters.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink manuscript lost; *Life of William Blake* volume
                    1 is a letterpress book</medium><inkcolor>unknown from original manuscript; *Life of William Blake*
                    volume 1 is printed in black ink</inkcolor><support>unknown from original manuscript; *Life of William Blake*
                    volume 1 is printed on laid paper</support><watermark>unknown from original manuscript; leaf containing page 219 (Object 1) and
                    page 220 (Object 2) includes a large fragment of a crown; <hi rend="i">Life of
                        William Blake</hi> volume 1 printed on paper with a large central watermark
                    depicting a crown on top of a fleur-de-lis with illegible cursive script at the
                    bottom of the fleur-de-lis; countermarks appearing in the volume include “TDEB”,
                    “LDER”, and “VanG” </watermark><binding>bound in publisher's dark blue-green cloth, elaborately gilt stamped; a
                    small sticker on the recto of the last endpaper states "Bound by Burn &amp;
                    Co.”; the front cover design is based on a drawing in Blake's *Notebook* that is now attributed to Blake's brother Robert (Bentley,
                        *Writings* volume 1, page 13); the design on the spine is a
                    modified version of one of the angels in Blake's engraved *Illustrations of the Book of Job*, Object 16 </binding><postmark>unknown</postmark><sealDesc>unknown</sealDesc><addressee>William Hayley</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Rare Book Collection, Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</name><note>William Hayley; sold from the Hayley Correspondence, Sotheby's, 20 May 1878,
                    lot 30 (£4.8s. to Quaritch); offered in Quaritch's 1880 General Catalogue
                    as part of Lot 12,803, which included Blake's letters to Hayley of 26 November
                    1800, 26 October 1803, 4 May 1804, 28 May 1804, 9 August 1804, 23 October 1804,
                    18 December 1804, 22 January 1805, 17 May 1805, 4 June 1805 (priced
                    £52.10s.); probably bought by Alexander MacMillan as part of group
                    advertised by Quaritch in 1880 (see Bentley, "A Checklist of Publications and
                    Discoveries in 1995," *Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly* (Summer
                    2010), page 137n32); original manuscript untraced; letter only known from
                    printed transcription appearing in *Life of William Blake*
                    volume 1 (London: Macmillan, 1880).<lb/><lb/>The transcription of Blake’s letter
                    to William Hayley, 22 January 1805, was among the materials added in the revised
                    and expanded second edition (1880) of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of
                        William Blake, "Pictor Ignotus"</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863). Blake's
                    posthumous biographer Alexander Gilchrist died in 1861 before completing his
                    biography of Blake, which was finished by his wife, Anne Gilchrist, with
                    assistance from Dante Gabriel Rossetti and others (see also Bentley, *Blake Books*, pages 24-27).<lb/><lb/> The title page of the
                    1880 volume containing the letter reads: "LIFE / OF / WILLIAM BLAKE / WITH
                    SELECTIONS FROM HIS POEMS AND OTHER WRITINGS / BY / ALEXANDER GILCHRIST / OF THE
                    MIDDLE TEMPLE, BARRISTER-AT-LAW / AUTHOR OF "THE LIFE OF WILLIAM ETTY, R.A." //
                    A NEW AND ENLARGED EDITION / ILLUSTRATED FROM BLAKE'S OWN WORKS / WITH
                    ADDITIONAL LETTERS AND A MEMOIR OF THE AUTHOR // IN TWO VOLUMES / VOL. 1 //
                    LONDON / MACMILLAN AND CO. / 1880 // The Right of Translation is Reserved". The
                    book was printed by R. Clay, Sons, and Taylor, Bread Street Hill,
                    London.<lb/><lb/>Images, object notes, and transcriptions are from a copy in the
                    Rare Book Collection of the Wilson Library at the University of North Carolina
                    at Chapel Hill. The copy photographed was owned by Annie G. Holden, and is
                    inscribed "Annie G. Holden / Xmas 1880" in brown ink on the recto of the first
                    flyleaf; later in the library of Tatton Henry Bower of Yorkshire (1867-1931),
                    whose armorial bookplate is also attached; the Wilson Library purchased this
                    copy from the dealer Claude Cox in 1978.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Wilson Library</institution><addressline>CB#3936 Wilson Library</addressline><addressline>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</addressline><addressline>Chapel Hill, NC 27514-8890</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 919-962-1143</addressline><addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: rbcref@email.unc.edu</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.lib.unc.edu/rbc/</addressline><department>Rare Books, Special Collections</department><repositoryid label="Call number">PR4146 .G5 1880 C.1 V.1</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt22jan1805.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I hope this letter will outstrip Mr. Phillips'</title> , <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript letter by Blake,
                        now lost. The letter begins in the top third of page 219 (Object 1) and ends
                        near the middle of page 220 (Object 2) of the revised 1880 edition of
                        Alexander Gilchrist's *Life of William Blake* volume 1,
                        described in the note on Provenance in the Work Information.</p><p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to Blake in his
                        letter to Hayley of 22 January 1805, which is surrounded by biographical
                        text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly including the hands
                        of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also Bentley, *Blake Books*, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to
                        Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page.</p><p>Page 219 (Object 1) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to
                        Hayley, 18 December 1804, which is also untraced beyond the transcription in
                        Gilchrist’s *Life of William Blake* volume 1. The full
                        letter of 18 December 1804 can be accessed through the Index of Letters.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="21"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="46">*Jan*.
                            22*nd*, 1805.</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="3">DEAR SIR,</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="7">I hope this letter will
                        outstrip Mr. Phillips', as I sit down to</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left">write immediately on returning
                        from his house. He says he is agree-</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left">able to every proposal you have
                        made, and will himself immediately</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.06" justify="left">reply to you. I should have
                        supposed him mad if he had not, for</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.07" justify="left">such clear and generous proposals
                        as yours to him he will not easily</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.08" justify="left">meet from any one else. He will,
                        of course, inform you what his</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.09" justify="left">sentiments are of the proposal
                        concerning the three dramas. I found</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.10" justify="left">it unnecessary to mention anything
                        relating to the purposed applica-</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.11" justify="left">tion of the profits, as he, on
                        reading your letter, expressed his wish that</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.12" justify="left">you should yourself set a price,
                        and that he would, in his letter to you,</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.13" justify="left">explain his reasons for wishing
                        it. The idea of publishing one volume</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.14" justify="left">a year he considers as impolitic,
                        and that a handsome general edi-</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.15" justify="left">tion of your works would be more
                        productive. He likewise objects to</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.16" justify="left">any periodical mode of publishing
                        any of your works, as he thinks</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.17" justify="left">it somewhat derogatory as well as
                        unprofitable. I must now express</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.18" justify="left">my thanks for your generous manner
                        of proposing the *Ballads* to</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.19" justify="left">him on my account, and inform you
                        of his advice concerning them;</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.20" justify="left">and he thinks that they should be
                        published *all together* in a volume</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.21" justify="left">the size of the small edition of
                        the *Triumphs of Temper*, with six or</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.22" justify="left">seven plates. That one thousand
                        copies should be the first edition,</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.01.23" justify="left">and if we choose, we might add to
                        the number of plates in a second</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt22jan1805.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">cont.</title> , <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 2</objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript letter by Blake,
                        now lost. The letter begins in the top third of page 219 (Object 1) and ends
                        near the middle of page 220 (Object 2) of the revised 1880 edition of
                        Alexander Gilchrist's *Life of William Blake* volume 1,
                        described in the note on Provenance in the Work Information.</p><p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to Blake in his
                        letter to Hayley of 22 January 1805, which is surrounded by biographical
                        text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly including the hands
                        of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also Bentley, *Blake Books*, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to
                        Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page.</p><p>Page 220 (Object 2) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to
                        Hayley of c. 22 March 1805, misdated in Gilchrist as "<hi rend="i">April
                            </hi>25*th*, 1805", which is now in the Houghton
                        Library, Harvard University (see the note on Composition Date in the Work
                        Information for the letter of c. 22 March 1805). The full letter of c. 22
                        March 1805 can be accessed through the Index of Letters.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">edition. And he will go equal
                        shares with me in the expense and</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left">the profits, and that Seagrave is
                        to be the printer. That we must</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">consider all that has been printed
                        as lost, and begin anew, unless we</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">can apply some of the plates to
                        the new edition. I consider myself</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">as only put in trust with this
                        work, and that the copyright is for ever</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">yours. I, therefore, beg that you
                        will not suffer it to be injured by my</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">ignorance, or that it should in
                        any way be separated from the grand</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">bulk of your literary property.
                        Truly proud I am to be in possession</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">of this beautiful little estate;
                        for that it will be highly productive, I</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">have no doubt, in the way now
                        proposed; and I shall consider myself</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">a robber to retain more than you
                        at any time please to grant. In</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">short, I am tenant at will, and
                        may write over my door as the poor</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">barber did, "Money for live
                        here."</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left" indent="2">I entreat your
                        immediate advice what I am to do, for I would not</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left">for the world injure this
                        beautiful work, and cannot answer P.'s pro-</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left">posal till I have your directions
                        and commands concerning it; for he</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.17" justify="left">wishes to set about it
                        immediately, and has desired that I will give</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.18" justify="left">him my proposal concerning it in
                        writing.</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.19" justify="left" indent="20">I remain, dear
                        Sir,</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.20" justify="left" indent="26">Your obliged and
                        affectionate,</l><l n="lt22jan1805.1.ltr.02.21" justify="left" indent="49">WILL. BLAKE.</l></lg><vspace extent="20"/></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>