<bad id="lt25nov1825.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, 25 November 1825" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="murray" catalog="wba" catid="lt86-25nov1825">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to John Linnell, 25 November 1825"><main>Letter to John Linnell,
                        25 November 1825</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 13KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 150KB
                to 765KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of
                electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence
                of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow
                artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i"
                    >Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to
                    Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died. <lb/><lb/> About ninety
                of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving
                correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before
                he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in
                August 1825—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and
                to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . .
                however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I
                have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.” <lb/><lb/> Blake traveled
                seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British
                contemporaries, most of them in London. His circle of correspondents was narrow and
                the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an
                absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly
                and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.
                Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic
                Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.
                <lb/><lb/> The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and
                contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him
                shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing
                facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters
                feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s
                hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another
                quite extraordinary thing. If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with
                an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting
                consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/> In his letter of 12 April 1825 to Linnell, Blake
                refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George
                Cumberland. An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.
                We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates
                and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/> The Archive now
                contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts
                and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color
                drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of
                full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of
                all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.
                <lb/><lb/> Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the
                Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications.
                Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions
                for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works
                in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in
                preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that
                restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for
                Java.<lb/><lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no
                access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by
                the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester,
                the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
            only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2013 Huntington Library and Art Gallery. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to John Linnell, 25 November 1825</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor,
                        </role><role>delineator</role></origination>
                <compdate value="1825.E">1825</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>2</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-2</objorder>
                <objsize>full sheet 20.4 x 16.6 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1<note>The address is on one side (object 1) and the letter on the
                        other side (object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed
                        packet for posting. The printing "job" Blake is discussing is his
                        "Illustrations of the Book of Job"; see also the articles about the
                        provenance and contents of this letter summarized in Bentley, "William Blake
                        and His Circle: A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2004," *Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly* 39.1 (summer 2005):
                        5.</note></numberleaves>
                <leafsize>20.4 x 16.6 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>figure of a lion rampant surrounded by an oval and three curved
                    lines</watermark>
                <binding>loose</binding>
                <postmark>"2", "T.P / StrandCO", "8.MORN.8 / 25.NO / 1825" </postmark>
                <note>Above the handwritten "2", an additional, partial handwritten mark is
                    inscribed in the same ink, perhaps a fragment of another "2" that ran over the
                    edge of the folded letter. </note>
                <sealDesc>red wafer</sealDesc>
                <addressee>John Linnell</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>John Murray Collection, London</name>
                <date>unknown</date>
                <dealer>unknown</dealer>
                <price>unknown</price>
                <note>John Linnell; acquired by John Murray II (1778-1843) or, more likely, John
                    Murray III (1808-1892), who included it in a collection of artist's autographs;
                    located in the John Murray Collection, London.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>John Murray Collection, London</institution>
                <addressline>50 Albemarle Street, Mayfair</addressline>
                <addressline>London W1S 4BD</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt25nov1825.1.1.LT">
            <objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1
                    </objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>16.6 x 20.4 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The address is on one side (object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet for
                        posting. The printing "job" Blake is discussing is his "Illustrations of the
                        Book of Job"; see also the articles about the provenance and contents of
                        this letter summarized in Bentley, "William Blake and His Circle: A
                        Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2004," <hi rend="i">Blake: An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 5.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="800" height="1040"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">John Linnell Esq<hi
                            rend="superscript">re</hi></l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="1">Cir<unclear resp="NW"
                            >e</unclear>ncester Place</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="3">Fitzroy Square</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt25nov1825.1.2.LT">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Banes says his
                    Kitchen is at our Service</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">object 2
                    </objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.4 x 16.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The address is on one side (object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet for
                        posting. The printing "job" Blake is discussing is his "Illustrations of the
                        Book of Job"; see also the articles about the provenance and contents of
                        this letter summarized in Bentley, "William Blake and His Circle: A
                        Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 2004," <hi rend="i">Blake: An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 39.1 (summer 2005): 5.</p>
                    <p>In the top margin near the center of the page, "Crazy Artist" is inscribed in
                        pencil in an unknown hand.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="800" height="1040"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">Dear Sir</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="6">M<hi rend="superscript"
                            >r</hi> Banes says his Kitchen is at our Service</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">to do as we please. S<subst><del
                                type="overwrite">tll</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline"
                                >till</add></subst> I should like to know from<note><illus
                                filename="lt25nov1825.2.3.note.jpg"/>Blake appears to have first
                            written "Stll", omitting the "i", which he adds by writing "till" over
                            the three original characters following the initial "S".</note></l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">the Printer whether our own
                        Kitchen would not be</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">equally or even more Convenient as
                        the Pres<unclear resp="NW">s</unclear> being</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">already there would save a good
                        deal of time &amp; trouble</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left"><gap reason="illegible"
                            agent="cutaway" extent="1"/><unclear resp="NW">n</unclear> taking down
                        &amp; putting up which is no slight job. <subst><del type="overwrite"
                                >a</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline"
                                >A</add></subst>lso<note><illus filename="lt25nov1825.2.7a.note.jpg"
                            />The first character and part of the second are missing where the sheet
                            was torn to open the seal. The missing word appears to be "i[n]". <illus
                                filename="lt25nov1825.2.7b.note.jpg"/>Blake appears to have first
                            written "a", before writing an "A" over it in the final word in this
                            line.</note></l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">the light is betterd in <space
                            extent="6"/>I am S<hi rend="superscript">ir</hi> Your<unclear resp="NW"
                            >s</unclear>Sincerely</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left" indent="4">our kitchen if</l>
                    <l n="lt25nov1825.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left" indent="1">there is but room
                        enough <space extent="8"/><hi rend="u">Will Blake</hi></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
