<bad id="lt28sept1804.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to William Hayley, 28 September 1804" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="lc" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-28sept1804"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to William Hayley, 28 September 1804"><main>Letter to William Hayley, 28 September 1804</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 15.2KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 264KB
                to 1200KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to his trial for sedition.
                <lb/>
                The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the next stage of Blake’s life.  <lb/><lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;    <lb/><lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.   <lb/><lb/>
                The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.   <lb/><lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.  
            </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This work copyright © 2014 William Blake Archive. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>December 2013-January 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to William Hayley, 28 September 1804</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1804.M">1804</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>full sheet 22.0 x 18.0 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1<note>Blake's letter is written on both sides (Objects 1 and 2) of a
                        single leaf.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>22.0 x 18.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper<note>Tape or fabric ribbon may have been used to attach the
                        leaves along the seam between Objects 2 and 3.</note></support><watermark>design partially visible</watermark><binding>none</binding><postmark>none</postmark><sealDesc>none</sealDesc><addressee>William Hayley</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Library of Congress</name><date>1979</date><price>gift</price><note>William Hayley; sold from the Hayley Correspondence, Sotheby's, 20 May 1878,
                    lot 24 (£2.13s. to Waller); sold from the collection of Joseph Mayer of
                    Liverpool, Sotheby's, 19 July 1887 in lot 189, which included an unspecified
                    copy of *Nollekens*, with 450 portraits and 200 letters
                    including Blake’s letters of 12 March 1804, 31 March 1804, 27 April 1804, 28
                    September 1804 (£10.5s. to Robson); aquired by H. Buxton Forman; sold from
                    the Buxton Forman collection at the Anderson Galleries in New York, 15 March
                    1920, lot 72 ($140); acquired by George C. Smith, jr.; sold at the Parke-Bernet
                    Galleries, New York, 2 Novemeber 1938, lot 6 ($325 to Rosenbach); Lessing J.
                    Rosenwald; transferred in 1979 to the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library
                    of Congress.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Library of Congress</institution><addressline>101 Independence Ave, SE</addressline><addressline>Washington, DC 20540</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 202-707-5000</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.loc.gov/index.html </addressline><department>Rare Book/Special Collections</department><repositoryid label="Call number">Rosenwald Coll. ms. no. 6</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt28sept1804.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I hope you will excuse my delay</title> , <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>22.0 x 18.0 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Blake's letter is written on both sides (Objects 1 and 2) of a single
                        leaf.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left"> Dear Sir</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="10">I hope you will
                        excuse my delay in sending the Books which I have had</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left">some time but kept them back till
                        I could send a Proof of the Shipwreck</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left">which I hope will please. It yet
                        wants all its last &amp; finishing touches. but I</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left">hope you will be enabled by it to
                        judge of the Pathos of the Picture</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.06" justify="left" indent="5">I send Washingtons
                            2<hi rend="superscript"> d</hi> Vol:___ 5 Numbers of Fuseli's
                        Shakespeare &amp;</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.07" justify="left">two Vol's with a Letter from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Spilsbury with whom I accidentally met</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.08" justify="left">in the Strand. he says that he
                        relinquishd Painting as a Profession. for</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.09" justify="left">which I think he is to be
                        applauded. but I concieve that he may be a much</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.10" justify="left">better Painter if he pract<subst><del type="overwrite">s</del><add place="inline">ic</add></subst>es secretly &amp; for amusement than he could ever be <note><illus filename="lt28sept1804.1.10.note.jpg"/>The "c" in "practices" here
                            appears to have been written over an "s". Both Erdman (page 755) and
                            Bentley (page 1611) read this word as "practises". </note></l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.11" justify="left">if employed in the drudgery of
                        fashionable dawbing for a poor pittance of</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.12" justify="left">money in return for the sacrifice
                        of Art &amp; Genius. he says he never will</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.13" justify="left">leave to Practise the Art because
                        he loves it &amp; This Alone will pay its labour <note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1611) reads "practice" for
                            "Practice".</note></l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.14" justify="left">by Success if not of money yet of
                        True Art. which is All _</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.15" justify="left">I had the pleasure of a call from
                            M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Chetwynd &amp; her Brother. a Giant
                        in</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.16" justify="left">body mild &amp; polite in soul as
                        I have in general found great bodies to be</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.17" justify="left">they were much pleased with
                        Romneys Designs, M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> C. sent to me the two</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.18" justify="left">articles for you &amp; for the
                        safety of which by the Coach I had some fears till</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.19" justify="left">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Meyer obligingly undertook to convey them safe he is now I suppose
                        enjoying</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.20" justify="left">the delights of the Turret of
                        Lovely Felpham please to give my affectionate</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.21" justify="left">compliments to him.</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.22" justify="left" indent="11">I cannot help
                        suggesting an Idea which has struck me very forcibly</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.23" justify="left">that the Tobit and Tobias in your
                        bedchamber would make a very beautiful Engraving done</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.24" justify="left">in the same manner as the Head of
                        Cowper after Lawrence. The Head to be finishd</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.25" justify="left">&amp; the figures left exactly in
                        imitation of the first strokes of the Painter The Expression</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.26" justify="left">of those truly Pathetic heads
                        would then be transmitted to the Public a singular Monument</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.27" justify="left">of Romneys Genius in that Highest
                        branch of Art</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.28" justify="left" indent="6">I must now tell my
                        wants &amp; beg the favor of some more of the needful</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.01.29" justify="left" indent="70">the <note><illus filename="lt28sept1804.1.29.note.jpg"/>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1612) and Erdman (page 755) insert the
                            catchword "the" into the line which carries over to the next page, so
                            that it reads "more of the needful the favor".</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt28sept1804.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>22.0 x 18.0 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>Blake's letter is written on both sides (Objects 1 and 2) of a single
                        leaf.</p></objnote><windowsize width="500" height="630"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">favor of ten Pounds more will
                        carry me thro this Plate &amp; the Head of Romney</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left">for which I am already paid . You
                        shall soon see a Proof of Him in a</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">very advancd state I have not yet
                        proved it but shall soon when I will</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">send you one _<space extent="3"/>I rejoice to hear from M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Meyer of Miss
                        Pooles</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">continued recovery My wife
                        desires with me her respects to you &amp; her &amp;</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">to all whom we love that is to
                        all Sussex</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">Sth Molton St <space extent="2"/>
                        I remain Your Sincere &amp; Obliged <choice><sic>Hble</sic><reg>humble</reg></choice> Servant</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">28 Sept<hi rend="superscript">
                            r</hi> 1804 <space extent="46"/><hi rend="underscore">Will. Blake</hi></l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left"/><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left" indent="31">To</l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left" indent="29">William Hayley Esq
                            <hi rend="superscript"> re</hi></l><l n="lt28sept1804.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left" indent="36">Felpham</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>