<bad catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-3july1827" copy="1" copyid="1" hidden="false" id="lt3july1827.1" institution="huntington" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, 3 July 1827">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to John Linnell, 3 July 1827">
                    <main>Letter to John Linnell, 3 July 1827</main>: electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; 
                    <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and 
                    <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>
                    , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt/>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 13KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 135KB
                to 645KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives
                <date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of
                electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence
                of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow
                artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved 
                <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>
                (1826) and 
                <hi rend="i">Illustrations to
                    Dante</hi>
                , on which he was still working when he died. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The
                surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the
                month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death
                at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending
                ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a
                relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as
                I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.” 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small
                circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London. His circle of
                correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of
                correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in
                progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical
                and intellectual substance. Occasionally they burst out into visions that
                amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized
                prose, and inspired poetry. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts
                for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift
                pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of
                character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer
                to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and
                some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite
                extraordinary thing. If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an
                international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences
                for readers.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he
                plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland. An impression of
                the card is attached to the final page of the letter. We are also publishing another
                impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed
                and Engraved by Blake).
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of
                important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera
                paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated
                books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful
                diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and
                extensive bibliographies. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive
                has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can
                still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all
                works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the
                Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview
                mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore
                the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © 
            <date>2013</date>
            by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            This image copyright © 2013 Huntington Library and Art Gallery. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to John Linnell, 3 July 1827</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake
                    <role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role></origination>
                <compdate value="1827.I">1827</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>2</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-2</objorder>
                <objsize>full sheet 16.7 x 20.6 cm.
                    <note>Unfolded full sheet and Leaf Size
                        dimensions (height x width) are given according to the vertical orientation
                        of the body of Blake's letter; the full sheet view of Object 2 is available
                        under Supplemental Views on the Show Me pull-down menu for that object; see
                        the note on Number of Leaves, below. Object 1 has been reoriented vertically
                        in the Object View Page, as would be customary when reading the
                        address.</note></objsize>
                <numberleaves>2
                    <note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with Blake's
                        letter written on the second recto (Object 2). This folded sheet was folded
                        further to form a sealed packet. The address appears on the first recto
                        (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the sealed packet. The
                        full sheet view of Object 2 is available under Supplemental Views on the
                        Show Me pull-down menu for that object.</note></numberleaves>
                <leafsize>16.7 x 10.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper
                    <note>
                        Bentley (
                        *Writings*
                        volume 2, page 1759)
                        notes that similarly spaced chain lines may indicate that Blake used the
                        same stock in this letter as that bearing the &quot;RUSE &amp; TURNERS / 1810&quot;
                        watermark present in his letters of 31 January 1826, 16 July 1826, and 12
                        April 1827.</note>
                </support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <binding>loose</binding>
                <postmark>none</postmark>
                <sealDesc>wafer</sealDesc>
                <addressee>John Linnell</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</name>
                <date>1918</date>
                <dealer>George D. Smith</dealer>
                <price>£84
                    <note>This price includes all items in lot 214 in the 1918 Linnell sale;
                        see the note on provenance below.</note></price>
                <note>John Linnell; sold from Linnell's estate, Christie's, 15 March 1918, probably
                    in lot 214 with 12 (?) other letters by Blake (£84 to the dealer George D. Smith
                    acting for Henry E. Huntington) including 9 letters by Blake to John Linnell of
                    10 November 1825, 19 May 1826, 5 July 1826, 16 July 1826, 29 July 1826, 1 August
                    1826, 27 January 1827, and 2 undated letters (one probably of March 1825,
                    inscribed &quot;12 O Clock / Wednesday&quot; with an 1818 watermark, and the other
                    probably of February 1827); 2 letters by Blake to Mrs. Linnell, one of 11
                    October 1825 and one undated (inscribed &quot;Sunday Morning&quot;, probably of 5 February
                    1826); and probably a draft of Blake's letter to Willey Reveley, undated,
                    written on Reveley's letter of 18 October 1791 to Blake.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</institution>
                <addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline>
                <addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline>
                <addressline>United States</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2100</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 626-405-2191</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 626-405-3477</addressline>
                <addressline>E-mail, Reader Services:
                    readerregistration@huntington.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline>
                <department>Manuscripts</department>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">HM 20014</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc dbi="lt3july1827.1.1.LT" id="lt3july1827.1.ltr.01">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">Address</title>, 
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber></objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.6 x 16.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with Blake's letter written on
                        the second recto (Object 2). This folded sheet was folded further to form a
                        sealed packet. The address appears on the first recto (Object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the sealed packet. The full sheet view of
                        Object 2 is available under Supplemental Views on the Show Me pull-down menu
                        for that object.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="1030" width="810"/>
            </physdesc>
            <supplemental>
                <desc dbi="lt3july1827.1.full-sheet.RM" id="supplt3july1827.1.rm.01">
            <objtitle>, 
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 2, full sheet view</Objnumber></objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>16.7 x 20.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with Blake's letter written on
                        the second recto (Object 2). This folded sheet was folded further to form a
                        sealed packet. The address appears on the first recto (Object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.</p>
                    <p>Along the top left edge of the full sheet an &quot;X&quot; is inscribed in ink in an
                        unknown hand. To the right of the fold, two inscriptions in an unknown hand
                        appear along the bottom edge of the sheet: &quot;[16]&quot;, and a note on the date of
                        Blake's Death reading &quot;Died Augt 12&quot; near the bottom right corner.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="850" width="985"/>
            </physdesc>
        </desc>
            </supplemental>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left" type="prose">
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.01.01">M
                        <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Linnell</l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.01.02">6 Cirencester Place</l>
                    <l indent="9" justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.01.03">Fitzroy Square</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc dbi="lt3july1827.1.2.LT" id="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">I thank you for the Ten Pounds</title>, 
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </Objnumber></objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>10.3 x 16.7 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with Blake's letter written on
                        the second recto (Object 2). This folded sheet was folded further to form a
                        sealed packet. The address appears on the first recto (Object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.The full sheet view of
                        Object 2 is available under Supplemental Views on the Show Me pull-down menu
                        for that object.</p>
                    <p>Two inscriptions in an unknown hand appear on Object 2: &quot;[16]&quot; near the
                        bottom left corner, and a note on the date of Blake's Death reading &quot;Died
                        Augt 12&quot; near the bottom right corner. An &quot;X&quot; inscribed in
                        ink in an unknown hand can be viewed on the full sheet view of Object 2.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="850" width="985"/>
            </physdesc>
            <supplemental>
                <desc dbi="lt3july1827.1.full-sheet.RM" id="supplt3july1827.1.rm.01">
            <objtitle>, 
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 2, full sheet view</Objnumber></objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>16.7 x 20.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves, with Blake's letter written on
                        the second recto (Object 2). This folded sheet was folded further to form a
                        sealed packet. The address appears on the first recto (Object 1), which
                        would have been the exterior of the sealed packet.</p>
                    <p>Along the top left edge of the full sheet an &quot;X&quot; is inscribed in ink in an
                        unknown hand. To the right of the fold, two inscriptions in an unknown hand
                        appear along the bottom edge of the sheet: &quot;[16]&quot;, and a note on the date of
                        Blake's Death reading &quot;Died Augt 12&quot; near the bottom right corner.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="850" width="985"/>
            </physdesc>
        </desc>
            </supplemental>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left" type="prose">
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.01">Dear Sir</l>
                    <l indent="6" justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.02">I thank you for the Ten
                        Pounds you are so kind</l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.03">as to send me at this time. My
                        journey to 
                        <choice>
                            <sic>Hampt</sic>
                            <reg>Hampstead</reg></choice>
                        <gap extent="1" reason="illegible_inkblot" unit="character"/>d on
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="lt3july1827.2.3.note.jpg"/>
                            Bentley (
                            *Writings*
                            volume 2, page 1670), Erdman (page 785), and Keynes
                                (
                            *Letters*
                            , page 170) read &quot;Hampstead&quot;.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.04">Sunday brought on a relapse which
                        is lasted till now. I find</l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.05">I am no
                        <subst>
                            <gap extent="1" reason="illegible"/>
                            <add place="inline" type="overwrite">t</add>
                            <gap extent="1"/></subst>so well as I thought I must not go on in a youthful </l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.06">Style however I am upon the
                        mending hand to day &amp; hope</l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.07">soon to look as I did for I have
                        been yellow accompanied by</l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.08">all the old Symptoms</l>
                    <l indent="25" justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.09">I am dear Sir</l>
                    <l indent="33" justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.10">Yours 
                        <choice>
                            <orig>Sincerly</orig>
                            <reg>Sincerely</reg></choice>
                        <note>
                            <illus filename="lt3july1827.2.10.note.jpg"/>Bentley (
                            *Writings*
                            volume 2, page 1670) and Erdman (page 785) read
                            &quot;Sincerely&quot;.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.11">3 July 1827</l>
                    <l indent="39" justify="left" n="lt3july1827.1.ltr.02.12">William Blake</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>