<bad id="lt4june1805.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to William Hayley, 4 June 1805" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="wilson" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-4june1805" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to William Hayley, 4 June 1805"><main>Letter to William Hayley, 4
                        June 1805</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 18.9KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from
                288KB to 1400KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                    2014</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of
                electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence
                of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the
                coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to
                his trial for sedition. <lb/> The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s
                publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including
                his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little
                    Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The
                    Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life
                    of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and
                engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by
                    William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805).
                Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of
                Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the
                bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also
                show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with
                his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert
                Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the
                next stage of Blake’s life. <lb/><lb/> About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an
                unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are
                known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of
                Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled
                seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the
                geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an
                absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly
                and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.
                Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic
                Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;
                <lb/><lb/> The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and
                contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him
                shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing
                facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters
                feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s
                hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.
                <lb/><lb/> The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic
                editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings,
                tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen
                illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each
                work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all
                images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/> As always, the William Blake
                Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription
                fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress,
                and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have
                generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the
                Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2014</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
            only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2014 Wilson Library, University of North Carolina. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>December 2013-January 2014</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator,
                        University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on
                        Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley
                        Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project
                        Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber
                        Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea
                        Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon
                        Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric
                        Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali
                        McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair
                        Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret
                        Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa
                        Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia
                        Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to William Hayley, 4 June 1805</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor,
                        </role><role>delineator</role></origination>
                <compdate value="1805.C">1805</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>2</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-2</objorder>
                <objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.<note>Dimensions unknown from original manuscript; given
                        dimensions refer to the photographed page of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
                            of William Blake</hi> volume 1; see note on Provenance in the Work
                        Information.</note></objsize>
                <numberleaves>2<note>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript
                        letter by Blake, now lost. The letter begins in the bottom third of page 222
                        (Object 1) and ends in the top third of page 223 (Object 2) of the revised
                        1880 edition of Alexander Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William
                            Blake</hi> volume 1, described in the note on Provenance in the Work
                        Information. The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to
                        Blake in his letter to Hayley of 4 June 1805, which is surrounded by
                        biographical text written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly
                        including the hands of Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others
                        (see also Bentley, *Blake Books*, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to
                        Blake can be viewed directly on the Object View Page. Page 222 (Object 2)
                        includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to Hayley of c. 22
                        March 1805, misdated in Gilchrist on page 220 as "*April *25*th*, 1805",
                        which is now in the Houghton Library, Harvard University (see the note on
                        Composition Date in the Work Information for the letter of c. 22 March
                        1805). The full letter of c. 22 March 1805 can be accessed through the Index
                        of Letters.</note></numberleaves>
                <leafsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink manuscript lost; *Life of William Blake* volume 1 is a
                    letterpress book</medium>
                <inkcolor>unknown from original manuscript; *Life of William Blake* volume 1 is
                    printed in black ink</inkcolor>
                <support>unknown from original manuscript; *Life of William Blake* volume 1 is
                    printed on laid paper</support>
                <watermark>unknown from original manuscript; leaf containing page 222 (Object 1)
                    includes a small fragment of a fleur-de-lis in a top corner of the page; *Life
                    of William Blake* volume 1 printed on paper with a large central watermark
                    depicting a crown on top of a fleur-de-lis with illegible cursive script at the
                    bottom of the fleur-de-lis; countermarks appearing in the volume include “TDEB”,
                    “LDER”, and “VanG” </watermark>
                <binding>bound in publisher's dark blue-green cloth, elaborately gilt stamped; a
                    small sticker on the recto of the last endpaper states "Bound by Burn &amp;
                    Co.”; the front cover design is based on a drawing in Blake's *Notebook* that is
                    now attributed to Blake's brother Robert (Bentley, *Writings* volume 1, page
                    13); the design on the spine is a modified version of one of the angels in
                    Blake's engraved *Illustrations of the Book of Job*, Object 16</binding>
                <postmark>unknown</postmark>
                <sealDesc>unknown</sealDesc>
                <addressee>William Hayley</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Rare Book Collection, Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</name>
                <note>William Hayley; sold from the Hayley Correspondence, Sotheby's, 20 May 1878,
                    lot 31 (£3.15s. to Quaritch); offered in Quaritch's 1880 General Catalogue as
                    part of Lot 12,803, which included Blake's letters to Hayley of 26 November
                    1800, 26 October 1803, 4 May 1804, 28 May 1804, 9 August 1804, 23 October 1804,
                    18 December 1804, 22 January 1805, 17 May 1805, 4 June 1805 (priced £52.10s.);
                    probably bought by Alexander MacMillan as part of group advertised by Quaritch
                    in 1880 (see Bentley, "A Checklist of Publications and Discoveries in 1995,"
                    *Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly* (Summer 2010), page 137n32); original
                    manuscript untraced; letter only known from printed transcription appearing in
                    *Life of William Blake* volume 1 (London: Macmillan, 1880).<lb/><lb/>The
                    transcription of Blake’s letter to William Hayley, 4 June 1805, was among the
                    materials added in the revised and expanded second edition (1880) of Alexander
                    Gilchrist's <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, "Pictor Ignotus"</hi> (London:
                    Macmillan, 1863). Blake's posthumous biographer Alexander Gilchrist died in 1861
                    before completing his biography of Blake, which was finished by his wife, Anne
                    Gilchrist, with assistance from Dante Gabriel Rossetti and others (see also
                    Bentley, *Blake Books*, pages 24-27).<lb/><lb/> The title page of the 1880
                    volume containing the letter reads: "LIFE / OF / WILLIAM BLAKE / WITH SELECTIONS
                    FROM HIS POEMS AND OTHER WRITINGS / BY / ALEXANDER GILCHRIST / OF THE MIDDLE
                    TEMPLE, BARRISTER-AT-LAW / AUTHOR OF "THE LIFE OF WILLIAM ETTY, R.A." // A NEW
                    AND ENLARGED EDITION / ILLUSTRATED FROM BLAKE'S OWN WORKS / WITH ADDITIONAL
                    LETTERS AND A MEMOIR OF THE AUTHOR // IN TWO VOLUMES / VOL. 1 // LONDON /
                    MACMILLAN AND CO. / 1880 // The Right of Translation is Reserved". The book was
                    printed by R. Clay, Sons, and Taylor, Bread Street Hill,
                    London.<lb/><lb/>Images, object notes, and transcriptions are from a copy in the
                    Rare Book Collection of the Wilson Library at the University of North Carolina
                    at Chapel Hill. The copy photographed was owned by Annie G. Holden, and is
                    inscribed "Annie G. Holden / Xmas 1880" in brown ink on the recto of the first
                    flyleaf; later in the library of Tatton Henry Bower of Yorkshire (1867-1931),
                    whose armorial bookplate is also attached; the Wilson Library purchased this
                    copy from the dealer Claude Cox in 1978.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Wilson Library</institution>
                <addressline>CB#3936 Wilson Library</addressline>
                <addressline>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</addressline>
                <addressline>Chapel Hill, NC 27514-8890</addressline>
                <addressline>United States</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 919-962-1143</addressline>
                <addressline>E-mail, Reader Services: rbcref@email.unc.edu</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.lib.unc.edu/rbc/</addressline>
                <department>Rare Books, Special Collections</department>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">PR4146 .G5 1880 C.1 V.1</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt4june1805.1.1.LT">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">I have fortunately, I ought to say providentially,
                    discovered</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1
                </objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript letter by Blake,
                        now lost. The letter begins in the bottom third of page 222 (Object 1) and
                        ends in the top third of page 223 (Object 2) of the revised 1880 edition of
                        Alexander Gilchrist's *Life of William Blake* volume 1, described in the
                        note on Provenance in the Work Information.</p>
                    <p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to Blake in his
                        letter to Hayley of 4 June 1805, which is surrounded by biographical text
                        written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly including the hands of
                        Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also Bentley, *Blake
                        Books*, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to Blake can be viewed
                        directly on the Object View Page.</p>
                    <p>Page 222 (Object 2) includes the transcription of another letter by Blake to
                        Hayley of c. 22 March 1805, misdated in Gilchrist on page 220 as "*April
                        *25*th*, 1805", which is now in the Houghton Library, Harvard University
                        (see the note on Composition Date in the Work Information for the letter of
                        c. 22 March 1805). The full letter of c. 22 March 1805 can be accessed
                        through the Index of Letters.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="32"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left" indent="50">*June* 4*th*,
                        1805.</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left">DEAR SIR,</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="6">I have fortunately, I
                        ought to say providentially, discovered</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left">that I have engraved one of the
                        plates for that ballad of *The Horse*</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.05" justify="left">which is omitted in the new
                        edition; time enough to save the extreme</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.06" justify="left">loss and disappointment which I
                        should have suffered had the work</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.07" justify="left">been completed without that
                        ballad's insertion. I write to entreat</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.08" justify="left">that you would contrive so as that
                        my plate may come into the work,</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.01.09" justify="left">as its ommission would be to me a
                        loss that I could not now sustain</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt4june1805.1.2.LT">
            <objtitle><title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object
                        2</objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>Objects 1 and 2 include a transcription from a manuscript letter by Blake,
                        now lost. The letter begins in the bottom third of page 222 (Object 1) and
                        ends in the top third of page 223 (Object 2) of the revised 1880 edition of
                        Alexander Gilchrist's *Life of William Blake* volume 1, described in the
                        note on Provenance in the Work Information.</p>
                    <p>The Textual Transcription includes only the text attributed to Blake in his
                        letter to Hayley of 4 June 1805, which is surrounded by biographical text
                        written by Gilchrist's posthumous editors, possibly including the hands of
                        Anne Gilchrist, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, and others (see also Bentley, *Blake
                        Books*, pages 24-27). The text not attributed to Blake can be viewed
                        directly on the Object View Page.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="500" height="630"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="2"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">as it would cut off ten guineas
                        from my next demand on Phillips,</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left">which sum I am in absolute want
                        of; as well as that I should lose</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">all the labour I have been at on
                        that plate, which I consider as one</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">of my best; I know it has cost me
                        immense labour. The way in</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">which I discovered this mistake is
                        odd enough. Mr. Phillips objects</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">altogether to the insertion of my
                        Advertisement, calling it an appeal</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">to charity, and says that it will
                        hurt the sale of the work, and he sent</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">to me the last sheet by the penny
                        (that is the twopenny) post,</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">desiring that I would forward it
                        to Mr. Seagrave. But I have</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left"
                                ><choice><sic>inclosed</sic><reg>enclosed</reg></choice> it to you,
                        as you ought and must see it. I am no judge in</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">these matters, and leave all to
                        your decision, as I know that you will</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">do what is right on all hands.
                        Pray accept my and my wife's sincerest</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left">love and gratitude.</l>
                    <l n="lt4june1805.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left" indent="46">WILL. BLAKE.</l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="26"/>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
