<bad id="lt7june1825.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, 7 June 1825" copy="1" copyid="1" institution="huntington" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-7june1825"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letter to John Linnell, 7 June 1825"><main>Letter to John Linnell, 7 June 1825</main> : electronic edition </title><principal><resp>Editors:</resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt> </respstmt><sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 15KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 110KB
                to 625KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>March 2013</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of
                electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence
                of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow
                artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to
                    Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died. <lb/><lb/> About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The
                surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the
                month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death
                at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending
                ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a
                relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as
                I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.” <lb/><lb/> Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small
                circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London. His circle of
                correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of
                correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in
                progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical
                and intellectual substance. Occasionally they burst out into visions that
                amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized
                prose, and inspired poetry. <lb/><lb/> The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts
                for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift
                pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of
                character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer
                to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and
                some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite
                extraordinary thing. If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an
                international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences
                for readers.<lb/><lb/> In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he
                plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland. An impression of
                the card is attached to the final page of the letter. We are also publishing another
                impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed
                and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/> The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of
                important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera
                paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated
                books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful
                diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and
                extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/> Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive
                has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can
                still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all
                works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the
                Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview
                mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore
                the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the
                continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2013 Huntington Library and Art Gallery. </userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>Letter to John Linnell, 7 June 1825</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator</role></origination><compdate value="1825.B">1825<note>Undated, inscribed "Tuesday Night", emended from
                        "M[onday]" (see note to Object 2, line 14); Blake refers to the “D of C”
                        (probably Gerrard Andrewes, Dean of Canterbury, who died 2 June 1825) and to
                        either the death or ill health of “L.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> L.-”
                        (probably Lord Lilford, who died 4 July 1825). Blake also thanks Linnell for
                        “Two Pounds”, apparently recently received. Since Linnell’s account book
                        records his paying £2 to Blake on 6 June 1825 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi> page 588), the most probable date for the letter is the
                        first Tuesday after the dean’s death, 7 June 1825. See also Essick, *The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections*
                        (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1985) 186, 191n36; and Bentley, *Writings* volume 2, page 1652n1.</note></compdate></objdescid><objinfo><numberobj>2</numberobj><objorder>1-2</objorder><objsize>full sheet 13.4 x 16.7 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>1<note>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the
                        other side (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed
                        packet for posting. The address appears on what would have been the exterior
                        of the sealed packet (Object 1).</note></numberleaves><leafsize>13.4 x 16.7 cm.</leafsize><medium>pen and ink</medium><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>laid paper<note>chain lines present</note></support><watermark>none</watermark><binding>loose</binding><postmark>none</postmark><sealDesc>red wafer</sealDesc><addressee>John Linnell</addressee><placeLet>London</placeLet></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</name><date>1918</date><dealer>George D. Smith</dealer><price>£25.4s </price><note>John Linnell; sold from Linnell’s estate, Christie's, 15 March 1918, lot 209
                    (£25.4s. to George D. Smith acting for Henry E. Huntington).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery</institution><addressline>1151 Oxford Road</addressline><addressline>San Marino, California 91108</addressline><addressline>United States</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 626-405-2100</addressline><addressline>Telephone, Reader Services: 626-405-2191</addressline><addressline>Fax, Reader Services: 626-405-3477</addressline><addressline>E-mail, Reader Services:
                    readerregistration@huntington.org</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.huntington.org</addressline><department>Manuscripts</department><repositoryid label="Call number">HM 20013</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="lt7june1825.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt7june1825.1.1.LT"><objtitle><title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </Objnumber></Objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>13.4 x 16.7 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet for
                        posting. The address appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        sealed packet (Object 1).</p><p>Along the right edge of Object 1 a note is incsribed vertically in an unknown
                        hand, which may read "[written out for Mrs. St. 3/91]".</p></objnote><windowsize width="800" height="685"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Linnell</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left">6 Cirencester Place</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="7">Fitzroy Square</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt7june1825.1.2.LT"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">I return you thanks for The Two Pounds</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </Objnumber></Objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>13.4 x 16.7 cm.</objsize><objnote><p>The address is on one side (Object 1) and the letter on the other side
                        (Object 2) of a single leaf, which was folded to form a sealed packet for
                        posting. The address appears on what would have been the exterior of the
                        sealed packet (Object 1).</p><p>Two inscriptions in an unknown hand appear along the top of Object 2, one on
                        each side of the seal. The inscription to the left of the seal may read
                            "[S<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> T. Lawrence]", in reference to Blake's
                        mention of Sir Thomas Lawrence in line 3. The inscription to the right of
                        the seal reads "[1825 ?]".</p></objnote><windowsize width="800" height="695"/></physdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">Dear Sir</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="7">I return you thanks for
                        The Two Pounds you now send me</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">As to S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><choice><sic> T.</sic><reg>Thomas</reg></choice> Lawrence I have not heard from him as yet, &amp; hope that</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">he has a good opinion of my
                        willingness to appear grateful <choice><sic>tho</sic><reg>though</reg></choice> not</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">able on account of this abominable
                        Ague or whatever it is I am in Bed</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">&amp; at Work my health I cannot
                        speak of for if it was not for th Cold<note>"th" is a probable slip for
                            "the". Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1652) and
                            Keynes (*Letters*, page 156) read "the". Erdman (page
                            774) omits the penultimate word in this line, reading only "for
                            Cold".</note></l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">weather I think I should soon get
                        about again. Great Men die equaly<note>Bentley (*Writings*
                            volume 2, page 1652), Erdman (page 774), and Keynes (*Letters*, page 156) read "equaly" as "equally".</note></l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">with the little. I am sorry for
                            L.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> L.- he is a man of very s<unclear resp="nw">in</unclear>gular abilities <note><illus filename="lt7june1825.2.8.note.jpg"/>The dash and period after
                            "L" in this line appear in the same space, the dash written over the
                            period. Erdman (page 774) reads "L.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> L.<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>". Bentley (*Writings*
                            volume 2, page 1652) places the superscript "<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>" above and in the same space as the second period in this
                            line, omitting the dash written over the third period. Keynes (*Letters*, page 156) reads "L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>;". Bentley and Keynes suggest
                            "Lord Lilford" for the abbreviated title. The letters "in" appear
                            unclear in the word "singular".</note></l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">as also for the <choice><sic>D of C</sic><reg>Dean of Canterbury</reg></choice> but perhaps &amp; I verily believe it Every Death is<note>Keynes
                                (*Letters*, page 156) reads "death". The "D of C" is
                            identified as the Dean of Canterbury by Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page 1652), Keynes (*Letters*, pages 156-57), and Erdman (page 774).</note></l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">an improvement of the State of the
                        Departed. I can draw as well a Bed<note>Bentley (*Writings*
                            volume 2, page 1653) reads "aBed". Keynes (*Letters*,
                            page 156) reads "a-Bed".</note></l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left">as Up &amp; perhaps better but I
                        cannot Engrave I am going on with Dante</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left">&amp; please myself.</l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left" indent="26">I am d<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Sir yours Sinc<unclear resp="nw">ere</unclear>ly<note><illus filename="lt7june1825.2.13.note.jpg"/>Keynes (*Letters*, page 156) reads a lower-case "s" in
                            "sincerely".</note></l><l n="lt7june1825.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left" indent="3"><subst><del type="overwrite">M</del><add type="overwrite" place="inline"><choice><sic>Tu</sic><reg>Tuesday&gt;</reg></choice></add></subst>esday Night <space extent="15"/> William Blake<note><illus filename="lt7june1825.2.14.note.jpg"/>"Tu" is written over "M",
                            indicating Blake emended this inscription from "M[onday]" to "Tuesday"
                            during composition. Erdman (page 773) reads "Mon" underneath the
                            overwritten "Tuesday".</note></l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>