<bad id="lt9june1818.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to Dawson Turner, 9 June 1818" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="huntington" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-9june1818">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to Dawson Turner, 9 June 1818">
                    <main>Letter to Dawson Turner, 9 June 1818</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 20.5KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 500KB
                to 1.6MBKB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>August 2019</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of digital editions of our third installment of Blake's 95 known letters. The latest 28, drawn from nine collections, span nearly the entire chronological range of Blake’s correspondence from 1791 to 1827, the year of his death. Three of this group are by Blake’s correspondents&#8212;included here because of especially tight connections with their associated documents. (Those pairs are 18 October [Reveley] and October 1791 [Blake]; 23 September [Blake] and September 1800 [Butts]; 18 December [Cumberland] and 19 December 1808 [Blake].)                
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                A sample of the many highlights from the 28 new letters might feature
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --2 October 1800 (to Blake’s London patron Thomas Butts): fresh with optimism after his recent arrival in Felpham, Blake’s awkward amalgam of down to earth excuse-making with 78 lines of visionary verses:
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                To my Friend Butts I write<lb/>
                My First Vision of Light<lb/>
                . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
                I saw you and your wife<lb/>
                By the fountains of Life<lb/>
                Such the Vision to me<lb/>
                Appeard on the Sea<lb/>
                Mrs Butts will I hope Excuse my not having finishd the Portrait.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                --16 August 1803 (to Thomas Butts): Blake’s “whole outline” of his dangerous and distressing encounter with the soldier Private John Scolfield in Blake’s garden, which resulted in a “very unwarrantable warrant,” a charge of sedition against Blake, depositions, a lawyer, a trial, and, finally, acquittal: a “perilous adventure” for sure. Its imaginative afterlife was the appearance of Scolfield and his companion Private John Cock as shady Sons of Albion in Blake’s illuminated epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --18 January 1808 (to Ozias Humphry): Blake’s detailed description of his intricate 1808 watercolor <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> (Petworth House, Sussex), commissioned by the Countess of Egremont on Humphry’s recommendation. (We reproduce one of the three copies that Blake made of his description; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Records</hi>, pages 249-50.)  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --25 November 1825 (to John Linnell): sometimes called the kitchen letter for Blake’s brief contention that his flat at 3 Fountain Court would be the optimal place (the press is already assembled there, the lighting is better) for printing a copy of his engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>. For details of the unearthing of the letter—which turned up in a box of autograph scraps in the archives of publisher John Murray&#8212;and its surprisingly rich contexts in Blake’s workaday life, see Angus Whitehead, “The Uncollected Letters of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 80.3: 423-35.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake's hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Once again, special thanks to the City of Westminster Archives Centre for courteous assistance, excellent digital images, and willingness to share Kerrison Preston’s Blake library with the world. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>This work copyright © 2019 Rosenbach Museum and Library. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication of 28 letters written between 1791 and 1827</change>
                <date>April 2019-August 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to Dawson Turner, 9 June 1818</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1818.A">1818 </compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>4</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-4</objorder>
                <objsize>full sheet 20.5 x 32.4 cm.<note>Unfolded full sheet and Leaf Size
                        dimensions (height x width) are given according to the vertical orientation
                        of the body of Blake's letter; see the note on Number of Leaves, below.
                        Object 1 has been reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as would be
                        customary when reading the address.</note></objsize>
                <numberleaves>2<note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. The letter
                        appears on the first recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second
                        recto (Object 4) of the folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded further
                        to form a sealed packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso
                        (Object 1), which would have been the exterior of the folded packet. The
                        letter appears to have been repaired along the corner of the leaf containing
                        Objects 1 and 4, probably where a wafer seal was torn open. Traces of what
                        appear to be a wafer seal, no longer present, are visible along the edges of
                        the folded letter.</note>
                </numberleaves>
                <leafsize>20.5 x 16.2 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>design</watermark>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <postmark>B / J[U?] / [1]818</postmark>
                <sealDesc>Traces of what appears to have been a wafer seal are visible; see note
                    on Number of Leaves above.</sealDesc>
                <addressee>Dawson Turner</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Rosenbach Museum and Library</name>
                <date>1921</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Dawson Turner; sold with the Dawson Turner collection at Puttick and
                    Simpson's, London, 6-10 June 1859, as part of lot 676, "AUTOGRAPHS: SECOND
                    SERIES; 6 vols." (£24); offered by J. S. Davey for £6.6.o. (Keynes *Letters*, page
                    215); acquired by W. A. White who lent it to the Grolier Club in 1905 and the
                    Fogg Art Museum in 1924; on White's death in 1929, sold to A. S. W. Rosenbach;
                    bequeathed to Rosenbach Museum and Library, Philadelphia.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Rosenbach Museum and Library</institution>
                <addressline>2008-2010 Delancey Place</addressline>
                <addressline>Philadelphia, Pennsylvannia 19103</addressline>
                <addressline>United States</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone, Library: 215-732-1600, ext. 115</addressline>
                    <addressline>http://www.rosenbach.org</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">Inventory no. 1010/2</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="lt9june1818.1.ltr.01" dbi="lt9june1818.1.1.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.5 x 16.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. The letter appears on the first
                        recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second recto (Object 4) of the
                        folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed packet
                        for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object 1), which would
                        have been the exterior of the folded packet. The letter appears to have been
                        repaired along the corner of the leaf containing Objects 1 and 4, probably
                        where a wafer seal was torn open. Traces of what appear to be a wafer seal,
                        no longer present, are visible along the edges of the folded letter.</p>
                    <p>In the bottom left corner, reoriented vertically, "1010/2" is inscribed in
                        pencil in an unknown hand. In the bottom right corner, reoriented vertically, a few illegible characters are inscribed in pencil in an uknown hand.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="800" height="685"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="5"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">To</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left">Dawson Turner <choice><orig>Esq<hi
                        rend="superscript">re</hi></orig><reg>Esquire</reg></choice></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="8">Yarmouth</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.01.04" justify="left" indent="9">Norfolk</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02" dbi="lt9june1818.1.2.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">I send you a List of the different Works</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.5 x 16.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. The letter appears on the first
                        recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second recto (Object 4) of the
                        folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed packet
                        for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object 1), which would
                        have been the exterior of the folded packet. The letter appears to have been
                        repaired along the corner of the leaf containing Objects 1 and 4, probably
                        where a wafer seal was torn open. Traces of what appear to be a wafer seal,
                        no longer present, are visible along the edges of the folded letter.</p>
                    <p>In the top left corner, "E L 3 / .B636 / MS1" is inscribed in pencil in an unknown
                        hand.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="800" height="695"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
<vspace extent="2"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left">Sir</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="7">I send you a List of
                        the different Works</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">you have done me the <choice><orig>honour</orig><reg>honor</reg></choice> to
                        <choice><orig>enquire</orig><reg>inquire</reg></choice> after_<del type="overstrike"><gap extent="3" reason="cancellation"
                            /></del></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">unprofitable enough to me <choice><orig>tho</orig><reg>though</reg></choice>
                        Expensive to the Buyer</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">Those I Printed for <choice><orig>M<hi
                        rend="superscript">r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice> <choice><orig>Humphry</orig><reg>Ozias Humphry</reg></choice> are a selection</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left">from the different Books of such
                        as could be Printed<note>Bentley (*Writings* volume 2, page
                            1648) reads "such" as "Such".</note></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">without the Wr<unclear resp="nw"
                            >i</unclear><choice><orig>ting</orig><reg>writing</reg></choice> <choice><orig>tho</orig><reg>though</reg></choice> to the Loss of some of the best</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">things For they when Printed
                        perfect accompany Poetical</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left">Personifications &#38; Acts
                        without Which Poems <unclear resp="nw">they</unclear> never<note>Bentley
                                (*Writings* volume 2, page 1648), Erdman (page 771),
                            and Keynes (*Letters*, page 142) read "Which" as
                            "which".</note></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left">could have been Executed <space
                            extent="19"/>&#163; <space extent="1"/>s <space extent="1"/>d</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.11" justify="left" indent="8">America <space
                            extent="9"/>18 Prints <space extent="4"/>folio . <space extent="1"
                                                                                    />5<unclear resp="EL">&#163;</unclear> 5 . 0<note>Bentley
                                (*Writings* volume 2, page 1648)
                                and Keynes (*Letters*, page 142) do not read the unclear characters, possibly "&#163;", after "5".</note></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.12" justify="left" indent="8">Europe <space
                            extent="11"/>17 do <space extent="6"/>folio <space extent="2"/>5 . 5 .
                        0</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.13" justify="left" indent="7">Visions &#38;<hi
                            rend="superscript">c</hi>
                        <space extent="10"/>8 do <space extent="6"/>folio <space extent="2"/>3 . 3.
                        0</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.14" justify="left" indent="8">Thel . <space
                            extent="14"/>6 do <space extent="5"/>Quarto 2 . 2 .
                        0</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.15" justify="left" indent="7">Songs of Innocence <space extent="2"/> 28
                        do. <space extent="2"/> Octavo 3 . 3 . 0</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.02.16" justify="left" indent="7">Songs of Experience <space extent="2" />26
                        do <space extent="3"/>Octavo<space extent="1"/>3 . 3 . 0</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03" dbi="lt9june1818.1.3.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.5 x 16.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. The letter appears on the first
                        recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second recto (Object 4) of the
                        folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed packet
                        for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object 1), which would
                        have been the exterior of the folded packet. The letter appears to have been
                        repaired along the corner of the leaf containing Objects 1 and 4, probably
                        where a wafer seal was torn open. Traces of what appear to be a wafer seal,
                        no longer present, are visible along the edges of the folded letter.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="800" height="695"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.01" justify="left" indent="7">Urizen <space
                            extent="3"/>28 Prints Quarto <space/>5 . 5 . 0</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.02" justify="left" indent="7">Milton <space
                            extent="4"/>50 do <space extent="2"/>Quarto <space/>10 .10 . 0</l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.03" justify="left" indent="2">12 <space extent="2"
                        />Large Prints Size of Each</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.04" justify="left" indent="7">about 2 feet by
                        1&#38;&#189; Historical</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.05" justify="left" indent="7">&#38; Poetical Printed
                        in <choice><orig>Colours</orig><reg>Colors</reg></choice></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.06" justify="left" indent="27">Each <space/>5 . 5 .
                        0<note>Lines 3-6 are enclosed by a single bracket on the right.</note></l>
                </lg>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.07" justify="left" indent="1">These last 12 Prints
                        are unaccompanied by any</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.08" justify="left" indent="2">writing</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.09" justify="left" indent="5">The few I have Printed
                        &#38; Sold are sufficient</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.10" justify="left">to have gained me great reputation
                        as an Artist</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.11" justify="left">which was the chief thing Intended
                        But I have</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.12" justify="left">never been able to produce a
                            Suf<unclear resp="nw">f</unclear><choice><orig>icient</orig><reg>sufficient</reg></choice> number</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.13" justify="left">for a general Sale by means of a
                        regular Publisher</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.14" justify="left">It is therefore necessary to me
                        that any Person</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.15" justify="left">wishing to have any or all of
                        them: Should Send<note>Erdman (page 771) and Keynes
                            (*Letters*, page 142) read "Should Send" as "should send".</note></l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.16" justify="left">me their Order to Print them on
                        the above terms</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.03.17" justify="left">&#38; I will take care that they
                        shall be done at</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04" dbi="lt9june1818.1.4.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">cont.</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>20.5 x 16.2 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. The letter appears on the first
                        recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second recto (Object 4) of the
                        folded sheet. This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed packet
                        for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object 1), which would
                        have been the exterior of the folded packet. The letter appears to have been
                        repaired along the corner of the leaf containing Objects 1 and 4, probably
                        where a wafer seal was torn open. Traces of what appear to be a wafer seal,
                        no longer present, are visible along the edges of the folded letter.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="800" height="695"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.01" justify="left">least as well as any I have yet
                        Produced</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.02" justify="left" indent="2">I am Sir with many
                        thanks for your very</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.03" justify="left">Polite approbation of my works</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.04" justify="left" indent="18">Your most obedient
                        Servant</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.05" justify="left">9 June 1818</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.06" justify="left" indent="21">William Blake</l>
                    <l n="lt9june1818.1.ltr.04.07" justify="left" indent="1">17 South Molton
                        Street</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
