<bad id="ltapril1827.1" type="ltr" work="Letter to John Linnell, c. April 1827" copy="1" copyid="1"
    institution="beinecke" catalog="bentley" catid="lt86-april1827">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to John Linnell, c. April 1827">
                    <main>Letter to John Linnell, c. April 1827</main> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                    Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                        Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt>
                </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill,
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 11.4KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from
                277KB to 972KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>August 2019</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> 
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of digital editions of our third installment of Blake's 95 known letters. The latest 28, drawn from nine collections, span nearly the entire chronological range of Blake’s correspondence from 1791 to 1827, the year of his death. Three of this group are by Blake’s correspondents&#8212;included here because of especially tight connections with their associated documents. (Those pairs are 18 October [Reveley] and October 1791 [Blake]; 23 September [Blake] and September 1800 [Butts]; 18 December [Cumberland] and 19 December 1808 [Blake].)                
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                A sample of the many highlights from the 28 new letters might feature
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --2 October 1800 (to Blake’s London patron Thomas Butts): fresh with optimism after his recent arrival in Felpham, Blake’s awkward amalgam of down to earth excuse-making with 78 lines of visionary verses:
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                To my Friend Butts I write<lb/>
                My First Vision of Light<lb/>
                . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
                I saw you and your wife<lb/>
                By the fountains of Life<lb/>
                Such the Vision to me<lb/>
                Appeard on the Sea<lb/>
                Mrs Butts will I hope Excuse my not having finishd the Portrait.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                --16 August 1803 (to Thomas Butts): Blake’s “whole outline” of his dangerous and distressing encounter with the soldier Private John Scolfield in Blake’s garden, which resulted in a “very unwarrantable warrant,” a charge of sedition against Blake, depositions, a lawyer, a trial, and, finally, acquittal: a “perilous adventure” for sure. Its imaginative afterlife was the appearance of Scolfield and his companion Private John Cock as shady Sons of Albion in Blake’s illuminated epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --18 January 1808 (to Ozias Humphry): Blake’s detailed description of his intricate 1808 watercolor <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> (Petworth House, Sussex), commissioned by the Countess of Egremont on Humphry’s recommendation. (We reproduce one of the three copies that Blake made of his description; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Records</hi>, pages 249-50.)  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                --25 November 1825 (to John Linnell): sometimes called the kitchen letter for Blake’s brief contention that his flat at 3 Fountain Court would be the optimal place (the press is already assembled there, the lighting is better) for printing a copy of his engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>. For details of the unearthing of the letter—which turned up in a box of autograph scraps in the archives of publisher John Murray&#8212;and its surprisingly rich contexts in Blake’s workaday life, see Angus Whitehead, “The Uncollected Letters of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 80.3: 423-35.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake's hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                Once again, special thanks to the City of Westminster Archives Centre for courteous assistance, excellent digital images, and willingness to share Kerrison Preston’s Blake library with the world. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
            </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright &#169; <date>2019</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and
            Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance
            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
            other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
            advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
            this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>This work copyright &#169; 2019 Beinecke Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Yale University. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication of 28 letters written between 1791 and 1827</change>
                <date>April 2019-August 2019</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>
                    University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name>
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Assistant Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                    <name>Grant Glass</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                    <name>Eric Loy</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Ani Govjian,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Joey Kingsley,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                    <name>Anneke Schwob,</name>
                    <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                    <name>Elizabeth Shand,</name>
                    <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                    <name>Jewell Thomas,</name>
                    <name>Marcie Woehl,</name>
                    <name>Meaghan Green,</name>
                    <name>Kendall DeBoer</name>
                    <name>Helen Davies</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to John Linnell, c. April 1827</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator</role>
                </origination>
                <compdate value="1827.F">1827<note>Keynes (*Letters*, page 168)
                        gives the approximate date of this letter as 1827, placing it in his edition
                        between Blake's letters of 14 March 1827 and 12 April
                    1827.</note></compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>2</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-2</objorder>
                <objsize>full sheet 17.4 x 22.0 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1<note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter
                        appears on the first recto (Object 2) and the address on the second verso
                        (Object 1) of the folded sheet. The bottom left corner of the leaf
                        containing Object 1 is torn away, leaving part of the other leaf of the
                        folded letter visible behind it in the image of Object 1.</note>
                </numberleaves>
                <leafsize>17.4 x 11.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>none visible</watermark>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <postmark>none</postmark>
                <sealDesc>none</sealDesc>
                <addressee>John Linnell</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Beinecke Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Yale University</name>
                <date>1965</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>unknown</price>
                <note>John Linnell; inserted in *Songs of Innocence* (copy Q); sold
                    at Sotheby's, 30 July 1893, as part of lot 1100, including *Songs of
                        Innocence* (copy Q), 28 colored plates, two colored drawings by Blake
                    (Butlin #785, "Timon"), pen and ink signed portrait by John Linnell and "a
                    drawing of the portrait by Schiavonetti" (&#163;49.10s to Heath); acquired by W.
                    A. White, New York; acquired by Alfred W. Van Sinderen; purchased from Van
                    Sinderen by Yale University through the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Fund, 1965;
                    located in Beinecke Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Yale University.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution> Beinecke Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Yale University </institution>
                <addressline>121 Wall Street</addressline>
                <addressline>P.O. Box 208240</addressline>
                <addressline>New Haven, CT 06511</addressline>
                <addressline>USA</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 203-432-2977</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: beinecke.library@yale.edu</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">GEN MSS 914, Box 1, Folder 8 (formerly MS Vault
                    Shelves Blake)</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="ltapril1827.1.ltr.01" dbi="ltapril1827.1.1.LT">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="editorial">Address</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1</objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>17.4 x 11.0 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the first recto (Object 2) and the address on the second verso (Object 1) of the
                        folded sheet. The bottom left corner of the leaf containing Object 1 is torn
                        away, leaving part of the other leaf of the folded letter visible behind it
                        in the image of Object 1.</p>
                    <p>Two pencil inscriptions by one or more unknown hands appear on Object 1: some
                        illegible wrting to the left of the first line of the address and "(4)" near
                        the tear along the bottom left corner.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="810" height="1000"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="7"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.01.01" justify="left">John Linnell <choice><orig>Esq<hi
                        rend="superscript">re</hi></orig><reg>Esquire</reg></choice></l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.01.02" justify="left" indent="3">Cirencester Place</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.01.03" justify="left" indent="7">Fitzroy Square</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02" dbi="ltapril1827.1.2.LT">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">I am still far from recoverd</title>, <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2</objnumber>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>17.4 x 11.0 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2) and the address on the second verso (Object 1) of the
                        folded sheet. The bottom left corner of the leaf containing Object 1 is torn
                        away, leaving part of the other leaf of the folded letter visible behind it
                        in the image of Object 1.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize width="810" height="1000"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.01" justify="left" indent="1">Dear Sir</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.02" justify="left" indent="8">I am still far from <choice>
                            <orig>recoverd</orig>
                            <reg>recovered</reg>
                    </choice></l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.03" justify="left">&#38; dare not get out in the cold
                        air. Yet I</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.04" justify="left">lose nothing by it Dante goes on
                        the better</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.05" justify="left">which is all I care about</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.06" justify="left" indent="5"><choice><orig>M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >r</hi></orig><reg>Mr</reg></choice> Butts is to have a Proof Copy</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.07" justify="left">for Three Guineas this is his own
                        decision</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.08" justify="left">quite in Character he <choice>
                            <orig>calld</orig>
                            <reg>called</reg>
                        </choice> on me this Week</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.09" justify="left" indent="17">Yours Sincerely</l>
                    <l n="ltapril1827.1.ltr.02.10" justify="left" indent="20">William Blake</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
