<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2007-04-24T19:34:08-04:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="mhh.k" type="illbk" work="The Marriage of Heaven and Hell" copy="K" copyid="K" institution="fitzwilliam" catalog="bentley" catid="K"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Marriage of Heaven and Hell"><main>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</main><copy> Copy K</copy>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>David Cosca</name> and 
<name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Jessica Kem, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Andrea Laue</name></respstmt><sponsor>The
Library of Congress and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, with a software grant from Inso Corporation and
hardware and software grants from Sun Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 340KB; 54 JPEG                   
(ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 78KB to 470KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; CDLA</publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of the electronic editions of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> Copies K, L, and M. The Archive is also publishing the collection list for the Victoria University Library in Toronto and Alexander Gourlay's revised Glossary of Terms, Names, and Concepts in Blake.<lb/><lb/> 
            Blake etched twenty-seven plates for <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> in relief in 1790. Copy K is an early printing of Plates 21-24, and Copies L and M are early printings of Plates 25-27, "A Song of Liberty." Copy K is in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Copy L is in the Essick Collection, and Copy M, formerly in the Bentley Collection, is in the Victoria University Library. Only nine complete copies of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> are known to exist; Copies K, L, and M, apparently printed as autonomous pamphlets, join six complete copies previously published in the Archive (and now republished with corrected transcriptions).<lb/><lb/>
            The four plates of Copy K were printed in black ink on both sides of a single sheet of wove paper, folded down the middle after printing to form two leaves. Plate 21 is in its first state and the vignette on Plate 24 is missing, probably masked during printing but possibly not yet executed. In Copies L and M, Plate 25 is in its first state, and thus these copies were also printed very early in the production process; in Copy M, the eight lines of the "Chorus" on Plate 27 were masked during printing. The plates were printed on single sheets folded down the middle to form pamphlets of two leaves. Copy L was printed in brownish-black on laid paper and Copy M was printed in grayish-black on wove paper.<lb/><lb/>
            Like all the illuminated books in the Archive, the text and images of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> Copies K, L, and M are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications. With the Archive's Compare feature, users can easily juxtapose multiple impressions of any plate across the different copies of this or any of the other illuminated books. New protocols for transcription, which produce improved accuracy and fuller documentation in editors' notes, have been applied to all copies of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> in the Archive.<lb/><lb/>
            With the publication of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> Copies K, L, and M, the Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of sixty-five copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. In addition to illuminated books, the Archive contains many important manuscripts and series of engravings, sketches, and water color drawings, including Blake's illustrations to Thomas Gray's <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, water color and engraved illustrations to Dante's <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>, the large color printed drawings of 1795 and c. 1805, the Linnell and Butts sets of the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi> water colors and the sketchbook containing drawings for the engraved illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, the water color illustrations to Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and the water color illustrations to John Milton's <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, <hi rend="i">L'Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>, as well as the Butts and Thomas sets of illustrations to Milton's <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, <hi rend="i">Nativity</hi> ode, and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>.<lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2008</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2008 Fitzwilliam Museum.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Preparations for final publication</change><date>Spring 2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name><name>Michelle Langston, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>This work has been revised to include corrections and improvements (to the
textual transcriptions and editors' notes for consistency, accuracy, and
visual presentation) that were not reflected in the original XML conversion.</change><date>2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2005</change><date>2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi></title></objtitle><note>The title does not appear in this copy, which consists only of Plates 21-24.</note><origination>William Blake<role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer</role><note>Blake's authorship is nowhere stated in the work, but the
attribution is certain.</note></origination><origination>Catherine Blake<role>printer</role></origination><imprint><publisher>William Blake 
<note>Blake's name as the publisher is nowhere stated in the work, but
the attribution is certain.</note></publisher><pubplace>London 
<note>The place of publication is not stated in the work, but Blake
lived in London until the autumn of 1790, when he moved to the suburb of
Lambeth.</note></pubplace><date>none</date></imprint><compdate value="1790">1790</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1790.A">1790<note>Plate 21 is in a proof state, and thus this copy was printed very early in the production process.</note></printdate><numberobj>4</numberobj><objorder>21-24<note>Bentley numbers are used here unless noted to the contrary.</note></objorder><objsize>ranging between 15.3 x 10.8 cm. and 14.9 x 9.8
cm.</objsize><numberleaves>2<note>The plates were probably printed in folio format on both sides of a single sheet of paper, folded down the middle after printing to form 2 leaves.  Plate 22 is on the verso of Plate 21, Plate 24 on the verso of Plate 23.  This copy may have been printed as an independent pamphlet of four plates.</note></numberleaves><leafsize>23.7 x 14.5 cm.</leafsize><medium>relief etching<note>Plate 21 is in a proof state before the addition of white-line work found in all other impressions.</note></medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><inkcolor>black</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>blue morocco by Riviere &amp; Son<note>The leaves were probably placed in their present binding between 1900 and 1912.</note></binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Fitzwilliam Museum</name><date>1912</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Henry Crabb Robinson, who probably inserted this copy, loose, in Copy Z of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> shortly after he acquired Copy Z from Blake, 10 Dec. 1825; by gift to Edwin Wilkins Field no later than 1865; by gift to Sir Frederick Burton, who gave the work to Charles Fairfax Murray in 1900; removed from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> Copy Z by Murray and separately bound; given by Murray to the Fitzwilliam Museum, July 1912.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Fitzwilliam Museum</institution><addressline>Trumpington Street</addressline><addressline>Cambridge CB2 1RB</addressline><addressline>England</addressline><addressline label="Telephone">1223-332900</addressline><addressline label="Fax">1223-332923</addressline><addressline label="URL">http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Department of Paintings, Drawings, and Prints</department><collection>Fitzwilliam Museum</collection><repositoryid label="Accession number">Bindman 11</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="mhh.k.illbk.01" dbi="mhh.K.P21"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B21">(Bentley 21, </objcode><objcode code="E21">Erdman 21, </objcode><objcode code="K21">Keynes 21)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The plate is in a proof state before the addition of white-line work to the large human figure, the hill 
on which he sits, and the vegetation above line 1 of the text.  This additional shading is found in all other known impressions.</p></objnote><objsize>15.3 x 10.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="796" width="562"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A curly-haired and youthful nude male with his head up to the right sits on a hilltop or mound.  
His right hand (and presumably his left, behind his back) rests on the ground to support the weight of his upper body.  His 
                  feet—the right foot more prominent and forward—are drawn up toward his groin and his legs are spread wide apart, genitals 
exposed but not clearly printed in this copy.  His left knee rests on a human skull.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>arm behind back</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>genitals</characteristic><characteristic>head up</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>hands on ground</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A curly-haired and youthful nude male with his head up to the right sits on a hilltop or mound.  
His right hand (and presumably his left, behind his back) rests on the ground to support the weight of his upper body.  His 
                     feet—the right foot more prominent and forward—are drawn up toward his groin and his legs are spread wide apart, genitals 
exposed although not clearly printed in this copy.  His left knee rests on a human skull.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>skull</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure's left knee rests on a human skull.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The nude male sits on a hilltop or mound.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The smaller figures, interspersed among various vegetative designs, all appear immediately above the 
first line of text: at the far left, a gowned and winged female reaches her arms out to a small child who leans slightly toward her.  
The female rests against a grain tassel.  Following a combination of stylized leaves and a three-looped vine, a child and adult face 
each other, the former lying with head raised, the latter kneeling with hands on ground or holding the child's hand.  To their right, 
the final figure sits reading on a vegetable surface.  A leaf-like extension arches above the figure.  Further down, an elaborate 
sequence of sinuous, looped vines and squiggles, as well as a branch with spiky leaves, follows "reasoning" in line 4 and stretches 
to the right margin.  Another such sequence occurs right of line 7, where wavy lines and other vegetative motifs follow the two words 
of text, "publish'd books."  A vine with leaves(?) immediately precedes the catchword "one."</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>infant</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Directly above "I have" in line 1, a gowned female reaches her arms out to a small child who leans slightly toward her.  
The child faces right, standing on a leaf.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>lifting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Directly above "I have" in line 1, a gowned, winged female reaches her arms out to a small child.  Resting against 
or sitting at the base of a grain tassel, she faces left and bends forward from the waist as though preparing to lift the child.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>grain tassel</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The gowned woman above "I have" in line 1 rests against the stem of a grain tassel.  The child she clasps stands 
on a leaf or frond, one of three that curve around the "I" in line 1.  To the right of the woman, the grain or leaf stem grows into two scanty 
                     leaves or branches.  Continuing the mixed vegetative motif, a triple-looped, serpentine vine—suggestive of a spiral—extends from the leaves 
toward the next pair of figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above "that Angels" in line 1, a child and an adult face each other.  The child lies on a vegetative slope.  
It faces right with head raised.  The child has at least one arm extended toward the adult and may be holding the adult's hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>hands on ground</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above "that Angels" in line 1, a child and an adult face each other.  The adult faces left and down, 
perhaps looking at the child.  The figure appears to be either kneeling with hands on ground or holding the child's hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beneath the child and female and above "that Angels" in line 1, a wavy, serpentine line represents a 
vegetative surface, perhaps a continuation of the vine motif on the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the far right of the plate and above the first line of text, the final figure in the series sits 
reading on a vegetative surface, perhaps a leaf.  The figure faces right, a book propped on its knees.  A leaf arches over the figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the far right of the plate and above the first line of text, a figure sits reading on a leaf or frond; a leaf-like canopy arches over the figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An elaborate sequence of snake-like, looped vines and serpentine motifs follow "reasoning" in line 4.  
The designs, which conclude with a branch bearing spiky leaves, stretch to the right margin of the plate.  A similar sequence occurs 
right of line 7, where wavy lines, one prominent leaf, and/or other vegetative motifs predominate over the two words of text, "publish'd books."</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine-like loop, which looks like a bird with neck and head twisted to the right, precedes line 8.  
A leaf precedes line 5 and a vine with leaves(?) precedes the catchword "one."</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The vegetative(?) form left of line 8 might be a bird with neck and head twisted to face right.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="11"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.01" justify="left" indent="5">I have always found that Angels have the vani- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.02" justify="left">-ty to speak of themselves as the only wise; this they </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.03" justify="left" indent="1">do with a confident insolence sprouting from systema- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.04" justify="left">-tic reasoning;</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.05" justify="left" indent="4">Thus Swedenborg boasts that what he writes is  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.06" justify="left" indent="1">new; tho' it is only the Contents or Index of already </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.07" justify="left" indent="1">publish'd books</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.08" justify="left" indent="3">A man carried a monkey about for a shew, &amp; be- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.09" justify="left">-cause he was a little wiser than the monkey, grew </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.10" justify="left" indent="1">vain, and conciev'd himself as much wiser than se- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.11" justify="left">-ven men.  It is so with Swedenborg; he shews the </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.12" justify="left" indent="1">folly of churches &amp; exposes hypocrites, till he im </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.13" justify="left">-agines that all are religious. &amp; himself the single</l></lg><textfoot justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.01.14" justify="left" indent="40"><catchword>one</catchword></l></textfoot></phystext></desc><desc id="mhh.k.illbk.02" dbi="mhh.K.P22"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B22">(Bentley 22, </objcode><objcode code="E22">Erdman 22, </objcode><objcode code="K22">Keynes 22)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>14.9 x 10.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="775" width="562"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>At the end of line 1, a scrolled shape with wavy lines intersecting its midsection has been seen as a sea 
creature entangled in the remnants of a net; the scene as a whole is said to illustrate the text that continues from the previous plate, 
which describes Swedenborg's self-deceptions: he imagines "himself the single / one on earth that ever broke a net."  In this copy, the 
shape seems vegetative or worm-like.  Beyond this shape, a hunched figure (probably holding a book or tablet) sits on a vine.  Following 
"falshoods" in line 4, a figure clad in a billowing garment hovers amidst some vegetation.  Below, two elaborate spirals radiate from a 
common center right of line 8.  To the right of "further" in line 11 are several large leaves.  Next to "number" in line 16, three birds 
soar on extended wings.  To the left of the long-tailed bird and below the small, nondescript bird are two swollen vegetable forms.  A loop 
extending from the "h" of "he" at the end of line 17 coincides with the wing of the largest bird.  Four figures bound the plate's inscription, 
"A Memorable Fancy" (line 20), on three sides.  The first figure reclines beneath some leaves and branches to the left of the text.  The 
vegetation transforms into loops and squiggles clinging to the margin of the plate.  Above the inscription, a hovering figure, arm(s) extended, 
seems to reach for a serpent.  The four-looped vine growing from the "F" of "Fancy" and the squiggly "y" of the same word continue the serpentine 
motif.  To the right of the text, the third figure of the vignette stands facing right with arms raised at 135 degrees.  His head is bent back, 
and his posture suggests he has just been impaled by the invisible arrow released from the bow of the fourth figure, who leaps through the air 
brandishing the weapon.  Behind him, a snake or vine coils around a tall tuft of grass.  Further down, a flower with leaves and/or thorns adorns 
the space following "words" in line 23.  Right of the flower, a flying bird or insect appears to carry a vine through the air, recalling similar 
motifs on Plates 5, 15, and 19, although this may only be more vegetation in this copy.  A vegetable form follows, with another large leaf or vine 
extending horizontally below the last line of text, lower left.  Ornamenting the left margin are various other small-scale vegetative designs attached 
to letters.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>fish</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>net</characteristic><characteristic>worm</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the end of line 1, a scrolled, serpentine shape with wavy lines intersecting its midsection is sometimes seen 
as a sea creature entangled in the remnants of a net; the scene as a whole is said to illustrate the text that continues from the previous plate, 
which describes Swedenborg's self-deceptions: he imagines "himself the single / one on earth that ever broke a net."  In this copy, the form seems 
vegetative or worm-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders hunched</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>tablet</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>writing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the end of line 1 near the right margin, a small figure sits with hunched shoulders on a vine.  
The figure faces left.  It seems to hold a book or tablet.  Thus, the figure may be reading or writing.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Various swirls and lines crossing the blue wash at the end of line 1 suggest vines.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>vegetating</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>pointing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "falshoods" in line 4 is a hovering figure swathed in billowing garments.  The swirls and folds 
of the garment appear vegetative in nature.  The figure appears to be facing left and down, with one arm extended and perhaps pointing to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "falshoods" in line 4 is a figure swathed in billowing garments.  The swirls and folds of the garment 
appear vegetative in nature, and the figure is flanked by a small leaf-bearing branch on the left and flat, stylized leaves or ribbons on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "notions" in line 8, two long, loopy vines—cf. a similar interlinear motif on Plate 15—radiate from 
a common center.  The first four loops in the spiral on the right reverse the direction of those on the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three leaves, the first of which is particularly large and broad, appear to the right of "further" in line 11.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "number" in line 16, three birds soar on extended wings.  The bird on the far left has a 
particularly long, forked tail.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the left of the long-tailed bird and below the smaller, nondescript bird at the end of line 16 are two 
swollen vegetable forms.  A vine-like loop extending from the "h" of "he" at the end of line 17 coincides with the wing of the largest bird.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four figures bound the plate's inscription, "A Memorable Fancy," on three sides in line 20.  The first 
figure reclines beneath some leaves and branches to the left of the text.  Like Ezekiel in Plate 13, this figure lies on its side, 
                     but—unlike the prophet—it faces the viewer with head resting on hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The first of four figures that ornament the space around the plate's inscription reclines beneath some 
leaves and branches to the left of the text.  The vegetative canopy arches over the figure.  The slope on which it lies is vine-like, 
                     becoming snaky—i.e., loopy and serpentine—as it clings to and climbs the left margin.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the inscription, "A Memorable Fancy," in line 20, the second figure hovers, facing right.  Its 
legs are apart; one of them is extended backward and bent slightly at the knee.  The figure's body is horizontal.  Arm(s) outstretched, 
it seems to reach for the squiggly snake in front of it.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The hovering figure above the plate's inscription, "A Memorable Fancy," in line 20 seems to reach for the 
squiggly serpent in front of it.  The serpent faces right; its mouth is open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><characteristic>leaning</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the plate's inscription, "A Memorable Fancy," a nude male stands facing right with arms 
raised at 135 degrees.  His hands are turned with palms facing up.  The figure's head is bent back, and his legs are together; leaning 
backward, he appears to have just been impaled by the invisible arrow released from the bow of the fourth figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leaping</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended backward</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>shooting</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Facing the third figure who stands leaning slightly backward to the right of the plate's inscription, a nude 
figure leaps through the air brandishing a bow in its right arm.  The left arm is drawn back.  One leg is bent at the knee and extended backward.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The four-looped, spiraling vine growing from the "F" of "Fancy" in line 20 and the squiggly "y" of the 
same word continue the serpentine motif of the plate and the vignette.  Behind the nude figure who leaps through the air brandishing a 
bow, a snake(?) or vine coils around a tall tuft of grass near the right margin of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>coiled</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Near the right margin of the plate and following the inscription, "A Memorable Fancy," in line 20, 
the form coiled around a tall tuft of grass might be a snake.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>thorn</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A flower with leaves and/or thorns adorns the space following "words" in line 23.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Next to the flower at the end of line 23, a bird or an insect flies on extended wings with vegetation 
attached to it.  The creature appears to be facing up.  The motif recalls similar hybrids on Plates 5, 15, and 19.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Next to the flower at the end of line 23, a bird or an insect flies on extended wings with vegetation 
attached to it.  Two more vegetable forms follow, the first of which is in this copy attached to the vegetation held by the hybrid creature.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large vine extends horizontally beneath the last line of text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Ornamenting the left margin of the plate are various small-scale vegetative motifs, most of which are 
attached to letters, e.g., the leafy flourish off the "N" of "Now" in line 2 and the serpentine vines growing next to the "A" of "And" 
in line 5 and from the "H" of "Have" in line 12.  Vines or small leaves appear left of the first letters of the first words in lines 9 and 17.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.01" justify="left" indent="1">one on earth that ever broke a net.  </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.02" justify="left" indent="4">Now hear a plain fact: Swedenborg has not writ- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.03" justify="left">-ten one new truth: Now hear another: he has written </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.04" justify="left" indent="1">all the old falshoods.  </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.05" justify="left" indent="4">And now hear the reason. He conversed with Angels  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.06" justify="left" indent="1">who are all religious, &amp; conversed not with Devils who </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.07" justify="left" indent="1">all hate religion, for he was incapable thro' his conceited </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.08" justify="left" indent="1">notions.  </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.09" justify="left" indent="4">Thus Swedenborgs writings are a recapitulation of </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.10" justify="left" indent="1">all superficial opinions, and an analysis of the more   </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.11" justify="left" indent="1">sublime. but no further. </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.12" justify="left" indent="4">Have now another plain fact;  Any man of mechani-</l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.13" justify="left">-cal talents may from the writings of Paracelsus or Ja-</l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.14" justify="left">-cob Behmen, produce ten thousand volumes of equal </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.15" justify="left" indent="1">value with Swedenborg's. and from those of Dante or </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.16" justify="left" indent="1">Shakespear, an infinite number. </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.17" justify="left" indent="3">But when he has done this, let him not say that he </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.18" justify="left" indent="1">knows better than his master, for he only holds a can- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.19" justify="left">-dle in sunshine. </l></lg><texthead justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.20" justify="left" indent="15">A Memorable Fancy  </l></texthead><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.21" justify="left" indent="5">Once I saw a Devil in a flame of fire, who arose be </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.22" justify="left" indent="1">-fore an Angel that sat on a cloud. and the Devil ut- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.23" justify="left" indent="1">terd these words, </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.24" justify="left" indent="2">The worship of God is. Honouring his gifts in other  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.25" justify="left" indent="1">men each according to his genius, and loving the </l></lg><lg justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.02.26" justify="left" indent="41"><catchword>great-</catchword></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="mhh.k.illbk.03" dbi="mhh.K.P23"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B23">(Bentley 23, </objcode><objcode code="E23">Erdman 23, </objcode><objcode code="K23">Keynes 23)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.1 x 10.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="785" width="520"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Sundry figure and animal motifs appear below the text: in the lower left corner of the plate, a snake with 
a gaping mouth(?) faces left.  Next to it is what appears to be an upside-down human figure, head on the right and upper left leg on the left.  
Continuing the sequence, a hovering figure facing down is followed by another snake.  A final figure also lies on its side, but the viewer sees 
it from behind.  Various vegetative motifs adorn the left and especially the right margin, e.g., the serpentine vine bearing a leaf and/or bud 
following "replied" in line 5.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the bottom left corner of the plate, a snake with an enormous, gaping mouth(?) faces left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>arms raised</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In other copies, the second motif from the left at the bottom of the plate clearly depicts a figure on hands 
and knees, upside-down.  In Copy K, however, the form appears to be an upside-down falling figure, with arms raised vertically, head on the 
right facing up, and upper leg on the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>legs together</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the bottom of the plate, the third design from the left depicts a figure facing down, its body slightly 
curved and perhaps falling.  One or both arms are raised vertically (in relation to the figure's head); the figure appears to rest its head 
in the crook of its arm.  Its legs are together.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the bottom of the plate, a snake(?), or possibly just a thick vine, is flanked by two human figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>lying on side</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following the snake at the bottom of the plate, the last figure of the series lies on its side.  The figure is seen 
from behind.  One leg is extended; the other is drawn up and bent at the knee.  The nude figure rests its head on one arm, which is bent at the elbow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>bud</characteristic><characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Various vegetative motifs adorn the left and especially the right margin, e.g., the snaky vine bearing a leaf or 
bud following "replied" in line 5; the somewhat anthropomorphic, vine-like squiggles following "he" in line 13; and the leaf-bearing, serpentine 
shape next to "virtue" in line 23.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>serpent</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "virtue" in line 23, a snake-like vine bearing a single leaf resembles a small, winged serpent facing left.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.01" justify="left" indent="1">greatest men best, those who envy or calumniate </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.02" justify="left" indent="1">great men hate God, for there is no other God. </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.03" justify="left" indent="4">The Angel hearing this became almost blue </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.04" justify="left" indent="1">but mastering himself he grew yellow, &amp; at last </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.05" justify="left" indent="1">white pink &amp; smiling, and then replied, </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.06" justify="left" indent="4">Thou Idolater, is not God One? &amp; is not he </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.07" justify="left" indent="1">visible in Jesus Christ? and has not Jesus Christ </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.08" justify="left" indent="1">given his sanction to the law of ten commandments </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.09" justify="left" indent="1">and are not all other men fools. sinners, &amp; nothings? </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.10" justify="left" indent="4">The Devil answer'd; bray a fool in a morter with  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.11" justify="left" indent="1">wheat. yet shall not his folly be beaten out of him: </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.12" justify="left" indent="1">if Jesus Christ is the greatest man, you ought to </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.13" justify="left" indent="1">love him in the greatest degree; now hear how he  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.14" justify="left" indent="1">has given his sanction to the law of ten command- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.15" justify="left" indent="1">-ments: did he not mock at the sabbath, and so  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.16" justify="left" indent="1">mock the sabbaths God? murder those who were </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.17" justify="left" indent="1">murderd because of him? turn away the law from </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.18" justify="left" indent="1">the woman taken in adultery? steal the labor of </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.19" justify="left" indent="1">others to support him? bear false witness when </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.20" justify="left" indent="1">he omitted making a defence before Pilate? covet  </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.21" justify="left" indent="1">when he pray'd for his disciples, and when he bid </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.22" justify="left" indent="1">them shake off the dust of their feet against such </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.23" justify="left" indent="1">as refused to lodge them?  I tell you, no virtue </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.24" justify="left" indent="1">can exist without breaking these ten command- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.25" justify="left">-ments; Jesus was all virtue, and acted from im- </l></lg><lg justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.03.26" justify="left" indent="36"><catchword>-pulse</catchword></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="mhh.k.illbk.04" dbi="mhh.K.P24"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B24">(Bentley 24, </objcode><objcode code="E24">Erdman 24, </objcode><objcode code="K24">Keynes 24)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>This impression lacks the design below the text and the proverb beneath the design.  These were probably masked during printing, but might not have been executed on the copperplate.  All other known impressions include the design and proverb.</p></objnote><objsize>14.8 x 9.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="770" width="510"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="interlinear" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>At the top of the plate, following "rules" in line 1, a hunched-over figure sits with its head resting on its 
knees at one end of a serpentine vegetative motif.  Completing the vignette is another figure striding along the wavy ascender of "the" in 
line 2.  The figure faces right, arm(s) raised horizontally and a scarf floating behind it.  Next to "Elijah" at the end of line 4, a gowned 
figure hovers, facing left.  A winged figure seen from behind hovers in the left margin between lines 4 and 5; leaf-like forms appear to the 
                  right.  A serried scene of six sundry figures—flanked by books on the right and more books, or possibly vegetation, on the left—also appears 
between the text of lines 4 and 5.  Each of the figures sits or kneels; the left-most figure appears to be reading.  A small horse leaps right 
above "world" in line 8.  Following "well" at the end of the same line, a figure runs rightward, reaching for a small child.  The top half of 
the plate is dense with interlinear loops, vines, banners, and leaves, e.g., the vines and/or roots on either side of the figures populating 
the space between lines 4 and 5; the looped vines growing from the descender of "my" and the ascender of "friend," both in line 6; the elaborate 
curlicues following the text of line 10; and the small branch with spiky leaves extending from the "l" of "also" in line 9.  Wing-like vegetable 
                  objects and/or soaring birds grace the plate—above "have" and "whether" in lines 8 and 10 respectively, for example.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders hunched</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head on knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the plate, following "rules" in line 1, a hunched-over figure sits with its head resting on its 
knees at one end of a serpentine vegetative motif.  The figure faces left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At the top of the plate, following "rules" in line 1, a hunched-over figure sits with its head resting on its 
knees at one end of a serpentine vegetative motif.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>walking</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Completing the vignette next to "rules" in line 1 is a second figure striding along the wavy ascender of 
"the" in line 2.  The figure faces right, a scarf floating behind it.  The figure's arms are extended horizontally.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>bud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine-, flame-, or even wave-like motif grows from the ascender of "the" in line 2, providing a surface on 
which a figure strides.  At one end of the serpentine line, a small bud or flower is barely discernible near the upper right corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>Elijah</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following the text of line 4, a gowned and somewhat shadowy figure hovers, facing left.  Its arms are extended.  
The figure may represent the angel who "arose as Elijah" (24:4).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude, winged figure seen from behind hovers in the left margin between lines 4 and 5.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two leaf-like forms, or possibly curling vines, appear right of the winged figure hovering in the left margin 
between lines 4 and 5.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A scene of six sundry figures—flanked by books on the right and more books, or possibly vegetation, on 
                     the left—appears between the text of lines 4 and 5.  Each of the figures sits or kneels.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>hat</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The first figure between lines 4 and 5 sits facing left and appears to be reading a book.  The figure wears a hat.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The second figure between lines 4 and 5 sits facing forward, possibly cross-legged, on the ground.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders hunched</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>reading</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>devil</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The third figure from the left between lines 4 and 5 kneels on one leg, its body hunched over.  It faces 
right and down, as though looking at some indeterminate object held by the fourth figure sitting on the right, who faces forward.  Perhaps 
the two are absorbed in a book, illustrating the angel and devil of lines 5-7 who read the Bible together.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders hunched</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The fifth figure from the left between lines 4 and 5 sits on the ground and faces left and down in a 
hunched-over posture.  The sixth figure kneels behind its companion, resting its head on the other's back.  It faces left, although the 
figure's head may be turned toward the viewer.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>book</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following the final figure in the vignette between lines 4 and 5 are four books, two of which are stacked.  
The other two lean against them.  More volumes(?) appear to the left of the group of figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Bracketing on the left the group of figures between lines 4 and 5 are either books—complementing the four 
                     volumes on the other side of the vignette—or else an indeterminate vegetable motif.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>root</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Roots and/or vines flank the group of figures in the vignette between lines 4 and 5.  A single-looped 
tendril appears in front of and below the hovering figure at the end of line 4.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>arms extended</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "well" at the end of line 8, a figure runs rightward with arms extended horizontally, as 
though reaching for the small child standing in front of it.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Following "well" at the end of line 8, a figure runs rightward with arms extended, as though reaching for 
the small child standing in front of it.  The child faces left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Stylized leaves and/or vines ensconce the figure and child following "well" at the end of line 8.  
One leg of the figure on the left emerges from this foliage.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>horse</characteristic><characteristic>leaping</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above "world" in line 8, on the left side of the plate, a small horse leaps or runs right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Soaring birds and/or wing-like vegetable forms grace the plate—above "sense," "have," and "whether" in 
lines 7, 8, and 10 respectively, for example.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The top half of the plate is dense with interlinear loops, vines, banners, and leaves, e.g., the looped vines 
growing from the descender of "my" and the ascender of "friend," both in line 6; the snake-like flourish above "diabolical" in line 7; the 
elaborate, serpentine curlicues following the text of line 10; and the small branch with spiky leaves extending from the "l" of "also" in line 9.  
                     Wing-like vegetable forms and/or soaring birds grace the plate—above "sense" "have" and "whether" in lines 7, 8, and 10 respectively, for example.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.01" justify="left">-pulse. not from rules. </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="4">When he had so spoken:  I beheld the Angel who </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.03" justify="left" indent="1">stretched out his arms embracing the flame of fire </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="1">&amp; he was consumed and arose as Elijah. </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.05" justify="left" indent="5">Note. This Angel, who is now become a Devil, is </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.06" justify="left" indent="1">my particular friend: we often read the Bible to- </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.07" justify="left">-gether in its infernal or diabolical sense which </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.08" justify="left" indent="1">the world shall have if they behave well. </l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.09" justify="left" indent="4">I have also; The Bible of Hell: which the world </l><l n="mhh.k.illbk.04.10" justify="left" indent="1">shall have whether they will or no. </l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>