<bad id="nnr.d" type="illbk" work="There is No Natural Religion" copy="D" copyid="D" institution="houghton" catalog="bentley" catid="D" hidden="false">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="There is No Natural Religion">
                    <main>There is No Natural Religion</main>
                    <copy>copy D</copy>
: electronic edition
</title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside;
and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at
Chapel Hill</principal>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. 90KB; 18 JPEG
(ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 66KB to 583KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries
         <date>August 2015</date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, copies A, D, and M, from the British Museum, Houghton Library, and Victoria and Albert Museum respectively. They join copy B, from Yale Center for British Art, copy C, from the Library of Congress, and copies G1-2 and L, from the Morgan Library and Museum. The Archive now has all seven extant copies of this illuminated book, making <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> the sixth illuminated book with its entire publishing history reproduced in the Archive, joining <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>. The Archive will add <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> to the list later this year. <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> was composed and executed in 1788, shortly after <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>. These were Blake's first works in illuminated printing, though no copy of either work survives from this date. Blake composed twenty plates for <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> plates in two antithetical sets (a and b series). Only copy L consists exclusively of the ten b series of plates. The other twelve recorded copies of this book share impressions of the same group of either eight or twelve plates, which appeared to be merely incomplete sets of impressions until it was discovered that six of these copies were 19th-century reproductions. Once the inauthentic impressions were weeded out, it became apparent that what remained was Blake's selection of a and b plates for an abridged version of the work printed around 1794.   
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                With the publication of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> copies A, D, and M, the Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of 95 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. New protocols for transcription, which produce improved accuracy and fuller documentation in editors' notes, have been applied to all copies of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> in the Archive. With the Archive's Compare feature, users can easily juxtapose multiple impressions of any plate across all or selected copies of this or any of the other illuminated books and, with the Virtual Lightbox, users can examine any images in the Archive, as well as crop, zoom, and juxtapose them for close study.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                In addition to illuminated books, the Archive contains many important manuscripts and series of engravings, sketches, and water color drawings, including Blake's illustrations to Thomas Gray's <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, water color and engraved illustrations to Dante's <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>, the large color printed drawings of 1795 and c. 1805, the Linnell and Butts sets of the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi> water colors and the sketchbook containing drawings for the engraved illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, the water color illustrations to Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and all nine of Blake's water color series illustrating the poetry of John Milton. 
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                In December 2014, the Archive launched a new wing, which contains searchable HTML and PDF editions of thirty-nine past issues of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> published from 2000 through 2009. PDF versions present the journal as originally published, but the HTML versions are re-implemented with many full-color images from the Blake Archive, making it possible for users to link directly to those works that have been published in the Archive.
                <lb/>
                <lb/>
                As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.</updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
 Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/>
            <lb/>
This work courtesy Houghton Library, Harvard University.</userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>August 2015</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Michael Fox</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
                    <name>Rachel Lee,</name>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Adam Engel,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                    <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Scott Robinson,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD created, transcription established, and illustration description created</change>
                <date>October 2013</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                    <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
                    <name>Laura Bell</name>
                    <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                    <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Esther Arnold,</name>
                    <name>Amber Bertin,</name>
                    <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                    <name>Andrea Everett,</name>
                    <name>Joseph Fletcher,</name>
                    <name>Mike Fox,</name>
                    <name>Duncan Graham,</name>
                    <name>Shannon Jaime,</name>
                    <name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name>
                    <name>Eric Loy,</name>
                    <name>Kate Massie,</name>
                    <name>Adam McCune,</name>
                    <name>Ali McGhee,</name>
                    <name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name>
                    <name>Adair Rispoli,</name>
                    <name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name>
                    <name>Margaret Speer,</name>
                    <name>Sarah Tolf,</name>
                    <name>Danny Tsegai,</name>
                    <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name>
                    <name>Alia Wegner,</name>
                    <name>Megan Wilson,</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Conversion to Blake Archive Description DTD 2.1; Styles 2.0</change>
                <date>Summer 2000</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name>
                    <resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp>
                    <name>Robert Bingler, </name>
                    <name>David Cosca, </name>
                    <name>Kirk V. Hastings</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change>
                <date>2004</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                    <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                    <resp>Conversion: </resp>
                    <name>Aziza Technology Associates</name>
                    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                    <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                    <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                    <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                    <name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name>
                    <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                    <name>William Shaw</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>author, </role>
                    <role>inventor, </role>
                    <role>delineator, </role>
                    <role>etcher, </role>
                    <role>printer, </role>
                    <role>colorist</role><note>"The Author &amp; Printer W Blake" is etched in reverse at the bottom of Object 1.  In this copy, the lettering is partly obscured by coloring.</note>
                </origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role>
                </origination>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher>William Blake<note>Blake is named as the printer on the frontispiece, but he is also the "publisher."</note>
                    </publisher>
                    <pubplace>London
<note>The place of publication is not given in
the work, but Blake was living in London at the time of its composition and etching.  He was living in the London suburb of Lambeth at the time of its printing.</note>
                    </pubplace>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1788.B">c. 1788</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1794.C">c. 1794</printdate>
                <numberobj>9</numberobj>
                <objorder>Bentley Plates a1, a2, b3, a5-a9, b12<note>The leaves are loose and thus the binding order cannot be determined definitively.  The order given here follows the standard sequence established by the frontispiece (Object 1), the title page (Object 2), the sequence of roman numeral headings I-VI etched at the tops of Objects 3-8, and the plate with text beginning "Therefore" (Object 9).  Placing Bentley Plate b3 as Object 3 may seem odd, because it comes at the start of a group of "a" series plates, but this is the only way to complete the sequence of roman numeral headings I-VI.  An alternative to this arrangement would be to place Bentley Plate b3 as the penultimate object, just before Bentley Plate b12 and thereby keeping the "b" series plates together.  The pen and ink numbers far top left or top right on Objects 1-3, 7-9 (see Penned Numbers, below) suggest a different order, but these numbers are not by Blake and have no authority.  These numbers are not displayed here.</note>
                </objorder>
                <objsize>ranging between 4.7 x 3.7 cm. and 6.1 x 4.6
cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>9</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>13.9 x 10.9 cm. (Objects 1-3 and 9), 13.2 x 10.1 cm. (Object 4), 13.4 x 10.7 cm. (Objects 5-8)</leafsize>
                <medium>relief etching with touches of white-line etching on some
plates, rudimentary color printing on Objects 1, 3-9, and hand coloring in water colors on Object 1</medium>
                <printingstyle>relief, with rudimentary color printing on Objects 1, 3-9</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>burnt umber (Object 1), black (Object 2), and olive brown (Objects 3-9)</inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none<note>The etched numbers I-VI on objects 3-8 are
headings, not plate numbers.</note>
                </etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>1, 2, and 4 on Objects 1-3, 5 on Object 7, 6 on Object 8, and 3 on Object 9<note>These numbers, far top left or right, are not by Blake and have no authority.  They are not displayed here.</note>
                </pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <binding>none<note>The stab holes (see below) indicate that the plates were once bound, probably in the nineteenth century.</note>
                </binding>
                <stabholes>11?<note>There are at least 11 stab holes.  Those in Object 1, the frontispiece, are in the right margin, indicating that it was formerly bound facing Object 2, the title page.</note>
                </stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Houghton Library, Harvard University</name>
                <date>1941</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>Early history not known; acquired no later than 1891 by Edward William Hooper; his daughter Mrs. Greely Curtis, probably by inheritance in 1901; given by Hooper's daughters to Harvard University in July 1941.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Houghton Library</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Printing and Graphic Arts</addressline>
                <addressline>Harvard Yard</addressline>
                <addressline>Harvard University</addressline>
                <addressline>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138</addressline>
                <addressline>USA</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: 1 617 495 2444</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: 1 617 495 1376</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: pga@fas.harvard.edu</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www-hcl.harvard.edu/houghton/</addressline>
                <department>Printing and Graphic Arts</department>
                <repositoryid label="Call number">Typ 6500.32d</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.01" dbi="nnr.D.P1-a1">
            <objtitle>
                <title type="transcribed">There is No Natural Religion</title>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba1">(Bentley a1, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea1">Erdman a1, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka2">Keynes a2)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>5.3 x 4.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>Two youthful males, both nude and with curly hair, stand
on the right.  The youth furthest to the right appears to have his left
arm raised and may have his left hand resting on (or perhaps through?) the tree trunk near the
right margin.  The youth furthest to the left holds a shepherd's crook
in his right hand, although this prints as only a line with no visible top in this copy.
On the left is a seated couple; both the old man, with a long beard, and
the woman wear gowns.  The man may be seated on a fluted pillar.
The woman may have long hair or be wearing drapery (a scarf?) over her head.  Another tree
stands along the left margin; its branches and leaves form a canopy over
the seated figures.  Mountains dominate the distant
landscape.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>contrapposto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A youthful male, nude and with curly hair, stands on the
right.  He appears to have his left arm raised, perhaps with his left
hand resting on (or perhaps through?) the tree trunk near the right margin.  His right arm is
at his side.  His body suggests a contrapposto posture.  He looks down
and to the left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shepherd's crook</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A youthful male, nude and with curly hair, stands to the
left of another such figure.  He holds a shepherd's crook in his right
hand, although this prints only as a line with no distinct top in this copy.  At least his right arm is by his side.  His face
is partly turned to the right; he may be looking at his
companion.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>An old, bearded man with long hair sits on what is likely a fluted
                     pillar.  He wears a long gown and looks to the right.  His right arm is slightly bent and may rest on the pillar that he is seated on; his left arm appears to rest on his knee.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scarf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm resting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A woman sits behind and to the right of the old bearded
man.  She wears a gown and has drapery (a scarf?) over her head.  Her
left arm rests at her side.  Though she faces right like the man beside her, she turns her head slightly to look forward, perhaps at her companion.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="C">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadows, perhaps from the tree above, darken the ground in the lower left corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tree stands on the right.  Its branches and perhaps some
leaves spread out near the top of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tree stands on the left.  Its branches and leaves
form a canopy at the top of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="structure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>pillar</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The old, bearded man on the left sits on what appears to
be a fluted pillar.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>mountain</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape background is dominated by two ranges of
hills or mountains.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The green coloring of the hills or mountains in the background suggests they are covered in grass.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>earth</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The orange coloring in the middle distance of the landscape suggests either bare earth or  a mature crop.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="8"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.01.01" justify="left" indent="10">The Author &amp; Printer W Blake<note>In reverse lettering, partly obscured by color printing in black.</note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.02" dbi="nnr.D.P2-a2">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba2">(Bentley a2, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea2">Erdman a2, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka2">Keynes a2)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>5.0 x 4.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>The Gothic structure of spires and arches filling most of the plate may be a church facade, a church portal, a church window, or an imaginative variation on a tomb canopy of the sort Blake saw (and probably drew) in Westminster Abbey during his apprentice years. The tracery includes at least seven human figures; the largest, upper center, may be the Virgin Mary (who more clearly holds the Christ child in other copies). She is flanked on each side by two praying figures. On each side of the design, between sets of spires, are a pair of standing figures, one arranged above the other. Perhaps we are to think of all these figures as statues in stone. The words of the title are incorporated into the design.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="structure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>Gothic art</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spire</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>door</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facade</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>church</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tomb canopy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Westminster Abbey</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>window</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tracery</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The Gothic structure of spires and arches filling most of the plate may be a church facade, a church portal, the tracery of a church window, or an imaginative variation on a tomb canopy of the sort Blake saw (and probably drew) in Westminster Abbey during his apprentice years. Perhaps were are to think of this architectural confection as being built of stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Virgin Mary</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The largest figure in the design stands above the title word "There." The figure appears to be gowned and may be holding a small child or baby in (her?) left arm, although this small form is more clearly printed in other copies. If so, this figure group suggests the Virgin Mary and the Christ child. Given the context, this may be a statute in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>infant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The figure standing above title word "There" may be holding a baby or small child (more clearly printed in other copies). If so, then this may be the Virgin Mary and the Christ child. Given the context, this may be a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="A">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure, apparently with hands together in prayer and looking up and to the right, stands above the first two letters of the title word "There." Given the context, this may be a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="B">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure, apparently with hands together in prayer and looking to the left, stands or kneels above the final letter of the title word "There." Given the context, this may be a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>saint</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Difficult to distinguish in this copy, a small gowned figure stands rigidly among the Gothic tracery left of "There" in the title inscription. Given the setting, this may be a saint; the architectural context suggests that this is a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>saint</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A small gowned figure stands rigidly among the Gothic tracery left of "Religion" in the title inscription. The figure's right arm may be raised, bent at the elbow before his/her chest. Given the setting, this may be a saint; the architectural context suggests that this is a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>saint</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A small gowned figure stands rigidly among the Gothic tracery right of "No" in the title inscription. Given the setting, this may be a saint; the architectural context suggests that this is a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms at side</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>saint</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>statue</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A small gowned figure stands rigidly among the Gothic tracery right of "Religion" in the title inscription. His/her arms appear to be at his/her side. Given the setting, this may be a saint; the architectural context suggests that this is a statue in stone.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="text" location="E">
                        <characteristic>inscription</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                        <transcription>
                            <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                <l justify="left">There is No Natural Religion</l>
                            </lg>
                        </transcription>
                        <illusobjdesc>The title words are incorporated within the design. Perhaps we are to think of the words as inscribed in stone or on a door.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <vspace extent="5"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.c.illbk.02.01" justify="center">
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        THERE
                    </l>
                    <l n="nnr.c.illbk.02.02" justify="center">is NO</l>
                    <l n="nnr.c.illbk.02.03" justify="center">
                        <space extent="1"/>
                        NATURAL
                    </l>
                    <l n="nnr.c.illbk.02.04" justify="center">RELIGION</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.03" dbi="nnr.D.P3-b3">
            <objtitle>,
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Bb3">(Bentley b3, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Eb3">Erdman b3, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Kb3">Keynes b3)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>5.9 x 4.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure of indeterminate gender lies on the ground facing forward.  The figure appears to prop its upper body up on its elbows.  In other copies, the figure may read, write, or hold a book.  On the left is a clump of vegetation or perhaps the stump of a
                        tree.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A gowned figure of indeterminate gender lies on the ground facing forward.  The figure appears to prop its upper body up on its elbows and may wear its hair in a bun.  In other copies, the figure may read, write, or hold a book.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>stump</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There is a clump of vegetation, or perhaps the stump of a
                            tree, in the lower left corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="A">
                    <illusobjdesc>Vines or several branches spring from the first letter of
                        the text and arch to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Vines or several branches spring from the first letter of
                            the text and arch to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="D">
                    <illusobjdesc>A scroll-like vine curls right of the last line of
                        text and above the figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>scroll</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A scroll-like vine curls right of the last line of
                            text and above the figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.01" justify="left" indent="9">I</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.02" justify="left" indent="3">Mans percepti-</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.03" justify="left">-ons are not bound</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.04" justify="left">-ed by organs of</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.05" justify="left" indent="1">perception, he per-</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.06" justify="left">-cieves more than</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.07" justify="left" indent="1">sense (tho' ever</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.08" justify="left" indent="1">so acute) can</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.03.09" justify="left" indent="1">discover</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.04" dbi="nnr.D.P4-a5">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba5">(Bentley a5, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea5">Erdman a5, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka5">Keynes a5)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The leaf is inscribed, lower left in brown ink, "W. Blake: Sc" followed by another letter, possible "t" as an abbreviation for "sculpsit."  This inscription is not by Blake.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>5.0 x 3.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A woman, with long or medium-length hair and wearing a
long gown, kneels on the ground.  She looks down and to the right at a
young child she holds around the waist with her extended right arm and
hand (left arm not pictured).  The child, also kneeling and facing
right, is probably male; he may also be gowned.  He
extends his arms horizontally toward a small bird near the right margin.
These motifs may relate to the theme of "desires" (Erdman page 2) first raised
textually on plate a8.  The background, right of the woman and above the
child, is filled with a clump of trees.  Tall grass or other indeterminate vegetation grows above and behind the woman at left.  A large, leafless tree grows up
the left margin and spreads a branch between the heading number ("II")
and the first line of text.  Dark shadows appear to cover the ground along the bottom edge of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A woman, with long or medium-length hair and wearing a
long gown, kneels on the ground.  She looks down and to the right at a
young child she holds around the waist with her extended right arm and
hand (left arm not pictured).</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A young child, probably male and gowned, kneels on the ground and faces to the right.  While being held by a woman on the left, the child reaches,
arms extended horizontally, toward a small bird near the right
margin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="D">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A bird flies from the grasp of a
child.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape background is filled with
trees.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Tall grass or other indeterminate vegetation grows above and behind the woman at left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A leafless tree grows up the left margin.  One if its
branches extends between the heading number ("II") and the first line of
text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Dark shadows cover the ground along the bottom edge of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="8">II</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="3">Man by his reason-</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.04.03" justify="left">-ing power. can only</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="1">compare &amp; judge of</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.04.05" justify="left" indent="1">what he has already</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.04.06" justify="left" indent="1">perciev'd.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.05" dbi="nnr.D.P5-a6">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba6">(Bentley a6, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea6">Erdman a6, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka6">Keynes a6)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>5.0 x 3.7 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A man, with curly hair and perhaps also a beard, sits on the ground.  He
may be wearing a gown, as indicated by folds over his left hip.  He is
facing to the left and reaching with both arms in the same direction.
His legs are extended horizontally to the left.  A winged and nude
putto, visible from the waist up, appears behind the seated man's legs.
This second figure looks to the right and reaches toward, and perhaps
touches, the seated man's right shoulder with his left hand.  The
putto's right arm is raised, with one finger of his right hand pointing
heavenward.  This gesture, and simply the winged child himself, may
indicate the spiritual perceptions not available to the "3 senses" (Erdman page 2).
A slender tree or vine, intertwined with a second vine, grows up the
right margin and extends in loops horizontally above and below the
heading number ("III") and terminates in three spirals.  There may be
some plants left of the putto, lower left.  Dark shadows appear to cover the ground beneath the man in the lower right corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>palm out</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A man with curly hair, who may also have a beard(?), sits on the ground.  He
may be wearing a gown, as indicated by folds over his left hip.  He is
facing to the left, with legs extended in the same direction, and
reaching with both arms to the left. His left palm is probably down, his right palm faces out toward the viewer.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>putto</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pointing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>upper body</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A winged putto, seen from the waist up, appears behind the
legs of the seated man.  The putto's left arm is extended horizontally;
his left hand reaches toward, and may touch, the right shoulder of the
seated man.  The putto's right arm is raised and a finger on his right
hand points heavenward.  There are no clear indications of
clothing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A slender tree or vine, intertwined with a second vine,
grows up the right margin and extends in loops horizontally above and
below the heading number ("III") and terminates in three
spirals.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine is intertwined around the tree or vine
growing
up the right margin.  This second vine seems to end in the top
right corner; the larger tree or vine extends horizontally to the
left margin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>There may be some plants left of the putto, lower
left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="D">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Dark shadows appear to cover the ground beneath the man in the lower right corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.05.01" justify="left" indent="10">III</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.05.02" justify="left" indent="3">From a perception of</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.05.03" justify="left" indent="1">only 3 senses or 3 ele</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.05.04" justify="left">-ments none could de-</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.05.05" justify="left">-duce a fourth or fifth</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.06" dbi="nnr.D.P6-a7">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba7">(Bentley a7, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea7">Erdman a7, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka7">Keynes a7)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>4.7 x 3.9 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc> A man, perhaps wearing tights or some other body-hugging
costume, sits on the ground with his back against a tree.  He is playing
a pipe, held near his mouth with his right hand and lower on the pipe
with his left.  He faces to the right, with his legs extended to the
right and crossed at the knee.  He wears a hat, decorated with what
appear to be feathers.  The landscape on the right is composed of a low
hill and a grove of trees or other indeterminate vegetation.  A single tree extends up the
left margin, its base visible to the left of the piper and its top visible to the left of lines 1-2 of the text.  Three birds fly in the sky above the text and on each side of the
heading number ("IV").</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tights</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaning</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs extended</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>playing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hat</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>feather</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>pipe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>earring</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A man, perhaps wearing tights or some other
body-hugging costume, sits on the ground with his back against a
tree.  He is playing a pipe, held near his mouth with his right
hand and lower on the pipe with his left.  He faces to the right,
with his legs extended to the right and crossed at the knee.  He
wears a hat, decorated with what appear to be two or three
feathers. Although clearer in other copies, he may also wear a hoop earring in his right ear.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape above the seated figure includes a low hill
and a grove of trees or other indeterminate vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The landscape above the seated figure includes a low hill and a grove of trees or other indeterminate vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tree grows up the left margin, its base visible to the left of the piper and its top visible to the left of lines 1-2 of the text.  One short branch
arches to the right near the top of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="AB">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Three birds fly above the text, one left of the
heading number ("IV") and two right of the number.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.06.01" justify="left" indent="11">IV</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.06.02" justify="left" indent="3">None could have other</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.06.03" justify="left">than natural or organic</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.06.04" justify="left">thoughts if he had none</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.06.05" justify="left">but organic perceptions</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.07" dbi="nnr.D.P7-a8">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba8">(Bentley a8, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea8">Erdman a8, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka8">Keynes a8)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>4.7 x 3.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A boy with curly hair strides, right foot forward, back
and to the left.  He wears knee-length breeches and perhaps a shirt.
With arms extended horizontally to the left and fingers spread open on
at least his left hand, he reaches toward a duck or swan floating on a
small body of water (perhaps a river or lake).  The boy's gestures
suggest the theme of "Mans desires" (Erdman page 2) in the text.  A tree, with an
intertwined vine, grows up the left margin.  One of the tree's branches,
perhaps bearing a few spiky leaves, arches over the heading number and
text at the top of the plate.  A dark shadow extends along the ground
from the base of the tree on the left to the boy's feet on the
right.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>child</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>short hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>breeches</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>shirt</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>fingers</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A boy with short, curly hair strides, right foot forward, back
and to the left.  He wears knee-length breeches and perhaps a shirt.
With arms extended horizontally to the left and fingers spread open on
at least his left hand, he reaches toward a duck or swan on the
left.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="animal" location="C">
                        <characteristic>bird</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>swan</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>duck</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>floating</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A duck or swan floats on a small body of water,
perhaps a lake or river.  The bird faces to the
right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tree grows up the left margin of the plate.  One of its
branches, bearing a few spiky leaves, arches over the heading number and
text at the top of the plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>entwined</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine is entwined around the lower half of the
tree
near the left margin.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lake</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>river</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The bird lower left appears to be floating on a
small
body of water, perhaps a lake or river.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A dark shadow extends along the ground from the
base
of the tree on the left to the boy's feet on the
right.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.07.01" justify="left" indent="8">V</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.07.02" justify="left" indent="2">Mans desires are</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.07.03" justify="left">limited by his percepti</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.07.04" justify="left" indent="4">ons. none can de<hi rend="superscript">.</hi>
                        <note>The slightly raised dot at the end of the line may be a fragment of a hyphen.</note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.07.05" justify="left">-sire what he has not</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.07.06" justify="left">perciev'd</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.08" dbi="nnr.D.P8-a9">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Ba9">(Bentley a9, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ea9">Erdman a9, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Ka9">Keynes a9)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>5.4 x 4.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A figure of indeterminate gender who may be gowned lies on the ground with legs
extended to the left and perhaps crossed.  He or she props up its upper body
with its arms.  The figure may hold its head in its left hand in a posture
traditionally associated with melancholy, though this is clearer in other copies.  The long, spiky leaves of two plants, or
exceptionally long grasses, arch over his head from both the right and
left sides of the plate.  A tree grows up the right margin; its branches
and leaves extend horizontally along the top of the plate.  A vine is
entwined around the tree's trunk.  One tendril of the vine terminates in
a lily-like flower just above and slightly to the right of the figure's
head.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head on hand</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>melancholy</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A figure of indeterminate gender who may be gowned lies on the ground with legs
                            extended to the left and perhaps crossed.  He or she props up its upper body
                            with its arms.  The figure may hold its head in its left hand in a posture
                            traditionally associated with melancholy, though this is clearer in other copies.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>The long leaves of two plants, or very long
grasses,
arch over the figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="E">
                        <characteristic>tree</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>branch</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A tree grows up the right margin.  Its branches and
leaves extend horizontally along the top margin of the
plate.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>intertwined</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lily</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine is intertwined around the tree near the
right margin of the plate.  One of the vine's tendrils terminates in a
lily-like flower just above and slightly to the right of the
figure's head.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.08.01" justify="left" indent="12">VI</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.08.02" justify="left" indent="2">The desires &amp; percepti-</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.08.03" justify="left">-ons of man untaught by</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.08.04" justify="left">any thing but organs of</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.08.05" justify="left">sense, must be limited</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.08.06" justify="left">to objects of sense.</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
        <desc id="nnr.d.illbk.09" dbi="nnr.D.P9-b12">
            <objtitle>,
<objid>
                    <objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber>
                    <objcode code="Bb12">(Bentley b12, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Eb12">Erdman b12, </objcode>
                    <objcode code="Kb12">Keynes b12)</objcode>
                </objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>6.1 x 4.6 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="400" height="400"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="CD">
                    <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, lies supine on a bed, bier,
or—if he is of great size—on hills.  His legs may be
crossed at the knees.  His right arm dangles rather limply at his side.  There are no clear
indications of clothing.  Perhaps he is sleeping or dead.  Lines of
radiance appear around his head.  This last motif suggests that this may
be Christ, the "God" who "becomes as we are" (Erdman page 3) in the
text.  Shadows darken the forms beneath the figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>supine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>dead</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>sleeping</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>aura</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hill</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bier</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>bed</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, lies supine on a bed, bier,
or—if he is of great size—on hills.  His legs may be
crossed at the knees.  His right arm dangles rather limply at his side.  There are no clear
indications of clothing.  Perhaps he is sleeping or dead.  Lines of
radiance appear around his head.  This last motif suggests that this may
be Christ, the "God" who "becomes as we are" (Erdman page 3) in the
text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Shadows darken what may be a bed, bier, or hills beneath the supine figure.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="AB">
                    <illusobjdesc>Several vines decorate the spaces on all sides of the
first line of text ("Therefore").  A single vine appears above the first four letters.  Though nearly indistinguishable here, in other copies there is a vine with three branches left of the word.  A vine with a single
loop and perhaps some leaves grows at the end of the word.  Two vines
lie beneath the word; the one on the right has a single loop and
terminates in three leaves or small flowers.  A horizontal line separates the text from the design below.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine appears above the first four letters of "Therefore" (line 1).  Though nearly indistinct here, in other copies there is also a vine with three branches left of the word.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="B">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine with a single loop and perhaps long, slender
leaves at its termination appears in the margin right of
"Therefore."</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="A">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine, perhaps with a few small leaves, appears
under
the first four letters of "Therefore."</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="B">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine with a single loop appears beneath and to
the
right of the last four letters of "Therefore."  It terminates in
three leaves or small flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="B">
                    <illusobjdesc>A vine descends in the margin right of the third
and
fourth lines of text.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="B">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine descends in the margin right of the third
and
fourth lines of text.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="C">
                    <illusobjdesc>A vine appears left of the last line of text
("is").</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="C">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine appears left of the last line of text
("is").</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="CD">
                        <characteristic>line</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A horizontal line separates the text from the design below.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
                <illustration type="interlinear" location="D">
                    <illusobjdesc>A vine with two loops descends right of the last
line
of text ("is") and into the space between the text and the
illustration at the bottom of the plate.  The vine bears several
leaves or small flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                        <characteristic>vine</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>loop</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leaf</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A vine with two loops descends right of the last
line
of text ("is") and into the space between the text and the
illustration at the bottom of the plate.  The vine bears several
leaves or small flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
            <phystext>
                <texthead justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.09.01" justify="left" indent="1">Therefore</l>
                </texthead>
                <vspace extent="1"/>
                <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.09.02" justify="left">God becomes as</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.09.03" justify="left">we are, that we</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.09.04" justify="left">may be as he</l>
                    <l n="nnr.d.illbk.09.05" justify="left" indent="5">is</l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>