<info id="pid">
    <worktitle>
        <div id="pid.title">
            <h1>Pen and Ink Drawings, 1774-c. 1825</h1>
        </div>
    </worktitle>
    <remarks>
        <div id="pid.top">
            <p>This group of pen and ink drawings, ranging chronologically from Blake's apprenticeship as an engraver to the final decade of his life, offers a comprehensive overview of his work in the medium.  Most were created when Blake was learning his craft as an artist and reveal his exploration of various themes and genres. His apprentice drawings for James Basire (<i>The Body of Edward I and Countess Aveline</i>) show his early engagement with medieval art. Another group (two drawings titled <i>Figures from a Greek Vase</i> and <i>Charon</i>) is clearly based on classical art or mythology, responses to which were central to British art and design in the second half of the eighteenth century. The cluster of related sketches on two leaves, each titled <i>Four Composition Sketches</i>, is the earliest extant example of Blake’s attempt to construct a pictorial narrative through a series of images. In these, he began to develop his own version of the sublime, an aesthetic more fully represented by the texts and designs in the illuminated books of the 1790s. Several works from the 1780s show the influence of neoclassicism and take their subjects from two fields of lasting interest to Blake: British history (<i>King Alfred</i>, <i>A Woman Enthroned</i>, and <i>Procession of Monks</i>) and the Bible (<i>Saul and David</i>, <i>Goliath Cursing David</i>, and two versions of <i>The Good Farmer</i>). The three much later drawings are exceptions to Blake’s customary procedures and subjects: a landscape <i>Garden Path</i>, <i>The Prophet Isaiah</i> drawn on a woodblock for a wood engraving never executed, and <i>Lady Torrens</i>, a copy of a family portrait by his friend and patron John Linnell.</p>
            <p>Blake did not execute a large number of pen and ink drawings. This is a bit surprising, given the compatibility between the linearity of the medium and his insistence on “the distinct, sharp, and wirey ... bounding line” as the “great and golden rule of art” (Blake’s <i>Descriptive Catalogue</i>, Erdman 550). He did, however, make extensive use of pen and ink work to outline forms in his water colors, color prints, and hand tinted relief etchings in the illuminated books. For preliminary sketching, Blake favored pencil over pen and ink, probably because of the lower cost of pencil and the ease of erasure and correction it offered.</p>
        </div>
    </remarks>
    <related>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Body of Edward I in His Coffin, Two Finished Drawings</i>
            <br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1774.  Butlin 2.<br/>
            
            Society of Antiquaries<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>Countess Aveline, Side View of Her Tomb</i>
            <br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, 1775.  Butlin 3.<br/>
            
            Society of Antiquaries<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>Countess Aveline, Effigy Seen from Above</i>
            <br/>
            Monochrome wash drawing, 1775.  Butlin 4.<br/>
            
            Society of Antiquaries<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>Countess Aveline, Three Details from Her Tomb</i>
            <br/>
            Water color, c. 1775.  Butlin 5.<br/>
            
            Society of Antiquaries<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Good Farmer</i>
            <br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1780-85.  Butlin 121.<br/>
            
            British Museum<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Good Farmer</i>, recto
            <br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1780-85.  Butlin 122.<br/>
            
            Collection of Robert N. Essick<br/>
            
            Altadena, California
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Good Farmer</i>, recto
            <br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1780-85.  Butlin 123.<br/>
            
            Tate Collection<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Good Farmer</i>
            <br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1780-85.  Butlin 124.<br/>
            
            Humanities Research Center, University of Texas<br/>
            
            Austin, Texas
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>Christ as the Good Farmer</i>
            <br/>
            Pencil (?).  Butlin 125.<br/>
            Untraced since 1863
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>A Man and Woman Kneeling and Warming Themselves at a Fire</i>
            <br/>
            
            Water color, c. 1785-90.  Butlin 87.<br/>
            
            British Museum<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            Charles Allen, <i>A New and Improved History of England</i>, 1798. Plate 1, "Alfred and the Neat-herd's Wife."
            <br/>
            
            Etching/engraving after Henry Fuseli, 1798.  Bentley 415, plate 1.<br/>
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>Landscape with a Spire</i>
            <br/>
            
            Pencil sketch, c. 1801.  Butlin 371.<br/>
            
            Yale Center for British Art<br/>
            
            New Haven, Connecticut
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>Milton a Poem</i>, plate 38
            <br/>
            
            Relief etching, c. 1804-11.  Bentley 118, plate 38.<br/>
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <link type="object" ptr="but457.1.wc.01">
                <i>Goliath Cursing David</i>
            </link>
            <br/> 
            
            Water color, c. 1803-05.  Butlin 457.<br/>
            
            Museum of Fine Arts<br/>
            
            Boston, Massachusetts
            
        </relationship>
        <relationship>
            <i>The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Crucifixion and the Ascension</i>
            <br/> 
            
            Pencil sketch, c. 1821.  Butlin 772.<br/>
            
            British Museum<br/>
            
            London
            
        </relationship>
    </related>
</info>