<bad id="relbut330.1" type="penc" work="Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Young's Night Thoughts" copy="1"
    copyid="1" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="butlin" catid="330">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Edward Young's &#34;Night Thoughts&#34;"
                        ><main>Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Edward Young's "Night Thoughts"</main> :
                    electronic edition </title>
                <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</principal>
                <respstmt> </respstmt>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. ??KB; 2 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from ???KB
                to ???KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                    Archives<date>???</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2013</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
            only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © 2013 British Museum.</userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        *Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Young's Night Thoughts*
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake<role>inventor, </role><role>delineator. See Work
                        Information for the whole series of water colors for further
                        information.</role></origination>
                <origination>Richard Edwards. Edwards, the publisher who commissioned Blake's
                    designs, signed the mount upper right in ink; see the Textual
                        Transcription.<role>delineator</role></origination>
                <origination>William A White. White, who acquired Blake's *Night
                        Thoughts* water colors from Marsden J. Perry in 1980, inscribed the
                    mount upper right in pencil. See the Note on Provenance on the Work Information
                    page and the Textual Transcription.<role>delineator</role></origination>
                <compdate value="1795">c. 1795-97</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>1<note>This pencil sketch on the verso of the first leaf of Blake's *Night Thoughts* water color illustrations is a preliminary
                        drawing for the water color on the recto; see object 1.</note></numberobj>
                <objsize>approximately 42.0 x 32.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>1</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>approximately 42.0 x 32.5 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pencil</medium>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <pennednumbers>none<note>The British Museum collection stamp appears lower
                        left.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>5<note>The frame lines are on the mount. The innermost frame line is
                        contiguous with the leaf on which Blake drew his sketch.</note></framelines>
                <binding>loose<note>Originally bound in two volumes in red morocco, probably no
                        later than 1798. The binder's label, "Benedict, No. 4, Mays Building, Saint
                        Martins Lane, London," appears in each volume. Disbound by the British
                        Museum c. 1929. This leaf, like its companions, is now encased in Perspex, a
                        polymethyl methacrylate plastic.</note></binding>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>British Museum</name>
                <date>1929</date>
                <dealer>none</dealer>
                <price>gift</price>
                <note>The entire series of water colors was commissioned by the publisher Richard
                    Edwards c. 1795; passed to his brother Thomas Edwards of Halifax c. 1799 when
                    Richard Edwards left Britain; offered by Thomas Edwards in his catalogue of *Superb Books of Prints, Atlases, Books Printed on Vellum with
                        Miniatures, and Other Superlatively Fine Articles* of 1821, item 3, two
                    volumes bound in red morocco (£300); offered at a Winstanley's auction,
                    Manchester, 10 May 1826, lot 1076 (not sold on a reserve of £50); offered at a
                    Stewart, Wheatley, and Adlard auction, London, 15-24 May 1828, ninth day, lot
                    1130 (bought-in at £52.10s.); by inheritance to the widow of Rev. John Edwards;
                    sold 1874 through the dealer H. W. Birtwhistle of Halifax and the London dealer
                    James Rimell for £475 to the dealer James Bain; sold by 1905 through Scribner,
                    the New York dealer, to Marsden J. Perry of Providence, Rhode Island, for £1500;
                    sold 1908 to William Augustus White of Brooklyn, New York; by inheritance in
                    1926 to White's daughter, Frances White Emerson; given by Emerson to the British
                    Museum in the winter of 1928-29. A label accompanying the designs, probably
                    written by W. A. White, states that he acquired them with other works by Blake
                    from Marsden J. Perry on 28 March 1908.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>British Museum</institution>
                <addressline>Department of Prints and Drawings</addressline>
                <addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline>
                <addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline>
                <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: +44 (0)20 7323 8408</addressline>
                <addressline>Fax: +44 (0)20 7323 8999</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: prints@britishmuseum.org</addressline>
                <addressline>URL:
                    http://www.britishmuseum.org/the_museum/departments/prints_and_drawings.aspx</addressline>
                <department>Prints and Drawings</department>
                <repositoryid label="Accession number">1929.7.13.1</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="relbut330.1.pd.01" dbi="BUT330.1.1v.PD">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Young's Night
                    Thoughts</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">object 1 </objnumber><objcode
                        code="U1">(Butlin 330.1 verso)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>This pencil sketch on the verso of the first leaf of Blake's *Night Thoughts* illustrations is a preliminary drawing for the
                        water color on the recto; see object 1. The mount, top right, is signed in
                        pen and ink by the publisher who commissioned Blake's designs, "Richard
                        Edwards / High Elms." He probably signed the mount no later than c. 1799
                        when he left Britain and the water colors passed into the possession of his
                        brother Thomas Edwards. Below the signature is a pencil inscription by
                        William Augustus White, "W a White / 28 March 19[08, trimmed off] / of M. J.
                        Perry." White acquired the entire series of designs from Marsden J. Perry in
                        1908; see the Note on Provenance on the Work Information page.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>42.0 x 32.5 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="680"/>
            </physdesc>
            <illusdesc>
                <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                    <illusobjdesc>A lightly sketched nude male stands in the center of the design.
                        This is Christ, as in the water color on the recto for which this sketch is
                        a preliminary drawing. Lines around his head suggest beams of light or
                        radiance. The figure faces right with his torso twisted forward and his head
                        turned to the left. Both arms are raised at 135 degrees and his hands are
                        not clearly pictured. The figure's left leg is bent with the left foot
                        raised on tiptoe; he may walk to the right. Alternatively, the figure may be
                        flying or hovering. Lightly sketched lines in the upper left corner and
                        along the right border suggest clouds or perhaps smoke. A lightly sketched
                        angel with folded wings kneels in the lower right portion of the design. The
                        figure faces left with his head turned down. His left arm is bent slightly
                        and may rest on his lap. A lightly sketched circle visible in the lower left
                        portion of the design may represent the head of an indistinct figure. This
                        is probably a rough indication of the angel pictured lower left in the water
                        color on the recto. Two lightly sketched male faces appear near the left
                        center border of the design. One with curly hair faces forward; the other,
                        pictured immediately to the left, faces left in profile. These faces were
                        not retained in the water color on the recto and may be unrelated to this
                        preliminary drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    <component type="figure" location="E">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>Christ</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>standing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>leg bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>tiptoe</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>walking</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>flying</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A lightly sketched nude male stands in the center of the
                            design. This is Christ, as in the water color on the recto for which
                            this sketch is a preliminary drawing. Lines around his head suggest
                            beams of light or radiance. The figure faces right with his torso
                            twisted forward and his head turned to the left. Both arms are raised at
                            135 degrees and his hands are not clearly pictured. The figure's left
                            leg is bent with the left foot raised on tiptoe; he may walk to the
                            right. Alternatively, the figure may be flying or
                            hovering.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="object" location="E">
                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>smoke</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Lightly sketched lines in the upper left corner and along the
                            right border suggest clouds or perhaps smoke.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="D">
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>arm on lap</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A lightly sketched angel with folded wings kneels in the lower
                            right portion of the design. The figure faces left with his head turned
                            down. His left arm is bent slightly and may rest on his
                            lap.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="C">
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>angel</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>A lightly sketched circle visible in the lower left portion of
                            the design may represent the head of an indistinct figure. This is
                            probably a rough indication of the angel, kneeling and facing right with
                            his head turned down, pictured lower left in the water color on the
                            recto.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                    <component type="figure" location="AC">
                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>head</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>face</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                        <illusobjdesc>Two lightly sketched male faces appear near the center left
                            border of the design. One with curly hair faces forward; the other,
                            pictured immediately to the left, faces left in profile. These faces
                            were not retained in the water color on the recto and may be unrelated
                            to this preliminary drawing.</illusobjdesc>
                    </component>
                </illustration>
            </illusdesc>
        </desc>
        <desc id="relbut330.1.pd.02" dbi="BUT330.1.1v-full.PD">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Young's Night
                    Thoughts</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">full sheet including frame lines
                    </objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The frame lines are on the mount. For further information about the mounts
                        and related topics, see Work Information for the entire water color
                        series.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>47.1 x 37.2 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="680"/>
            </physdesc>
        </desc>
        <desc id="relbut330.1.pd.03" dbi="BUT330.1.1v-insc.PD">
            <objtitle><title type="transcribed">Verso Sketch on Object 1 of Young's Night
                    Thoughts</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">top mount inscription
                    </objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objnote>
                    <p>The first two lines of the inscription were written by Richard Edwards, who
                        commissioned Blake's *Night Thoughts* illustrations. William
                        Augustus White, who acquired the water color series from Marsden J. Perry in
                        1908, wrote lines 3-5 in pencil.</p>
                </objnote>
                <objsize>4.9 x 6.3 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize width="600" height="680"/>
            </physdesc>
            <phystext>
                <lg justify="left">
                    <l n="relbut330.1.pd.03.01" justify="left">Richard Edwards<note>Edwards, who
                            commissioned Blake's *Night Thoughts* illustrations,
                            signed the mount and inscribed his place of residence (line 2) in pen
                            and ink upper right. He probably signed the mount no later than c. 1799
                            when he left Britain and the water colors passed into the possession of
                            his brother Thomas Edwards.</note></l>
                    <l n="relbut330.1.pd.03.02" justify="left" indent="3">High Elms</l>
                    <l n="relbut330.1.pd.03.03" justify="left" indent="6">W a White<note>Lines 3-5
                            were inscribed by William Augustus White in pencil.</note></l>
                    <l n="relbut330.1.pd.03.04" justify="left" indent="6">28 March 19<note>The last
                            two digits of the year are trimmed off. White acquired Blake's <hi
                                rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> water colors from Marsden J. Perry in
                            1908; see the Note on Provenance on the Work Information
                        page.</note></l>
                    <l n="relbut330.1.pd.03.05" justify="left" indent="6">of M. J. Perry<note>Perry
                            owned Blake's <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> water colors between c.
                            1905 and 1908; see the Note on Provenance on the Work Information
                            page.</note></l>
                </lg>
            </phystext>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
