<bad id="s-los.c" type="illbk" work="The Song of Los" copy="C" copyid="C" institution="morgan" catalog="bentley" catid="C"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Song of Los"><main>The Song of Los</main><copy> Copy C</copy>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt>
               
            </respstmt><sponsor>The
               Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the University of Rochester
            </sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>1 XML file approx. 90KB; 16 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 175KB to 1600KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>July 2009</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> Copies C and E, from the Morgan Library and Museum and the Huntington Library and Art Gallery, respectively. They join Copies A and D from the British Museum and Copy B from the Library of Congress, giving the Archive five of the six extant copies of this illuminated book.
            <lb/><lb/>
            
            The eight plates of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> were produced in 1795; all extant copies (A-F) were color printed in that year in a single press run. Divided into sections entitled "Africa" and "Asia," <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> is the last of Blake's "Continental Prophecies" (see also <hi rend="i">America</hi> [1793] and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> [1794], exemplary printings of which are in the Archive). Blake abandons direct references to contemporary events to pursue the junctures among biblical narrative, the origins of law and religion, and his own developing mythology. Adam, Noah, Socrates, Brama, Los, Urizen, and several others represent both historical periods and states of consciousness. The loose narrative structure reaches towards a vision of universal history ending with apocalyptic resurrection.
            <lb/><lb/>
            Plates 1, 2, 5, and 8 (frontispiece, title page, and full page designs) are color printed drawings, executed on millboards and printed in the planographic manner of—and probably concurrent with—the twelve Large Color Printed Drawings of 1795, which are also in the Archive. Plates 3 and 4, which make up "Africa," and Plates 6 and 7, which make up "Asia," were executed first, side by side on two oblong pieces of copper (Plates 3/4, 6/7). Initially designed with double columns in landscape format, the texts of the poems were transformed into vertical pages by printing the oblong plates with one side masked. In Copies C and E, Plates 5 and 8 are differently arranged: 8 follows Plate 1 and 5 is placed at the end in Copy C; 8 follows Plate 3 and 5 follows Plate 6 in Copy E.
            
            <lb/><lb/>
            Like all the illuminated books in the Archive, the text and images of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> Copies C and E are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications. With the Archive's Compare feature, users can easily juxtapose multiple impressions of any plate across the different copies of this or any of the other illuminated books. New protocols for transcription, which produce improved accuracy and fuller documentation in editors' notes, have been applied to all copies of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> in the Archive.
            <lb/><lb/>
            With the publication of these copies of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, the Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of seventy copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. In addition to illuminated books, the Archive contains many important manuscripts and series of engravings, sketches, and water color drawings, including Blake's illustrations to Thomas Gray's <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, water color and engraved illustrations to Dante's <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>, the large color printed drawings of 1795 and c. 1805, the Linnell and Butts sets of the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi> water colors and the sketchbook containing drawings for the engraved illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, the water color illustrations to Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and all nine of Blake's water color series illustrating the poetry of John Milton.
            <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2009</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 2009 Morgan Library and Museum.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication</change><date>July 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants:</resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Michelle Langston,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>BAD and illustration description creation</change><date>Summer 2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin,</name><name>Christopher N. Jackson,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Image scanning, metadata creation and color correction</change><date>November 2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue </name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Ashley Reed,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The Song of Los*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination><imprint><publisher> William Blake</publisher><pubplace>Lambeth</pubplace><date>1795</date></imprint><compdate value="1795.A">1795</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1795.C">1795</printdate><numberobj>8</numberobj><objorder>1, 8, 2-4, 6-7, 5<note>This binding order is recorded in Bentley page 358.  This would appear to be the most recent binding order before the stitching (see Bentley page 362) was removed and the plates separately matted.  This unusual sequence of plates was almost certainly not established by Blake and may have been created when this copy was bound, with two other illuminated books, early in the nineteenth century.  The evidence of offsets is ambiguous but suggests an earlier binding order of 2-7, 1, 8.  It is also possible that Blake’s original arrangement was the standard 1-8 sequence.  Bentley plate numbers are used here.</note></objorder><objsize>ranging between 24.3 x 17.5 cm. and 21.5 x 13.5
cm.</objsize><numberleaves>8</numberleaves><leafsize>35.9 x 24.8 cm.</leafsize><medium>Relief etching with color printing and hand coloring. The title page and full-plate designs (Plates 1-3, 8 as arranged in this copy, Bentley Plates 1, 8, 2, 5) were color printed planographically.</medium><printingstyle>Relief with color printing. The title page and
full-plate designs (Plates 1-3, 8 as arranged in this copy, Bentley Plates 1, 8, 2, 5) were color printed
planographically.</printingstyle><inkcolor>olive brown<note>Plates 1, 2, and 8 as arranged in this copy (Bentley Plates 1, 8, and 5) may not contain any underlying ink beneath the thick color printing.  The olive brown color of the text on Plate 3 as arranged in this copy (Bentley Plate 2, the title page) may be color-printing medium rather than ink.</note></inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>disbound and matted<note>Formerly bound with *Visions of the Daughters of Albion* Copy H and *Europe a Prophecy* Copy G in early nineteenth-century half red morocco.  The volume was disbound after its sale at auction in May 1958, but the leaves remained stitched together until at least 1977.</note></binding><stabholes>originally stabbed through three holes, 8.6 cm. from the top and 9.6 cm. and 10.3 cm. apart</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Morgan Library and Museum</name><date>1972</date><dealer>none</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Acquired by H. A. Mair at an unknown time in the nineteenth century; sold from his collection at auction, Puttick and Simpson's, London, 19 Nov. 1900, lot 338, bound with *Visions of the Daughters of Albion* Copy H, *Europe a Prophecy* Copy G, and three water-color drawings attributed to Blake "added," one apparently related to *The Song of Los* (£225 to the dealer Bernard Quaritch, possibly acting for Marsden J. Perry); acquired in 1900 by Perry, who may have removed the drawings; the three illuminated books, still bound together, acquired by William A. White in March 1908; the volume given in July 1917 by White to his daughter, Frances White Emerson; the three illuminated books, still bound together but without the drawings, sold from Emerson's collection at Sotheby's, 19 May 1958, lot 4 (£23,000 to the dealer John Fleming, who apparently disbound the three illuminated books); *The Song of Los* Copy C sold by Fleming to Mrs. Landon K. Thorne, apparently shortly after the 1958 auction; given by Thorne in Feb. 1972 to the Pierpont Morgan Library (now Morgan Library and Museum).</note></provenance><repository><institution>Morgan Library and Museum</institution><addressline>225 Madison Avenue</addressline><addressline>New York, New York 10016</addressline><addressline>USA</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 212-685-0008</addressline><addressline>Fax: 212-481-3484</addressline><addressline>Email: photoservices@themorgan.org</addressline><addressline>URL (general): http://www.morganlibrary.org</addressline><addressline>UL (Photography and Rights): http://www.morganlibrary.org/research/photo.asp</addressline><department>Department of Printed Books and Bindings</department><collection>Morgan Library and Museum</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">077236</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.01" dbi="s-los.c.P1"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="E1">Erdman 1, </objcode><objcode code="K1">Keynes 1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.4 x 17.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1217" width="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>We see from behind a figure, probably male, kneeling 
and bowing over an altar.  He may be praying.  His feet are 
prominently displayed beneath the hem of a garment that extends 
only to his waist.  The altar, perhaps made of stone, has a top 
that could be an open book, seen only along its lower edge.  The 
mottled ground on which the figure kneels may be covered with 
grass or lichens.  Above the figure is a large disc (probably 
meant to be a globe) covered with dark patches suggestive of 
unreadable inscriptions, hieroglyphics, or simply chaos.  This 
may be a dark or occluded sun.  Four beams of dark radiance, most prominent on the bottom, 
extend from this sun, diagonally in relation to the sides of the 
design.  The area surrounding the globe is probably the void of 
space.  A thin, lightly-colored line, rising from the left to the right 
margin and above the figure's head, may be the outline of a distant mountain.  The figure might be either Urizen (note the white hair) 
or a priest who represents false religion.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>priest</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see from behind a figure, probably male, kneeling 
and bowing over an altar.  He may be praying.  His feet are 
prominently displayed beneath the hem of a garment that extends 
only to his waist.  The figure might be either Urizen (note the 
white hair) or a priest who represents false 
religion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>altar</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure kneels before and bows over what is 
probably a stone altar.  The top of the altar may be an open book,
seen only along its lower edge.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>hieroglyphic</characteristic><characteristic>chaos</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>void</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the figure is a large disc (probably meant to 
be a globe) covered with dark patches suggestive of unreadable 
inscriptions, hieroglyphics, or simply chaos.  This may be a dark 
or occluded sun.  Four beams of dark radiance, most prominent on the bottom, extend from this 
sun, diagonally in relation to the sides of the design.  The area 
around the globe is probably just the void of 
space.  A thin, lightly-colored line, rising from the left 
to the right margin and above the figure's head, may be the outline of a distant mountain.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The mottled ground on which the figure kneels may be 
covered with grass or lichens.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><!-- [Full-page design] --></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.02" dbi="s-los.c.P2-8"><objtitle>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 8, </objcode><objcode code="E8">Erdman 8, </objcode><objcode code="K8">Keynes 8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.5 x 17.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1222" width="910"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits or kneels, with legs spread apart, on what 
                  may be clouds or partly formed cosmic globes.  He faces forward, 
                  but looks down at the darkened globe of an occluded sun or star.  
                  He holds, with both hands, a large hammer.  His hair is curly or 
                  flame-like; his expression is serious, perhaps even melancholy, though his lips suggest just the hint of a smile.  The dark sun or star below him has around its 
                  circumference spiky beams of light.  Right and left of this man 
                  are at least two other suns or stars, also radiating beams of 
                  light.  Beyond is the void of space.  The figure is almost 
                  certainly Los, in his character as the blacksmith-like creator of 
                  the temporal universe.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Los</characteristic><characteristic>blacksmith</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><characteristic>smiling</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>hammer</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits or kneels, with legs spread apart, on what 
                     may be clouds or partly formed cosmic globes.  He faces forward, 
                     but looks down at the darkened globe of an occluded sun or star.  
                     He hold, with both hands, a large hammer.  His left arm is bent under his head, his right arm is bent upward with his right hand resting on the top of the handle of the hammer.  His hair is curly or 
                     flame-like; his expression is serious, perhaps even melancholy, though his lips suggest just the hint of a smile.  A prominent shadow falls over the upper portion of his right leg.  This figure is almost certainly Los, in his character as the 
                     blacksmith-like creator of the temporal universe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure may be sitting on either clouds or 
                     partly formed cosmic globes.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The man looks down upon a dark or occluded sun or 
                     star.  Spiky beams of light surround its circumference.  The dark, horizontal forms in front of the globe suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>void</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least two suns or stars hover right and left of 
                     the figure.  Spiky beams of light emanate from both.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><!-- [Full-page design] --></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.03" dbi="s-los.c.P3-2"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">THE SONG of LOS</title>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="E2">Erdman 2, </objcode><objcode code="K2">Keynes 2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>24.3 x 17.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1264" width="894"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The title page is treated as a full-page design, 
                  with the area bearing the title words (lines 1-3) treated as the sky.  At the 
                  lower margin, an old bearded man lies supine on the ground.  His 
                  gown covers all but his left hand, which rests on a skull, and 
                  his face.  He faces and looks up, with his legs extended to the 
                  left.  This figure has been variously identified as Urizen, 
                  Moses, Adam, and Noah—see "And Noah as white as snow / On the 
                  mountains of Ararat" (Plate 7, lines 22-23).  The skull may be Adam's—see "For 
                  Adam, a mouldering skeleton / Lay bleach'd on the garden of Eden" 
                  (Plate 7, lines 20-21).  The background behind and above the figure may be hills 
                  (covered with indeterminate vegetation) closest to the figure, 
                  and either more distant hills or waves of the sea in the far 
                  background.  The spiky forms, colored red, could be flames.  Above, in the sky, are two birds (one very faint in this copy) in flight with 
                  extended wings to the left of the first letter of "LOS" (line 3) in the title.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>Adam</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>Moses</characteristic><characteristic>Noah</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old bearded man with long hair lies supine on the 
                     ground.  His gown covers all but his left hand, which rests on a 
                     skull, and his face.  He faces and looks up, with his legs 
                     extended to the left.  This figure has been variously identified 
                     as Urizen, Moses, Adam, and Noah—see "And Noah as white as snow 
                     / On the mountains of Ararat" (Plate 7, lines 22-23).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>skull</characteristic><characteristic>Adam</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The old man rests his left hand on a human skull, 
                     perhaps the skull of Adam—see "For Adam, a mouldering skeleton / 
                     Lay bleach'd on the garden of Eden" (Plate 7, lines 20-21).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The background behind and above the figure may be 
                     composed of hills, closest to him, and either hills or waves of 
                     the sea in the distance.  The spiky forms, colored red, could be flames.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The hill directly behind and above the figure may be 
                     covered with some sort of vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The area containing the text of the title is treated as though it were the sky.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two birds, one very faint, fly with extended wings below the "S" of 
                     "SONG" (line 2) in the title inscription.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.03.01" justify="center">THE </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.03.02" justify="center">SONG of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.03.03" justify="center">LOS</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.03.04" justify="center">Lambeth<space extent="2"/>Printed by W Blake<space extent="2"/>1795</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.04" dbi="s-los.c.P4-3"><objtitle>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4  </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3, </objcode><objcode code="E3">Erdman 3, </objcode><objcode code="K3">Keynes 3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>21.5 x 13.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1200" width="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A snake is intertwined through the letters of the 
                  heading ("AFRICA," line 1).  The snake's head points down and its mouth 
                  is open; its forked tongue hangs down.  The reptilian theme is 
                  continued by a small lizard, apparently climbing the first 
                  diagonal of the first "A" in the heading.  Many vines, some with 
                  loops and spirals (far left), and a few leaves also play about 
                  and are intertwined with the heading.  Several flying insects, 
                  perhaps moths or butterflies, are also pictured, particularly 
                  below the first "A" and the "F" of the heading and just left of, above, and below the final "A."  Below, with five lines of text intervening, is the lower half of 
                  what is probably a unified composition, particularly given the 
                  marginal vegetation linking them.  On the left is a nude young 
                  male, probably a shepherd boy, lying on the ground in a 
                  contracted posture and probably sleeping.  The downward-directed 
                  mouth of the serpent above may be threatening him.  The male's 
                  legs are drawn up and his head, with curly hair, rests face down 
                  on his left arm.  To the right is at least one sheep, also lying 
                  on the ground with its face on the left.  Further to the right 
                  may be more sheep plus some vegetation.  Above this area, and 
                  just below the final word of line 3, is a flying 
                  insect with bat-like wings. A caterpillar crawls on a vine beneath this bat-winged insect.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A snake is intertwined through the letters of the 
                     heading ("AFRICA," line 1).  The snake's mouth is open; its forked tongue 
                     hangs down.  The snake may be threatening the sleeping youth 
                     below his downward-pointing head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>lizard</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A small lizard climbs the first diagonal of the 
                     first "A" in the heading ("AFRICA," line 1).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least one sheep lies on the ground right of the 
                     sleeping youth.  The sheep's head is on the left; it may be 
                     asleep.  The densely color-printed area to the right may include 
                     other sheep.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several winged insects, perhaps butterflies or 
                     moths, hover below the first "A" and the "F" of the heading 
                     ("AFRICA," line 1).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><characteristic>bird</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several winged insects, perhaps butterflies or 
                     moths, hover between the "C" and final "A" of the heading 
                     ("AFRICA," line 1).  Two winged insects hover below the final "A" near the right margin.  The winged creature flying between the snake's tail and the final word of line 2 ("Prophet") might be either an insect or a bird.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bat-winged insect, perhaps a moth or butterfly, 
                     hovers below and to the right of the final word in line 3.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A caterpillar climbs a vine right of the sheep and below the bat-winged insect.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male youth, perhaps a child, lies on the 
                     ground.  His legs are drawn up and his face rests on his left 
                     arm.  We see only the top of his head and his curly hair.  Given 
                     his proximity to the sheep to the right, this may be a sleeping 
                     shepherd.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Many vines, some with leaves, are intertwined with 
                     the heading ("AFRICA," line 1).  At least one, far left, includes loops and a spiral.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Green color printing left of the sleeping figure and 
                     extending along most of the left margin of the plate probably 
                     represents vegetation.  One vine or bare branch extends from this 
                     marginal coloring to the indented beginning of line 4 of the 
                     text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dense color printing right of the sheep may 
                     represent vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">AFRICA</l></lg></transcription><illusobjdesc>The text of the heading is fully integrated into the 
                     design.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The plate contains a good deal of interlinear 
                  decoration.  Several vines with leaves and loops extend between 
                  lines 10 and 12 of the text.  This area also includes three flying 
                  birds, wings extended, below "children of Los" in line 10.  Other 
                  vines follow line 14 and fill the space 
                  between lines 20 and 21.  Green color printing, probably 
                  representing vegetation, extends along the right margin from 
                  line 16 to the bottom of the plate.  A reptile of some sort, possibly 
                  a snake or lizard, emerges from this vegetation and faces left, 
                  holding its mouth open; it is colored dark olive green like the vegetation in this copy.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three birds fly, with wings extended, below "children 
                     of Los" in line 10 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several vines extend horizontally between lines 10 
                     and 12 of the text.  The vine on the left forms loops; the center 
                     vine bears ivy-like leaves.  This vine merges with at least one 
                     other near the right margin.  Two of its tendrils form loops 
                     suggestive of (if not quite forming) spirals.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with ivy-like leaves extends horizontally from the end of line 14 of 
                     the text toward the right margin.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A snake-like vine twists horizontally between lines 
                     20 and 21 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>lizard</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A reptile of some sort, possibly a snake or lizard, emerges 
                     from the vegetation right of lines 17-19 and faces left; it is colored dark olive green 
                     in this copy, and its mouth may be open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dark green and brown color printing along the right 
                     margin, extending from line 16 to the bottom of the plate, 
                     suggests vegetation.  These patches extend in roughly triangular 
                     form into the interstices between lines of text.  The extension 
                     between lines 27 and 28 reaches to the left margin and looks like 
                     a vine.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="15">AFRICA</l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.02" justify="left">I will sing you a song of Los, the Eternal Prophet:</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.03" justify="left">He sung it to four harps at the tables of Eternity, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="8">In heart-formed Africa, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.05" justify="left">Urizen faded! Ariston shudderd!</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.06" justify="left" indent="5">And thus the Song began</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.07" justify="left" indent="3">Adam stood in the garden of Eden;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.08" justify="left">And Noah on the mountains of Ararat;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.09" justify="left">They saw Urizen give his Laws to the Nations</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.10" justify="left">By the hands of the children of Los.</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.11" justify="left" indent="38">African</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.12" justify="left">Adam shudderd! Noah faded! black grew the sunny</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.13" justify="left">When Rintrah gave Abstract Philosophy to Brama in the East.</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.14" justify="left" indent="4">(Night spoke to the Cloud!</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.15" justify="left">Lo these Human form'd spirits in smiling hipocrisy, War</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.16" justify="left">Against one another; so let them War on; slaves to the</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.17" justify="left" indent="11">eternal Elements)</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.18" justify="left">Noah shrunk beneath the waters,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.19" justify="left">Abram fled in fires from Chaldea;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.20" justify="left">Moses beheld upon Mount Sinai forms of dark delusion;</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.21" justify="left" indent="2">To Trismegistus. Palamabron gave an abstract Law;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.22" justify="left" indent="2">To Pythagoras Socrates &amp; Plato.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.23" justify="left">Times rolled on o'er all the sons of Har, time after time </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.24" justify="left">Orc on Mount Atlas howld. chain'd down with the Chain of Jealousy</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.25" justify="left">Then Oothoon hoverd over Judah &amp; Jerusalem</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.26" justify="left">And Jesus heard her voice (a man of sorrows) he recievd</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.27" justify="left">A Gospel from wretched Theotormon, </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.28" justify="left">The human race began to wither. for the healthy built</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.29" justify="left">Secluded places, fearing the joys of Love</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.30" justify="left">And the disease'd only propagated;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.31" justify="left">So Antamon call'd up Leutha from her valleys of delight:</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.32" justify="left">And to Mahomet a loose Bible gave.</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.33" justify="left" indent="1">But in the North, to Odin, Sotha gave a Code of War.</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.04.34" justify="left" indent="2">Because of Diralada thinking to reclaim his joy.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.05" dbi="s-los.c.P5-4"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 4, </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode><objcode code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>21.5 x 13.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1200" width="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The plate is treated as a full-page design, with the 
text areas representing clouds in the sky.  On the earth below 
the text, an embracing couple runs to the right.  These are 
probably Har and Heva, who "fled" from the "War &amp; Lust" of "their 
brethren" (lines 5-6).  They face forward, but may be looking back to 
the left.  Both faces express fear or horror.  The male is nude.  Both figures have their mouths open, as though speaking or uttering a 
cry.  The female wears a skirt but would appear to be undraped 
above the waist.  The female's hair is long, the man's curly.  
They appear to be fleeing from some unrepresented presence on the 
left.  The man's left arm holds the woman's waist. His right arm is not visible.  The woman's left arm is wrapped around the 
man's head.  Her right arm is extended at 135 degrees, with the 
palm facing to the left as though fending off a pursuer.  The 
ground on which they run may be covered with low vegetation. A hill or mound of vegetation slopes upward in the immediate background beneath a dark sky; a distant mountain peak rises on the right.  Just 
above, in the cloud or text panel into which the woman's right 
arm extends, are two birds with wings extended.  The entire scene 
is apocalyptic.  Above, on the upper cloud or text panel, is a nude 
human figure, probably male, hovering in the air. We see him from behind, 
with one leg drawn up and the other extended. He faces to the left, 
with his arms extended horizontally. His large, bat-like wings extend below his arms.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Har</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male embraces a woman and runs to the right.  
He faces forward, but may be looking back to the left at some 
unrepresented presence from which he is fleeing.  His hair is 
curly.  His left arm holds the woman around the waist. His right arm is not visible.  His mouth is open; he may be speaking or crying out.  His 
face expresses fear or terror.  He is probably Har, who "fled" with Heva from the "War &amp; Lust" of "their brethren" 
(lines 5-6).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Heva</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>crying out</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A woman, embracing and embraced by a man, runs with 
an exaggerated stride to the right.  She has long hair and a 
skirt, but would appear to be nude above the waist.  She faces 
forward, but perhaps looks back to the left at some unrepresented 
presence from which she is fleeing.  Her left arm is wrapped 
around the man's head; her right arm is extended at 135 degrees 
with the palm facing to the left, as though she were fending off 
some pursuer.  Her mouth is slightly open; she may be speaking or crying out.  Her face suggests fear or terror.  She is probably 
Heva, who with Har "fled" from the "War &amp; Lust" of "their 
brethren" (lines 5-6).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, nude and probably male, hovers 
in the upper cloud or text panel. We see him from behind, with one leg 
extended and one drawn up. He faces to the left; his arms are raised 
horizontally. His large, bat-like wings extend just below his arms.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two birds with extended wings fly to the left of the 
woman's extended right arm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground over which the embracing couple runs may 
be covered with low vegetation, such as grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A hill or mound of vegetation rises behind the embracing couple.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind and above the embracing couple is a dark sky; a distant mountain peak rises on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Given their shape, the text panels would seem to 
function as clouds within the pictorial image.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The left margin of the text is decorated with 
several vines.  One extends vertically from line 12 to line 1.  
Horizontal vines extend from the beginning of line 3 to the left 
margin and between lines 4 and 5.  Vines with loops appear in the 
left margin at lines 1 to 4, lines 18 to 20, and at the start of line 21.  A 
bird soars on extended wings above "Rousseau" in line 18. In addition, several 
very faintly printed forms occupy the left margin, including a bird 
left of line 1, and two insects, possibly moths, left of lines 8 and 9. </illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><characteristic>insect</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A faintly printed bird appears in the margin left of line 1.  Left of lines 8 and 9 flit two insects, possibly moths.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bird soars on extended wings above "Rousseau" in 
line 18 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A curving line that may represent a vine extends 
vertically in the right margin of the text from lines 12 to 
1.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine, perhaps with small leaves, extends 
horizontally between the left margin and the beginning of line 
3.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine extends from the first letter in line 5 of 
the text and continues horizontally between lines 4 and 5.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the first letter in line 13 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A horizontal line between lines 17 and 18 of the text
                     may represent a vine or low hills—or possibly a break in the clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with one loop appears in the margin left of 
                     lines 1 to 4 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with many loops appears in the margin left of 
lines 18 to 20 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with two branches and several loops extends 
downward left of the first word in line 21. Below it are two very faintly printed leaves. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine extends from the "d" of "clouds" in line 18.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.01" justify="left" indent="5">These were the Churches: Hospitals; Castles; Palaces;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.02" justify="left" indent="3">Like nets &amp; gins &amp; traps to catch the joys of Eternity</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.03" justify="left" indent="18">And all the rest a desart;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.04" justify="left" indent="2">Till like a dream Eternity was obliterated &amp; erased, </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.05" justify="left" indent="3">Since that dread day when Har and Heva fled,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.06" justify="left" indent="3">Because their brethren &amp; sisters liv'd in War &amp; Lust;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.07" justify="left" indent="3">And as they fled they shrunk</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.08" justify="left" indent="3">Into two narrow doleful forms;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.09" justify="left" indent="3">Creeping in reptile flesh upon</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.10" justify="left" indent="3">The bosom of the ground;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.11" justify="left" indent="3">And all the vast of Nature shrunk</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.12" justify="left" indent="3">Before their shrunken eyes.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.13" justify="left">Thus the terrible race of Los &amp; Enitharmon gave</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.14" justify="left">Laws &amp; Religions to the sons of Har binding them more</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.15" justify="left">And more to Earth: closing and restraining;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.16" justify="left">Till a Philosophy of Five Senses was complete</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.17" justify="left">Urizen wept &amp; gave it into the hands of Newton &amp; Locke</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.18" justify="left" indent="7">Clouds roll heavy upon the Alps round Rousseau &amp; Voltaire:</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.19" justify="left" indent="7">And on the mountains of Lebanon round the deceased Gods</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.20" justify="left" indent="7">Of Asia; &amp; on the desarts of Africa round the Fallen Angels</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.05.21" justify="left" indent="7">The Guardian Prince of Albion burns in his nightly tent </l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.06" dbi="s-los.c.P6"><objtitle>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 6, </objcode><objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes 6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.2 x 13.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1200" width="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Although containing considerable text, the plate 
                  would seem to be treated as a single, interrelated pictorial 
                  image.  Several figures, not very clearly defined, disport among 
                  the letters of the heading ("ASIA," line 1).  A seated figure, 
                  with at least the left leg drawn up, appears just left of the first letter.  
                  His head may be bent back or turned to the right.  Within the upper 
                  loop of the second letter, a figure clutches his head and falls 
                  head first.  In the lower part of this same letter, there may be 
                  a gowned figure hunched over and with its hands clutching its head.  
                  Two embracing(?) figures, poorly defined but probably a 
                  male and female, stride to the left just left of the lower part 
                  of the letter "I."  An ill-defined cluster of lines may be a 
                  seated figure at the lower parts of the final "A."  The sky 
                  behind the heading contains clouds; the pink and red coloring behind the heading suggests a sunrise or sunset.  Below, we see a great 
                  tree arching over from left to right.  In a cave-like niche below 
                  the tree are two figures, a nude male holding a gowned woman.  He 
                  squats or sits on the ground, apparently with his head lowered 
                  since we see only the curly hair on the top of his head.  The 
                  female's head and left arm fall downward; she may be dead. 
                  The dark green coloring to the left of the man and woman may be vegetation.
                  Undifferentiated vegetation continues down both margins of the 
                  text; some vine-like shapes intrude between lines of text and 
                  fill areas on the right of the text.  A nude figure, probably male, sits or kneels in an extremely 
                  contracted posture in the lower right corner of the plate.  His 
                  left leg is drawn up to his left shoulder.  His head is turned to 
                  the left (his face is not pictured); he clutches his lowered head 
                  with both hands.  He (or, perhaps, she) may have long hair.  </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A small figure with at least the left leg drawn up to the chest 
                     sits  to the left of the first "A" in the heading ("ASIA," line 1). 
                     His right leg is not clearly represented, but may also be drawn up to 
                     his chest. He appears to be looking up and facing to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at the knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably male, falls head first at 
                     the top of the letter "S" of the heading (line 1).  He clutches his head 
                     with both hands.  His legs are spread apart, with one leg bent at the knee.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><illusobjdesc>In the lower part of the letter "S" of the heading (line 1), there may be a gowned figure hunched over and with its arms wrapped around its head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two figures, probably a male and female, stride to 
                     the left just left of the lower part of the letter "I" in the 
                     heading (line 1).  Both seem to wear gowns and may be embracing.  The lower portions of their gowns trail to the right; a long scarf floats to the right behind one of the 
                     figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A cluster of lines between the two diagonals of the 
                     final "A" of the heading (line 1) may represent a gowned and seated 
                     figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits or kneels on one leg (just above line 2)
                     and holds a dead or dying female.  His right leg is drawn up just to
                     the left of his right shoulder.  His face is not shown; we see only
                     his curly hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female (just above line 2) is
                     held by a nude man.  Her head, long hair, and left arm descend limply downward; she
                     may be dead.  Her legs and the drapery from her gown are bent beneath her.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>knee</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably male, sits or kneels in an extremely 
                     contracted posture in the lower right corner of the plate.  His 
                     left leg is drawn up to his left shoulder.  His head is turned to 
                     the left (his face is not pictured); he clutches his lowered head 
                     with both hands.  He (or, perhaps, she) may have long hair.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>cave</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large tree arches over and forms a cave for the 
                     man holding the (dead?) woman.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dark green coloring to the left of the man and woman may be vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A good deal of undifferentiated vegetation decorates 
                     both margins of the text.  Some of this vegetation intrudes, in 
                     the form of vines or branches, between lines 7-8, 15-16, 19-20, and 23-24.  The vine between 7-8 grows into a leafy branch
                     that extends downward into the right margin.  An additional vine descends right of "laborious" in line 17, 
                     merges with the vegetation beneath the kneeling figure, and attaches to the final letter of "path" in line 24. 
                     A vine with two loops also grows from the first letter of line 24.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky behind and above the heading contains 
                     clouds.  The pink and red coloring suggests a sunrise or 
                     sunset.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">ASIA</l></lg></transcription><illusobjdesc>The heading is fully integrated into the pictorial 
                     image.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A good deal of undifferentiated vegetation decorates both margins of the text.  Some of this vegetation intrudes in the form of vines or branches between lines 
                  7-8, 15-16, 19-20, and 23-24.    </illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A good deal of undifferentiated vegetation decorates 
                     both margins of the text.  Some of this vegetation intrudes, in 
                     the form of vines or branches, between lines 7-8, 15-16, 19-20, and 23-24.  The vine between 7-8 grows into a leafy branch
                     that extends downward into the right margin.  An additional vine descends right of "laborious" in line 17, merges with the vegetation beneath the kneeling figure, 
                     and attaches to the final letter of "path" in line 24.  A vine with two loops also grows from the first letter of line 24.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with several loops extends from the first letter of line 1. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with several loops extends from the first letter of line 10 and connects to the first letter of "King" later in the same line.  </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.01" justify="left" indent="10">ASIA</l></texthead><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.02" justify="left" indent="3">The Kings of Asia heard</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.03" justify="left">The howl rise up from Europe!</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.04" justify="left">And each ran out from his Web;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.05" justify="left">From his ancient woven Den;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.06" justify="left">For the darkness of Asia was startled</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.07" justify="left">At the thick-flaming, thought-creating fires of Orc.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.08" justify="left">And the Kings of Asia stood</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.09" justify="left">And cried in bitterness of soul.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.10" justify="left" indent="1">Shall not the King call for Famine from the heath </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.11" justify="left">Nor the Priest, for Pestilence from the fen?</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.12" justify="left">To restrain! to dismay! to thin!</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.13" justify="left">The inhabitants of mountain and plain;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.14" justify="left">In the day of full-feeding prosperity;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.15" justify="left">And the night of delicious songs.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.16" justify="left" indent="1">Shall not the Councellor. throw his curb</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.17" justify="left">Of Poverty on the laborious?</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.18" justify="left">To fix the price of labour;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.19" justify="left">To invent allegoric riches; </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.20" justify="left" indent="1">And the privy admonishers of men</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.21" justify="left">Call for fires in the City</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.22" justify="left">For heaps of smoking ruins,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.23" justify="left">In the night of prosperity &amp; wantonness</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.24" justify="left" indent="1">To turn man from his path,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.06.25" justify="left">To restrain the child from the womb,</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.07" dbi="s-los.c.P7"><objtitle>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7, </objcode><objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes 7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>22.3 x 13.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1200" width="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Although it contains considerable text, the plate is 
                  treated pictorially as a full-page design.  Upper right, a nude 
                  male falls head first in front of clouds.  His legs are bent at 
                  the knee, so that his lower legs are not shown, and his arms are 
                  similarly bent at the elbows.  His posture is contracted, with 
                  his head bent back.  Both margins of the text are filled with 
                  undifferentiated masses of vegetation, some of which intrude between lines of text.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male falls head first in front of clouds.  
                     His legs are bent at the knee, so that his lower legs are not 
                     shown, and his arms are similarly bent at the elbows.  His 
                     posture is contracted, with his head bent back.  He may be 
                     bound.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Large masses of undifferentiated vegetation, perhaps 
                     including branches and leaves, decorate both margins of the text. 
                     Some of this vegetation intrudes between lines of 
                     text.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Vine-like extensions of the "y" in "may" and "y" in "obey" (line 2) 
                  extend horizontally between lines 2 and 3 of the text.  Other letters of the 
                  text have similar vine-like extensions, such as the "p" in "weeping" (line 16), 
                  the "d" in "clouds" (line 19), which includes a loop, and the "d" in "Adam" 
                  (line 20).  An independent vine with multiple loops extends horizontally 
                  between lines 8 and 9 of the text. The horizontal forms between lines 34 and 35 may also represent vines.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Vine-like extensions of the "y" in "may" and "y" in "obey" 
                     (line 2) extend horizontally between lines 2 and 3 of the text.  
                     Other letters of the text have similar vine-like extensions, such as 
                     the "p" in "weeping" (line 16). An independent vine with multiple 
                     loops extends horizontally between lines 8 and 9 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The horizontal forms between lines 34 and 35 of the
                     text may represent vines.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The right-hand margin of the top half of the plate resembles a dark sky, and the upper text panels seem to function as clouds. </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.01" justify="left">To cut off the bread from the city,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.02" justify="left">That the remnant may learn to obey.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.03" justify="left" indent="1">That the pride of the heart may fail;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.04" justify="left">That the lust of the eyes may be quench'd, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.05" justify="left">That the delicate ear in its infancy</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.06" justify="left">May be dull'd; and the nostrils clos'd up, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.07" justify="left">To teach mortal worms the path</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.08" justify="left">That leads from the gates of the Grave.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.09" justify="left" indent="5">Urizen heard them cry;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.10" justify="left">And his shudd'ring waving wings</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.11" justify="left">Went enormous above the red flames</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.12" justify="left">Drawing clouds of despair thro' the heavens</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.13" justify="left">Of Europe as he went; </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.14" justify="left" indent="1">And his Books of brass iron &amp; gold</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.15" justify="left" indent="1">Melted over the land as he flew,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.16" justify="left" indent="1">Heavy-waving, howling, weeping.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.17" justify="left" indent="20">And he stood over Judea, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.18" justify="left" indent="19">And stay'd in his ancient place; </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.19" justify="left" indent="18">And stretch'd his clouds over Jerusalem, </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.20" justify="left" indent="18">For Adam, a mouldering skeleton</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.21" justify="left" indent="18">Lay bleach'd on the garden of Eden; </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.22" justify="left" indent="18">And Noah as white as snow</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.23" justify="left" indent="18">On the mountains of Ararat, </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.24" justify="left" indent="12">Then the thunders of Urizen bellow'd aloud</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.25" justify="left" indent="12">From his woven darkness above. </l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.26" justify="left" indent="13">Orc raging in European darkness</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.27" justify="left" indent="13">Arose like a pillar of fire above the Alps</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.28" justify="left" indent="13">Like a serpent of fiery flame!</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.29" justify="left" indent="22">The sullen Earth</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.30" justify="left" indent="23">Shrunk! </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.31" justify="left" indent="2">Forth from the dead dust rattling bones to bones</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.32" justify="left" indent="2">Join: shaking convuls'd the shivring clay breathes, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.33" justify="left" indent="3">And all flesh naked stands; Fathers and Friends;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.34" justify="left" indent="3">Mothers &amp; Infants; Kings &amp; Warriors;</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.35" justify="left" indent="10">The Grave shrieks with delight, &amp; shakes</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.36" justify="left" indent="10">Her hollow womb, &amp; clasps the solid stem;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.37" justify="left" indent="10">Her bosom swells with wild desire;</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.38" justify="left" indent="10">And milk &amp; blood &amp; glandous wine,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.39" justify="left" indent="10">In rivers rush &amp; shout &amp; dance,</l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.40" justify="left" indent="10">On mountain, dale and plain, </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.41" justify="left" indent="17">The SONG of LOS is Ended. </l><l n="s-los.c.illbk.07.42" justify="left" indent="19">Urizen Wept.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.c.illbk.08" dbi="s-los.c.P8-5"><objtitle>,
            <objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 5, </objcode><objcode code="E5">Erdman 5, </objcode><objcode code="K5">Keynes 5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.2 x 17.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1206" width="910"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Two figures rest on large lilies.  The ground from 
                  which the lily plant grows is not clearly represented, but there 
                  may be a river behind its stems.  If we assume that this is a 
                  plant of normal size, then the human figures are diminutive, 
                  perhaps fairies.  The female, wearing a gown that seemingly does 
                  not cover her left shoulder and breast, lies on one blossom with eyes 
                  closed; she may be asleep.  Her head rests on her right arm and 
                  hand.  Her hair is long.  The male wears a long gown and a 
                  separate cloak.  He is crowned, and thus probably a king; by 
                  association, the woman may be a queen.  His eyes are open and he 
                  faces forward.  He has long hair and a beard.  He is more seated than lying on his blossom, with 
                  his upper body propped up with his right arm.  He holds a scepter 
                  in his left hand.  The night sky in the distance contains indications of stars.  The design is based loosely on a 
                  monochrome wash drawing, now usually attributed to Blake's 
                  brother Robert, in Blake's Notebook, page 5.  There is also a 
                  separate water color of the design by William Blake (private 
                  collection).  The two figures have traditionally been identified 
                  as Oberon and Titania, although the relevance of Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">A 
                     Midsummer Night's Dream</hi> to *The Song of Los* is not immediately 
                  apparent.  Other critics have identified the figures as Har and 
                  Heva, as on Plate 5 (Bentley Plate 4).  Perhaps, given the cosmic scale of Plate 2 (Bentley Plate 8), this plate represents the microscopic world of the Blakean 
                  imagination.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>fairy</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>Har</characteristic><characteristic>Oberon</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure, wearing a gown and a separate cloak, 
                     sits on a lily.  If the flower determines the scale, then this 
                     diminutive male may be a fairy.  He is crowned and holds a 
                     scepter in his left hand; he may be a king.  He props up his 
                     upper body with his right arm; his right leg is drawn up and his left 
                     leg dangles from the edge of the flower.  He faces forward and has long hair and a beard.  He has been 
                     identified by modern critics as either Har (see Plate 5) or 
                     Oberon from Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night's 
                        Dream</hi>.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>fairy</characteristic><characteristic>queen</characteristic><characteristic>Heva</characteristic><characteristic>Titania</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female wearing a gown lies on a lily.  Her left 
                     shoulder and breasts are bare.  Her head and long hair rest on her right arm.  
                     Her eyes are closed and she may be sleeping.  If the scale of the 
                     design is determined by the flower, then this diminutive female 
                     may be a fairy.  Given her association with the crowned male to 
                     the right, she may be a queen.  She has been identified by modern 
                     critics as either Heva (see Plate 5) or Titania from 
                     Shakespeare's *A Midsummer Night's Dream*.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>lily</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>stamen</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A lily plant, with three blossoms (two fully open), two stamens, and numerous
                     stems and leaves dominates the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>river</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gray horizontal section of color printing may 
                     represent a river behind the lily plant.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The night sky bears white spots that may 
                     indicate stars.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><!-- [Full-page design] --></desc></objdesc></bad>