<bad id="s-los.b" type="illbk" work="The Song of Los" copy="B" copyid="B" institution="lc" catalog="bentley" catid="B"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Song of Los, The"><main>The Song of Los</main><copy> Copy B</copy>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Gerald Miller, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the
Library of Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software
grants from Sun Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 65KB; 16 JPEG (ISO/IEC
10918)
files ranging in size from 135KB to 1000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH</publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The editors of the William Blake Archive are pleased to announce the publication of seven new electronic editions of Blake's illuminated books. They are: <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen</hi> Copy G, <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> Copy A, <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> Copy A, <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> Copy B, <hi rend="i">America, a Prophecy</hi> Copy A, <hi rend="i">Europe, a Prophecy</hi> Copy E, and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> Copy F.<lb/><lb/>
            We had announced <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> Copy G as forthcoming two months ago, but formatting the double-columned text diplomatically in SGML for both Netscape and Internet Explorer proved more taxing and time consuming than anticipated. Such are the joys and tribulations of electronic publishing. Solving the problems there, though, ensured diplomatic transcriptions for Blake's other books with double-columned texts, <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>. Together, these three works are often referred to as Blake's Bible of Hell or, simply, the Urizen books. <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, of which there are only seven extant copies, was first produced in 1794, color printed to form Copies A, C, D, E (untraced), F, and J. It was printed again in 1795 to form Copy B, which was produced as part of a set of illuminated books printed on large paper, and then one last time in c. 1818 to form Copy G, which was produced in Blake's late printing and coloring style. The editors are currently working on Copies A, B, C, and F and expect to have them in the Archive by the end of the year. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> exist in unique copies, with only a few proof impressions extant. They were printed in 1795 and executed in intaglio instead of in relief etching, the technique Blake normally used for his illuminated books. Although their texts are printed in intaglio, their frontispieces are beautifully color printed from the surface of the plates.<lb/><lb/>
            With <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, which consists of two parts entitled "Africa" and "Asia," we complete Blake's other series of illuminated books, sometimes known as the Continental Prophecies, begun in 1793 with <hi rend="i">America</hi> and continued in 1794 with <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>. The copy of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> included here is one of six extant; all were color printed in the same printing session in 1795.<lb/><lb/>
            With fourteen complete copies extant, <hi rend="i">America</hi> is not as rare as these other illuminated books, but Copy A, which was printed and colored in 1795 as part of Blake's large-paper set of books, is, along with Copies K, O, and M, one of only four colored copies—and it was the model for Copy K. Moreover, only it and Copy O have the last four lines on Plate 4, which was masked in the printing of the other copies. The Archive will include Copies M and O (c. 1807 and 1818) later this year.<lb/><lb/>
            Only nine copies of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are extant, and only two of those, Copies H and O (1795 and 1818), have Plate 3, the Preludium. The Archive will include both of these Copies by the end of the year. Copy E, included here, was lightly color printed on both sides of the paper in 1794 and joins Copy B, color printed more heavily on one side of the paper the same year.<lb/><lb/><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> Copy F is an exquisitely beautiful copy, heavily color printed (especially its frontispiece) in c. 1794, and never before reproduced. It joins Copies C and J (both 1793), and will be joined later this year by Copies G and P (1795 and 1818).<lb/><lb/>
            All of these editions have newly edited texts; all images in the editions were scanned from either 4x5 or 8x10 transparencies, nearly all of which were made specifically for the Archive. Like our other editions, these are all SGML-encoded, fully searchable for both text and images and supported by the unique Inote and ImageSizer applications described in our previous updates.<lb/><lb/>
            The Archive now contains sixteen copies of ten illuminated books. In the coming months, we will be adding copies of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, along with copies of books already in the Archive but from different printings. Our goal is to have the entire illuminated canon online this year. In addition, work continues on the SGML edition of David V. Erdman's <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, which we anticipate releasing sometime this spring.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2003</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
         This work courtesy The William Blake Archive.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Conversion to Blake Archive Description DTD 2.1; Styles 2.0</change><date>Summer 2000</date><respstmt><resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Scott Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Gerald Miller, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>This work has been revised in order to meet the Archive's more rigorous standards (established summer 2002) for textual transcriptions and illustration descriptions.</change></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*The Song of Los*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination><imprint><publisher> William Blake<note>Blake is named as the printer on the title page, but he is also the "publisher."</note></publisher><pubplace>Lambeth</pubplace><date>1795</date></imprint><compdate value="1795.A">1795</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1795.B">1795</printdate><numberobj>8</numberobj><objorder>Bentley Plates 1-8</objorder><objsize>ranging between 24.3 x 17.5 cm. and 21.5 x 13.5
cm.</objsize><numberleaves>8</numberleaves><leafsize>32.0 x 24.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>Relief etching with color printing and hand coloring.
The title page and full-plate designs (Objects 1-2, 5, 8) were
color printed planographically.</medium><printingstyle>Relief with color printing. The title page and
full-plate designs (Objects 1-2, 5, 8) were color printed
planographically.</printingstyle><inkcolor>gray-brown (Objects 2-4, 6, and 7)<note>Objects 1, 5, and 8 may not contain any underlying ink beneath the thick color printing.  The gray-brown color of the text on Object 2 may be color-printing medium rather than ink.</note></inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>Objects 2-8 numbered 2, 4, 6-8, 10, 11 top right.<note>The pen and ink numbers are very probably not by Blake but were added by another hand when *The Song of Los* Copy B was interleaved and bound with three other prints by Blake.</note></pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>loose in portfolio<note>Once bound with several other works by Blake, but disbound and separated by 1904.</note></binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Library of
Congress</name><date>Acquired by Lessing J. Rosenwald in 1929; given to the
Library of Congress in 1945.</date><dealer>A. S. W. Rosenbach</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Probably acquired by the Earl of Beaconsfield between 1856 and 1862; sold anonymously, Hodgson's, 14 Jan. 1904, lot 224 (£144 to the dealer Bernard Quaritch); acquired by William A. White; sold from White's estate in 1927 through the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach to Lessing J.Rosenwald; given by Rosenwald to the Library of Congress in 1945.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Library of Congress</institution><addressline>101 Independence Avenue SE</addressline><addressline>Washington, D.C. 20540-4740</addressline><addressline>USA</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 202-707-5434</addressline><addressline>Fax: 202-707-4142</addressline><addressline>Email: rbsc@loc.gov</addressline><addressline>URL: http://lcweb.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/</addressline><department>Rare Book and Special Collections</department><collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">PR4144.S47 1795</repositoryid><repositoryid label="Catalog number">1808</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.01" dbi="s-los.B.P1"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="E1">Erdman 1, </objcode><objcode code="K1">Keynes 1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.4 x 17.3 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1217" width="900"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>We see from behind a figure, probably male, kneeling 
and bowing over an altar.  He may be praying.  His feet are 
prominently displayed beneath the hem of a garment that extends 
only to his waist.  The altar, perhaps made of stone, has a top 
that could be an open book, seen only along its lower edge.  The 
mottled ground on which the figure kneels may be covered with 
grass or lichens.  Above the figure is a large disc (probably 
meant to be a globe) covered with dark patches suggestive of 
unreadable inscriptions, hieroglyphics, or simply chaos.  This 
may be a dark or occluded sun.  Four beams of dark radiance 
extend from this sun, diagonally in relation to the sides of the 
design.  The area surrounding the globe is probably the void of 
space.  The dark area beneath the globe, rising from the left to the 
right margin and above the figure's head, may be a distant mountain.  The figure might be either Urizen (note the white hair) 
or a priest who represents false religion.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>priest</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see from behind a figure, probably male, kneeling 
and bowing over an altar.  He may be praying.  His feet are 
prominently displayed beneath the hem of a garment that extends 
only to his waist.  The figure might be either Urizen (note the 
white hair) or a priest who represents false 
religion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>altar</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>book</characteristic><characteristic>open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure kneels before and bows over what is 
probably a stone altar.  The top of the altar may be an open book,
seen only along its lower edge.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><characteristic>inscription</characteristic><characteristic>hieroglyphic</characteristic><characteristic>chaos</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>void</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the figure is a large disc (probably meant to 
be a globe) covered with dark patches suggestive of unreadable 
inscriptions, hieroglyphics, or simply chaos.  This may be a dark 
or occluded sun.  Four beams of dark radiance extend from this 
sun, diagonally in relation to the sides of the design.  The area 
around the globe is probably just the void of 
space.  The dark area beneath the globe, rising from the left to the 
right margin and above the figure's head, may be a distant mountain.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The mottled ground on which the figure kneels may be 
covered with grass or lichens.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><!-- [Full-page design] --></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.02" dbi="s-los.B.P2"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">THE SONG of LOS</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="E2">Erdman 2, </objcode><objcode code="K2">Keynes 2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>24.3 x 17.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1264" width="894"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The title page is treated as a full-page design, 
with the area bearing the title words (lines 2-4) treated as the sky.  At the 
lower margin, an old bearded man lies supine on the ground.  His 
gown covers all but his left hand, which rests on a skull, and 
his face.  He faces and looks up, with his legs extended to the 
left.  This figure has been variously identified as Urizen, 
Moses, Adam, and Noah--see "And Noah as white as snow / On the 
mountains of Ararat" (Plate 7, lines 23-24).  The skull may be Adam's--see "For 
Adam, a mouldering skeleton / Lay bleach'd on the garden of Eden" 
(Plate 7, lines 21-22).  The background behind and above the figure may be hills 
(covered with indeterminate vegetation) closest to the figure, 
and either more distant hills or waves of the sea in the far 
background.  The spiky forms, colored red, could be flames.  Above, in the sky, are four birds in flight with 
extended wings: a bird right of "The" in the title (line 2), and three 
birds (one large, color printed in red) above and to the left of 
the first letter of "LOS" (line 4) in the title.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>Adam</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>Moses</characteristic><characteristic>Noah</characteristic><characteristic>legs extended</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>body horizontal</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An old bearded man with long hair lies supine on the 
ground.  His gown covers all but his left hand, which rests on a 
skull, and his face.  He faces and looks up, with his legs 
extended to the left.  This figure has been variously identified 
as Urizen, Moses, Adam, and Noah--see "And Noah as white as snow 
/ On the mountains of Ararat" (Plate 7, lines 23-24).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>skull</characteristic><characteristic>Adam</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The old man rests his left hand on a human skull, 
perhaps the skull of Adam--see "For Adam, a mouldering skeleton / 
Lay bleach'd on the garden of Eden" (Plate 7, lines 21-22).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The background behind and above the figure may be 
composed of hills, closest to him, and either hills or waves of 
the sea in the distance.  The spiky forms, colored red, could be flames.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The hill directly behind and above the figure may be 
covered with some sort of vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The area containing the text of the title is treated as though it were the sky.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The faint outline of a bird in flight, with extended 
wings, can be seen to the right of the first word in the title 
("The," line 2).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Three birds fly with extended wings below the "S" of 
"SONG" (line 3) in the title inscription.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.02.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">2</physnumber><space extent="20"/></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.02.02" justify="center">THE</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.02.03" justify="center">SONG of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.02.04" justify="center">LOS</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.02.05" justify="center">Lambeth<space extent="2"/>Printed by W Blake<space extent="2"/>1795</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.03" dbi="s-los.B.P3"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3, </objcode><objcode code="E3">Erdman 3, </objcode><objcode code="K3">Keynes 3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>21.5 x 13.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1118" width="723"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A snake is intertwined through the letters of the 
heading ("AFRICA," line 2).  The snake's head points down and its mouth 
is open; its forked tongue hangs down.  The reptilian theme is 
continued by a small lizard, apparently climbing the first 
diagonal of the first "A" in the heading.  Many vines, some with 
loops and spirals (far left), and a few leaves also play about 
and are intertwined with the heading.  Several flying insects, 
perhaps moths or butterflies, are also pictured, particularly 
below the first "A" and the "F" of the heading and just below and left of 
the final "A."  A bird with extended wings flies below the 
snake's tail where it twists below the final "A" of the heading.  
Below, with five lines of text intervening, is the lower half of 
what is probably a unified composition, particularly given the 
marginal vegetation linking them.  On the left is a nude young 
male, probably a shepherd boy, lying on the ground in a 
contracted posture and probably sleeping.  The downward-directed 
mouth of the serpent above may be threatening him.  The male's 
legs are drawn up and his head, with curly hair, rests face down 
on his left arm.  To the right is at least one sheep, also lying 
on the ground with its face on the left.  Further to the right 
may be more sheep plus some vegetation.  Above this area, and 
just below the final word of line 4, is a flying 
                  insect with bat-like wings.  A caterpillar crawls on a vine beneath this bat-winged insect. </illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A snake is intertwined through the letters of the 
heading ("AFRICA," line 2).  The snake's mouth is open; its forked tongue 
hangs down.  The snake may be threatening the sleeping youth 
below his downward-pointing head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>lizard</characteristic><characteristic>climbing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A small lizard climbs the first diagonal of the 
first "A" in the heading ("AFRICA," line 2).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="AB"><characteristic>sheep</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least one sheep lies on the ground right of the 
sleeping youth.  The sheep's head is on the left; it may be 
asleep.  The densely color-printed area to the right may include 
other sheep.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several winged insects, perhaps butterflies or 
moths, hover below the first "A" and the "F" of the heading 
("AFRICA," line 2).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several winged insects, perhaps butterflies or 
moths, hover between the "C" and final "A" of the heading 
("AFRICA," line 2).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A small bird flies on extended wings below the 
snake's tail where it curls beneath the final "A" of the 
heading (line 2).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><characteristic>butterfly</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bat-winged insect, perhaps a moth or butterfly, 
hovers below and to the right of the final word in line 4.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>caterpillar</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A caterpillar climbs a vine right of the sheep and below the bat-winged insect.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>shepherd</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>child</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male youth, perhaps a child, lies on the 
ground.  His legs are drawn up and his face rests on his left 
arm.  We see only the top of his head and his curly hair.  Given 
his proximity to the sheep to the right, this may be a sleeping 
shepherd.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>intertwined</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Many vines, some with leaves, are intertwined with 
the heading ("AFRICA," line 2).  At least one, far left, includes loops 
and a spiral.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Green color printing left of the sleeping figure and 
extending along most of the left margin of the plate probably 
represents vegetation.  One vine or bare branch extends from this 
marginal coloring to the indented beginning of line 5 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dense color printing right of the sheep may 
represent vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">AFRICA</l></lg></transcription><illusobjdesc>The text of the heading is fully integrated into the 
design.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The plate contains a good deal of interlinear 
decoration.  Several vines with leaves and loops extend between 
lines 11 and 13 of the text.  This area also includes two flying 
birds, wings extended, below "children of Los" in line 11.  Other 
vines follow line 15 (very poorly printed) and fill the space 
between lines 21 and 22.  Green color printing, probably 
representing vegetation, extends along the right margin from 
line 17 to the bottom of the plate.  A reptile of some sort, possibly a snake or lizard, emerges from this vegetation and faces left, holding its mouth open.</illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two birds fly, with wings extended, below "children 
of Los" in line 11 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Several vines extend horizontally between lines 11 
and 13 of the text.  The vine on the left forms loops; the center 
vine bears at least one ivy-like leaf.  This vine merges with at least one 
other near the right margin.  Two of its tendrils form loops 
suggestive of (if not quite forming) spirals.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Fragments of a poorly-printed vine, perhaps with 
ivy-like leaves, extends horizontally from the end of line 15 of 
the text toward the right margin.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A snake-like vine twists horizontally between lines 
21 and 22 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="D"><characteristic>lizard</characteristic><characteristic>snake</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A reptile of some sort, possibly a snake or lizard, emerges from the vegetation right of lines 17-19 and faces left, holding its mouth open.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dark green and brown color printing along the right 
margin, extending from line 17 to the bottom of the plate, 
suggests vegetation.  These patches extend in roughly triangular 
form into the interstices between lines of text.  The extension 
between lines 28 and 29 reaches to the left margin and looks like 
a vine.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">4</physnumber><space extent="20"/></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.02" justify="left" indent="15">AFRICA</l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.03" justify="left">I will sing you a song of Los, the Eternal Prophet:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.04" justify="left">He sung it to four harps at the tables of Eternity.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.05" justify="left" indent="10">In heart-formed Africa.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.06" justify="left">Urizen faded! Ariston shudderd!</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.07" justify="left" indent="5">And thus the Song began</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.08" justify="left" indent="3">Adam stood in the garden of Eden:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.09" justify="left">And Noah on the mountains of Ararat:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.10" justify="left">They saw Urizen give his Laws to the Nations</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.11" justify="left">By the hands of the children of Los.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.12" justify="left" indent="40">African</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.13" justify="left">Adam shudderd! Noah faded! black grew the sunny</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.14" justify="left">When Rintrah gave Abstract Philosophy to Brama in the East.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.15" justify="left" indent="5">(Night spoke to the Cloud!</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.16" justify="left">Lo these Human form'd spirits in smiling hipocrisy. War</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.17" justify="left">Against one another; so let them War on; slaves to the</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.18" justify="left" indent="11">eternal Elements)</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.19" justify="left">Noah shrunk beneath the waters:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.20" justify="left">Abram fled in fires from Chaldea;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.21" justify="left">Moses beheld upon Mount Sinai forms of dark delusion;</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.22" justify="left" indent="3">To Trismegistus. Palamabron gave an abstract Law;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.23" justify="left" indent="3">To Pythagoras Socrates &amp; Plato.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.24" justify="left">Times rolled on o'er all the sons of Har, time after time </l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.25" justify="left">Orc on Mount Atlas howld. chain'd down with the Chain of Jealousy</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.26" justify="left">Then Oothoon hoverd over Judah &amp; Jerusalem</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.27" justify="left">And Jesus heard her voice (a man of sorrows) he recievd</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.28" justify="left">A Gospel from wretched Theotormon.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.29" justify="left">The human race began to wither. for the healthy built</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.30" justify="left">Secluded places, fearing the joys of Love</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.31" justify="left">And the disease'd only propagated;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.32" justify="left">So Antamon call'd up Leutha from her valleys of delight:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.33" justify="left">And to Mahomet a loose Bible gave.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.34" justify="left" indent="1">But in the North, to Odin, Sotha gave a Code of War.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.03.35" justify="left" indent="2">Because of Diralada thinking to reclaim his joy.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.04" dbi="s-los.B.P4"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 4, </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode><objcode code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>21.5 x 13.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1118" width="707"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The plate is treated as a full-page design, with the 
text areas representing clouds in the sky.  On the earth below 
the text, an embracing couple runs to the right.  These are 
probably Har and Heva, who "fled" from the "War &amp; Lust" of "their 
brethren" (lines 6-7).  They face forward, but may be looking back to 
the left.  Both faces express fear or horror.  The male is nude 
and has his mouth slightly open, as though speaking or uttering a 
cry.  The female wears a skirt but would appear to be undraped 
above the waist.  The female's hair is long, the man's curly.  
They appear to be fleeing from some unrepresented presence on the 
left.  The man's left arm holds the woman's waist; his right arm 
is not visible.  The woman's left arm is wrapped around the 
man's head.  Her right arm is extended at 135 degrees, with the 
palm facing to the left as though fending off a pursuer.  The 
ground on which they run may be covered with low vegetation.  A 
hill rises on the right; left of the figures is a dark sky 
streaked with red, perhaps indicating a sunrise or sunset.  A mountain, perhaps partly covered with snow, rises in the right background.  Just 
above, in the cloud or text panel into which the woman's right 
arm extends, are two birds with wings extended.  The entire scene 
is apocalyptic.  Above, on the upper cloud or text panel, is a 
nude human figure, probably male, hovering in the air.  We see 
him from behind, with one leg drawn up and the other extended.  
He faces to the left, with his arms extended horizontally.  His 
large, bat-like wings extend below his arms.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Har</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male embraces a woman and runs to the right.  
He faces forward, but may be looking back to the left at some 
unrepresented presence from which he is fleeing.  His hair is 
curly.  His left arm holds the woman around the waist; his right arm is not visible.  His mouth is open; he may be speaking or crying.  His 
face expresses fear or terror.  He is probably Har, who "fled"
with Heva from the "War &amp; Lust" of "their brethren" 
(lines 6-7).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>Heva</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>skirt</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palm vertical</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>fleeing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A woman, embracing and embraced by a man, runs with 
an exaggerated stride to the right.  She has long hair and a 
skirt, but would appear to be nude above the waist.  She faces 
forward, but perhaps looks back to the left at some unrepresented 
presence from which she is fleeing.  Her left arm is wrapped 
around the man's head; her right arm is extended at 135 degrees 
with the palm facing to the left, as though she were fending off 
some pursuer.  Her mouth is open; she may be speaking or crying out.  Her face suggests fear or terror, and her mouth is partly open.  She is probably 
Heva, who with Har "fled" from the "War &amp; Lust" of "their 
brethren" (lines 6-7).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>bat-winged</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, nude and probably male, hovers in the 
upper cloud or text panel.  We see him from behind, with one leg 
extended and one drawn up.  He faces to the left; his arms are 
raised horizontally.  His large, bat-like wings extend just below 
his arms.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="C"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two birds with extended wings fly to the left of the 
woman's extended right arm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground over which the embracing couple runs may 
be covered with low vegetation, such as grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A hill or mound of vegetation rises in the background behind the embracing couple.  
                     Farther back there may be a low mountain range. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>mountain</characteristic><characteristic>snow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A mountain, perhaps partly covered with snow, rises in the right background.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Red streaks in the sky left of the embracing couple 
suggest a sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Given their shape, the text panels would seem to 
function as clouds within the pictorial image.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The left margin of the text is decorated with 
several vines.  One extends vertically from line 13 to line 2.  
Horizontal vines extend from the beginning of line 4 to the left 
margin and between lines 5 and 6.  Vines with loops appear in the 
left margin at lines 19 to 21, and at the start of line 22.  A 
bird soars on extended wings above "Rousseau" in line 19.  What 
might be another bird appears in the top left corner of the 
plate.  Two insects, possibly moths, appear left of lines 8 and 9, beneath a faintly printed vine with a loop. </illusobjdesc><component type="animal" location="B"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bird soars on extended wings above "Rousseau" in 
line 19 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><illusobjdesc>What might be a bird flying on extended wings 
appears at the top left corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="A"><characteristic>insect</characteristic><characteristic>moth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two insects, possibly moths, hover in the margin left of lines 8 and 9. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A curving line that may represent a vine extends 
vertically in the right margin of the text from lines 13 to 
2.  To the left of this vine is another, more faintly printed vine with at least one loop. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine, perhaps with small leaves, extends 
horizontally between the left margin and the beginning of line 
4.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine extends from the first letter in line 6 of 
the text and continues horizontally between lines 5 and 
6.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine grows from the first letter in line 14 of the 
text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A horizontal line between lines 18 and 19 of the text
may represent a vine or low hills--or possibly a break in the clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine extends from the "d" of "clouds" in line 18. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with many loops appears in the margin left of 
lines 19 to 21 of the text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with two branches and several loops extends 
downward left of the first word in line 22.  Below it are two very faintly printed leaves. </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">6</physnumber><space extent="20"/></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="5">These were the Churches: Hospitals: Castles; Palaces;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.03" justify="left" indent="3">Like nets &amp; gins &amp; traps to catch the joys of Eternity</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="14">And all the rest a desart;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.05" justify="left" indent="2">Till like a dream Eternity was obliterated &amp; erased.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.06" justify="left" indent="3">Since that dread day when Har and Heva fled.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.07" justify="left" indent="3">Because their brethren &amp; sisters liv'd in War &amp; Lust;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.08" justify="left" indent="3">And as they fled they shrunk</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.09" justify="left" indent="3">Into two narrow doleful forms:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.10" justify="left" indent="3">Creeping in reptile flesh upon</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.11" justify="left" indent="3">The bosom of the ground:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.12" justify="left" indent="3">And all the vast of Nature shrunk</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.13" justify="left" indent="3">Before their shrunken eyes.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.14" justify="left">Thus the terrible race of Los &amp; Enitharmon gave</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.15" justify="left">Laws &amp; Religions to the sons of Har binding them more</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.16" justify="left">And more to Earth: closing and restraining:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.17" justify="left">Till a Philosophy of Five Senses was complete</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.18" justify="left">Urizen wept &amp; gave it into the hands of Newton &amp; Locke</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.19" justify="left" indent="7">Clouds roll heavy upon the Alps round Rousseau &amp; Voltaire:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.20" justify="left" indent="7">And on the mountains of Lebanon round the deceased Gods</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.21" justify="left" indent="7">Of Asia; &amp; on the desarts of Africa round the Fallen Angels</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.04.22" justify="left" indent="7">The Guardian Prince of Albion burns in his nightly tent</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.05" dbi="s-los.B.P5"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 5, </objcode><objcode code="E5">Erdman 5, </objcode><objcode code="K5">Keynes 5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.2 x 17.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1206" width="910"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Two figures rest on large lilies.  The ground from 
which the lily plant grows is not clearly represented, but there 
may be a river behind its stems.  If we assume that this is a 
plant of normal size, then the human figures are diminutive, 
perhaps fairies.  The female, wearing a gown that seemingly does 
not cover her left shoulder, lies on one blossom with eyes 
closed; she may be asleep.  Her head rests on her right arm and 
hand.  Her hair is long.  The male wears a long gown and a 
separate cloak.  He is crowned, and thus probably a king; by 
association, the woman may be a queen.  His eyes are open and he 
faces forward.  He has long hair and a beard.  He is more seated than lying on his blossom, with 
his upper body propped up with his right arm.  He holds a scepter 
in his left hand.  The night sky in the distance contains a few 
indications of stars.  The design is based loosely on a 
monochrome wash drawing, now usually attributed to Blake's 
brother Robert, in Blake's Notebook, page 5.  There is also a 
separate water color of the design by William Blake (private 
collection).  The two figures have traditionally been identified 
as Oberon and Titania, although the relevance of Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">A 
Midsummer Night's Dream</hi> to *The Song of Los* is not immediately 
apparent.  Other critics have identified the figures as Har and 
Heva, as on Plate 4.  Perhaps, given the cosmic scale of Plate 8, this plate represents the microscopic world of the Blakean 
imagination.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg dangling</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>crown</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><characteristic>fairy</characteristic><characteristic>king</characteristic><characteristic>Har</characteristic><characteristic>Oberon</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male figure, wearing a gown and a separate cloak, 
sits on a lily.  If the flower determines the scale, then this 
diminutive male may be a fairy.  He is crowned and holds a 
scepter in his left hand; he may be a king.  He props up his upper body with his right arm; 
his right leg is drawn up and his left leg dangles from the edge of the flower.  He faces forward and has long hair and a beard.  He has been 
identified by modern critics as either Har (see Plate 4) or 
Oberon from Shakespeare's <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night's 
Dream</hi>.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>reclining</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>sleeping</characteristic><characteristic>fairy</characteristic><characteristic>queen</characteristic><characteristic>Heva</characteristic><characteristic>Titania</characteristic><characteristic>head on arm</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm at side</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female wearing a gown lies on a lily.  Her left 
shoulder is bare.  Her head and long hair rest on her right arm.  
Her eyes are closed and she may be sleeping.  If the scale of the 
design is determined by the flower, then this diminutive female 
may be a fairy.  Given her association with the crowned male to 
the right, she may be a queen.  She has been identified by modern 
critics as either Heva (see Plate 4) or Titania from 
Shakespeare's *A Midsummer Night's Dream*.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>lily</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A lily plant, with three blossoms (two fully open), 
and its stems and leaves dominate the image.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>river</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gray horizontal section of color printing may 
represent a river behind the lily plant.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The night sky bears a few white spots that may 
indicate stars.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><!-- [Full-page design] --><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.05.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">7</physnumber><space extent="20"/></l></texthead></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.06" dbi="s-los.B.P6"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 6, </objcode><objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes 6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.2 x 13.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1206" width="707"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Although containing considerable text, the plate 
would seem to be treated as a single, interrelated pictorial 
image.  Several figures, not very clearly defined, disport among 
the letters of the heading ("ASIA," line 2).  A seated figure, with knees 
drawn up, appears just left of the first letter.  This figure, of 
uncertain gender, has her or his head lowered.  Within the upper 
loop of the second letter, a figure clutches his head and falls 
head first.  Two embracing figures, poorly defined but probably a 
male and female, stride to the left just left of the lower part 
of the letter "I."  An ill-defined cluster of lines may be a 
seated figure at the lower parts of the final "A."  The sky 
behind the heading contains clouds and is streaked with red, 
perhaps representing a sunrise or sunset.  Below, we see a great 
tree arching over from left to right.  In a cave-like niche below 
the tree are two figures, a nude male holding a gowned woman.  He 
squats or sits on the ground, apparently with his head lowered 
since we see only the curly hair on the top of his head.  The 
female's head and left arm fall downward; she may be dead.
The dark green coloring to the left of the man and woman may be vegetation.
Undifferentiated vegetation continues down both margins of the 
text; some vine-like shapes intrude between lines of text and 
fill areas on the right of the text.  A nude figure, probably male, sits or kneels in an extremely 
contracted posture in the lower right corner of the plate.  His 
left leg is drawn up to his left shoulder.  His head is turned to 
the left (his face is not pictured); he clutches his lowered head 
with both hands.  He (or, perhaps, she) may have long hair. </illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head on knees</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A small figure, with legs drawn up to the chest, sits
to the left of the first "A" in the heading ("ASIA," line 2).  The figure's
head may be lowered to his or her knees.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably male, falls head first at 
the top of the letter "S" of the heading (line 2).  He clutches his head 
with both hands.  His legs are spread apart, with one leg bent at the knee.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>group of figures</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>embracing</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>scarf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two figures, probably a male and female, stride to 
the left just left of the lower part of the letter "I" in the 
heading (line 2).  Both seem to wear gowns and are probably embracing.  The lower portions of their gowns trail to the right; a long scarf floats to the right behind one of the 
figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A cluster of lines between the two diagonals of the 
final "A" of the heading (line 2) may represent a gowned and seated 
figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits or kneels on one leg (just above line 3)
and holds a dead or dying female.  His right leg is drawn up just to
the left of his right shoulder.  His face is not shown; we see only
his curly hair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>limp</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female (just above line 3) is held by a nude man. 
                     Her head, long hair, and left arm descend limply downward; she may be dead. 
                     Her legs and the drapery from her gown are bent beneath her. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>knee</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably male, sits or kneels in an extremely 
contracted posture in the lower right corner of the plate.  His 
left leg is drawn up to his left shoulder.  His head is turned to 
the left (his face is not pictured); he clutches his lowered head 
with both hands.  He (or, perhaps, she) may have long hair. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>cave</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large tree arches over and forms a cave for the 
man holding the (dead?) woman.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dark green coloring to the left of the man and woman may be vegetation.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A good deal of undifferentiated vegetation decorates 
both margins of the text.  Some of this vegetation intrudes, in 
the form of vines, between lines of text.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky behind and above the heading contains 
clouds.  The red and pink coloring suggests a sunrise or 
sunset.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">ASIA</l></lg></transcription><illusobjdesc>The heading is fully integrated into the pictorial 
image.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A good deal of undifferentiated vegetation decorates both margins of the text. Some of this vegetation intrudes in the form of vines or branches between lines 
                  7-8, 15-16, 19-20, and 23-24. </illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A good deal of undifferentiated vegetation decorates 
                     both margins of the text.  Some of this vegetation intrudes, in 
                     the form of vines or branches, between lines 7-8, 15-16, 19-20, and 23-24.  The vine between 7-8 grows into a leafy branch
                     that extends downward into the right margin.  An additional vine descends right of "laborious" in line 17, merges with the vegetation beneath the kneeling figure, and attaches to the final letter of "path" in line 24. A vine with two loops also grows from the first letter of line 24.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with several loops extends from the first letter of line 1. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with several loops extends from the first letter of line 10 and connects to the first letter of "King" later in the same line.  </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">8</physnumber><space extent="25"/></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.02" justify="left" indent="10">ASIA</l></texthead><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.03" justify="left" indent="3">The Kings of Asia heard</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.04" justify="left">The howl rise up from Europe!</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.05" justify="left">And each ran out from his Web;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.06" justify="left">From his ancient woven Den;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.07" justify="left">For the darkness of Asia was startled</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.08" justify="left">At the thick-flaming, thought-creating fires of Orc.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.09" justify="left">And the Kings of Asia stood</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.10" justify="left">And cried in bitterness of soul.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.11" justify="left" indent="1">Shall not the King call for Famine from the heath?</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.12" justify="left">Nor the Priest, for Pestilence from the fen?</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.13" justify="left">To restrain! to dismay! to thin!</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.14" justify="left">The inhabitants of mountain and plain;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.15" justify="left">In the day of full-feeding prosperity;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.16" justify="left">And the night of delicious songs.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.17" justify="left" indent="1">Shall not the Councellor throw his curb</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.18" justify="left">Of Poverty on the laborious?</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.19" justify="left">To fix the price of labour;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.20" justify="left">To invent allegoric riches:</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.21" justify="left" indent="1">And the privy admonishers of men</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.22" justify="left">Call for fires in the City</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.23" justify="left">For heaps of smoking ruins,</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.24" justify="left">In the night of prosperity &amp; wantonness</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.25" justify="left" indent="1">To turn man from his path,</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.06.26" justify="left">To restrain the child from the womb,</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.07" dbi="s-los.B.P7"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7, </objcode><objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes 7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>22.3 x 13.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1160" width="702"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Although it contains considerable text, the plate is 
treated pictorially as a full-page design.  Upper right, a nude 
male falls head first in front of clouds.  His legs are bent at 
the knee, so that his lower legs are not shown, and his arms are 
similarly bent at the elbows.  His posture is contracted, with 
his head bent back.  Both margins of the text are filled with 
undifferentiated masses of vegetation, some of which intrude between lines of text.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>upside down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male falls head first in front of clouds.  
His legs are bent at the knee, so that his lower legs are not 
shown, and his arms are similarly bent at the elbows.  His 
posture is contracted, with his head bent back.  He may be 
bound.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The right-hand margin of the top half of the plate resembles a dark sky, and the upper text panels seem to function as clouds. </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Large masses of undifferentiated vegetation, perhaps 
including branches and leaves, decorate both margins of the text. 
Some of this vegetation intrudes between lines of 
text.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Vine-like extensions of the "y" in "may" and "y" in "obey" 
                  (line 3) extend horizontally between lines 3 and 4 of the text. 
                  Other letters of the text have similar vine-like extensions, 
                  such as the "p" in "weeping" (line 17), the "d" in "clouds" (line 20), 
                  which includes a loop, and the "d" in "Adam" (line 21). An independent 
                  vine with multiple loops extends horizontally between lines 9 and 10 of the text.  
                  The horizontal forms between lines 34 and 35 may also represent vines.  </illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Vine-like extensions of the "y" in "may" and "y" in "obey" 
                     (line 3) extend horizontally between lines 3 and 4 of the text.  Other 
                     letters of the text have similar vine-like extensions, such as the "p" 
                     in "weeping" (line 17).  An independent vine with multiple loops 
                     extends horizontally between lines 9 and 10 of the text.  The 
                     horizontal forms between lines 35 and 36 may also represent vines.  </illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The horizontal forms between lines 35 and 36 of the
text may represent vines.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The right-hand margin of the top half of the plate resembles a dark sky, 
                     and the upper text panels seem to function as clouds. </illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">10</physnumber><space extent="20"/></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.02" justify="left">To cut off the bread from the city,</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.03" justify="left">That the remnant may learn to obey.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.04" justify="left" indent="1">That the pride of the heart may fail;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.05" justify="left">That the lust of the eyes may be quench'd:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.06" justify="left">That the delicate ear in its infancy</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.07" justify="left">May be dull'd; and the nostrils clos'd up:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.08" justify="left">To teach mortal worms the path</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.09" justify="left">That leads from the gates of the Grave.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.10" justify="left" indent="5">Urizen heard them cry;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.11" justify="left">And his shudd'ring waving wings</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.12" justify="left">Went enormous above the red flames</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.13" justify="left">Drawing clouds of despair thro' the heavens</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.14" justify="left">Of Europe as he went:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.15" justify="left" indent="1">And his Books of brass iron &amp; gold</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.16" justify="left" indent="1">Melted over the land as he flew,</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.17" justify="left" indent="1">Heavy-waving, howling, weeping.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.18" justify="left" indent="20">And he stood over Judea;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.19" justify="left" indent="19">And stay'd in his ancient place:</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.20" justify="left" indent="18">And stretch'd his clouds over Jerusalem;</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.21" justify="left" indent="18">For Adam, a mouldering skeleton</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.22" justify="left" indent="18">Lay bleach'd on the garden of Eden;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.23" justify="left" indent="18">And Noah as white as snow</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.24" justify="left" indent="18">On the mountains of Ararat.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.25" justify="left" indent="12">Then the thunders of Urizen bellow'd aloud</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.26" justify="left" indent="12">From his woven darkness above. </l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.27" justify="left" indent="13">Orc raging in European darkness</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.28" justify="left" indent="13">Arose like a pillar of fire above the Alps</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.29" justify="left" indent="13">Like a serpent of fiery flame!</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.30" justify="left" indent="22">The sullen Earth</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.31" justify="left" indent="23">Shrunk! </l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.32" justify="left" indent="2">Forth from the dead dust rattling bones to bones</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.33" justify="left" indent="2">Join: shaking convuls'd the shivring clay breathes</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.34" justify="left" indent="3">And all flesh naked stands; Fathers and Friends;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.35" justify="left" indent="3">Mothers &amp; Infants; Kings &amp; Warriors;</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.36" justify="left" indent="10">The Grave shrieks with delight, &amp; shakes</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.37" justify="left" indent="10">Her hollow womb, &amp; clasps the solid stem;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.38" justify="left" indent="10">Her bosom swells with wild desire;</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.39" justify="left" indent="10">And milk &amp; blood &amp; glandous wine</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.40" justify="left" indent="10">In rivers rush &amp; shout &amp; dance,</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.41" justify="left" indent="10">On mountain, dale and plain.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.42" justify="left" indent="17">The SONG of LOS is Ended.</l><l n="s-los.b.illbk.07.43" justify="left" indent="19">Urizen Wept.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="s-los.b.illbk.08" dbi="s-los.B.P8"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 8, </objcode><objcode code="E8">Erdman 8, </objcode><objcode code="K8">Keynes 8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>23.5 x 17.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="1222" width="910"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits or kneels, with legs spread apart, on what 
may be clouds or partly formed cosmic globes.  He faces forward, 
but looks down at the darkened globe of an occluded sun or star.  
He holds, with both hands, a large hammer.  His hair is curly or 
flame-like; his expression is serious, perhaps even melancholy.  
The dark sun or star below him has, around the lower half of its 
circumference, spiky beams of light.  Right and left of this man 
are at least two other suns or stars, also radiating beams of 
light.  Beyond is the void of space.  The figure is almost 
certainly Los, in his character as the blacksmith-like creator of 
the temporal universe.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Los</characteristic><characteristic>blacksmith</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent upward</characteristic><characteristic>hand resting</characteristic><characteristic>hammer</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits or kneels, with legs spread apart, on what 
may be clouds or partly formed cosmic globes.  He faces forward, 
but looks down at the darkened globe of an occluded sun or star.  
He hold, with both hands, a large hammer.  His left arm is bent under his head, his right arm is bent upward with his right hand resting on top of the handle of the hammer.  His hair is curly or 
flame-like; his expression is serious, perhaps even melancholy.  
This figure is almost certainly Los, in his character as the 
blacksmith-like creator of the temporal universe.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure may be sitting on either clouds or 
partly formed cosmic globes.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The man looks down upon a dark or occluded sun or 
star.  Spiky beams of light surround the lower half of its 
circumference.  The dark, horizontal forms in front of the globe suggest clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>star</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>globe</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>void</characteristic><illusobjdesc>At least two suns or stars hover right and left of 
the figure.  Spiky beams of light emanate from 
both.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><!-- [Full-page design] --><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="s-los.b.illbk.08.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">11</physnumber><space extent="20"/></l></texthead></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>