<bad catalog="wba" catid="supplt11oct1825" copy="1" copyid="1" hidden="false" id="supplt11oct1825.1" institution="huntington" type="rm" work="Letter to Mary Ann Linnell, wife of John Linnell, 11 October 1825, supplemental views">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="Letter to Mary Ann Linnell, wife of John Linnell, 11 October 1825, supplemental views">
                    <main>Letter to Mary Ann Linnell, wife of John Linnell, 11 October 1825</main>:
                    electronic edition </title>
                <principal>
                    <resp>Editors:</resp>
                    <name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of Rochester; 
                    <name>Robert
                        Essick,</name>
                    University of California, Riverside; and 
                    <name>Joseph
                            Viscomi</name>
                    , University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal>
                <respstmt/>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt>
            <extent>1 XML file approx. ??KB; 4 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from ??KB
                to ??KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and
                Archives
                <date>???</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt/>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © 
            <date>2009</date>
            by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            This image copyright © 2009 Huntington Library and Art Gallery. </userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>Letter to William Hayley, 7 August 1804, supplemental views</title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake
                    <role>author,</role>
                    <role>inventor,</role>
                    <role>delineator</role></origination>
                <compdate value="1804.L">1804</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <numberobj>4</numberobj>
                <objorder>1-4</objorder>
                <objsize>full sheet 22.8 x 36.6 cm.
                    <note>Full sheet and Leaf Size dimensions (height
                    x width) are given according to the vertical orientation of the body of
                    Blake's letter; see the note on Number of Leaves, below. Object 1 has been
                    reoriented vertically in the Object View Page, as would be customary when
                    reading the address.</note></objsize>
                <numberleaves>2
                    <note>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter
                    appears on the first recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second
                    recto (Object 4). This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed
                    packet for posting. The address appears on the second verso (Object 1),
                    which would have been the exterior of the sealed packet. A large round hole
                    is visible along the edge of Objects 1-4 where the red wax seal was opened.
                    Unfolded full sheet views of the letter are available under Supplemental
                    Views on the Show Me pull-down menu for those objects.</note></numberleaves>
                <leafsize>22.8 x 18.3 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>pen and ink</medium>
                <inkcolor>black</inkcolor>
                <support>laid paper</support>
                <watermark>A large watermark in the center of the full sheet shows a horn within a
                    shield, the shield surmounted by a crown and a finial at the lower termination
                    of the shield. Below these motifs is an elaborate JW cipher that identifies the
                    paper as Whatman. The chain lines are 2.4 cm. apart.</watermark>
                <binding>none</binding>
                <postmark>&quot;6&quot;, &quot;A U / [7?] / [1]804&quot;</postmark>
                <sealDesc>red wax</sealDesc>
                <addressee>William Hayley</addressee>
                <placeLet>London</placeLet>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                <date>18 December 2009</date>
                <dealer>John Windle</dealer>
                <price>£38,000 hammer price (£46,850 inclusive of the buyer’s premium)</price>
                <note>William Hayley; sold from the Hayley Correspondence, Sotheby's, 20 May 1878,
                    lot 22 (£3.10s. to Naylor); sold posthumously from Naylor's stock, Sotheby's, 1
                    August 1885, lot 1031 (£3.18s. to Molini and Green of King William Street,
                    Strand); according to Sotheby's 17 December 2009 auction catalog, lot 72, the
                    letter had resided for many decades, possibly since the 1880s, in the collection
                    of Robert Griffin (c. 1840-1921) of Court Garden, Marlow, Buckinghamshire, from
                    whom it passed &quot;by descent&quot; to Sotheby’s anonymous seller at the 2009 auction;
                    sold 17 December 2009, lot 72 (£38,000 hammer price, £46,850 inclusive of the
                    buyer’s premium, to John Windle of San Francisco, acting for Robert N. Essick);
                    received by Essick 9 February 2010.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Collection of Robert N. Essick</institution>
                <addressline>Altadena, CA</addressline>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc dbi="lt11oct1825.1.1+2.RM" id="supplt11oct1825.1.rm.01">
            <objtitle>, 
                <objid>
                    <objnumber code="A1">full sheet view, Objects 1 and 2</objnumber></objid>
            </objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>22.8 x 36.6 cm.</objsize>
                <objnote>
                    <p>The full sheet was folded to form two leaves. Blake's letter appears on the
                        first recto (Object 2), first verso (Object 3), and second recto (Object 4).
                        This folded sheet was folded further to form a sealed packet for posting.
                        The address appears on the second verso (Object 1), which would have been
                        the exterior of the sealed packet. A large round hole is visible along the
                        edge of Objects 1-4 where the red wax seal was opened. Unfolded full sheet
                        views of the letter are available under Supplemental Views on the Show Me
                        pull-down menu for those objects.</p>
                </objnote>
                <windowsize height="630" width="500"/>
            </physdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>