<bad id="supps-los.f" type="rm" work="The Song of Los, copy F, supplemental views" copy="F"
    copyid="F" institution="munich" catalog="bentley" catid="F">
    <header>
        <filedesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title reg="The Song of Los, copy F, supplemental views"><main>The Song of
                        Los</main><copy>copy F</copy> : electronic edition </title>
                <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                    Hill</principal>
                <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                    and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                <funder/>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
            <extent>XML file approx. 112KB; 16 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size from 150KB
                to 1300KB</extent>
            <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>February
                    2015</date></publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
            <updatestmt> The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an
                electronic edition of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> copy F, from the Bayerische
                Staatsbibliothek, Munich, Germany. It joins copies A and D from the British Museum,
                copy B from the Library of Congress, copy C from the Morgan Library and Museum, and
                copy E from the Huntington Library. The Archive now has all six extant copies of
                this illuminated book, making <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> the fifth
                illuminated book whose entire publishing history is reproduced in the Archive,
                joining <hi rend="i">Milton a Poem</hi>, <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>,
                    <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>. The
                Archive will add <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and all complete
                copies of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> to the list later this
                year. <lb/><lb/> The eight plates of <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> were produced
                in 1795; all extant copies (A-F) were color printed in that year in a single
                pressrun. Divided into sections entitled "Africa" and "Asia," <hi rend="i">The Song
                    of Los</hi> is the last of Blake's "Continental Prophecies" (see also <hi
                    rend="i">America</hi> [1793] and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> [1794], exemplary
                printings of which are in the Archive). Blake abandons direct references to
                contemporary events to pursue the junctures among biblical narrative, the origins of
                law and religion, and his own developing mythology. Adam, Noah, Socrates, Brama,
                Los, Urizen, and several others represent both historical periods and states of
                consciousness. The loose narrative structure reaches towards a vision of universal
                history ending with apocalyptic resurrection. <lb/><lb/> Plates 1, 2, 5, and 8
                (frontispiece, title page, and full-page designs) are color printed drawings,
                executed on millboards and printed in the planographic manner of—and probably
                concurrent with—the twelve Large Color Printed Drawings of 1795, which are also in
                the Archive. Plates 3 and 4, which make up "Africa," and plates 6 and 7, which make
                up "Asia," were executed first, side by side on two oblong pieces of copper (plates
                3/4, 6/7). Initially designed with double columns in landscape format, the texts of
                the poems were transformed into vertical pages by printing the oblong plates with
                one side masked. <lb/><lb/> With the publication of <hi rend="i">The Song of
                    Los</hi> copy F, the Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable
                electronic editions of 92 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books in the
                context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic
                transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive
                bibliographies. New protocols for transcription, which produce improved accuracy and
                fuller documentation in editors' notes, have been applied to all copies of <hi
                    rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> in the Archive. With the Archive's Compare
                feature, users can easily juxtapose multiple impressions of any plate across all or
                selected copies of this or any of the other illuminated books and, with the Virtual
                Lightbox, users can examine any images in the Archive, as well as crop, zoom, and
                juxtapose them for close study. <lb/><lb/> This is the first time that works from
                the Bayerische Staatsbibliothek have been represented in the Archive. Accordingly,
                we are also publishing the library’s Blake collection list, which includes all of
                its original works by Blake, not just those published in the Archive, and joins the
                Collection Lists of over thirty other contributing institutions. <lb/><lb/> In
                addition to illuminated books, the Archive contains many important manuscripts and
                series of engravings, sketches, and water color drawings, including Blake's
                illustrations to Thomas Gray's <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, water color and engraved
                illustrations to Dante's <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>, the large color printed
                drawings of 1795 and c. 1805, the Linnell and Butts sets of the <hi rend="i">Book of
                    Job</hi> water colors and the sketchbook containing drawings for the engraved
                illustrations to the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, the water color illustrations to
                Robert Blair's <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and all nine of Blake's water color
                series illustrating the poetry of John Milton. In December 2014, the Archive
                launched a new wing, which contains searchable HTML and PDF editions of thirty-nine
                past issues of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> published from 2000
                through 2009. PDF versions present the journal as originally published, but the HTML
                versions are re-implemented with many full-color images from the Blake Archive,
                making it possible for users to link directly to those works that have been
                published in the Archive. <lb/><lb/> As always, the William Blake Archive is a free
                site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is
                made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University
                of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation
                of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
            <notesstmt/>
        </filedesc>
        <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2015</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
            Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the
            Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
            terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
            notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
            archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
            only.<lb/><lb/> This work courtesy Bayerische Staatsbibliothek,
            Munich</userestrict>
        <encodingdesc/>
        <profiledesc/>
        <revisiondesc>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>February 2015</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator,
                        University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on
                        Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley
                        Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project
                        Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber
                        Bertin,</name><name>Abby Brengle,</name><name>Katherine
                        Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea
                        Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon
                        Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric
                        Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali
                        McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie
                        Regan,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret
                        Speer,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus
                        Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>BAD and illustration description creation</change>
                <date>Spring 2014</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator,
                        University of Rochester: </resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Consultant on
                        Special Projects: </resp><name>Ashley
                        Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project
                        Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Amber
                        Bertin,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Andrea
                        Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Shannon
                        Jaime,</name><name>Gabrielle Kiriloff,</name><name>Eric
                        Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali
                        McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Adair
                        Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret
                        Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa
                        Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia
                        Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson,</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
            <changestmt>
                <change>Image acquisition, metadata creation, and color correction</change>
                <date>Fall 2012</date>
                <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                        <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                        <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                        <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw </name><resp>Project
                        Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator,
                        University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel
                        Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project
                        Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate
                        Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren
                        Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra
                        Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph
                        Fletcher,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer
                        Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep
                        Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus
                        Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt>
            </changestmt>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <objdesc>
        <source>
            <objdescid>
                <objtitle>
                    <title>
                        <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
                    </title>
                </objtitle>
                <origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor,
                        </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer,
                        </role><role>colorist</role></origination>
                <origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher> William Blake</publisher>
                    <pubplace>Lambeth</pubplace>
                    <date>1795</date>
                </imprint>
                <compdate value="1795.A">1795</compdate>
            </objdescid>
            <objinfo>
                <printdate value="1795.F">1795</printdate>
                <numberobj>8</numberobj>
                <objorder> Bentley plate numbers 1-8</objorder>
                <objsize>ranging between 24.3 x 17.5 cm. and 21.5 x 13.5 cm.</objsize>
                <numberleaves>8</numberleaves>
                <leafsize>37.1 x 26.0 cm.</leafsize>
                <medium>Relief etching with color printing and hand coloring. The title page and
                    full-plate designs (objects 1-2, 5, 8) were color printed
                    planographically.</medium>
                <printingstyle>Relief with color printing. The title page and full-plate designs
                    (objects 1-2, 5, 8) were color printed planographically.</printingstyle>
                <inkcolor>olive brown<note>objects 1, 5, and 8 may not contain any underlying ink
                        beneath the thick color printing. The brownish-gray color of the text on
                        object 2 may be color-printing medium rather than ink.</note></inkcolor>
                <support>wove paper</support>
                <watermark>none</watermark>
                <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                <pennednumbers>objects 3-8 numbered 1-6 top right<note>Object 1 is inscribed "a"
                        (top left) and object 2 is inscribed "b" (top right) in pencil. These
                        letters are not by Blake and may have been added during rebinding in May
                        1963 to indicate the proper sequence of these plates.</note></pennednumbers>
                <framelines>none</framelines>
                <binding>bound May 1963 in light beige cloth</binding>
                <stabholes>stabbed through four holes, 6.8 cm. from the top and 8.3, 7.5, and 4.6
                    cm. apart</stabholes>
            </objinfo>
            <provenance n="1">
                <name>Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich</name>
                <date>no later than c. 1841</date>
                <dealer>not recorded</dealer>
                <price>not recorded</price>
                <note>Acquired at an unknown time, no later than c. 1841, from an unrecorded source
                    by the library of Ludwig I of Bavaria and listed in his library catalogue dated
                    "1832-1840/41"; the court library of Ludwig I renamed the Bayerische
                    Staatsbibliothek, Munich, in 1919.</note>
            </provenance>
            <repository>
                <institution>Bayerische Staatsbibliothek</institution>
                <addressline>Ludwigstrasse 16</addressline>
                <addressline>80539 Munich</addressline>
                <addressline>Germany</addressline>
                <addressline>Telephone: ++49 89 28638-2322</addressline>
                <addressline>Email: direktion@bsb-muenchen.de</addressline>
                <addressline>URL: http://www.bsb-muenchen.de/index.php</addressline>
                <repositoryid label="Catalogue number">BV001649164, shelf mark Chalc.
                    160</repositoryid>
            </repository>
        </source>
        <desc id="supps-los.f.rm.01" dbi="s-los.F.P5-full">
            <objtitle>,
                <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 5 Full Leaf View</objnumber></objid></objtitle>
            <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                <objsize>37.1 x 26.0 cm.</objsize>
                <windowsize height="1206" width="910"/>
            </physdesc>
        </desc>
    </objdesc>
</bad>
