<bad id="vda.mpi" type="illbk" work="Visions of the Daughters of Albion" copy="MPI" copyid="MPI"
     institution="morgan tate" catalog="bentley" catid="mpi">
     <header>
          <filedesc>
               <titlestmt>
                    <title reg="Visions of the Daughters of Albion"><main>Visions of the Daughters
                              of Albion</main><copy> Miscellaneous Plates and Impressions</copy> :
                         electronic edition </title>
                    <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                         Rochester; <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside;
                         and <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University of North Carolina at Chapel
                         Hill</principal>
                    <sponsor>The Library of Congress, the University of North Carolina at Chapel
                         Hill, and the University of Rochester</sponsor>
                    <funder/>
               </titlestmt>
               <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt>
               <extent>1 XML encoded file approx. 71KB; 6 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files ranging in size
                    from 150KB to 1500KB</extent>
               <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March
                         2018</date></publicationstmt>
               <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
               <updatestmt>The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publications of a
                    digital edition of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> copy R
                    from the Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich; colored impressions of <hi
                         rend="i">Visions</hi> plates 1, 2, and 3 from the Morgan Library and
                    Museum; a proof of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> plate 6 from the Fitzwilliam Museum
                    that belongs to our previously published copy a; and five monochrome wash
                    drawings for the wood engravings in Thornton’s Virgil added to the seven
                    previously published designs.<lb/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, extant in eighteen complete copies, consists of
                    eleven relief-etched plates executed and first printed in 1793. Blake initially
                    printed <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> on both sides of six quarto-size leaves in a
                    print run of eleven copies, in yellow ochre (as in copy A), raw sienna (copies
                    B, C, and E), and green (copies H, I, and J), and he finished the impressions in
                    light watercolor washes. Copy R represents a complete departure from this early
                    mode of producing illuminated books. It was printed in 1794 with copy F in thick
                    colors from the shallows and surfaces of the plates on large sheets of folio
                    size paper to produce impressions resembling oil sketches or paintings rather
                    than watercolor drawings. Examples of the full leaf can be seen in "Supplemental
                    Views" in the navigation bar below the images of Objects 1 and 10. <lb/>
                    <lb/>With this publication the Archive is introducing a new category of graphic
                    works, referred to in the index of copies of a work as Miscellaneous Plates and
                    Impressions, which allows us to group together a work’s proofs, impressions in
                    different states, posthumous impressions, and lifetime impressions not used or
                    extracted from copies. The three loose impressions of plates from <hi rend="i"
                         >Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> at the Morgan Library and Museum
                    were printed in the green of copies H, I, and J and finished in watercolors in
                    Blake's early style, but they appear not to have belonged to a copy. These three
                    plates from <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> can be accessed like plates in other
                    copies of a work and compared with other impressions from the same matrix using
                    the "Objects from the Same Matrix" feature in the second navigation bar below
                    the image. The Archive will gradually publish groups of miscellaneous prints and
                    proofs for each illuminated book (some groups consisting of upward of fifty
                    impressions), which will enable users to trace the evolution of Blake's printed designs.<lb/>
                    <lb/><hi rend="i">Visions</hi> copy a consists of uncolored impressions of six
                    plates printed in black ink; plates 1 and 2 are of the full plate, but plates 3,
                    7, 9, and 10 were cut from their leaves and show just the vignettes. The loose
                    impression in the Fitzwilliam Museum is similarly cut from plate 6 and appears
                    certainly to have once belonged to the set of proofs making up copy a.<lb/>
                    <lb/>The Archive is also pleased to announce the addition of five of Blake's
                    monochrome wash drawings for "The Pastorals of Virgil" to the seven drawings
                    that had previously been available. The drawings can be examined in comparison
                    with their finished wood engravings by using the "Objects from the Same
                    Production Sequence" feature in the second navigation bar below the image. The
                    addition of the new drawings marks the first time that the Archive has published
                    a work from the Beinecke Library. Accordingly, we are also publishing the
                    Beinecke's Blake collection list, which includes all of its original works by
                    Blake, not just those published in the Archive. We have also recently published
                    the collection lists for the Brooklyn Museum, Cleveland Museum of Art, Houghton
                    Library, Mead Art Museum, Minneapolis Institute of Art, National Gallery of
                    Scotland, and Rhode Island School of Design. Under "Resources for Further
                    Research," the Archive now offers thirty-eight collection lists of contributing institutions.<lb/>
                    <lb>All works in the Archive are accessible via the Table of Contents, which is
                         accessible via the "sandwich" button at the right end of the banner. This
                         drops down a second banner that identifies the categories of works in the
                         Archive: Illuminated books, Commercial Book Illustrations, Separate Prints
                         and Prints in Series, Drawings and Paintings, Manuscripts and Typographic
                         Works. To further improve accessibility to the works, we've added a Table
                         of Contents item, "All Works," which twice lists all of the works in the
                         Archive without categorizing them according to medium. One list puts the
                         works in alphabetical order and the other in order of composition date. The
                         latter list would of course be of interest to any Blake scholars mindful of
                         the historical progression of Blake's works.</lb>
                    <lb/>With the publication of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> copy R, the Archive now
                    contains fully searchable and scalable digital editions of 106 copies of Blake's
                    nineteen illuminated books—including twelve other copies of <hi rend="i"
                         >Visions</hi>. Users may view color-corrected digital images of Blake's
                    works at their true size, and enlarge and rotate these images to examine the
                    text and illustrations in detail. The images are accompanied by diplomatic
                    transcriptions and editors' notes, as well as illustration descriptions that
                    make it possible to search Blake's works for visual motifs. The Archive also
                    provides full bibliographic and provenance information for each digital edition
                    it publishes. Though the Archive retains its focus on the material conditions of
                    Blake's art, presenting images in the context of works and copies, the newly
                    designed site contextualizes each work, copy, and object in a network of
                    relations. Users of the site can view each Blakean object alongside objects in
                    the same copy, objects printed from the same matrix, objects from the same
                    production sequence, and objects with similar designs. This contextualization,
                    which draws on the expertise of the Archive's editors, enables comparisons
                    across time, medium, and genre, and foregrounds the immense variety and the
                    recurring themes of Blake's art.<lb/>
                    <lb/>As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access
                    restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the
                    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester,
                    the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the
                    international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us
                    permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive. </updatestmt>
               <notesstmt/>
          </filedesc>
          <userestrict>Copyright © <date>2018</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick, and Joseph
               Viscomi, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with
               the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on
               other terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
               advance notification of the publisher. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in
               this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication
               only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © 2018 Morgan Library and Museum</userestrict>
          <encodingdesc/>
          <profiledesc/>
          <revisiondesc>
               <changestmt>
                    <change>BAD created, 1 image acquired, final proofing and publication</change>
                    <date>February 2018</date>
                    <respstmt>
                         <resp>Editors:</resp>
                         <name>Morris Eaves,</name> University of Rochester; <name>Robert
                              Essick,</name> University of California, Riverside; and <name>Joseph
                              Viscomi,</name> University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                              <resp>Technical Editor:</resp>
                         <name>Michael Fox</name>
                         <resp>Managing Editor:</resp>
                         <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
                         <resp>Assistant Project Manager:</resp>
                         <name>Grant Glass</name>
                         <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp>
                         <name>Eric Loy</name>
                         <resp>Consultants on Special Projects:</resp>
                         <name>Ashley Reed</name>
                         <name>Nikolaus Wasmoen</name>
                         <name>Laura Whitebell</name>
                         <resp>Bibliographer:</resp>
                         <name>Mark Crosby</name>
                         <resp>Project Assistants:</resp>
                         <name>Anna Alden,</name>
                         <name>Katherine Calvin,</name>
                         <name>Patrick Delehanty,</name>
                         <name>Alison Harper,</name>
                         <name>Jarrod Ingles,</name>
                         <name>Rachael Isom,</name>
                         <name>Joel Kingsley,</name>
                         <name>Mary Learner,</name>
                         <name>Rob Rich,</name>
                         <name>Oishani Sengupta,</name>
                         <name>Matthew Skwiat,</name>
                         <name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name>
                    </respstmt>
               </changestmt>
               <changestmt>
                    <change>2 images acquired</change>
                    <date>February 1998</date>
                    <respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves,</name>University of
                         Rochester; <name>Robert Essick,</name>University of California, Riverside;
                         and <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel
                         Hill <resp>Technical Editor: </resp>
                         <name>Andrea Laue</name>
                         <resp>Programmer/Analyst: </resp>
                         <name>Robert Bingler</name>
                         <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
                         <name>Justin Van Kleeck</name>
                         <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
                         <name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name>
                         <name>Kari Kraus, </name>
                         <name>Gerald Miller, </name>
                         <name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name>
                         <name>Sarah Trippensee</name></respstmt>
               </changestmt>
          </revisiondesc>
     </header>
     <objdesc>
          <source>
               <objdescid>
                    <objtitle>
                         <title>*Visions of the Daughters of Albion*</title>
                    </objtitle>
                    <origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor,
                              </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer,
                              </role><role>colorist</role></origination>
                    <origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination>
                    <imprint>
                         <publisher> William Blake<note>Blake is named as the printer on the title
                                   page, but he is also the "publisher."</note></publisher>
                         <pubplace>London<note>The place of publication is not given in the book,
                                   but Blake lived in London during the writing, etching, and
                                   printing of these impressions.</note></pubplace>
                         <date>1793</date>
                    </imprint>
                    <compdate value="1793.A">1793</compdate>
               </objdescid>
               <objinfo>
                    <printdate value="1818.D">1793, 1796<note>1793 (Objects 1, 3, and 4), 1796 (Objects 2 and 5)</note></printdate>
                    <numberobj>5</numberobj>
                    <objorder>Bentley Plates 1, 1, 2, 3, 7</objorder>
                    <objsize>various
                         <note>Object 1 (Bentley Plate 1): 17.1 x 11.9 cm.</note>  
                         <note>Object 2 (Bentley Plate 1): 17.1 x 11.9 cm.</note>
                         <note>Object 3 (Bentley Plate 2): 16.3 x 12.9 cm.</note> 
                         <note>Object 4 (Bentley Plate 3): 14.2 x 11.2 cm.</note> 
                         <note>Object 5 (Bentley Plate 7): 7.5 x 11.5 cm.</note>                          
                      </objsize>
                    <numberleaves>4<note>Object 4 (Bentley Plate 3) is printed on the verso of Object 3 (Bentley Plate
                    2).  The full leaves of Objects 3 and 4 are reproduced as Supplemental Views of those two objects.</note></numberleaves>
                    <leafsize>various
                         <note>Object 1 (Bentley Plate 1): 37.5 x 27.2 cm.</note>  
                         <note>Object 2 (Bentley Plate 1): 35.5 x 26.7 cm.</note>
                         <note>Object 3 (Bentley Plate 2): 37.5 x 27.2 cm.</note> 
                         <note>Object 4 (Bentley Plate 3): 37.5 x 27.2 cm.</note> 
                         <note>Object 5 (Bentley Plate 7): 28.2 x 24.5 cm.</note> 
                         <note>The full leaves of Objects 3 and 4 are reproduced as Supplemental Views of those two objects.</note>                         
                         </leafsize>
                    <medium>relief etching, with white-line etching on Object 3, and with hand coloring.  Objects 2 and 5 (Bentley Plates 1 and 7) are richly color printed.</medium>
                    <printingstyle>relief</printingstyle>
                    <inkcolor>green (Objects 1, 3, and 4), yellow ochre (Objects 2 and 5)</inkcolor>
                    <support>wove paper</support>
                    <watermark>none</watermark>
                    <etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers>
                    <pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers>
                    <framelines>There are no framing lines around Objects 1, 3, and 4.  There are two framing lines, the inner line contiguous with the edges of the images, around Objects 2 and 5.</framelines>
                    <binding>loose<note>Objects 1, 3, and 4 were formerly bound with *Visions of the Daughters of Albion*
                              copy F in red levant half morocco.</note></binding>
                    <stabholes>Objects 1, 3, and 4 were originally stabbed through three holes, 10.3 cm. from the top and 7.6
                         cm. and 8.0 cm. apart.  There are no stab holes in Objects 2 and 5.</stabholes>
               </objinfo>
               <provenance n="1">
                    <name>Multiple</name>

                    <note>Objects 1, 3, 4:  Early history of all three plates (Objects 1, 3, 4) not known; Objects 3 and 4
                         (Bentley Plates 2 and 3), printed recto/verso, offered in Ellis and White
                         Nov. 1882 catalogue 50, item 81, inserted in *Visions of the Daughters of
                         Albion* copy F (&#163;63); the volume acquired by Bernard Buchanan
                         Macgeorge no later than 1892 and Object 1 (Bentley Plate 1) inserted into
                         the volume no later than that date; the volume with Objects 1, 3, and 4 sold from
                         the Macgeorge collection, Sotheby's, 1 July 1924 lot 113 (&#163;385 to the
                         dealer Bernard Quaritch); the volume offered by Quaritch, catalogue 388 of
                         Oct. 1924, item 324, catalogue 401 of May 1926, item 217, and catalogue 405
                         of Dec. 1926, item 242 (&#163;525 in each); the volume acquired by Paul
                         Hyde Bonner no later than 1930; the volume sold from Bonner's collection,
                         American Art Association-Anderson Galleries auction, New York, 15 Feb.
                         1934, lot 11 ($5200 to the dealer A. S. W. Rosenbach, probably acting for
                         Mrs. Landon K. Thorne); the volume given by Thorne in 1972 to the Pierpont
                         Morgan Library (now Morgan Library and Museum). In the provenance record of
                         *Visions of the Daughters of Albion* copy F there is no indication of the
                         presence of Objects 3 and 4 (Bentley Plates 2 and 3) until the Ellis and
                         White catalogue of 1882, and no indication of the presence of Object 1
                         (Bentley Plate 1) until the Macgeorge collection catalogue of 1892.</note>
                    <note>Object 2: Acquired by John Linnell directly from Blake no later than 1827 or from Blake's wife Catherine between 1827 and 1831; sold from Linnell's collection, Christie's, 15 March 1918, lot 174 (&#163;52.10s. to Alec Martin of Christie's acting for the National Art Collections Fund); presented by the National Art Collections Fund to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection) in 1919.</note>
                    <note>Object 5: Acquired by John Linnell directly from Blake no later than 1827 or from Blake's wife Catherine between 1827 and 1831; sold from Linnell's collection, Christie's, 15 March 1918, lot 175 (&#163;17.17s. to Alec Martin of Christie's acting for the National Art Collections Fund); presented by the National Art Collections Fund to the Tate Gallery (now Tate Collection) in 1919.</note>
                    
               </provenance>
               <institution>Objects 1, 3, and 4: Morgan Library and Museum; Objects 2 and 5: Tate Collection</institution>
               <repositories>
               <repository>
                    <institution>Objects 1, 3, and 4: Morgan Library and Museum</institution>
                    <department>Printed Books and Bindings</department>
                    <repositoryid label="Accession numbers">063138 plates 1b, 2b, 3b</repositoryid>
               </repository>
                    <repository>
                         <institution>Objects 2 and 5: Tate Collection</institution>
                         <repositoryid label="Accession numbers">N03373 (Object 2), N03374 (Object 5)</repositoryid>
                    </repository>
               </repositories>
          </source>
          <desc id="vda.mpi.illbk.01" dbi="vda.mpi.P1" compwith="bb85.B5">
               <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1"
                              >(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode><objcode
                              code="Ki">Keynes i)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objsize>17.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                    <windowsize height="889" width="619"/>
               </physdesc>
               <illusdesc>
                    <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                         <illusobjdesc>Three nude figures are seen within the mouth of a cave that
                              opens onto the sea. Clouds may fill the sky, but fail to cover the
                              disc of the sun. The shape of the area where the sun appears suggests
                              and eye socket, perhaps within a skull outlined by the cave's mouth
                              and in left profile. Indeterminate vegetation dangles from the roof of
                              the cave. The figures sit or kneel on large stones or, in the case of
                              the two leftmost figures, perhaps on sand. Water may intrude into the
                              area of the cave below the figures. On the left is a heavily-muscled
                              and bearded male seen in left profile. He sits or squats on sand or
                              stones at the cave's mouth. He looks to the left with wide-open eyes;
                              his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his hair stands on end.
                              His mouth is open and he may be howling. His knees are drawn up in a
                              contracted position; his right arm is drawing backwards as though
                              bound behind him. A large shackle is affixed to his left ankle; a
                              massive chain with multiple links descends below his left hip. He may
                              be bound back to back with the female directly to the right. This pair
                              is probably Oothoon, the central female figure in the poem, and her
                              tormentor Bromion. She kneels, with her body bent down and to the
                              right. The right-most section of the chain below Bromion may be
                              attached to Oothoon. Her face is pointed down; her long hair cascades
                              over her neck and down behind her head. Above her and to the right, an
                              extremely contracted figure sits among rocks. This is probably
                              Theotormon, Oothoon's ineffectual lover. His legs appear to be
                              crossed, with the left foot prominently poised below his heavy knees.
                              He faces down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with
                              curly hair. His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm
                              bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps
                              clutching his curly hair. His right arm descends along the right side
                              of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left
                              elbow.</illusobjdesc>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sand</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The three figures are situated within the mouth of a
                                   cave formed of stones and possibly a sandy floor.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>We see the sea behind and on each side of the figure on
                                   the left. Perhaps some of its waters come near to his feet. The
                                   dark area just above the lower margin of the plate may be more
                                   water with small waves.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="AB">
                              <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The sky, seen above the figures and below the roof of
                                   the cave, is filled with clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="A">
                              <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>eye</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>eye socket</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The round disc of the sun and its surrounding radiance
                                   appears through a break in the clouds. The shape of the area in
                                   which it appears suggests an eye socket, in which case the sun
                                   itself fulfill the role of an eye.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="C">
                              <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A shackle is affixed to the left ankle of the male on
                                   the left. A chain appears below his left hip.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                              <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Clumps of vegetation of an indeterminate type dangle
                                   from the roof of the cave.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="structure" location="E">
                              <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>skull</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The setting for the design-the mouth of a cave-can be
                                   considered a structure with both a roof and a floor. The outline
                                   of the cave, plus the eye-like sun and the area in which it is
                                   placed, suggest a human skull in left profile.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="AC">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Bromion</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>howling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>On the left is a nude, heavily-muscled, and bearded male
                                   seen in left profile. He sits or squats on the sandy or stony
                                   surface of a cave's mouth. He looks to the left with wide-open
                                   eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his flame-like
                                   hair stands on end. His mouth is open and he may be howling. His
                                   knees are drawn up in a contracted position; his right arm is
                                   drawing backwards as though bound behind him. A large shackle is
                                   affixed to his left ankle; three links of a massive chain descend
                                   below his left hip. This is probably Bromion, the tormentor of
                                   the central female figure in the text, Oothoon. </illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude female, seen in right profile, kneels on the
                                   stones or sand of the cave's mouth. She may be bound back to back
                                   to the male to the left. This pair is probably Oothoon, the
                                   central female figure in the poem, and her tormentor Bromion. Her
                                   body is bent down and to the right. The right-most link of the
                                   chain below Bromion may be attached to Oothoon. Her face is
                                   pointed down; her long hair cascades over her neck and down
                                   behind her head.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="BD">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude male squats in an extremely contracted posture
                                   among rocks. This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's ineffectual
                                   lover. His legs appear to be crossed, with the left foot
                                   prominently poised below his heavy knees. He faces forward and
                                   down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly
                                   hair. His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm
                                   bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps
                                   clutching his hair. His right arm descends along the right side
                                   of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left
                                   elbow.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                    </illustration>
               </illusdesc>

               <!--[Full-page design]-->
          </desc>
          <desc id="vda.mpi.illbk.02" dbi="vda.mpi.P2" compwith="bb85.B5">
               <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B1"
                              >(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode><objcode
                              code="Ki">Keynes i)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objnote>
                         <p>Blake printed this impression immediately after printing Object 5 (Bentley Plate 1) in *A Large Book of Designs* copy A.</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <objsize>17.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize>
                    <windowsize height="889" width="619"/>
               </physdesc>
               <illusdesc>
                    <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                         <illusobjdesc>Three nude figures are seen within the mouth of a cave that
                              opens onto the sea. Clouds may fill the sky, but fail to cover the
                              disc of the sun. The shape of the area where the sun appears suggests
                              an eye socket, perhaps within a skull outlined by the cave's mouth and
                              seen in left profile. Indeterminate vegetation dangles from the roof
                              of the cave. The figures sit or kneel on large stones or, in the case
                              of the two leftmost figures, perhaps on sand. Water may intrude into
                              the area of the cave below the figures. On the left is a
                              heavily-muscled and bearded male seen in left profile. He sits or
                              squats on sand or stones at the cave's mouth. He looks to the left
                              with wide-open eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his
                              hair stands on end. His mouth is open and he may be howling. His knees
                              are drawn up in a contracted position; his right arm is drawn
                              backwards as though bound behind him. Large shackles are affixed to
                              his ankles; a massive chain with multiple links descends below his
                              left hip. He may be bound back to back with the female directly to the
                              right. This pair is probably Oothoon, the central female figure in the
                              poem, and her tormentor Bromion. She kneels, with her body bent down
                              and to the right, seen in right profile. Her face is pointed down; her
                              long hair cascades over her neck and down behind her head. Above her
                              and to the right, an extremely contracted figure sits among rocks.
                              This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's ineffectual lover. His legs
                              appear to be crossed, with the left foot prominently poised below his
                              heavy knees. He faces down so that we see only the top of his head,
                              covered with curly hair. His arms are wrapped around his head, with
                              the left arm bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist,
                              perhaps clutching his curly hair. His right arm descends along the
                              right side of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left
                              elbow.</illusobjdesc>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>cave</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sand</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The three figures are situated within the mouth of a
                                   cave formed of stones and possibly a sandy floor.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>shore</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>We see the sea behind and on each side of the figure on
                                   the left. Perhaps some of its waters come near to his feet. The
                                   dark area just above the lower margin of the plate may be more
                                   water with small waves.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="AB">
                              <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The sky, seen above the figures and below the roof of
                                   the cave, is filled with dark clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="A">
                              <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>eye</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>eye socket</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The round disc of the sun appears through a break in the
                                   clouds. The shape of the area in which it appears suggests an eye
                                   socket, in which case the sun itself fulfills the role of an
                                   eye.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="C">
                              <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Large shackles are affixed to the ankles of the male on
                                   the left. A chain appears below his left hip.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="vegetation" location="AB">
                              <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Clumps of vegetation of an indeterminate type dangle
                                   from the roof of the cave.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="structure" location="E">
                              <characteristic>roof</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>floor</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>skull</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The setting for the design--the mouth of a cave--can be
                                   considered a structure with both a roof and a floor. The outline
                                   of the cave, plus the eye-like sun and the area in which it is
                                   placed, suggests a human skull in left profile.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="AC">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Bromion</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>terror</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fear</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>howling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>muscular</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>On the left is a nude, heavily-muscled, and bearded male
                                   seen in left profile. He sits or squats on the sandy or stony
                                   surface of a cave's mouth. He looks to the left with wide-open
                                   eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his flame-like
                                   hair stands on end. His mouth is open and he may be howling. His
                                   knees are drawn up in a contracted position; his right arm is
                                   drawing backwards as though bound behind him. Large shackles are
                                   affixed to his ankles; two links of a massive chain descend below
                                   his left hip. This is probably Bromion, the tormentor of the
                                   central female figure in the text, Oothoon. </illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bowing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>eyes down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs bent</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude female, seen in right profile, kneels on the
                                   stones or sand of the cave's mouth. She may be bound back to back
                                   to the male to the left. This pair is probably Oothoon, the
                                   central female figure in the poem, and her tormentor Bromion. Her
                                   body is bent down and to the right. Her face is pointed down; her
                                   long hair cascades over her neck and down behind her
                                   head.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="BD">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>left foot</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fist</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude male squats in an extremely contracted posture
                                   among rocks. This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's ineffectual
                                   lover. His legs appear to be crossed, with the left foot
                                   prominently poised below his heavy knees. He faces forward and
                                   down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly
                                   hair. His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm
                                   bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps
                                   clutching his hair. His right arm descends along the right side
                                   of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left
                                   elbow.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                    </illustration>
               </illusdesc>

               <!--[Full-page design]-->
          </desc>
          <desc id="vda.mpi.illbk.03" dbi="vda.mpi.P3">
               <objtitle>
                    <title type="transcribed">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>,
                              <objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B2"
                              >(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii,
                              </objcode><objcode code="Kii">Keynes ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objnote>
                         <p>Object 4 (Bentley Plate 3) is printed on the verso of this Object 3
                              (Bentley plate 2).</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <objsize>16.3 x 12.9 cm.</objsize>
                    <windowsize height="848" width="671"/>
               </physdesc>

               <illusdesc>
                    <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                         <illusobjdesc>The title page is a seascape, with two storm-tossed waves in
                              the lower margin, heavy clouds, rain, and eleven human figures. The
                              angle of the waves suggests a strong wind blowing from left to right.
                              A nude female runs toward us with her right foot touching a trough
                              between waves, lower center. She is probably the central female figure
                              in the poem, Oothoon. Her left leg is extended behind her, her arms
                              are raised at 135 degrees, and the fingers of both hands are separated
                              and extended. She appears to look back and up; her long hair streams
                              back and to the right as though blown by a wind. She may be looking at
                              the figure hovering in the air above her, a bearded male who looks
                              directly at the viewer and may be pursuing Oothoon. This threatening
                              male may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor; or Urizen, the evil sky-god
                              (among other attributes). We see only his head and face, shoulders,
                              and arms and hands wrapped around his shoulders in a contracted
                              posture. His large wings extend horizontally. His face is heavily
                              lined, particularly the forehead. Flames spring from below his wings
                              and rise above them. To the left is a ring of three female figures
                              pictured as though nude but with the twisted, spiraling hems of gowns
                              trailing behind them. They form a circle, as though participating in
                              an ecstatic dance. The figure at the bottom of the right holds hands
                              with her two companions. Her arms are extended horizontally and her
                              legs are spread apart as though she were striding energetically to the
                              right. Her head is turned away from the viewer. The dancer furthest to
                              the left also has her arms extended horizontally (relative to her
                              body); her head is tilted back as though she were looking up. Like her
                              companion below, a strand of long hair extends from her head. The
                              final dancer, top right in the circle, has her arms raised at 135
                              degrees and has her legs spread. Her back and neck are arched
                              backwards and she appears to be looking up. Above the ring of dancers,
                              and just left of the first diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in
                              line 4, is a slender, nude figure seen from the side with at least one
                              arm extended downward. She may be holding a small scepter in her
                              extended hand. This figure, probably female, seems to be descending
                              head-first. To the left of this figure, near the left margin of the
                              plate, is a nude figure, probably female, seen from the side and
                              sitting on a cloud. Her knees are drawn up towards her head, which is
                              tilted down and to the left. Her left arm, which we see only from the
                              shoulder to the elbow, extends behind her as though it is propping her
                              up or possibly bound behind her. To the right of these two figures,
                              and near the center of the plate, is a figure, probably female and
                              gowned, sitting on a cloud just above the letters "b" and "i" of
                              "Albion" in line 4. She faces to the left and we see only her left
                              side. Her upper body and head are bent over at such a sharp angle that
                              they touch her upper left leg. In this contracted posture, her long
                              hair cascades over her left knee. Higher along the left margin of the
                              design and left of the word "of" in line 2 are two figures on a cloud.
                              Both appear to be nude; at least the one on the left is probably
                              female. We see this figure on the left from behind. Her upper body is
                              bent over, with her left arm extending downwards (perhaps touching the
                              head of the figure below) and her long hair cascading downwards. Her
                              right arm is bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or
                              balance. Her companion to the right lies on the cloud, with her or his
                              prominent knees on the left in a twisted and contracted posture. We
                              apparently see only the top of her or his head; the figure may be
                              looking down. The left arm is bent at the elbow with the left hand
                              beneath the head. To the right, and right of the word "of" in line 2,
                              is a nude figure who may be male(?) with legs crossed. He sits on a
                              cloud. His hair is long; he faces down and to the right. He leans to
                              the right, with arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative
                              to his body) and extended downward and to the right. The fingers of
                              both hands are spread and extended as though he were casting down the
                              indications of rain (white lines against a dark background with
                              additional shadows that extend below the cloud) lower in the design.
                              Slightly below and to the right of the winged figure, the rain appears
                              to be cascading over cliffs or some sort of vegetation (these resemble
                              old men in some copies, but the indications of the human form are too
                              slight for such a conclusion in this copy). A rainbow arches
                              dramatically from lower left, through the ring of dancers, and ends
                              below the figure with crossed legs upper right. The words of the title
                              are integrated into the design and seem to float on clouds. The motto
                              and imprint appear to float on the sea below the two
                              waves.</illusobjdesc>
                         <component type="object" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The lower quarter of the plate is dominated by two large
                                   waves of a storm-tossed sea. The angle of the waves suggests a
                                   strong wind blowing from left to right.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The sky-the background for most of the plate-is filled
                                   with the outlines of clouds. Their number and billowing shapes
                                   suggest a storm. Blue sky extends along the upper margin of the
                                   design.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="BD">
                              <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>White lines against a dark background apparently
                                   indicate rain. These lines are most clearly seen below and to the
                                   right of "of" in line 3 and between the left wing of the hovering
                                   figure and the waves below. The slight angle of these lines, left
                                   to right, suggests a wind blowing left to right. Shadows
                                   emphasize the white lines. The horizontal patches below the word
                                   "of" in line 3 may be cliffs over which the rain cascades. The
                                   vertical white patches further down the plate may also be cliffs;
                                   they are less anthropomorphic in this copy than in
                                   others.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>rainbow</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A rainbow arches from the lower left margin towards the
                                   upper right margin, running through the ring of dancers and lines
                                   4 and 5.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Tongues of fire rise from beneath the wings of the
                                   hovering figure and extend above the upper edges of his wings,
                                   particularly on the right.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                              <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The green coloring of the cliffs suggests some sort of
                                   vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude female runs toward the viewer, her right foot
                                   touching a trough between two waves. Her left leg is extended
                                   backwards. Her arms are raised at an angle of 135 degrees; her
                                   upper body and neck are twisted back and to the right. She is
                                   probably looking up and back at the winged figured hovering over
                                   her. The fingers of her upraised hands, with palms facing the
                                   viewer, are spread apart. Her long hair streams out to the right,
                                   as though blown by a wind. She is probably Oothoon, the central
                                   figure in the text, who "over the waves ... went" (Bentley Plate
                                   4, not included in this group of plates; Erdman page
                                   46).</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Bromion</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Urizen</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms wrapped around body</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A bearded male hovers above the running female. This
                                   male may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or Urizen,
                                   the evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in the text.
                                   We see only his head and face, shoulders, arms and hands wrapped
                                   around his shoulders in a contracted posture, and large wings
                                   extended horizontally. He looks out at the viewer. His face is
                                   heavily lined, particularly the forehead. His mouth is open.
                                   Flames spring from below his wings and rise above them. He may be
                                   pursuing the female figure below him.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="C">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A female figure, the lowest of three females in a
                                   circle, strides energetically to the right. She appears to be
                                   nude, except that the hem of a gown spirals to the left below her
                                   right leg. She holds hands with the two other women in this
                                   circle of dancers. Her arms are extended horizontally, with her
                                   head apparently seen from behind. A strand of her long hair curls
                                   to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="C">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A female figure, furthest to the left in a circle of
                                   three female dancers, rises near the left margin of the plate.
                                   She appears to be nude, except that the hem of a gown spirals
                                   below her left hand. Her right arm is raised vertically but
                                   arches to the right; her left arm descends to hold hands with the
                                   dancer below. Her back is arched, with her head facing up. A
                                   strand of her long hair curls below her head.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="C">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A female figure, at the top of a circle of three female
                                   dancers, appears to be nude except that the hem of a long gown
                                   spirals between her spread legs and above and below her torso.
                                   Her back is arched and her arms are raised at an angle of 135
                                   degrees relative to her upper body. With her left hand she holds
                                   the right hand of the dancer below her. Her head appears to be
                                   thrown back, but neither her face nor her hair is clearly
                                   indicated.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="A">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Near the left margin of the plate is a nude figure,
                                   probably female, seen from the side and sitting on a cloud. Her
                                   knees are drawn up towards her head, which is tilted down and to
                                   the left. Her left arm, which we see only from the shoulder to
                                   the elbow, extends behind her as though it is propping her up or
                                   possibly bound behind her.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="A">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Above the ring of dancers, and just left of the first
                                   diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in line 4, is a slender,
                                   nude figure seen from the side with at least one arm extended
                                   downward. She may be holding a small object, possibly a scepter,
                                   in her extended hand. This figure, probably female, seems to be
                                   falling head-first.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="AB">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably female and gowned, sits on a cloud
                                   just above the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 4. She
                                   faces to the left and we see only her left side. Her upper body
                                   and head are bent over at such a sharp angle that they touch her
                                   upper left leg. In this contracted posture, her long hair
                                   cascades over her left knee.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="A">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>We see a nude female figure near the left margin from
                                   the back. Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm
                                   extending downwards (perhaps touching the head of the figure
                                   below) and her long hair cascading downwards. Her right arm is
                                   bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or
                                   balance.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="A">
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hand under head</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude figure of indeterminate gender lies on a cloud,
                                   with her or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted and
                                   contracted posture. We apparently see only the top of her or his
                                   head; the figure may be looking down. The left arm is bent at the
                                   elbow with the left hand beneath the head.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="B">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>casting</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>To the right of the word "of" in line 2 is a nude figure
                                   who may be male with legs crossed. He sits on a cloud. His hair
                                   is long; he faces down and to the right. He leans to the right,
                                   with arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative to his
                                   body) and extended downward and to the right. The fingers of both
                                   hands are spread and extended as though he were casting down the
                                   slight indications of rain below.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="text" location="AB">
                              <transcription>
                                   <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l justify="left">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</l>
                                   </lg>
                              </transcription>
                              <illusobjdesc>The words of the title are integrated into the design
                                   and seem to float on clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="text" location="CD">
                              <transcription>
                                   <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                        <l justify="left">The Eye sees more than the Heart
                                             knows.</l>
                                        <l justify="left"> Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript"
                                                  >m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l>
                                   </lg>
                              </transcription>
                              <illusobjdesc>The words of the motto and imprint are integrated into
                                   the design and seem to float on the sea below the two
                                   waves.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                    </illustration>
               </illusdesc>
               <phystext>
                    <vspace extent="2"/>
                    <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.01" justify="center">VISIONS</l>
                    </lg>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.02" justify="center">of</l>
                    </lg>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.03" justify="center">the Daughters of</l>
                    </lg>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.04" justify="center">Albion</l>
                    </lg>
                    <vspace extent="6"/>
                    <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.05" justify="center">The Eye sees more than the
                              Heart knows.</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.06" justify="center">Printed by Will:<hi
                                   rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l>
                    </lg>
               </phystext>
               <supplemental>
                    <desc dbi="vda.mpi.p3-full" id="suppvda.mpi.rm.03">
                         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3, full leaf view
                                        </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2,
                                        </objcode><objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii, </objcode><objcode
                                        code="Kii">Keynes ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                              <objnote>
                                   <p/>
                              </objnote>
                              <objsize> 37.5 x 27.2 cm.</objsize>
                              <windowsize height="889" width="619"/>
                         </physdesc>

                         <illusdesc>
                              <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                   <illusobjdesc>The title page is a seascape, with two storm-tossed
                                        waves in the lower margin, heavy clouds, rain, and eleven
                                        human figures. The angle of the waves suggests a strong wind
                                        blowing from left to right. A nude female runs toward us
                                        with her right foot touching a trough between waves, lower
                                        center. She is probably the central female figure in the
                                        poem, Oothoon. Her left leg is extended behind her, her arms
                                        are raised at 135 degrees, and the fingers of both hands are
                                        separated and extended. She appears to look back and up; her
                                        long hair streams back and to the right as though blown by a
                                        wind. She may be looking at the figure hovering in the air
                                        above her, a bearded male who looks directly at the viewer
                                        and may be pursuing Oothoon. This threatening male may be
                                        Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor; or Urizen, the evil sky-god
                                        (among other attributes). We see only his head and face,
                                        shoulders, and arms and hands wrapped around his shoulders
                                        in a contracted posture. His large wings extend
                                        horizontally. His face is heavily lined, particularly the
                                        forehead. Flames spring from below his wings and rise above
                                        them. To the left is a ring of three female figures pictured
                                        as though nude but with the twisted, spiraling hems of gowns
                                        trailing behind them. They form a circle, as though
                                        participating in an ecstatic dance. The figure at the bottom
                                        of the right holds hands with her two companions. Her arms
                                        are extended horizontally and her legs are spread apart as
                                        though she were striding energetically to the right. Her
                                        head is turned away from the viewer. The dancer furthest to
                                        the left also has her arms extended horizontally (relative
                                        to her body); her head is tilted back as though she were
                                        looking up. Like her companion below, a strand of long hair
                                        extends from her head. The final dancer, top right in the
                                        circle, has her arms raised at 135 degrees and has her legs
                                        spread. Her back and neck are arched backwards and she
                                        appears to be looking up. Above the ring of dancers, and
                                        just left of the first diagonal of the letter "A" of
                                        "Albion" in line 4, is a slender, nude figure seen from the
                                        side with at least one arm extended downward. She may be
                                        holding a small scepter in her extended hand. This figure,
                                        probably female, seems to be descending head-first. To the
                                        left of this figure, near the left margin of the plate, is a
                                        nude figure, probably female, seen from the side and sitting
                                        on a cloud. Her knees are drawn up towards her head, which
                                        is tilted down and to the left. Her left arm, which we see
                                        only from the shoulder to the elbow, extends behind her as
                                        though it is propping her up or possibly bound behind her.
                                        To the right of these two figures, and near the center of
                                        the plate, is a figure, probably female and gowned, sitting
                                        on a cloud just above the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in
                                        line 4. She faces to the left and we see only her left side.
                                        Her upper body and head are bent over at such a sharp angle
                                        that they touch her upper left leg. In this contracted
                                        posture, her long hair cascades over her left knee. Higher
                                        along the left margin of the design and left of the word
                                        "of" in line 2 are two figures on a cloud. Both appear to be
                                        nude; at least the one on the left is probably female. We
                                        see this figure on the left from behind. Her upper body is
                                        bent over, with her left arm extending downwards (perhaps
                                        touching the head of the figure below) and her long hair
                                        cascading downwards. Her right arm is bent sharply at the
                                        elbow as though braced for support or balance. Her companion
                                        to the right lies on the cloud, with her or his prominent
                                        knees on the left in a twisted and contracted posture. We
                                        apparently see only the top of her or his head; the figure
                                        may be looking down. The left arm is bent at the elbow with
                                        the left hand beneath the head. To the right, and right of
                                        the word "of" in line 2, is a nude figure who may be male(?)
                                        with legs crossed. He sits on a cloud. His hair is long; he
                                        faces down and to the right. He leans to the right, with
                                        arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative to his
                                        body) and extended downward and to the right. The fingers of
                                        both hands are spread and extended as though he were casting
                                        down the indications of rain (white lines against a dark
                                        background with additional shadows that extend below the
                                        cloud) lower in the design. Slightly below and to the right
                                        of the winged figure, the rain appears to be cascading over
                                        cliffs or some sort of vegetation (these resemble old men in
                                        some copies, but the indications of the human form are too
                                        slight for such a conclusion in this copy). A rainbow arches
                                        dramatically from lower left, through the ring of dancers,
                                        and ends below the figure with crossed legs upper right. The
                                        words of the title are integrated into the design and seem
                                        to float on clouds. The motto and imprint appear to float on
                                        the sea below the two waves.</illusobjdesc>
                                   <component type="object" location="CD">
                                        <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>The lower quarter of the plate is dominated by
                                             two large waves of a storm-tossed sea. The angle of the
                                             waves suggests a strong wind blowing from left to
                                             right.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="E">
                                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>storm</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>The sky-the background for most of the
                                             plate-is filled with the outlines of clouds. Their
                                             number and billowing shapes suggest a storm. Blue sky
                                             extends along the upper margin of the
                                             design.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="BD">
                                        <characteristic>rain</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>wind</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>White lines against a dark background
                                             apparently indicate rain. These lines are most clearly
                                             seen below and to the right of "of" in line 3 and
                                             between the left wing of the hovering figure and the
                                             waves below. The slight angle of these lines, left to
                                             right, suggests a wind blowing left to right. Shadows
                                             emphasize the white lines. The horizontal patches below
                                             the word "of" in line 3 may be cliffs over which the
                                             rain cascades. The vertical white patches further down
                                             the plate may also be cliffs; they are less
                                             anthropomorphic in this copy than in
                                             others.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="E">
                                        <characteristic>rainbow</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A rainbow arches from the lower left margin
                                             towards the upper right margin, running through the
                                             ring of dancers and lines 4 and 5.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="CD">
                                        <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>Tongues of fire rise from beneath the wings of
                                             the hovering figure and extend above the upper edges of
                                             his wings, particularly on the right.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="vegetation" location="BD">
                                        <characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>The green coloring of the cliffs suggests some
                                             sort of vegetation.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>running</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A nude female runs toward the viewer, her
                                             right foot touching a trough between two waves. Her
                                             left leg is extended backwards. Her arms are raised at
                                             an angle of 135 degrees; her upper body and neck are
                                             twisted back and to the right. She is probably looking
                                             up and back at the winged figured hovering over her.
                                             The fingers of her upraised hands, with palms facing
                                             the viewer, are spread apart. Her long hair streams out
                                             to the right, as though blown by a wind. She is
                                             probably Oothoon, the central figure in the text, who
                                             "over the waves ... went" (Bentley Plate 4, not
                                             included in this group of plates; Erdman page
                                             46).</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Bromion</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Urizen</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>pursuing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>old</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms wrapped around body</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>wing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>beard</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>mouth open</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A bearded male hovers above the running
                                             female. This male may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor
                                             in the poem; or Urizen, the evil sky-god (among other
                                             attributes) also named in the text. We see only his
                                             head and face, shoulders, arms and hands wrapped around
                                             his shoulders in a contracted posture, and large wings
                                             extended horizontally. He looks out at the viewer. His
                                             face is heavily lined, particularly the forehead. His
                                             mouth is open. Flames spring from below his wings and
                                             rise above them. He may be pursuing the female figure
                                             below him.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="C">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>striding</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A female figure, the lowest of three females
                                             in a circle, strides energetically to the right. She
                                             appears to be nude, except that the hem of a gown
                                             spirals to the left below her right leg. She holds
                                             hands with the two other women in this circle of
                                             dancers. Her arms are extended horizontally, with her
                                             head apparently seen from behind. A strand of her long
                                             hair curls to the right.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="C">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hem</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A female figure, furthest to the left in a
                                             circle of three female dancers, rises near the left
                                             margin of the plate. She appears to be nude, except
                                             that the hem of a gown spirals below her left hand. Her
                                             right arm is raised vertically but arches to the right;
                                             her left arm descends to hold hands with the dancer
                                             below. Her back is arched, with her head facing up. A
                                             strand of her long hair curls below her
                                             head.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="C">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing up</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>drapery</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>spiral</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>legs spread</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head bent back</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hand holding</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A female figure, at the top of a circle of
                                             three female dancers, appears to be nude except that
                                             the hem of a long gown spirals between her spread legs
                                             and above and below her torso. Her back is arched and
                                             her arms are raised at an angle of 135 degrees relative
                                             to her upper body. With her left hand she holds the
                                             right hand of the dancer below her. Her head appears to
                                             be thrown back, but neither her face nor her hair is
                                             clearly indicated.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="A">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>bound</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>Near the left margin of the plate is a nude
                                             figure, probably female, seen from the side and sitting
                                             on a cloud. Her knees are drawn up towards her head,
                                             which is tilted down and to the left. Her left arm,
                                             which we see only from the shoulder to the elbow,
                                             extends behind her as though it is propping her up or
                                             possibly bound behind her.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="A">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>falling</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>holding</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>scepter</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>Above the ring of dancers, and just left of
                                             the first diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in
                                             line 4, is a slender, nude figure seen from the side
                                             with at least one arm extended downward. She may be
                                             holding a small object, possibly a scepter, in her
                                             extended hand. This figure, probably female, seems to
                                             be falling head-first.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="AB">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing left</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably female and gowned, sits on
                                             a cloud just above the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion"
                                             in line 4. She faces to the left and we see only her
                                             left side. Her upper body and head are bent over at
                                             such a sharp angle that they touch her upper left leg.
                                             In this contracted posture, her long hair cascades over
                                             her left knee.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="A">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>reaching</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm braced</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>We see a nude female figure near the left
                                             margin from the back. Her upper body is bent over, with
                                             her left arm extending downwards (perhaps touching the
                                             head of the figure below) and her long hair cascading
                                             downwards. Her right arm is bent sharply at the elbow
                                             as though braced for support or balance.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="A">
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>lying</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hand under head</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arm bent</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A nude figure of indeterminate gender lies on
                                             a cloud, with her or his prominent knees on the left in
                                             a twisted and contracted posture. We apparently see
                                             only the top of her or his head; the figure may be
                                             looking down. The left arm is bent at the elbow with
                                             the left hand beneath the head.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="B">
                                        <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>casting</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>To the right of the word "of" in line 2 is a
                                             nude figure who may be male with legs crossed. He sits
                                             on a cloud. His hair is long; he faces down and to the
                                             right. He leans to the right, with arms raised at 45
                                             degrees (but horizontally relative to his body) and
                                             extended downward and to the right. The fingers of both
                                             hands are spread and extended as though he were casting
                                             down the slight indications of rain
                                             below.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="text" location="AB">
                                        <transcription>
                                             <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                                  <l justify="left">VISIONS of the Daughters of
                                                  Albion</l>
                                             </lg>
                                        </transcription>
                                        <illusobjdesc>The words of the title are integrated into the
                                             design and seem to float on clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="text" location="CD">
                                        <transcription>
                                             <lg type="prose" justify="left">
                                                  <l justify="left">The Eye sees more than the Heart
                                                  knows.</l>
                                                  <l justify="left"> Printed by Will:<hi
                                                  rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l>
                                             </lg>
                                        </transcription>
                                        <illusobjdesc>The words of the motto and imprint are
                                             integrated into the design and seem to float on the sea
                                             below the two waves.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                              </illustration>
                         </illusdesc>
                         <phystext>
                              <vspace extent="2"/>
                              <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.01" justify="center">VISIONS</l>
                              </lg>
                              <vspace extent="1"/>
                              <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.02" justify="center">of</l>
                              </lg>
                              <vspace extent="1"/>
                              <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.03" justify="center">the Daughters of</l>
                              </lg>
                              <vspace extent="1"/>
                              <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.04" justify="center">Albion</l>
                              </lg>
                              <vspace extent="6"/>
                              <lg type="prose" justify="center">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.05" justify="center">The Eye sees more
                                        than the Heart knows.</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.03.06" justify="center">Printed by Will:<hi
                                             rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l>
                              </lg>
                         </phystext>
                    </desc>
               </supplemental>



          </desc>
          <desc id="vda.mpi.illbk.04" dbi="vda.mpi.P4" compwith="bb136.B20">
               <objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Argument</title>, <objid><objnumber code="A4"
                              >Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3,
                              </objcode><objcode code="Eiii">Erdman iii, </objcode><objcode
                              code="Kiii">Keynes iii)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objnote>
                         <p>This Object 4 (Bentley Plate 3) is printed on the verso of Object 3
                              (Bentley Plate 2).</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <objsize>14.2 x 11.2 cm.</objsize>
                    <windowsize height="738" width="582"/>
               </physdesc>

               <illusdesc>
                    <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                         <illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to the
                              right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands over her
                              breasts. Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun, yet a few strands
                              of long hair curl down her back. She appears to be kissing a much
                              smaller (apparently female) figure, although this "kiss" is less clear
                              than in other copies because the smaller figure's head does not appear
                              to be bent back. This second nude figure is seen from behind; her arms
                              are extended horizontally. Her right foot is poised just above one of
                              the two flowers, probably marigolds, growing on a plant lower right.
                              Her left leg is bent at the knee in a dance-like posture. She seems to
                              hover in the air. The kneeling figure is probably Oothoon, the smaller
                              figure probably the "nymph" who personifies the marigold. The
                              landscape is probably Leutha's Vale, named in the text on this plate.
                              The hovering nymph may also be identified with Leutha (see "Leutha's
                              flower," Plate 4, line 6). The flat land is colored as though covered
                              with grass. A dark shadow is visible on the ground to the left of
                              Oothoon. Etched shafts of radiance seem to emanate from the
                              illuminated area lower right, perhaps the product of a rising or
                              setting sun (not pictured) or perhaps in part produced by the
                              marigolds. The background wash suggests clouds in the sky above the
                              figures.</illusobjdesc>
                         <component type="figure" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to the
                                   right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands over
                                   her breasts. Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun, yet a
                                   few strands of long hair curl down her back. She appears to be
                                   kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female. Given the
                                   text on this plate, she is almost certainly
                                   Oothoon.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="D">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nymph</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Leutha</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>marigold</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, is seen from behind. She
                                   hovers in the air, with her right foot poised just above a flower
                                   from which she may be rising. Her arms are extended horizontally
                                   and her left knee bent forward. This dance-like posture includes
                                   a gracefully twisted torso. She appears to be kissing the larger
                                   figure in other copies, but this "kiss" is less clear in this
                                   copy because the smaller figure's head does not appear to be bent
                                   back. This small figure is probably the "nymph" who personifies
                                   the marigold flower below her. She may also be identified with
                                   Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," Plate 4, line 6).</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                              <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>marigold</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>petal</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Leutha</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A low-growing plant, perhaps leafless, appears lower
                                   right in the landscape. Two arching stems terminate in large
                                   flowers, probably marigolds. Their petals are spiky. These may be
                                   "Leutha's flower[s]" (Plate 4, line 6).</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="CD">
                              <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Leutha</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>valley</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The flat landscape with low horizon is colored as though
                                   covered with grass. This is probably part of "Leutha's vale"
                                   (Plate 4, line 5).</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="C">
                              <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A dark shadow is visible on the ground to the left of
                                   Oothoon, the kneeling figure at left.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Four etched lines of radiance fill the sky. Most of the
                                   light seems to emanate from an illuminated area lower right,
                                   perhaps the product of a rising or setting sun (not pictured) or
                                   in part the product of the marigolds. Two rays may emanate from
                                   the flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A few horizontal lines and a blue wash in the sky just
                                   above the figures suggest stratus clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                    </illustration>
               </illusdesc>
               <phystext>
                    <texthead justify="left">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="3">The Argument</l>
                    </texthead>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="1">I loved Theotormon</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.03" justify="left">And I was not ashamed</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="1">I trembled in my
                              virgin fears</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.05" justify="left">And I hid in Leutha's vale!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <vspace extent="1"/>
                    <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.06" justify="left" indent="1">I plucked Leutha's
                              flower,</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.07" justify="left">And I rose up from the vale;</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.08" justify="left" indent="2">But the terrible
                              thunders tore</l>
                         <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.09" justify="left" indent="2">My virgin mantle in
                              twain.</l>
                    </lg>
               </phystext>
               <supplemental>
                    <desc dbi="vda.mpi.p4-full" id="suppvda.mpi.rm.04">
                         <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4, full leaf view
                                        </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3,
                                        </objcode><objcode code="Eiii">Erdman iii,
                                        </objcode><objcode code="Kiii">Keynes
                              iii)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
                         <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                              <objnote>
                                   <p/>
                              </objnote>
                              <objsize>37.5 x 27.2 cm.</objsize>
                              <windowsize height="889" width="619"/>
                         </physdesc>

                         <illusdesc>
                              <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                                   <illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans
                                        to the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her
                                        hands over her breasts. Her hair appears to be drawn back in
                                        a bun, yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.
                                        She appears to be kissing a much smaller (apparently female)
                                        figure, although this "kiss" is less clear than in other
                                        copies because the smaller figure's head does not appear to
                                        be bent back. This second nude figure is seen from behind;
                                        her arms are extended horizontally. Her right foot is poised
                                        just above one of the two flowers, probably marigolds,
                                        growing on a plant lower right. Her left leg is bent at the
                                        knee in a dance-like posture. She seems to hover in the air.
                                        The kneeling figure is probably Oothoon, the smaller figure
                                        probably the "nymph" who personifies the marigold. The
                                        landscape is probably Leutha's Vale, named in the text on
                                        this plate. The hovering nymph may also be identified with
                                        Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," Plate 4, line 6). The flat
                                        land is colored as though covered with grass. A dark shadow
                                        is visible on the ground to the left of Oothoon. Etched
                                        shafts of radiance seem to emanate from the illuminated area
                                        lower right, perhaps the product of a rising or setting sun
                                        (not pictured) or perhaps in part produced by the marigolds.
                                        The background wash suggests clouds in the sky above the
                                        figures.</illusobjdesc>
                                   <component type="figure" location="CD">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>kneeling</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>bun</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>bending forward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and
                                             leans to the right with her arms crossed in front of
                                             her and her hands over her breasts. Her hair appears to
                                             be drawn back in a bun, yet a few strands of long hair
                                             curl down her back. She appears to be kissing a much
                                             smaller figure, probably also female. Given the text on
                                             this plate, she is almost certainly
                                             Oothoon.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="figure" location="D">
                                        <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>hovering</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>dancing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>rising</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>kissing</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>facing away</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>nymph</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Leutha</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>marigold</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, is seen from
                                             behind. She hovers in the air, with her right foot
                                             poised just above a flower from which she may be
                                             rising. Her arms are extended horizontally and her left
                                             knee bent forward. This dance-like posture includes a
                                             gracefully twisted torso. She appears to be kissing the
                                             larger figure in other copies, but this "kiss" is less
                                             clear in this copy because the smaller figure's head
                                             does not appear to be bent back. This small figure is
                                             probably the "nymph" who personifies the marigold
                                             flower below her. She may also be identified with
                                             Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," Plate 4, line
                                             6).</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="vegetation" location="D">
                                        <characteristic>plant</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>leafless</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>flower</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>marigold</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>petal</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>spiky</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Leutha</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A low-growing plant, perhaps leafless, appears
                                             lower right in the landscape. Two arching stems
                                             terminate in large flowers, probably marigolds. Their
                                             petals are spiky. These may be "Leutha's flower[s]"
                                             (Plate 4, line 6).</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="CD">
                                        <characteristic>grass</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>Leutha</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>valley</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>The flat landscape with low horizon is colored
                                             as though covered with grass. This is probably part of
                                             "Leutha's vale" (Plate 4, line 5).</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="C">
                                        <characteristic>shadow</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A dark shadow is visible on the ground to the
                                             left of Oothoon, the kneeling figure at
                                             left.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="E">
                                        <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sky</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                                        <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>Four etched lines of radiance fill the sky.
                                             Most of the light seems to emanate from an illuminated
                                             area lower right, perhaps the product of a rising or
                                             setting sun (not pictured) or in part the product of
                                             the marigolds. Two rays may emanate from the
                                             flowers.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                                   <component type="object" location="E">
                                        <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                                        <illusobjdesc>A few horizontal lines and a blue wash in the
                                             sky just above the figures suggest stratus
                                             clouds.</illusobjdesc>
                                   </component>
                              </illustration>
                         </illusdesc>
                         <phystext>
                              <texthead justify="left">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="3">The
                                        Argument</l>
                              </texthead>
                              <vspace extent="1"/>
                              <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="1">I loved
                                        Theotormon</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.03" justify="left">And I was not
                                        ashamed</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="1">I trembled
                                        in my virgin fears</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.05" justify="left">And I hid in Leutha's
                                        vale!</l>
                              </lg>
                              <vspace extent="1"/>
                              <lg type="verse" justify="left">
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.06" justify="left" indent="1">I plucked
                                        Leutha's flower,</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.07" justify="left">And I rose up from the
                                        vale;</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.08" justify="left" indent="2">But the
                                        terrible thunders tore</l>
                                   <l n="vda.mpi.illbk.04.09" justify="left" indent="2">My virgin
                                        mantle in twain.</l>
                              </lg>
                         </phystext>
                    </desc>

               </supplemental>

          </desc>
          <desc id="vda.mpi.illbk.05" dbi="vda.mpi.P5" compwith="vda.B7">
               <objtitle>, <objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B7"
                              >(Bentley 7, </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4,</objcode><objcode
                              code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid></objtitle>
               <physdesc desclevel="brief">
                    <objnote>
                         <p>Only the design, and not the text, is printed in this impression.  Blake printed this impression immediately after printing Object 4 (the design only of Bentley Plate 7) in *A Large Book of Designs* copy A.</p>
                    </objnote>
                    <objsize>7.5 x 11.5 cm.</objsize>
                    <windowsize height="450" width="650"/>
               </physdesc>
               <illusdesc>
                    <illustration type="plate" location="E">
                         <illusobjdesc>Two figures appear on the seashore. One figure, probably
                              male, is seated on the sand or stones near the water. He wears a long
                              gown that covers his arms, knees, and lower legs. We see him from the
                              front; his knees are drawn up to his upper chest in a very contracted
                              posture. Given the position of his right foot, his legs are probably
                              crossed at the ankles. His hands rest upon his knees, and in turn his
                              head is bent forward and rests upon his hands. We see only the top of
                              his head, covered with curly hair. This is probably Theotormon,
                              "weeping" (Plate 5, line 23) near "the margind ocean" (Plate 11, line
                              13). To the left is a giant wave, shaped like a tongue of flame.
                              Within this wave is a nude female, shackled and chained on her left
                              ankle. Her right leg is apparently extended behind her left. She
                              arches to the right, with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands
                              clasped together just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer
                              or supplication. She faces down and apparently looks at the
                              self-enclosed male below her. Her long hair drifts behind her neck and
                              back. She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover. Right and
                              left of the wave in which she appears is a rocky cliff. Wavy lines
                              along the lower margin of the design below both figures suggest small
                              waves of the sea. Far right is the sea, showing a few indications of
                              waves. A sun rises or (more probably) sets on the horizon, with about
                              half of its disc visible. The sun's radiance extends in beams of light
                              upwards to clouds higher in the sky.</illusobjdesc>
                         <component type="object" location="BD">
                              <characteristic>sun</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sunrise</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sunset</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>radiance</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>beams of light</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>cloud</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A sun rises or (more probably) sets on the horizon, with
                                   about half of its disc visible. The sun's radiance extends in
                                   beams of light upwards to clouds higher in the
                                   sky.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="BD">
                              <characteristic>male</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>crying</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>gown</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>squatting</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>contracted</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing forward</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>right foot</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>curly hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head on hands</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>head on knees</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, is seated on the sand or stones
                                   near the water. He wears a long gown that covers his arms, knees,
                                   and lower legs. We see him from the front; his knees are drawn up
                                   to his upper chest in a very contracted posture. Given the
                                   position of his right foot, his legs are probably crossed at the
                                   ankles. His hands rest upon his knees, and in turn his head is
                                   bent forward and rests upon his hands. We see only the top of his
                                   head, covered with curly hair. This is probably Theotormon,
                                   "weeping" (Plate 5, line 23) near "the margind ocean" (Plate 11,
                                   line 13).</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="figure" location="E">
                              <characteristic>female</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>young</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>nude</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>shackled</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chained</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>hands together</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>leg extended</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>praying</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>supplicating</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>speaking</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing down</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>facing right</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>long hair</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arms bent</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>looking</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>arching</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>twisted</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Within a tongue- or flame-like wave is a nude female,
                                   shackled and chained on her left ankle. Her right leg is
                                   apparently extended behind her left. She arches to the right,
                                   with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands clasped together
                                   just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
                                   supplication. She faces down and apparently looks at the
                                   self-enclosed male below her. Her long hair drifts behind her
                                   neck and back. She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her
                                   lover Theotormon. Although her mouth is not clearly open, she may
                                   be speaking.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="C">
                              <characteristic>shackle</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>chain</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The left foot of the female figure is shackled and
                                   chained.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>seashore</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>cliff</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The landscape shows a cliff on the left near the
                                   seashore. The lower margin of the design has wavy lines
                                   indicating small waves of the sea.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="D">
                              <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>stone</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sand</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>Both stones and sand may be represented below the seated
                                   figure. The dark waters of the sea on the right show indications
                                   of waves.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                         <component type="object" location="E">
                              <characteristic>waves</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>sea</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>water</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>dark</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>tongue</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>flame-like</characteristic>
                              <characteristic>fire</characteristic>
                              <illusobjdesc>The female is pictured within a giant wave of dark water
                                   which, in its shape, resembles a tongue—of a creature or of
                                   fire.</illusobjdesc>
                         </component>
                    </illustration>
               </illusdesc>
               <!--[Full-page design]-->
          </desc>
     </objdesc>
</bad>
