<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2005-10-06T17:15:56-04:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><!-- Step 2 Conversion to BAD DTD 2004 using modblake.pl Thu Oct  6 17:15:18 2005 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="vda.a-proof" type="illbk" work="Visions of the Daughters of Albion" copy="a" copyid="a" institution="lc" value="proof" catalog="Bentley" catid="a"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Visions of the Daughters of Albion"><main>Visions of the Daughters of Albion</main><copy> Copy a</copy>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;  
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah C. Jones, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt><sponsor/><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 135KB; 22 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files
ranging in size from 10KB to 635KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH<date>June 2004</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, Copy A (British Museum) and proof Copy a (Library of Congress). Like all the illuminated books in the Archive, both the texts and images of these new publications are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.<lb/><lb/>
            Like Copies C and J, previously published in the Archive, Copy A was produced in Blake's first printing session for <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> in 1793. Probably to lend variety to his stock of copies on hand, Blake used three ink colors in this first printing: yellow ochre (as in Copy A), raw sienna (Copy C), and green (Copy J). All three copies exemplify his use of semi-transparent washes to color his illuminated books in the early 1790s. Like several other illuminated books in the British Museum collection, the leaves of Copy A are mounted close to the image in windows cut in thick paper. The inner edges of these mounts appear in some of our reproductions.<lb/><lb/>
            Proof Copy a is an unusual, and probably fragmentary, remnant of Blake's typical proofing of his illuminated prints in black ink (which takes on a brownish hue when thinly printed). This group of just 6 proofs was printed in 1793; they are probably the earliest extant impressions of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>. All but the frontispiece and title page have been trimmed within the platemarks to the designs only. Blake very probably printed the entire plates, to check the progress of his work, and a later owner was responsible for trimming off the texts. Yet, even if reduced after they left Blake's hands, these impressions offer a glimpse into his etching and printing methods.<lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible through the continuing support of the Library of Congress, the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the University of Virginia, by a major grant from the Preservation and Access Division of the National Endowment for the Humanities, by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and by the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2004</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/> This image copyright © 2004 William Blake Archive.
         <lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>This work has been revised to include corrections and improvements to the textual transcriptions and editors' notes (for consistency, accuracy, and visual presentation) that were not reflected in the original XML conversion.</change><date>2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah C. Jones, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Visions of the Daughters of Albion*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination><imprint><publisher>William Blake</publisher><pubplace>London<note>The place of publication is not given in the book, but Blake lived in London during the writing, etching, and printing of this copy.</note></pubplace><date>1793</date></imprint><compdate value="1793.A">1793</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1793.A">1793</printdate><numberobj>6</numberobj><objorder>1-3, 7, 9-10<note>Bentley plate numbers are used here unless noted otherwise.</note></objorder><objsize>16.9 x 11.9 cm. (Plate 1), 16.3 x 12.9 cm. (Plate 2), 8.8 x 10.0 cm. (Plate 3), 7.2 x 11.5 cm. (Plate 7), 6.8 x 11.5 cm. (Plate 9), 4.8 x 11.2 cm. (Plate 10).<note>Plates 3, 7, 9-11 are trimmed to the design only.</note></objsize><numberleaves>6</numberleaves><leafsize>16.9 x 11.9 cm. (Plate 1), 16.3 x 12.9 cm. (Plate 2), 8.8 x 10.0 cm. (Plate 3), 7.2 x 11.5 cm. (Plate 7), 6.8 x 11.5 cm. (Plate 9), 4.8 x 11.2 cm. (Plate 10)</leafsize><medium>relief etching with white-line etching on Plate 2</medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><inkcolor>black<note>The ink takes on a brownish hue where thinly printed.</note></inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>none</watermark><etchednumbers>none</etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>red straight grain morocco</binding><stabholes>none</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress,   
Washington, D. C.</name><date>Acquired by Lessing J. Rosenwald in 1939; given to the
Library of Congress 1945.</date><dealer>A. C. Stonehill in 1939</dealer><price>not recorded</price><note>Perhaps acquired by Thomas Chevalier (1767-1824) and pasted by him or a member of his family in a manuscript book; the manuscript book with Blake's prints sold by Ellen M. Chevalier Dobinson, Sotheby's, 1 Dec. 1910, lot 125 (£3.3s. to the dealer Dobell); acquired before 1921 by W. E. Moss, who removed the Blake plates and had them separately mounted and bound; sold from
               the Moss collection, 2 March 1937, lot 178 (£10 to the dealer A. C. Stonehill); acquired by 1939 by Lessing J. Rosenwald; given by Rosenwald to the Library of Congress in 1945.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Library of Congress</institution><addressline>101 Independence Avenue SE</addressline><addressline>Washington, D.C. 20540-4740</addressline><addressline>USA</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 202-707-5434</addressline><addressline>Fax: 202-707-4142</addressline><addressline>Email: rbsc@loc.gov</addressline><addressline>URL: http://lcweb.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/</addressline><department>Rare Book and Special Collections Division</department><collection>Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">PR4144.V5.1810, Copy 2</repositoryid><repositoryid label="Catalog number">1803</repositoryid><lb/></repository></source><desc id="vda.a-proof.illbk.01" dbi="vda.a.proof.P1" compwith="bb85.B5"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode><objcode code="Ki">Keynes i)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The impression is trimmed along, or slightly within, the platemark.</p></objnote><objsize>16.9 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="879" width="619"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Three nude figures are seen within the mouth of a
cave that opens onto the sea.  The outlines of clouds fill the
sky, but fail to cover the disc of the sun.  The open area where
the sun appears suggests an eye socket, perhaps in a skull
outlined by the cave and seen in left profile.  Indeterminate
vegetation dangles from the roof of the cave.  The figures sit or
kneel on large stones or, in the case of the single female,
perhaps on sand.  On the left is a heavily-muscled and bearded
male seen in left profile.  He sits or squats at the cave's
mouth.  He looks to the left with wide-open eyes; his face is
deeply marked by fear or worse; his hair stands on end.  His
mouth is open and he may be howling.  His knees are drawn up in a
contracted position; his left arm is drawn backwards as though
bound behind him.  A large shackle is attached to his left ankle. 
At least three links of a massive chain descend below his left
hip.  He may be bound back to back with the female directly to
the right.  This pair is probably Oothoon, the central female
figure in the poem, and her tormentor Bromion.  She kneels, with
her body bent down and to the right.  The right-most link of the
chain below Bromion may be attached to Oothoon.  Her face,
probably with eyes closed, is pointed down; her long hair
cascades over her neck and down behind her head.  Above her and
to the right, an extremely contracted figure sits among rocks. 
This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's ineffectual lover.  His
legs appear to be crossed, with the left foot poised
below his heavy knees.  He faces down so that we see only the top
of his head, covered with curly hair.  His arms are wrapped
around his head, with the left arm bent at the elbow and his left
hand, formed into a fist, perhaps clutching his curly hair.  His
right arm descends along the right side of his hidden face and
disappears beneath his left elbow.  The design may illustrate the
following lines on Plate 5: "Bound back to back in Bromions caves
terror &amp; meekness dwell / At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the
threshold hard" (Erdman page 46; plate not in this copy).  Given this textual parallel, the two
figures on the left may be personifications of terror (note the
expression on Bromion's face) and meekness.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The three figures are situated within the mouth of a cave formed of stones and possibly a sandy floor.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see the sea behind and on each side of the figure on the left.  Perhaps some of its waters come near to his feet.  The dark area just above the lower margin of the plate might also be water with small waves.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky, seen above the figures and below the roof of the cave, is filled with the outlines of clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>eye socket</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The round disc of the sun appears through a break in the clouds.  The shape of this opening suggests an eye socket.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Clumps of vegetation of an indeterminate type dangle from the roof of the cave.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>skull</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting for the design—the mouth of a cave—can
be considered a structure with both a roof and a floor.  Given   
the shape of the sun, the opening in the clouds around it, and    
the outline of the cave's mouth, the setting may also suggest a 
skull seen in left profile.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left is a nude, heavily-muscled, and bearded
male seen in left profile.  He sits or squats on the sandy or
stoney surface of a cave's mouth.  He looks to the left with
wide-open eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his
flame-like hair stands on end.  His mouth is open and he may be
howling.  His knees are drawn up in a contracted position; his
left arm is drawing backwards as though bound behind him.  A
large shackle is affixed to his left ankle.  Three links of a massive chain
descend below his left hip.  This is probably Bromion, the
tormentor of the central female figure in the text, Oothoon.  He
                     may also be a personification of terror—see the following lines
on Plate 5: "Bound back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp;
meekness dwell / At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the
threshold hard" (Erdman page 46; plate not in this copy).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>meekness</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>eyes down</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female, seen in right profile, kneels on the
stones or sand of the cave's mouth.  She may be bound back to
back to the male to the left.  This pair is probably Oothoon, the
central female figure in the poem, and her tormentor Bromion. 
Her body is bent down and to the right.  The right-most link of
the chain below Bromion may be attached to Oothoon.  Her face,
perhaps with eyes closed, is pointed down; her long hair cascades
over her neck and down behind her head.  She may also personify
                     meekness—see the following lines on Plate 5: "Bound back to back
in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell / At entrance
Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard" (Erdman page 46; plate not in this copy).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A shackle is affixed to the left ankle of the figure on the left.  At least three links of a massive chain appear below him and the woman to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>fist</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male squats in an extremely contracted
posture among rocks.  This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's 
ineffectual lover.  His legs appear to be crossed, with the left
foot poised below his heavy knees.  He faces forward and down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly hair.
His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm bent at
the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps
clutching his hair.  His right arm descends along the right side
of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left
elbow.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="vda.a-proof.illbk.02" dbi="vda.a.proof.P2"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii, </objcode><objcode code="Kii">Keynes ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.3 x 12.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="848" width="671"/><objnote><p>The impression is cut approximately on the platemarks on the sides and bottom, but is trimmed about 1.0 cm. below the platemark at the top.</p></objnote></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The title page is a seascape, with two storm-tossed
waves in the lower margin, heavy clouds, rain, and at least
eleven human figures.  The angle of the waves suggests a strong
wind blowing from left to right.  A nude female runs toward us
with her right foot touching a trough between waves, lower
center.  She is probably the central female figure in the poem,
Oothoon, who "Over the waves ... went" (Erdman page 46; plate not in this copy).  Her left leg is extended behind her, her arms are raised at 135 degrees, and the
fingers of both hands are separated and extended.  She appears to
look back and up; her long hair streams back and to the right as
though blown by a wind.  She may be looking at the figure
hovering in the air above her, a bearded male who looks directly
at the viewer and may be pursuing Oothoon.  This threatening male
may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or Urizen, the
evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in the text.  We
see only his head and face, shoulders, and arms and hands wrapped
around his shoulders in a contracted posture.  His large wings
extend horizontally.  His face is heavily lined, particularly the
forehead, and his mouth is open.  Flames spring from below his wings and rise above
them.  To the left is a ring of three female figures pictured as
though nude but with the twisted, spiraling hems of gowns
trailing behind them.  They form a circle, as though
participating in an ecstatic dance.  The figure at the bottom of
the circle holds hands with her two companions.  Her arms are
extended horizontally and her legs are spread apart as though she
were striding energetically to the right.  Her head is turned away from the viewer.  The dancer furthest to the left
also has her arms extended horizontally (relative to her body);
her head is tilted back as though she were looking up.  Like her
companion below, a strand of long hair extends from her head. 
The final dancer, top right in the circle, has her arms raised at
135 degrees and has her legs spread.  Her back and neck are
arched backwards and she appears to be looking up.  Above the
ring of dancers, and just left of the first diagonal of the
letter "A" of "Albion" in line 4, is a slender,
nude figure seen from the side with at least one arm extended
downward.  She may be holding a small scepter in her extended
hand.  This figure, probably female, seems to be descending
head-first.  To the left of this figure, near the left margin of
the
plate, is a nude figure, probably female, seen from the side and
sitting on a cloud.  Her left leg, the only one visible, is drawn up towards her head,
which is tilted down and to the left.  Her left arm, which we see
only from the shoulder to the elbow, extends behind her as though
it is propping her up or possibly bound behind her.  To the right
of these two figures, and near the center of the plate, is a
figure, probably female and gowned, sitting on a cloud just above
the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 5. 
She faces to the left and we see only her left side.  Her upper
body and head are bent over at such a sharp angle that they touch
her upper left leg.  In this contracted posture, her long hair
cascades over her left knee.  Higher along the left margin of the
design and left of the first "of" in line 2 are
two figures on a cloud.  Both appear to be nude; at least the one
on the left is probably female.  We see this figure on the left
from behind.  Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm
extending downwards (almost touching the head of the figure
below) and her long hair cascading downwards.  Her right arm is
bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or
balance.  Her companion to the right lies on the cloud, with her
or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted and contracted
posture.  We apparently see only the top of her or his head; the
figure may be looking down.  The left arm is bent at the elbow
with the left hand beneath the head.  To the right, and right of
the first "of" in line 2, is a nude and possibly
bearded male with legs crossed.  He sits on a cloud.  His hair is
long; he faces down and to the right.  He leans to the right,
with arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative to his
body) and extended downward and to the right.  The fingers of
both hands are spread and extended as though he were casting down
the indications of rain lower in the design.  Slightly
below and to the right of the winged figure, the rain appears to
be cascading over cliffs that suggest the shapes of aged figures with shoulders hunched and heads lowered.  An arching line above
and to the left of the ring of dancers extending toward the
figure upper left, and a shorter line below and to the right of
the ring of dancers, indicate what will become a rainbow in
colored versions of the design.  The words of the title are
integrated into the design and seem to float on clouds.  The
motto and imprint appear to float on the sea below the two
waves.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The lower quarter of the plate is dominated by two   
large waves of a storm-tossed sea.  The angle of the waves      
suggests a strong wind blowing from left to right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky—the background for most of the plate—is   
filled with the outlines of clouds.  Their number and billowing   
shapes suggest a storm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>rain</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Diagonal white lines indicate rain.  These lines are
most clearly seen below and to the right of "of" in line 3 and between the left wing of the
hovering figure and the waves below.  The slight angle of these
lines, left to right, suggests a wind blowing left to
right.  The rain may be falling over cliffs below the second "of" in line 3.  Lower on the plate are more cliffs that suggest the forms of aged figures facing forward, with heads lowered and long hair cascading downward between hunched shoulders.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>rainbow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An arching line above and to the left of the ring of
dancers extending toward the figure upper left, and a shorter
line below and to the right of the ring of dancers, indicate what
will become a rainbow in colored versions of the
design.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Tongues of fire rise from beneath the wings of the   
hovering figure and extend above the upper edges of his wings,  
particularly on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female runs toward the viewer, her right foot
touching a trough between two waves.  Her left leg is extended
backwards.  Her arms are raised at an angle of 135 degrees; her
upper body and neck are twisted back and to the right.  She is
probably looking up and back at the winged figured hovering over
her.  The fingers of her upraised hands, with palms facing the
viewer, are spread apart.  Her long hair streams out to the
right, as though blown by a wind.  She is probably Oothoon, the
central figure in the text, who "Over the waves ... went"
(Erdman page 46; plate not in this copy).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>pursuing</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bearded male hovers above the running female.
This male may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or
Urizen, the evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in
the text.  We see only his head and face, shoulders, arms and
hands wrapped around his shoulders in a contracted posture, and
large wings extended horizontally.  He looks out at the viewer.   
His face is heavily lined, particularly the forehead, and his mouth is open.  Flames
spring from below his wings and rise above them.  He may be
pursuing the female figure below him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, the lowest of three females in a
circle, strides energetically to the right.  She appears to be
nude, except that the hem of a gown curls to the left below her
right leg.  She holds hands with the two other women in this
circle of dancers.  Her arms are extended horizontally; she faces
away from the viewer.  A strand of her long hair curls to the
right.  We see her back from behind.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, furthest to the left in a circle of
three female dancers, rises near the left margin of the plate.
She appears to be nude, except that the hem of a gown spirals
below her left hand.  Her right arm is raised vertically but
arches to the right; her left arm descends to hold hands with the
dancer below.  Her back is arched, with her head facing up.  A
strand of her long hair curls below her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, at the top of a circle of three
female dancers, appears to be nude except that the hem of a long
gown spirals between her spread legs and above and below her
torso.  Her back is arched and her arms are raised at an angle of
135 degrees relative to her upper body.  With her left hand she
holds the right hand of the dancer below her.  Her right hand
appears to hold a piece of her gown.  Her head appears to be
thrown back, but neither her face nor her hair is clearly
indicated.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>conracted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Near the left margin of the plate is a nude figure,
probably female, seen from the side and sitting on a cloud.  Her left leg, the only one visible, is drawn up towards her head, which is tilted down and to
the left.  Her left arm, which we see only from the shoulder to
the elbow, extends behind her as though it is propping her up or
possibly bound behind her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the ring of dancers, and just left of the
first diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in line 4, is a slender, nude figure seen from the side with at
least one arm extended downward.  She may be holding a small
object, possibly a scepter, in her extended hand.  This figure,
probably female, seems to be falling head-first.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably female and gowned, sits on a
cloud just above the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 4.  She faces to the left and we see only her left
side.  Her upper body and head are bent over at such a sharp
angle that they touch her upper left leg.  In this contracted
posture, her long hair cascades over her left knee.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see a nude female figure near the left margin
from the back.  Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm
extending downwards (almost touching the head of the figure 
below) and her long hair cascading downwards.  Her right arm is
bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or
balance.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hand under head</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure of indeterminate gender lies on a     
cloud, with her or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted  
and contracted posture.  We apparently see only the top of her or
his head; the figure may be looking down.  The left arm is bent  
at the elbow with the left hand beneath the head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>casting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the first "of" in line 2 is a nude male with legs crossed.
He sits on a cloud.  His hair is long; he faces down and to the
right.  He twists and leans to the right, with arms raised at 45 degrees
(but horizontally relative to his body) and extended downward and
to the right.  The fingers of both hands are spread and extended
as though he were casting down the slight indications of rain
below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>The words of the title are integrated into the       
design and seem to float on clouds.</illusobjdesc><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</l></lg></transcription></component><component type="text" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>The words of the motto and imprint are integrated   
into the design and seem to float on the sea below the two       
waves.</illusobjdesc><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.</l><l justify="left">Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l></lg></transcription></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="vda.a-proof.illbk.02.01" justify="center">VISIONS</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="vda.a-proof.illbk.02.02" justify="center">of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="vda.a-proof.illbk.02.03" justify="center">the Daughters of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="vda.a-proof.illbk.02.04" justify="center">Albion</l></lg><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="vda.a-proof.illbk.02.05" justify="center">The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.</l></lg><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l n="vda.a-proof.illbk.02.06" justify="center">Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.a-proof.illbk.03" dbi="vda.a.proof.P3" compwith="bb136.B20"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3, </objcode><objcode code="Eiii">Erdman iii, </objcode><objcode code="Kiii">Keynes iii)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The impression is trimmed within the platemark to the design only.</p></objnote><objsize>8.8 x 10.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="458" width="520"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to
the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands
over her breasts.  Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun,
yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.  She appears
to be kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female.  This
second nude figure is seen from behind; her arms are extended
horizontally.  Her right foot is poised just above one of the two
flowers, probably marigolds, growing on a plant lower right.  Her
left leg is bent at the knee in a dance-like posture.  She seems
to hover in the air.  The kneeling figure is probably Oothoon,
the smaller figure probably the "nymph" who personifies the
marigold.  As the text on Plate 4 explains, "Oothoon wandered in  
woe, / Along the vales of Leutha seeking flowers to comfort her;  
/ And thus she spoke to the bright Marygold of Leutha's vale /
Art though a flower! art thou a nymph! I see thee now a flower; /
Now a nymph!" (Erdman pages 45-6).  Given this textual point of contact, the 
landscape is Leutha's Vale, also named in the text on this plate.
The hovering nymph may also be identified with Leutha (see 
"Leutha's flower," Erdman page 45).  Four etched shafts of radiance extend into the sky; they would
seem to emanate from a sun just below the horizon on the right
and perhaps in part from the marigold furthest to the right. 
Higher in the sky are slight suggestions of stratus clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to
the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands
over her breasts.  Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun,
yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.  She appears
to be kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female.  Given
the text on this and the next plate in other copies, she is almost certainly
Oothoon.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>nymph</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><characteristic>marigold</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, is seen from behind.  She hovers in the air, with her right foot poised just
above a flower from which she may be rising.  Her arms are
extended horizontally and her left knee bent forward.  This
dance-like posture includes a gracefully twisted torso.  She
appears to be kissing the much larger female on the left.  If so,
then her head may be bent back slightly, although this is more clearly the case in other copies.  Given the textual
parallels for the design, this small figure is probably the
"nymph" who personifies the marigold flower below her (Erdman pages 45-6).
She may also be identified with Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," Erdman page 45).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>marigold</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>petal</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A low-growing plant, perhaps leafless, appears lower
right in the landscape.  Two arching stems terminate in large
                     flowers—probably the marigolds noted in the text on Plate 4 in other copies (Erdman page 45).  Their petals are spiky or flame-like.  These may be    
"Leutha's flower[s]" (Erdman page 45).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><characteristic>valley</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><characteristic>shadow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The kneeling figure is placed on a small mound of earth.  This is probably part of "Leutha's vale"
(Erdman page 45).  The dark area on the ground left of the figure may be a shadow.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four etched lines of radiance extend into the sky. 
Most of the light seems to emanate from a rising or setting sun
just below the horizon on the right, but a one ray may emerge
from the flower also lower right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few horizontal lines in the sky just above the 
figures suggest low clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="vda.a-proof.illbk.04" dbi="vda.a.proof.P4-7" compwith="bb85.B4"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7, </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode><objcode code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The impression is trimmed within the platemark to the design only.</p></objnote><objsize>7.2 x 11.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="374" width="598"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Two figures appear on the seashore.  One figure,
probably male, is seated on the sand or stones near the water.
He wears a long gown that covers all but his head, hands, and
prominent right foot.  We see him from the front; his knees are
drawn up to his upper chest in a very contracted posture.  Given 
the position of his right foot, his legs are probably crossed at
the ankles.  His hands rest upon his knees, and in turn his head
is bent forward and rests upon his hands.  We see only the top of
his head, covered with curly hair.  This is probably Theotormon,
"weeping" (Erdman page 47; plate not in this copy) near "the margind ocean" (Erdman page 51; plate not in this copy).  To the left is
a giant wave, shaped like a tongue of flame.  Within this wave is
a nude female, shackled and chained on her left ankle.  Her right
leg is apparently extended behind her left.  She arches to the
right, with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands clasped
together just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
supplication.  She faces down and apparently looks at the         
self-enclosed male below her.  Her long hair drifts behind her neck
and back.  She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover.
Right and left of the wave in which she appears is a rocky cliff.
Wavy lines along the lower margin of the design below both
figures suggest small waves of the sea.  Far right is the dark sea, showing a few indications of waves.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>head on knees</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, is seated on the sand or
stones near the water.  He wears a long gown that covers all but
his head, hands, and prominent right foot.  We see him from the
front; his knees are drawn up to his upper chest in a very
contracted posture.  Given the position of his right foot, his
legs are probably crossed at the ankles.  His hands rest upon his
knees, and in turn his head is bent forward and rests upon his
hands.  We see only the top of his head, covered with curly hair.
This is probably Theotormon, "weeping" (Erdman page 47; plate not in this copy) near "the margind ocean" (Erdman page 51; plate not in this copy).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Within a tongue- or flame-like wave is a nude
female, shackled and chained on her left ankle.  Her right leg is
apparently extended behind her left.  She arches to the right,
with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands clasped together
just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
supplication.  She faces down and apparently looks at the
self-enclosed male below her.  Her long hair drifts behind her neck
and back.  She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover
Theotormon.  Although her mouth is not clearly open, she may be
speaking.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The left foot of the female figure is shackled and chained.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>seashore</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The landscape shows a cliff on the left near the 
seashore.  Both stones and sand may be represented below the   
seated figure.  The lower margin of the design has wavy lines
indicating small waves of the sea.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dark waters of the sea on the right show very slight indications of waves.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The female is pictured within a giant wave of dark water which, in its shape, resembles a tongue—of a creature or of              
fire.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="vda.a-proof.illbk.05" dbi="vda.a.proof.P5-9"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B9">(Bentley 9, </objcode><objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes 6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The impression is trimmed within the platemark to the design only.</p></objnote><objsize>6.8 x 11.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="350"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on what is clearly a cloud in other copies (although it could be seen as a rocky landscape in this copy) and holds a whip with
three tails in his left hand.  His left upper arm is raised
vertically, with his forearm bent to the left over his head.  His
right arm is raised and arches over his head; he clutches his 
forehead with his right hand.  His left leg is extended, his
right bent at the knee.  Both his facial features and his         
head-clutching gesture suggest despair.  To the right is a female
nude.  She strides, legs spread apart, forward and to the right.
Her arms are bent, with her hands clutching her face and head.
She is facing down and we see only the top of her head.  Her long
hair trails over her right shoulder.  She too may be supported by
the cloud(?) on which the male sits, although perhaps we are meant
to think of her as hovering in the air.  The female is very probably Oothoon;
the male may be Bromion, in his character as a slave owner, about
to strike the woman.  Alternatively, he may be Theotormon as a
self-flagellant.  No such scene is described in the
text.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>whipping</characteristic><characteristic>slave owner</characteristic><characteristic>self-flagellant</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a cloud(?) and holds a whip
with three tails in his left hand.  His left upper arm is raised
vertically, with his forearm bent to the left over his head.  His
right arm is raised and arches over his head; he clutches his
forehead with his right hand.  His left leg is extended, his
right bent at the knee.  His body faces forward but his head is turned to the right.  His hair
is short and perhaps a little curly.  Both his facial features
and his head-clutching gesture suggest despair.  He may be
Bromion, in his character as a slave owner, about to strike the
woman on the right.  Alternatively, he may be Theotormon as a
self-flagellant.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female strides, legs spread apart, forward  
and to the right.  Her arms are bent, with her hands clutching
her face and head.  She is facing down and we see only the top of
her head.  Her long hair trails over her right shoulder.
She may be supported by the cloud(?) below her left foot, although
perhaps we are meant to think of her as hovering in the air.  She
is very probably Oothoon in despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>whip</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><characteristic>knot</characteristic><characteristic>spike</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male holds a whip with three snake-like tails.
Each tail appears to terminate in a knot or cluster of           
spikes.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>hill</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male sits on what is clearly a cloud in other copies, although the lines in this copy could be interpreted as the outline of a rocky landscape with a small hill behind the figure on the left.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc><desc id="vda.a-proof.illbk.06" dbi="vda.a.proof.P6-10" compwith="bb136.B17"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B10">(Bentley 10, </objcode><objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes 7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objnote><p>The impression is trimmed within the platemark to the design only.</p></objnote><objsize>4.8 x 11.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize width="550" height="300"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Four (possibly five) female figures huddle together
in contracted postures.  The three foreground figures wear gowns; the large background figure in the center of the composition is probably also gowned, as indicated by lines at her wrists that would appear to represent cuffs.
The figure on the right squats with knees drawn up toward her
chest; her head leans forward onto her knees and we see only the
top of her head.  Her hair is long.  The figure in the center
foreground faces to the right, with her knees drawn up and her
upper body leaning forward.  Her right knee and lower leg cover
her face; we see only her head and long hair.  Above this central
figure and slightly behind are the shoulders and face of a woman
with long hair (spread out on both sides of her head) and a
desperate expression on her face.  Her hands are raised to her
shoulders with palms turned upward.  Her eyes look up.  The
left-most figure faces left.  Her upper body is bent over her legs
in a severely contracted posture.  Her head is on the far left,
bent low over her extended left arm.  Above this figure is an 
indeterminate cluster of wavy lines that may be the right shoulder and hair of a
fifth female figure.  These females are probably the Daughters of
Albion.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female in a very contracted posture squats
on the ground.  Her large knees are drawn up to her chest; her
head is bent forward and rests on her knees.  We see only the top
of her head and long hair.  She is probably one of the
Daughters of Albion in this huddled group of four or five
females.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female sits in a contracted posture as the
front-most figure in the huddled group.  She faces to the right,
with her right knee drawn up and her upper body bent forward.    
Her face is covered by her right knee and lower leg; we see only
her head and long, dark hair.  She is probably one of the    
Daughters of Albion in this group of four or five             
figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind two other figures, we see the shoulders,
hands, and face of a female.  Like three of her companions, she is probably also gowned, for lines at her wrists would appear to represent cuffs.  Her long hair extends 
horizontally on either side of her head.  Her face and eyes are
turned upward; her facial expression suggests despair.  Her hands
are raised to her shoulders, palms turned upward.  She is
probably one of the Daughters of Albion, sitting with others in
this huddled group.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the far left of the huddle group of figures is a
gowned female with her upper body bent over her legs in an
extremely contracted posture.  She faces to the left, with her   
head bent down and resting on her left arm.  Her left arm and hand dangle to the left.  Her hair is probably
long, as indicated by the lines resting on her back.  She is probably one of the Daughters of
Albion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few wavy lines, just above the left-most figure in
this huddled group of figures, may be the lowered head, curly(?)
hair, and right shoulder of a fifth female.  She is probably one of
the Daughters of Albion, like the others in this
group.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc></desc></objdesc></bad>