<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2006-10-16T20:01:18-05:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="vda.o" type="illbk" work="Visions of the Daughters of Albion" copy="O" copyid="O" institution="britishmuseum" catalog="bentley" catid="O"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Visions of the Daughters of Albion"><main>Visions of the Daughters of Albion</main><copy> Copy O</copy>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;  
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah C. Jones, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the Library of Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software grants from Sun Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 135KB; 22 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files
ranging in size from 10KB to 635KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH<date>December 2006</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
   The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, Copies B and O, both in the British Museum. Like all the illuminated books in the Archive, both the texts and images of these new publications are fully searchable and are supported by our Inote and ImageSizer applications.<lb/><lb/>
   Copy B was produced in Blake's first printing session for <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> in 1793 and joins Copies A, C, and J, also from this session and previously published in the Archive. Probably to lend variety to his stock of copies on hand, Blake used three ink colors in this first printing: yellow ochre (as in Copy A), raw sienna (Copies B and C), and green (Copy J). As is characteristic of illuminated books produced in the early 1790s, these copies were printed on both sides of the leaves and finished in semi-transparent washes. As with several other illuminated books in the British Museum collection, the leaves of Copy B are mounted close to the image in windows cut in thick paper. The inner edges of these mounts appear in some of our reproductions.<lb/><lb/><hi rend="i">Visions</hi> Copy O is the sister copy of Copy P, also in the Archive. Both are printed in red-orange ink on one side of RUSE &amp; TURNERS/1815 paper and finished in watercolors and pen and ink. Each impression is numbered in the top right corner and bordered by one thin line drawn in red-orange ink a little over a centimeter around the image, setting off each page like a miniature painting.<lb/><lb/>
   As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible through the continuing support of the Library of Congress, the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the University of Virginia, the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and by the cooperation of the international array of libraries, museums, and private collectors that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.
</updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>2006</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>This image copyright © 2006 British Museum.<lb/><lb/></userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2005</change><date>2006</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah C. Jones, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley </name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title>*Visions of the Daughters of Albion*</title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination><imprint><publisher>William Blake</publisher><pubplace>London<note>The place of publication is not given in
the book, but Blake lived in London during the writing, etching,
and printing of this copy.</note></pubplace><date>1793</date></imprint><compdate value="1793">1793</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1818.B">c. 1818</printdate><numberobj>11</numberobj><objorder>1-11</objorder><objsize>ranging between 17.2 x 12.9 cm. and 14.2 x 11.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>11</numberleaves><leafsize>28.0 x 22.0 cm.</leafsize><medium>relief etching with white-line etching on Plate 2</medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><inkcolor>orange</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>Ruse &amp; Turners 1815<note>The watermark appears only on the leaf bearing Plate 1, the frontispiece.</note></watermark><etchednumbers><note>Numbered 2-3, 5-7 upper right on Plates 5-6,
8-10.  In this copy, the number (2) on Plate 5 is partly covered with a vine or branch; the top half of the number (3) on Plate 6 is partly obscured by coloring; the number (5) on Plate 8 is very lightly printed; the number (6) on Plate 9 is very lightly printed and barely visible; the number (7) on Plate 10 is covered with washes.  Bentley plate numbers are used here unless noted otherwise.</note></etchednumbers><pennednumbers>1-11<note>The inscribed number in orange ink appears top right within the framing line on each plate.</note></pennednumbers><framelines>1</framelines><binding>red morocco<note>The plates are mounted in windows cut in heavy paper.  The present binding was created in 1969.</note></binding><stabholes>two holes, 14.0 cm. from the top and 4.8 cm. apart<note>A third stab hole, at the top, may have been trimmed off during rebinding.</note></stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>British Museum, Department of Prints and Drawings</name><date>1940</date><dealer>bequest</dealer><price>bequest</price><note>Acquired, probably directly from Blake (as stated in a note on the third front-flyleaf), by Henry Crabb Robinson; given by Robinson to Edwin Wilkins Field, 2 June 1865 (according to the flyleaf note); apparently inherited by a relative of Field's, recorded as "Miss Field" by Bentley, who presented it to the Red Cross for a charity auction at Christie's, 26 April 1916, lot 2009 (£210 to Alice G. E. Carthew); bequeathed by Carthew to the British Museum, which accessioned the volume on 13 July 1940.</note></provenance><repository><institution>British Museum</institution><addressline>Great Russell Street</addressline><addressline>London WC1B 3DG</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 44-2076-361555</addressline><addressline>URL: http://www.thebritishmuseum.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Department of Prints and Drawings</department><collection>none</collection><repositoryid label="Accession number">1940.7.13.27(1-12)</repositoryid><repositoryid label="Catalog number">none</repositoryid><lb/></repository></source><desc id="vda.o.illbk.01" dbi="vda.O.P1" compwith="bb85.B5"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode><objcode code="Ki">Keynes i)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="889" width="619"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Three nude figures are seen within the mouth of a
cave that opens onto the sea.  Dark, heavy clouds fill the sky, but
fail to cover the disc of the sun.  The open area where the sun
appears particularly suggests an eye socket, perhaps in a skull outlined by
the cave and seen in left profile.  Indeterminate vegetation
dangles from the roof of the cave, and yellow-green coloring suggests lichens.  The figures sit or kneel on large stones, also perhaps covered with lichens, or, in the case of the single female, perhaps on sand.  On the left is a heavily-muscled and bearded male seen in left profile.  He sits or squats at the cave's mouth.  He looks to the left with wide-open eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his hair stands on end.  His mouth is open and he
may be howling.  His knees are drawn up in a contracted position;
his left arm is drawing backwards as though bound behind him.  Large shackles are attached to both his ankles.  At least three links of a massive chain descend below his left hip.  He may be
bound back to back with the female directly to the right.  This
pair is probably Oothoon, the central female figure in the poem,
and her tormentor Bromion.  She kneels, with her body bent down
and to the right.  The right-most link of the chain below Bromion
may be attached to Oothoon; her long hair cascades over her neck and down behind her head.  Above her and to the right, an extremely contracted figure sits among rocks.  This is probably Theotormon,
Oothoon's ineffectual lover.  His legs appear to be crossed, with
the left foot prominently poised below his heavy knees.  He faces
down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly
hair.  His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm 
bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps
clutching his curly hair.  His right arm descends along the right
side of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left elbow. 
The design may illustrate the following lines on Plate 5: "Bound
back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell / At     
entrance Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard" (lines 7-8).  Given this textual parallel, the two figures on the left may be
personifications of terror (note the expression on Bromion's   
face) and meekness.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The three figures are situated within the mouth of a
cave formed of stones and possibly a sandy floor.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see the waves of the sea behind and on each side of the figure
on the left.  Perhaps some of its waters come near to his feet.  More waves, perhaps an arm of the sea, fill the lower margin below the rocks and sand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky, seen above the figures and below the roof
of the cave, is almost completely filled with dark, heavy clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>eye socket</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The round disc of the sun, with radiating beams of light, appears through a break in
the clouds.  The shape of this opening suggests an eye socket.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><characteristic>lichens</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Clumps of vegetation of an indeterminate type dangle
from the roof of the cave.  Yellow-green coloring on the cave's mouth and the stones below suggests lichens.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>skull</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting for the design—the mouth of a cave—can be considered a structure with both a roof and a floor.  Given the shape of the sun, the opening in the clouds around it, and the outline of the cave's mouth, the setting may also suggest a skull seen in left profile.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left is a nude, heavily-muscled, and bearded male seen in left profile.  He sits or squats on the surface of a cave's mouth.  He looks to the left with wide-open eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his flame-like hair stands on end.  His mouth is open and he may be howling.  His knees are drawn up in a contracted position; his left arm is drawing backwards as though bound behind him.  Large shackles are affixed to his ankles.  Three links of a massive chain descend below his left hip.  This is probably Bromion, the tormentor of the central female figure in the text, Oothoon.  He
                     may also be a personification of terror—see the following lines
on Plate 5: "Bound back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell / At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard" (lines 7-8). </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>meekness</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female, seen in right profile, kneels on the stones or sand of the cave's mouth.  She may be bound back to back to the male to the left.  This pair is probably Oothoon, the
central female figure in the poem, and her tormentor Bromion.  Her body is bent down and to the right.  The right-most link of the chain below Bromion may be attached to Oothoon.  Her face is pointed down; her long hair cascades over her neck and down behind her head.  She may also personify
                     meekness—see the following lines on Plate 5: "Bound back to back
in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell / At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard" (lines 7-8).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Both ankles of the figure on the left bear shackles, with heavy links of a chain below.  The link on the right may be attached to the female figure to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>fist</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male squats in an extremely contracted posture among rocks.  This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's ineffectual lover.  His legs appear to be crossed, with the left foot prominently poised below his heavy knees.  He faces forward and down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly hair.  His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps clutching his hair.  His right arm descends along the right side
of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left elbow.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.01.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">1</physnumber></l></texthead></phystext><!--[Full-page design]--></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.02" dbi="vda.O.P2"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii, </objcode><objcode code="Kii">Keynes ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.3 x 12.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="848" width="671"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The title page is a seascape, with two storm-tossed
waves in the lower margin, heavy clouds, rain, and at least
eleven human figures.  The angle of the waves suggests a strong
wind blowing from left to right.  A nude female runs toward us
with her right foot touching a trough between waves, lower
center.  She is probably the central female figure in the poem,
Oothoon, who "Over the waves ... went" (Plate 4, line 17).  Her left leg is
extended behind her, her arms are raised at 135 degrees, and the
fingers of both hands are separated and extended.  She appears to
look back and up; her long hair streams back and to the right as
though blown by a wind.  She may be looking at the figure         
hovering in the air above her, a bearded male who looks directly  
at the viewer and may be pursuing Oothoon.  This threatening male
may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or Urizen, the
evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in the text.  We
see only his head and face, shoulders, and arms and hands wrapped
around his shoulders in a contracted posture.  His large wings
extend horizontally.  His face is heavily lined, particularly the
forehead, and his mouth may be open.  Flames spring from below his wings and rise above
them.  To the left is a ring of three female figures pictured as
though nude but with the twisted, spiraling hems of gowns trailing behind them.  They form a circle, as though participating in an ecstatic dance.  The figure at the bottom of
the circle holds (or at least touches) hands with her two companions.  Her arms are extended horizontally and her legs are spread apart as though she
were striding energetically to the right.  Her head probably
faces away from the viewer.  The dancer furthest to the left
also has her arms extended horizontally (relative to her body);
her head is tilted back as though she were looking up.  Like her
companion below, a strand of long hair extends from her head.  The final dancer, top right in the circle, has her arms raised at
135 degrees and has her legs spread.  Her back and neck are arched backwards and she appears to be looking up.  Above the ring of dancers, and just left of the first diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in line 5, is a slender, 
nude figure seen from the side with at least one arm extended downward.  She may be holding a small scepter in her extended hand.  This figure, probably female, seems to be descending head-first.  To the left of this figure, near the left margin of the plate, is a nude figure, probably female, seen from the side and sitting on a cloud.  Her left leg, the only one visible, is drawn up towards her head, which is tilted down and to the left.  Her left arm, which we see
only from the shoulder to the elbow, extends behind her as though
it is propping her up or possibly bound behind her.  To the right
of these two figures, and near the center of the plate, is a figure, probably female and possibly gowned, sitting on a cloud just above
the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 5.  She faces to the left and we see only her left side.  Her upper
body and head are bent over at such a sharp angle that they touch
her upper left leg.  In this contracted posture, her long hair cascades over her left knee.  Higher along the left margin of the design and left of the word "of" in line 2 are two figures on a cloud.  Both figures appear to be nude; at least the one on the left is probably female.  We see this figure on the left from behind.  Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm extending downwards (almost touching the head of the figure below) and her long hair cascading downwards.  Her right arm is bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or balance.  Her companion to the right lies on the cloud, with her or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted and contracted posture.  We apparently see only the top of her or his head; the
figure may be looking down.  The left arm is bent at the elbow with the left hand beneath the head.  To the right, and right of the word "of" in line 3, is a nude male with legs crossed.  He sits on a cloud.  His hair is
long; he faces down and to the right.  He twists and leans to the right, with arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative to his body) and extended downward and to the right.  The fingers of
both hands are spread and extended as though he were casting down
the indications of rain lower in the design.  Slightly below and to the right of the winged figure, the rain appears to
be cascading over cliffs that suggest the shapes of aged figures with shoulders hunched and heads lowered.  A rainbow arches dramatically from lower left, through the ring of dancers, and ends below the figure with crossed legs upper right.  The words of the title are integrated into the design and seem to float on clouds.  The motto and imprint appear to float on the sea below
the two waves.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The lower quarter of the plate is dominated by two large waves of a storm-tossed sea.  The angle of the waves suggests a strong wind blowing from left to right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky—the background for most of the plate—is filled with the outlines of clouds.  Their number and billowing shapes suggest a storm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>rain</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Diagonal streaks of wash set against a darker background of washes apparently indicate rain.  These lines are most clearly seen below "of" in line 4 and between the left wing of the hovering figure and the waves below.  The slight angle of these lines, left to right, suggests a wind blowing left to right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>rainbow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A rainbow arches from the lower left margin towards the upper right margin, running through the ring of dancers and the third and fourth lines of the title inscription.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Tongues of fire rise from beneath the wings of the hovering figure and extend above the upper edges of his wings, particularly on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders hunched</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>arms reaching down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The cliffs over which the rain cascades are shaped like old men with long hair standing with their shoulders hunched
and their heads lowered.  The figure (if it is a figure) on the left may have his arms reaching down.  Both figures appear to have long hair cascading downwards.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms out</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female runs toward the viewer, her right foot touching a trough between two waves.  Her left leg is extended backwards.  Her arms are raised at an angle of 135 degrees; her upper body and neck are twisted back and to the right.  She is probably looking up and back at the winged figured hovering over her.  The fingers of her upraised hands, with palms facing the viewer, are spread apart.  Her long hair streams out to the right, as though blown by a wind.  She is probably Oothoon, the central figure in the text, who "Over the waves ... went" (Plate 4, line 17).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>pursuing</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bearded male hovers above the running female.  This male may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or Urizen, the evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in the text.  We see only his head and face, shoulders, arms and hands wrapped around his shoulders in a contracted posture, and large wings extended horizontally.  He looks out at the viewer.  
His face is heavily lined, particularly the forehead, and his mouth may be open.  Flames spring from below his wings and rise above them.  He may be pursuing the female figure below him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, the lowest of three females in a circle, strides energetically to the right.  She appears to be nude, except that the hem of a gown curls to the left below her right leg.  She holds (or at least touches) hands with the two other women in this circle of dancers.  Her arms are extended horizontally; she faces
away from the viewer and to the right.  A strand of her long hair curls to the right.  We see her back from behind.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>touching</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, furthest to the left in a circle of
three female dancers, rises near the left margin of the plate.  She appears to be nude, except that the hem of a gown spirals below her left hand.  Her right arm is raised vertically but arches to the right; her left arm descends, and she may touch the hand of the figure below.  Her back is arched, with her head facing up.  A strand of her long hair curls below her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>bending backward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, at the top of a circle of three female dancers, appears to be nude except that the hem of a long gown or cloak spirals between her spread legs and above and below her torso.  Her back is arched and her arms are raised at an angle of 135 degrees relative to her upper body.  With her left hand she holds the right hand of the dancer below her.  Her right hand appears to hold a piece of her gown.  Her head appears to be thrown back, but neither her face nor her hair is clearly indicated.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>conracted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Near the left margin of the plate is a nude figure, probably female, seen from the side and sitting on a cloud.  Her left leg, the only one visible, is drawn up towards her head, which is tilted down and to the left.  Her left arm, which we see only from the shoulder to the elbow, extends behind her as though it is propping her up or possibly bound behind her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the ring of dancers, and just left of the first diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in line 5, is a slender, nude figure seen from the side with at least one arm extended downward.  She may be holding a small object, possibly a scepter, in her extended hand.  This figure, probably female, seems to be falling head-first.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>hunched over</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably female and possibly gowned, sits on a cloud just above the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 5.  She faces to the left and we see only her left side.  Her upper body and head are bent over at such a sharp angle that they touch her upper left leg.  In this contracted posture, her long hair cascades over her left knee.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see a nude female figure near the left margin from behind.  Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm extending downwards (almost touching the head of the figure below) and her long hair cascading downwards.  Her right arm is bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or balance.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hand under head</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure of indeterminate gender lies on a cloud, with her or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted and contracted posture.  We apparently see only the top of her or his head; the figure may be looking down.  The left arm is bent at the elbow with the left hand beneath the head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>casting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the word "of" in line 3 is a nude male with legs crossed.  He sits on a cloud.  His hair is long; he faces down and to the right.  He twists and leans to the right, with arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative to his body) and extended downward and to the right.  The fingers of both hands are spread and extended as though he were casting down the slight indications of rain below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>The words of the title are integrated into the design and seem to float on clouds.</illusobjdesc><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</l></lg></transcription></component><component type="text" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>The words of the motto and imprint are integrated into the design and seem to float on the sea below the two waves.</illusobjdesc><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.</l><l justify="left"> Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l></lg></transcription></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.01" justify="right"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">2</physnumber><space extent="15"/></l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.02" justify="center">VISIONS</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.03" justify="center">of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.04" justify="center">the Daughters of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.05" justify="center">Albion</l></lg><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.06" justify="center">The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.02.07" justify="center">Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.03" dbi="vda.O.P3" compwith="bb136.B20"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">The Argument</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3, </objcode><objcode code="Eiii">Erdman iii, </objcode><objcode code="Kiii">Keynes iii)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>14.2 x 11.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="738" width="582"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands over her breasts.  Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun, yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.  She appears to be kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female.  This second nude figure is seen from behind; her arms are extended horizontally.  Her right foot is poised just above one of the two flowers, probably marigolds, growing on a plant lower right.  Her left leg is bent at the knee in a dance-like posture.  She seems to hover in the air.  The kneeling figure is probably Oothoon, the smaller figure probably the "nymph" who personifies the
marigold.  As the text on Plate 4 explains, "Oothoon wandered in woe, / Along the vales of Leutha seeking flowers to comfort her; / And thus she spoke to the bright Marygold of Leutha's vale / Art though a flower! art thou a nymph! I see thee now a flower; / Now a nymph!" (lines 5-9).  Given this textual point of contact, the landscape is Leutha's Vale, also named in the text on this plate.  The hovering nymph may also be identified with Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," Plate 3, line 7).  The mound on which the figure kneels is colored as though covered with grass.  Shafts of radiance and complementary washes fill the sky; they would seem to emanate from a sun just below the horizon on the right and perhaps in part from the marigold furthest to the right.  The coloring of the cloudy sky suggests sunrise or sunset.  Semi-circular bands of color above Oothoon suggest a rainbow.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands over her breasts.  Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun, yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.  She appears to be kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female.  Given the text on this and the next plate, she is almost certainly Oothoon.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>nymph</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><characteristic>marigold</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure with short and curly hair, probably female, is seen from the back.  She hovers in the air, with her right foot poised just above a flower from which she may be rising.  Her arms are extended horizontally and her left knee bent forward.  This dance-like posture includes a gracefully twisted torso.  She appears to be kissing the much larger female on the left.  If so, then her head may be bent back so that she is looking up.  Given the textual parallels for the design, this small figure is probably the "nymph" who personifies the marigold flower below her (Plate 4, line 8).  She may also be identified with Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," Plate 3, line 7).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>marigold</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>petal</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A low-growing plant, perhaps leafless, appears lower right in the landscape.  Two arching stems terminate in large flowers—probably the marigolds noted in the text on Plate 4 (line 7).  Their petals are spiky or flame-like.  These may be "Leutha's flower[s]" (Plate 3, line 7).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><characteristic>valley</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The mound on which the figure kneels is colored as though covered with grass.  This is probably part of "Leutha's vale" (line 6).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>clouds</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Lines of radiance and complementary washes, colored to suggest sunrise or sunset, fill the sky.  Some of the washes, above and to the right of Oothoon, suggest clouds.  Most of the light seems to emanate from a rising or setting sun just below the horizon on the right, but one ray may emerge from the flower also lower right.  Horizontal etched lines above the figures head suggest stratus clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>rainbow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Semi-circular bands of color above Oothoon suggest a rainbow.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.01" justify="left" indent="40"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">3</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.02" justify="left" indent="3">The Argument</l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.03" justify="left" indent="1">I loved Theotormon</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.04" justify="left">And I was not ashamed</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.05" justify="left" indent="1">I trembled in my virgin fears</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.06" justify="left">And I hid in Leutha's vale!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.07" justify="left" indent="1">I plucked Leutha's flower,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.08" justify="left">And I rose up from the vale;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.09" justify="left" indent="2">But the terrible thunders tore</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.03.10" justify="left" indent="2">My virgin mantle in twain.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.04" dbi="vda.O.P4"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Visions</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 4, </objcode><objcode code="E1">Erdman 1, </objcode><objcode code="K1">Keynes 1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.0 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="884" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Five figures sport in the sky surrounding the letters of the heading ("Visions," line 2).  Top left, a nude(?) figure, probably female, sits on top of the first diagonal of the letter "V."  She faces left, with her left knee bent and her right leg extended below her.  She holds in her left hand and to her mouth a curled horn; she is very probably playing this musical instrument.  To the right, just above the first "i," is a billowing cloud with a long trailing edge.  On it sits a long-haired, gowned figure who is probably female.  She sits on the cloud sidesaddle, as though it were a horse.  Her legs are crossed and her head rests on her left hand—a posture traditionally associated with melancholy.  Further to the right are two energetic male nudes.  Both hover in the air with their legs extended and their bodies twisted.  The male above the letters "o" and "n" draws his bow, held in his right hand with the bowstring pulled back by his left hand.  The arrow, pointed down and to the left, has not yet been released.  His companion to the right holds his bow below him in his right hand.  Neither a bowstring nor an arrow are pictured; perhaps he has just released the latter.  His left arm is bent and appears to reach behind his head; perhaps he is reaching for another arrow (not pictured).  Below the final letter of the heading is a hovering figure, very probably female.  The long hem of her gown trails off to the top right in several snake-like curves.  She faces to the left, with at least one arm extended horizontally.  She may be holding something in her left hand; a few vertical lines indicate that some liquid is falling from her hand or what she holds.  Dark blue washes above the text, and yellow and rose washes behind the text, suggest sky at sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude(?) figure, probably female, sits on top of the first diagonal of the letter "V" in the heading ("Visions," line 2).  She
faces left, with her left knee bent and her right leg extended
below her.  She holds in her left hand and to her mouth a curled
horn or trumpet; she is very probably playing this musical instrument.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A long-haired, gowned figure, probably female, sits on a cloud above the letter "i" in the heading ("Visions," line 2).  Her crossed legs dangle on one side of the cloud as though she were riding it sidesaddle.  Her head rests in her left hand in a posture traditionally representative of melancholy.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shooting</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>arm extended</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male hovers above the letter "n" in the heading ("Visions," line 2).  One leg (the right?) is extended down and to the left; his body is twisted as he draws the string of his bow
next to his face with his left arm.  He holds the bow with his extended right arm.  He appears to be about to shoot the arrow clearly visible below and to the left of his right hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>shooting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male hovers above the final "s" in the heading ("Visions," line 2).  Like his companion to the left, he seems to
be shooting arrows, although none is pictured.  One leg (the
right?) is extended down and to the left.  His body is twisted,
with his left arm bent at the elbow and perhaps reaching behind him
for another arrow.  He holds his bow in his extended right hand. 
He appears to be facing down and to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>vial</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below the final letter of the heading ("Visions," line 2) is
a hovering figure, very probably female.  The long hem of her gown trails off to the top right in several snake-like curves.  She faces to the left, with at least one arm extended horizontally.  She may be holding something in her left hand, perhaps a vial; a few vertical lines indicate that some liquid is
falling from her hand or what she holds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure above the first "i" in line 2 sits on a long, billowing cloud.  Its upper right extension looks like
a tail.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Dark blue washes above the text, and yellow and rose washes behind the text, suggest sky at sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="plate" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>Two nude figures sprawl in a rocky landscape.  The left-most figure appears to be female.  She lies on her back with her body twisted.  Her head is turned downwards and her arms
extended horizontally.  On the right is a muscular male, also lying on his back, with knees bent, and his right arm extended horizontally.  One knee is raised, the other turned to the left.  His barely-visible head leans backwards.  Both figures may be exhausted or dead.  These figures may be Oothoon and Bromion after the latter has raped Oothoon.  The figures may rest on rocks, while the foreground is colored to suggest grass.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>exhausted</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, lies supine with her long hair spread out on the ground.  Her body is twisted, with her head turned back and downwards.  Her arms are extended horizontally.  Her right leg is extended and
bent at the knee.  This posture suggests a dead body or perhaps
Oothoon exhausted after being raped by Bromion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>exhausted</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A muscular nude male lies supine.  His right arm is
extended horizontally and his barely-visible head twisted
backward.  His legs are bent at the knees; the left leg is lifted
vertically and his right leg turned down and to the left.  This
                     posture suggests that the figure is dead—or perhaps Bromion
exhausted after he has raped Oothoon.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The two figures may lie on stones.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The foreground is colored to suggest grass.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="AC"><illusobjdesc>Two vines extend upward from the beginning of line 4.  The lower vine arches to the
right.  Branches extending from the left margin, opposite lines 9-10, may indicate a tree growing up the margin or a vine descending along the upper left margin.  Vines, perhaps with leaves, extend into the left
margin from lines 8 and 12.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two vines extend upward from the beginning of line 4.  The lower vine arches to the
right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Branches extending from the left margin, opposite lines 9-10, may indicate a tree growing up the margin or a vine descending along the upper left margin.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Vines, perhaps with leaves, extend into the left
margin from lines 8 and 12.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="65"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">4</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="20">Visions</l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.03" justify="left" indent="1">Enslav'd, the Daughters of Albion weep; a trembling lamentation</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.04" justify="left" indent="1">Upon their mountains; in their valleys, sighs toward America.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.05" justify="left">For the soft soul of America, Oothoon wanderd in woe,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.06" justify="left">Along the vales of Leutha seeking flowers to comfort her;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.07" justify="left">And thus she spoke to the bright Marygold of Leutha's vale</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.08" justify="left" indent="8">Art thou a flower! art thou a nymph! I see thee now a flower;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.09" justify="left" indent="8">Now a nymph! I dare not pluck thee from thy dewy bed!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.10" justify="left" indent="60">(mild
               </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.11" justify="left" indent="10">The Golden nymph replied; pluck thou my flower Oothoon the</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.12" justify="left" indent="10">Another flower shall spring. because the soul of sweet delight</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.13" justify="left" indent="10">Can never pass away, she ceas'd &amp; closd her golden shrine.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.14" justify="left">Then Oothoon pluck'd the flower saying, I pluck thee from thy bed </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.15" justify="left">Sweet flower. and put thee here to glow between my breasts</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.16" justify="left">And thus I turn my face to where my whole soul seeks.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.17" justify="left">Over the waves she went in wing'd exulting swift delight;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.18" justify="left">And over Theotormons reign, took her impetuous course.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.19" justify="left">Bromion rent her with his thunders, on his stormy bed</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.20" justify="left">Lay the faint maid, and soon her woes appalld his thunders hoarse</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.21" justify="left">Bromion spoke, behold this harlot here on Bromions bed,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.22" justify="left">And let the jealous dolphins sport around the lovely maid;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.23" justify="left">Thy soft American plains are mine, and mine thy north &amp; south:<note>In Copy O, in the second half of the line, the "n" in "mine" printed poorly.</note></l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.24" justify="left">Stampt with my signet are the swarthy children of the sun:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.25" justify="left">They are obedient, they resist not, they obey the scourge:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.04.26" justify="left">Their daughters worship terrors and obey the violent;</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.05" dbi="vda.O.P5"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 5, </objcode><objcode code="E2">Erdman 2, </objcode><objcode code="K2">Keynes 2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.1 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="889" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A male nude with curly hair lies prone on the ground.  He faces
down, with his right arm extended to the left and bent at the
elbow.  His right hand is on the ground, as though to support
himself.  He may be trying to rise.  His left arm, also bent at the
elbow, extends below his head.  One leg is extended to
the right, the other bent at the knee.  Given his dark coloring, he may be an African slave
(see "slaves beneath the sun," line 11).  Right of the figure is a
leafless tree, bent over to the right.  A pickax rests against
the trunk of the tree.  A vine with a few ivy-like leaves extends
horizontally to the left from the trunk of the tree near the
pickax and toward the figure.  Another vine with leaves extends
vertically over the trunk of the tree right of the
pickax.  Slight green washes at the tree's base and yellow-green washes below the figure and right of the tree in the left margin suggest grass.  A limb or root of the tree on the left extends along a small cliff toward the figure.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>African</characteristic><characteristic>slave</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male nude with curly hair lies in a twisted but basically prone posture on the ground.  He faces
down, with his right arm extended to the left and bent at the
elbow.  His right hand is on the ground, as though to support
him.  He may be trying to rise.  His left arm, also bent at the
elbow, extends below his head.  One leg is extended to
the right, the other bent at the knee.  Given his dark coloring, he may be an African slave (see "slaves beneath the sun," line 11).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="E"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>root</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tree leans sharply to the right.  Its branches,
far right, are leafless; it may be dead.  Another tree grows up the left margin.  Slight green washes at the tree's base and yellow-green washes below the figure and right of the tree in the left margin suggest grass.  A limb or root of the tree on the left extends along a small cliff toward the figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AC"><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ground left of the figure falls off precipitously to form a small cliff.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine grows horizontally from the trunk of the tree
and extends to the left.  A few ivy-like leaves appear near its
left end.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with a few leaves extends vertically across
the trunk of the tree right of the pickax.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>pickax</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A pickax leans against the trunk of the tree.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Rose, yellow, and blue washes in the background suggest sky at sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A nude female falls head-first, with her body facing to the left, in the left margin of
the text.  Her legs are spread, with the left leg extended
vertically and the right leg bent to the right.  Her arms appear
to be extended downward; perhaps she has long hair which is also
dangling down.  Above and to the left of her right leg is the
outline of a cloud, or possibly a limb from the tree that demarcates areas of the sky, as is the case with the limb below her.  A few small branches or vines appear in the upper right corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few small branches or vines appear in the upper right corner of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female falls head-first, with her body facing to the left, in the left margin of
the text.  Her legs are spread, with the left leg extended
vertically and the right leg bent to the right.  Her arms appear
to be extended downward; perhaps she has long hair which is also
dangling down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above and to the left of the falling figure's right leg is the
outline of a cloud, or possibly a limb from the tree that demarcates areas of the sky, as is the case with the limb below her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above and to the left of the falling figure's right leg is the
outline of a cloud, or possibly a limb from the tree that demarcates areas of the sky, as is the case with the limb below her.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>The bottom of the plate is colored to suggest grass.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The bottom of the plate is colored to suggest grass.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">5</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.02" justify="left" indent="60"><physnumber type="etched">2</physnumber><note>In Copy O, the etched number "2" is partially obscured by a vine or branch design at the border.</note></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.03" justify="left">Now thou maist marry Bromions harlot, and protect the child</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.04" justify="left">Of Bromions rage, that Oothoon shall put forth in nine moons</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.05" justify="left" indent="50">time</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.06" justify="left">Then storms rent Theotormons limbs: he rolld his waves around.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.07" justify="left">And folded his black jealous waters round the adulterate pair</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.08" justify="left">Bound back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.09" justify="left">At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.10" justify="left">With secret tears; beneath him sound like waves on a desart shore </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.11" justify="left">The voice of slaves beneath the sun, and children bought with money.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.12" justify="left">That shiver in religious caves beneath the burning fires</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.13" justify="left">Of lust, that belch incessant from the summits of the earth</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.14" justify="left">Oothoon weeps not, she cannot weep! her tears are locked up;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.15" justify="left">But she can howl incessant writhing her soft snowy limbs.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.16" justify="left">And calling Theotormons Eagles to prey upon her flesh.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.17" justify="left">I call with holy voice! kings of the sounding air.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.18" justify="left">Rend away this defiled bosom that I may reflect.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.19" justify="left">The image of Theotormon on my pure transparent breast.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.20" justify="left">The Eagles at her call descend &amp; rend their bleeding prey;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.21" justify="left">Theotormon severely smiles. her soul reflects the smile;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.22" justify="left">As the clear spring mudded with feet of beasts grows pure &amp; smiles</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.23" justify="left">The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.24" justify="left">Why does my Theotormon sit weeping upon the threshold:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.25" justify="left">And Oothoon hovers by his side, perswading him in vain;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.26" justify="left">I cry arise O Theotormon for the village dog</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.27" justify="left">Barks at the breaking day, the nightingale has done lamenting,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.28" justify="left">The lark does rustle in the ripe corn, and the Eagle returns</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.29" justify="left">From nightly prey, and lifts his golden beak to the pure east;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.30" justify="left">Shaking the dust from his immortal pinions to awake</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.31" justify="left">The sun that sleeps too long.  Arise my Theotormon I am pure.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.32" justify="left">Because the night is gone that clos'd me in its deadly black.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.33" justify="left">They told me that the night &amp; day were all that I could see:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.34" justify="left">They told me that I had five senses to inclose me up.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.35" justify="left">And they inclos'd my infinite brain into a narrow circle.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.36" justify="left">And sunk my heart into the Abyss, a red round globe hot burning </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.37" justify="left">Till all from life I was obliterated and erased.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.38" justify="left">Instead of morn arises a bright shadow, like an eye</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.39" justify="left">In the eastern cloud; instead of night a sickly charnel house;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.40" justify="left">That Theotormon hears me not! to him the night and morn</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.05.41" justify="left">Are both alike: a night of sighs, a morning of fresh tears;</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.06" dbi="vda.O.P6"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 6, </objcode><objcode code="E3">Erdman 3, </objcode><objcode code="K3">Keynes 3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.8 x 11.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="874" width="603"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>A nude female lies supine on a cloud.  Her left arm
is extended horizontally to the right (but raised vertically relative to her body).  Her long
hair can be seen above her left forearm.  Her head is thrown back
and her belly exposed.  Her legs are spread apart and bent back
sharply at the knees so we see only her upper legs.  This posture
suggests erotic (or at least highly emotional) abandon.  Above
her hovers a large bird, probably an eagle.  The bird seems to
descend upon the female, with its beak touching her torso between
                  her stomach and breasts.  Above the female's head is another cloud—or an extension of the
cloud on which the female lies.  The female is probably Oothoon
since, on Plate 5, she is described as "calling" upon
"Theotormons Eagles to prey upon her flesh" (line 16).</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>erotic</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female lies supine on a cloud.  Her left arm
is extended horizontally to the right (but raised vertically relative to her body).  Her long
hair can be seen above her left forearm.  Her head is thrown back
and her belly exposed.  Her legs are spread apart and bent back
sharply at the knees so we see only her upper legs.  This posture
suggests erotic (or at least highly emotional) abandon.  She is
probably Oothoon who, on Plate 5, is described as "calling" upon
"Theotormons Eagles to prey upon her flesh" (line 16).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>eagle</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>flying</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>preying</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large bird, probably one of "Theotormons Eagles" that Oothoon calls on to "prey upon her flesh" (Plate 5, line 16), hovers over
the supine female.  Its wings extend horizontally; its head faces
downward toward the woman.  The bird's beak touches her torso; its prominent tail is slightly forked.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The nude female lies supine on a cloud.  Either an
extension of this cloud, or a second cloud, can be seen above her
head.  The blue background tinting indicates sky.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>The suggestions of vines, added to the etching border, line the top margin.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The suggestions of vines, added to the etching border, line the top margin.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">6</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.02" justify="left" indent="60"><physnumber type="etched">3</physnumber><note>In Copy O, the etched number "3" in the upper right-hand corner is largely obscured by watercolor.</note></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.03" justify="left">And none but Bromion can hear my lamentations.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.04" justify="left">With what sense is it that the chicken shuns the ravenous hawk?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.05" justify="left">With what sense does the tame pigeon measure out the expanse?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.06" justify="left">With what sense does the bee form cells? have not the mouse &amp; frog</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.07" justify="left">Eyes and ears and sense of touch? yet are their habitations.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.08" justify="left">And their pursuits, as different as their forms and as their joys:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.09" justify="left">Ask the wild ass why he refuses burdens; and the meek camel</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.10" justify="left">Why he loves man; is it because of eye ear mouth or skin</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.11" justify="left">Or breathing nostrils? No. for these the wolf and tyger have.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.12" justify="left">Ask the blind worm the secrets of the grave, and why her spires</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.13" justify="left">Love to curl round the bones of death! and ask the rav'nous snake </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.14" justify="left">Where she gets poison: &amp; the wing'd eagle why he loves the sun</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.15" justify="left">And then tell me the thoughts of man, that have been hid of old.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.16" justify="left">Silent I hover all the night. and all day could be silent.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.17" justify="left">If Theotormon once would turn his loved eyes upon me;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.18" justify="left">How can I be defild when I reflect thy image pure?<space extent="10"/>(woe</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.19" justify="left">Sweetest the fruit that the worm feeds on. &amp; the soul prey'd on by</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.20" justify="left">The new wash'd lamb ting'd with the village smoke &amp; the bright swan</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.21" justify="left">By the red earth of our immortal river; I bathe my wings,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.22" justify="left">And I am white and pure to hover round Theotormons breast.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.23" justify="left">Then Theotormon broke his silence, and he answered.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.24" justify="left">Tell me what is the night or day to one o'erflowd with woe?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.25" justify="left">Tell me what is a thought? &amp; of what substance is it made?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.26" justify="left">Tell me what is a joy? &amp; in what gardens do joys grow?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.06.27" justify="left">And in what rivers swim the sorrows? and upon what mountains</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.07" dbi="vda.O.P7" compwith="bb85.B4"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7, </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode><objcode code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.0 x 11.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="884" width="598"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Two figures appear on the seashore.  One figure,
probably male, is seated on the sand or stones near the water.  He wears a 
long gown, or at least some drapery, that covers his knees and lower legs.  We
see him from the front; his knees are drawn up to his upper chest
in a very contracted posture.  Given the position of his right
foot, his legs are probably crossed at the ankles.  His hands
rest upon his knees, and in turn his head is bent forward and
rests upon his hands.  We see only the top of his head, covered
with curly hair.  This is probably Theotormon, "weeping" (Plate 5, line 24) 
near "the margind ocean" (Plate 11, line 14).  To the left is a giant wave,
shaped like a tongue of flame.  Within this wave is a nude
female, shackled and chained on her left ankle.  Her right leg is
apparently extended behind her left.  She arches to the right, with her arms 
bent at the elbows and her hands clasped together
just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
supplication.  She faces down and apparently looks at the self-enclosed male below her.  
Her long hair drifts behind her neck
and back.  She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover.  
Right and left of the wave in which she appears is a rocky cliff.  Far right is the sea, 
showing a few indications of waves.  The edge of a rising or setting sun peeps above the 
horizon to the right of the seated figure.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>head on knees</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, is seated on the sand or
stones near the water.  He wears a long gown, or at least some drapery, that covers his knees and lower legs.  We see him from the front; his knees are
drawn up to his upper chest in a very contracted posture.  Given
the position of his right foot, his legs are probably crossed at
the ankles.  His hands rest upon his knees, and in turn his head
is bent forward and rests upon his hands.  We see only the top of
his head, covered with curly hair.  This is probably Theotormon,
"weeping" (Plate 5, line 24) near "the margind ocean" (Plate 11, line 14).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Within a tongue- or flame-like wave is a nude
female, shackled and chained on her left ankle.  Her right leg is
apparently extended behind her left.  She arches to the right,
with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands clasped together
just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
supplication.  She faces down and apparently looks at the
self-enclosed male below her.  Her long hair drifts behind her neck
and back.  She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover
Theotormon.  Although her mouth is not clearly open, she may be
speaking.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The left foot of the female figure is shackled and chained.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>seashore</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The landscape shows a cliff on the left near the seashore.  Both stones and sand may be represented below the seated figure.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dark waters of the sea on the right show indications of waves.  The edge of a rising or setting sun peeps above the horizon to the right of the seated figure.  Beams of light radiate from the sun.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The female is pictured within a giant wave of dark water which, in its shape, resembles a tongue—of a creature or of
fire.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="BD"><illusobjdesc>Right of the text, a tree grows up the margin of the plate; it has three limbs and appears to be encircled by a small vine.  The shape following line 7 might represent a branch bearing a leaf.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="BD"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Right of the text, a tree grows up the margin of the plate; it has three limbs and appears to be encircled by a small vine.  The shape following line 7 might represent a branch bearing a leaf.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">7</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.02" justify="left">Wave shadows of discontent? and in what houses dwell the wretched </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.03" justify="left">Drunken with woe forgotten. and shut up from cold despair,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.04" justify="left">Tell me where dwell the thoughts forgotten till thou call them forth </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.05" justify="left">Tell me where dwell the joys of old? &amp; where the ancient loves?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.06" justify="left">And when will they renew again &amp; the night of oblivion past?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.07" justify="left">That I might traverse times &amp; spaces far remote and bring</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.08" justify="left">Comforts into a present sorrow and a night of pain</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.09" justify="left">Where goest thou O thought! to what remote land is thy flight?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.10" justify="left">If thou returnest to the present moment of affliction</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.11" justify="left">Wilt thou bring comforts on thy wings, and dews and honey and balm;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.12" justify="left">Or poison from the desart wilds, from the eyes of the envier.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.13" justify="left">Then Bromion said; and shook the cavern with his lamentation</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.14" justify="left">Thou knowest that the ancient trees seen by thine eyes have fruit;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.15" justify="left">But knowest thou that trees and fruits flourish upon the earth</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.16" justify="left">To gratify senses unknown? trees beasts and birds unknown:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.17" justify="left">Unknown, not unpercievd, spread in the infinite microscope,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.18" justify="left">In places yet unvisited by the voyager. and in worlds</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.19" justify="left">Over another kind of seas, and in atmospheres unknown?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.20" justify="left">Ah! are there other wars, beside the wars of sword and fire!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.21" justify="left">And are there other sorrows, beside the sorrows of poverty?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.22" justify="left">And are there other joys, beside the joys of riches and ease.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.23" justify="left">And is there not one law for both the lion and the ox?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.24" justify="left">And is there not eternal fire, and eternal chains?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.25" justify="left">To bind the phantoms of existence from eternal life?</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.07.26" justify="left">Then Oothoon waited silent all the day, and all the night,</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.08" dbi="vda.O.P8"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 8, </objcode><objcode code="E5">Erdman 5, </objcode><objcode code="K5">Keynes 5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.2 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="894" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A figure lies huddled on the ground.  The figure is of indeterminate gender but is probably female given the long gown, drapery, or blanket covering her.  She is basically prone, but the position of her legs is unclear because of the
heavy drapery.  We see only the back of her head; her left arm
curls around in front of her head and appears to rest on a pillow into which her face seems buried.  A snake-like tail
extends from the lower left corner of this pillow; this
may be part of the drapery covering the figure.  She may be Oothoon in
despair.  The etching border along the margins has been embellished to suggest vines or small trees, which also send out tendrils or branches into the design; one vine, with a few leaves, extends from the left margin toward the prone figure (the other vines on the plate are classified as interlinear designs).  A thin wash on the bottom of the plate suggests dirt.  Yellow and rose washes in the background suggest sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure lies huddled on the ground.  The figure is of indeterminate gender but is probably female given the long gown, drapery, or blanket covering her.  She is basically prone, but the position of her legs is unclear because of the
heavy drapery.  We see only the back of her head; her left arm
curls around in front of her head and appears to rest on a pillow into which her face seems buried.  A snake-like tail
extends from the lower left corner of this pillow; this
may be part of the drapery covering the figure.  She may be Oothoon in
despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure appears to have her face pressed against a pillow.  A snake-like tail extends from the lower left corner of
this pillow; this may be part of the figure's drapery.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="C"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The etching border along the margins has been embellished to suggest vines or small trees, which also send out tendrils or branches into the design; one vine, with a few leaves, extends from the left margin toward the prone figure (the other vines on the plate are classified as interlinear designs).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Yellow and rose washes in the background of the design suggest sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A long vine, perhaps a grape vine, extends from the margin and wends its way
horizontally between lines 3 and 4.  A tendril on the left forms a spiral of three loops; the vine ends
on the right with many loops suggestive of (but not quite
forming) a spiral.  Five (grape?) leaves are
pictured.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>grape</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A long vine, perhaps a grape vine, extends from the left margin and wends its way
horizontally between lines 3 and 4.  A tendril on the left forms a spiral of three loops; the vine ends
on the right with many loops suggestive of (but not quite
forming) a spiral.  Five (grape?) leaves are
pictured.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="D"><illusobjdesc>A snake-like vine, possibly ending with several loops, grows from the right margin and fills space right of lines 25-28.  A second, smaller vine just above also extends from the margin and ends in a flower or leaf.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>serpentine</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A snake-like vine, possibly ending with several loops, grows from the right margin and fills space right of lines 25-28.  A second, smaller vine just above also extends from the margin and ends in a flower or leaf.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">8</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.02" justify="left" indent="60"><physnumber type="etched">5</physnumber><note>In Copy O, the etched number "5" in the upper right-hand corner is very lightly printed.</note></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.03" justify="left">But when the morn arose, her lamentation renewd,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.04" justify="left">The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.05" justify="left">O Urizen! Creator of men! mistaken Demon of heaven;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.06" justify="left">Thy joys are tears! thy labour vain, to form men to thine image,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.07" justify="left">How can one joy absorb another? are not different joys</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.08" justify="left">Holy, eternal, infinite! and each joy is a Love.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.09" justify="left">Does not the great mouth laugh at a gift? &amp; the narrow eyelids mock </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.10" justify="left">At the labour that is above payment, and wilt thou take the ape</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.11" justify="left">For thy councellor? or the dog. for a schoolmaster to thy children?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.12" justify="left">Does he who contemns poverty, and he who turns with abhorrence</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.13" justify="left">From usury: feel the same passion or are they moved alike?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.14" justify="left">How can the giver of gifts experience the delights of the merchant?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.15" justify="left">How the industrious citizen the pains of the husbandman.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.16" justify="left">How different far the fat fed hireling with hollow drum;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.17" justify="left">Who buys whole corn fields into wastes, and sings upon the heath:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.18" justify="left">How different their eye and ear! how different the world to them!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.19" justify="left">With what sense does the parson claim the labour of the farmer?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.20" justify="left">What are his nets &amp; gins &amp; traps. &amp; how does he surround him</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.21" justify="left">With cold floods of abstraction, and with forests of solitude,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.22" justify="left">To build him castles and high spires, where kings &amp; priests may dwell.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.23" justify="left">Till she who burns with youth, and knows no fixed lot; is bound </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.24" justify="left">In spells of law to one she loaths; and must she drag the chain </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.25" justify="left">Of life, in weary lust! must chilling murderous thoughts, obscure </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.26" justify="left">The clear heaven of her eternal spring? to bear the wintry rage</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.27" justify="left">Of a harsh terror driv'n to madness, bound to hold a rod</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.28" justify="left">Over her shrinking shoulders all the day; &amp; all the night</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.29" justify="left">To turn the wheel of false desire: and longings that wake her womb</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.30" justify="left">To the abhorred birth of cherubs in the human form</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.31" justify="left">That live a pestilence &amp; die a meteor &amp; are no more.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.32" justify="left">Till the child dwell with one he hates, and do the deed he loaths</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.33" justify="left">And the impure scourge force his seed into its unripe birth</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.34" justify="left">E'er yet his eyelids can behold the arrows of the day.</l></lg><vspace extent="4"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.35" justify="left">Does the whale worship at thy footsteps as the hungry dog?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.36" justify="left">Or does he scent the mountain prey, because his nostrils wide</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.37" justify="left">Draw in the ocean? does his eye discern the flying cloud</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.38" justify="left">As the ravens eye? or does he measure the expanse like the vulture?<note>In Copy O, the "ns" in "expanse" printed poorly.</note></l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.39" justify="left">Does the still spider view the cliffs where eagles hide their young?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.40" justify="left">Or does the fly rejoice, because the harvest is brought in?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.41" justify="left">Does not the eagle scorn the earth &amp; despise the treasures beneath?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.42" justify="left">But the mole knoweth what is there, &amp; the worm shall tell it thee.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.08.43" justify="left">Does not the worm erect a pillar in the mouldering church yard<note>In Copy O, a question mark at the end of the line printed illegibly.</note></l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.09" dbi="vda.O.P9"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber><objcode code="B9">(Bentley 9, </objcode><objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes 6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.9 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="827" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a cloud and holds a whip with
three tails in his left hand.  His left upper arm is raised
vertically, with his forearm bent to the left over his head.  His
right arm is raised and arches over his head; he clutches his forehead with his right hand.  His left leg is extended, his
right bent at the knee.  Both his facial features and his
head-clutching gesture suggest despair.  To the right is a female
nude.  She strides, legs spread apart, forward and to the right.  Her arms are bent, with her hands clutching her face and head.  She is facing down and we see only the top of her head.  Her long
hair trails over her right shoulder.  She too may be supported by
the cloud on which the male sits, although perhaps we are meant
to think of her as hovering in the air.  The female is very probably Oothoon; the
male may be Bromion, in his character as a slave owner, about to
strike the woman.  Alternatively, he may be Theotormon as a self-flagellant.  No such scene is described in the
text.  The lavishly colored clouds below the figures continue up the right margin; a small tail extends down and left from the upper-right corner.  Background washes suggest sky, the yellow and rose coloring of the large clouds possibly hinting at a sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>whipping</characteristic><characteristic>slave owner</characteristic><characteristic>self-flagellant</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a dark cloud and holds a whip
with three tails in his left hand.  His left upper arm is raised
vertically, with his forearm bent to the left over his head.  His
right arm is raised and arches over his head; he clutches his
forehead with his right hand.  His left leg is extended, his
right bent at the knee.  His body faces forward but his head is turned to the right.  His hair
is short and perhaps a little curly.  Both his facial features
and his head-clutching gesture suggest despair.  He may be
Bromion, in his character as a slave owner, about to strike the
woman on the right.  Alternatively, he may be Theotormon as a
self-flagellant.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female strides, legs spread apart, forward
and to the right.  Her arms are bent, with her hands clutching
her face and head.  She is facing down and we see only the top of
her head.  Her long hair trails over her right shoulder.  She may be supported by the cloud below her left foot, although
perhaps we are meant to think of her as hovering in the air.  She
is very probably Oothoon in despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>whip</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><characteristic>knot</characteristic><characteristic>spike</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male holds a whip with three snake-like tails.  Each tail appears to terminate in a knot or cluster of spikes.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>smoke</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>earth</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male sits on a cloud.  At least the left foot of
the female may also rest on this cloud.  The lavishly colored clouds below the figures continue, almost smoke-like, up the right margin; a small tail, or possibly another cloud, extends down and left from the upper-right corner.  The yellow and rose coloring of these main clouds suggests a sunrise or sunset.  Blue background washes indicate a sky, perhaps with distant clouds.  There may be a patch of earth below the cloud, lower left.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">9</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.02" justify="left" indent="60"><physnumber type="etched">6</physnumber><note>In Copy O, the etched number "6" in the upper right-hand corner is lightly printed and largely obscured by watercolor and the border design.</note></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.03" justify="left">And a palace of eternity in the jaws of the hungry grave</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.04" justify="left">Over his porch these words are written. Take thy bliss O Man!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.05" justify="left">And sweet shall be thy taste &amp; sweet thy infant joys renew!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.06" justify="left">Infancy, fearless, lustful, happy! nestling for delight</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.07" justify="left">In laps of pleasure; Innocence! honest, open, seeking</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.08" justify="left">The vigorous joys of morning light; open to virgin bliss.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.09" justify="left">Who taught thee modesty, subtil modesty! child of night &amp; sleep </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.10" justify="left">When thou awakest. wilt thou dissemble all thy secret joys</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.11" justify="left">Or wert thou not awake when all this mystery was disclos'd!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.12" justify="left">Then com'st thou forth a modest virgin knowing to dissemble</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.13" justify="left">With nets found under thy night pillow, to catch virgin joy,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.14" justify="left">And brand it with the name of whore; &amp; sell it in the night,<note>In Copy O, the comma at the end of the line printed very faintly.</note></l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.15" justify="left">In silence, ev'n without a whisper, and in seeming sleep;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.16" justify="left">Religious dreams and holy vespers, light thy smoky fires:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.17" justify="left">Once were thy fires lighted by the eyes of honest morn</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.18" justify="left">And does my Theotormon seek this hypocrite modesty?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.19" justify="left">This knowing, artful, secret, fearful, cautious, trembling hypocrite. </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.20" justify="left">Then is Oothoon a whore indeed! and all the virgin joys</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.21" justify="left">Of life are harlots; and Theotormon is a sick mans dream</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.22" justify="left">And Oothoon is the crafty slave of selfish holiness.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.23" justify="left">But Oothoon is not so, a virgin fill'd with virgin fancies</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.24" justify="left">Open to joy and to delight where ever beauty appears</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.09.25" justify="left">If in the morning sun I find it: there my eyes are fix'd</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.10" dbi="vda.O.P10" compwith="bb136.B17"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber><objcode code="B10">(Bentley 10, </objcode><objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes 7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.9 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="879" width="624"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Four (possibly five) female figures huddle together
in contracted postures.  The four clearly pictured wear gowns.  The figure on the right squats with knees drawn up toward her
chest; her head leans forward onto her knees and we see only the
top of her head.  The figure in the center
foreground faces to the right, with her knees drawn up and her
upper body leaning forward.  Her right knee and lower leg cover
her face; we see only her head and long hair.  Above this central
figure and slightly behind are the shoulders and face of a woman
with long hair (spread out on both sides of her head) and a
desperate expression on her face.  Her hands are raised to her
shoulders with palms turned upward.  Her eyes look up.  The left-most figure faces left.  Her upper body is bent over her legs
in a severely contracted posture.  Her head is on the far left,
bent low over her extended left arm.  Above this figure is an indeterminate design that may be the hair and right shoulder of a
fifth female figure.  These females are probably the Daughters of
Albion.  The cloudy sky behind the figures is colored to suggest a sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female in a very contracted posture squats
on the ground far right.  Her large knees are drawn up to her chest; her
head is bent forward and rests on her knees.  We see only the top
of her head and long(?) blonde hair.  She is probably one of the Daughters of Albion in this huddled group of four or five females.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female sits in a contracted posture as the
front-most figure in the huddled group.  She faces to the right,
with her right knee drawn up and her upper body bent forward.  Her face is covered by her right knee and lower leg; we see only
her head and long hair.  She is probably one of the
Daughters of Albion in this group of four or five
figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind two other figures, we see the shoulders,
hands, and face of a gowned female.  Her long hair extends
horizontally on either side of her head.  Her face and eyes are
turned upward; her facial expression suggests despair.  Her hands
are raised to her shoulders, palms turned upward.  She is
probably one of the Daughters of Albion, sitting with others in
this huddled group.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the far left of the huddled group of figures is a
gowned female with her upper body bent over her legs in an extremely contracted posture.  She faces to the left, with her head bent down and resting on her left arm.  Her left arm, and particularly her left hand, dangle to the left.  Her hair is probably
long.  She is probably one of the Daughters of Albion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>upper body</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>An indeterminate design just above the left-most figure in
this huddled group of figures may be the lowered head, curly(?)
hair, and right shoulder of a fifth female.  She is probably one of
the Daughters of Albion, like the others in this group.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting for the huddled figures consists of
a cloudy sky colored to suggest sunrise or sunset.  Light washes behind the text also suggest sky.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">10</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.XX" justify="left"><note>In Copy O, the etched number "7" in the upper right-hand corner is obscured by washes.</note></l></texthead><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.02" justify="left">In happy copulation; if in evening mild. wearied with work;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.03" justify="left">Sit on a bank and draw the pleasures of this free born joy.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.04" justify="left" indent="2">The moment of desire! the moment of desire! The virgin</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.05" justify="left">That pines for man; shall awaken her womb to enormous joys</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.06" justify="left">In the secret shadows of her chamber; the youth shut up from</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.07" justify="left">The lustful joy, shall forget to generate, &amp; create an amorous image</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.08" justify="left">In the shadows of his curtains and in the folds of his silent pillow.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.09" justify="left">Are not these the places of religion? the rewards of continence?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.10" justify="left">The self enjoyings of self denial? Why dost thou seek religion?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.11" justify="left">Is it because acts are not lovely, that thou seekest solitude,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.12" justify="left">Where the horrible darkness is impressed with reflections of desire.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.13" justify="left">Father of Jealousy, be thou accursed from the earth!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.14" justify="left">Why hast thou taught my Theotormon this accursed thing?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.15" justify="left">Till beauty fades from off my shoulders darken'd and cast out,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.16" justify="left">A solitary shadow wailing on the margin of non-entity.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.17" justify="left">I cry, Love! Love! Love! happy happy Love! free as the mountain wind!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.18" justify="left">Can that be Love, that drinks another as a sponge drinks water?</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.19" justify="left">That clouds with jealousy his nights, with weepings all the day;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.20" justify="left">To spin a web of age around him, grey and hoary! dark!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.21" justify="left">Till his eyes sicken at the fruit that hangs before his sight.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.22" justify="left">Such is self-love that envies all! a creeping skeleton</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.23" justify="left">With lamplike eyes watching around the frozen marriage bed.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.24" justify="left">But silken nets and traps of adamant will Oothoon spread,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.25" justify="left">And catch for thee girls of mild silver, or of furious gold:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.26" justify="left">I'll lie beside thee on a bank &amp; view their wanton play</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.27" justify="left">In lovely copulation bliss on bliss with Theotormon;</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.28" justify="left">Red as the rosy morning, lustful as the first born beam,</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.29" justify="left">Oothoon shall view his dear delight, nor e'er with jealous cloud </l><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.30" justify="left">Come in the heaven of generous love; nor selfish blightings bring.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.10.31" justify="left">Does the sun walk in glorious raiment, on the secret floor</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.o.illbk.11" dbi="vda.O.P11"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber><objcode code="B11">(Bentley 11, </objcode><objcode code="E8">Erdman 8, </objcode><objcode code="K8">Keynes 8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.9 x 11.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="879" width="614"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design would appear to illustrate line 15: "The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho
back her [Oothoon's] sighs."  Three gowned female
                  figures—the Daughters of Albion—huddle together on the seashore,
lower right.  The right-most figure in the group has her legs drawn
up in a sitting or squatting position similar to her companions.  She looks up and to the left at the figure hovering above.  Her
companion to the left also looks up and to the left.  Both legs
are drawn up; her right arm is extended horizontally to the
right, with her right hand resting on her companion's left shoulder.  The left-most figure in the group has both legs drawn
up and her head lowered; we see only the top of her head.  All three females have long hair.  Above the group and to the left is
Oothoon, hovering in the air or on a cloud.  We see only her
unclothed chest, head facing forward, long hair streaming out on
both sides of her head, and long arms extended horizontally.  Her
hands seem to rest on or hold the cloud.  Flames emanate from
just below her chest and extend over both arms.  The sea, lower
left, includes some waves.  Rose and yellow washes in the background suggest sky at sunrise or sunset; a dark gray wash left of Oothoon may suggest a storm cloud.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>One of the Daughters of Albion huddles in a seated
or squatting position, the right-most figure in a group of three
gowned women.  Her legs are drawn up to her chest.  She faces to
the left and looks up at the hovering figure above.  Her long
hair cascades over her left shoulder.  Both feet can be seen just
below the hem of her gown.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>One of the Daughters of Albion sits in the center of
the group of three huddled women who sit or squat on the
seashore.  Like her companions, she is gowned.  Both legs are drawn up toward her chest.  Her left foot appears
just below the hem of her gown.  Her right arm extends
horizontally to the right and her right hand rests on the left
shoulder of her companion on the right.  She faces left and looks
up to the hovering figure above.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>One of the Daughters of Albion huddles with three
others to the right.  Like her companions, she is gowned.  We see only her legs, drawn up to her chest, and the
top of her lowered head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female hovers in the sky or on a cloud with arms
extended horizontally.  We see only her unclothed chest, arms and
hands, face, and long hair streaming out on each side of her
head.  She faces forward with a serious, perhaps worried,
expression.  In other copies, her mouth is open, but it appears to be closed in this copy.  Her hands appear to rest on or hold the
cloud below her.  Flames emanate from beneath her chest and curl
over her arms.  This is almost certainly Oothoon addressing the
Daughters of Albion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Fire emanates from below the hovering figure's chest
and curls upward over her arms.  The tongues of flame are snake-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>seashore</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wave</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>island</characteristic><characteristic>peninsula</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting is the seashore, with the sea on the
left and a sandy or stony shore on the right.  A thin arm of the sea extends below the shore on which the three figures sit.  Thus, they may be sitting on an island or peninsula.  There are clear
indications of waves in the sea and along the shore.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky is dominated by a cloud extending from left 
to right across the middle of the plate.  Rose and yellow washes in the background suggest sky at sunrise or sunset; a dark gray wash left of Oothoon may suggest a storm cloud.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.01" justify="left" indent="62"><physnumber type="pen-and-ink">11</physnumber></l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.02" justify="left" indent="50">(drop</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.03" justify="left">Where the cold miser spreads his gold? or does the bright cloud</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.04" justify="left">On his stone threshold? does his eye behold the beam that brings</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.05" justify="left">Expansion to the eye of pity? or will he bind himself</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.06" justify="left">Beside the ox to thy hard furrow? does not that mild beam blot</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.07" justify="left">The bat, the owl, the glowing tyger, and the king of night.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.08" justify="left">The sea fowl takes the wintry blast, for a cov'ring to her limbs:</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.09" justify="left">And the wild snake, the pestilence to adorn him with gems &amp; gold.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.10" justify="left">And trees, &amp; birds. &amp; beasts, &amp; men, behold their eternal joy.</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.11" justify="left">Arise you little glancing wings, and sing your infant joy!</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.12" justify="left">Arise and drink your bliss. for every thing that lives is holy!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.13" justify="left">Thus every morning wails Oothoon. but Theotormon sits</l><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.14" justify="left">Upon the margind ocean conversing with shadows dire,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.15" justify="left">The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.o.illbk.11.16" justify="left" indent="25">The End</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>