<!--Step 3 conversion -Data modification/normalization  datamodsblake.xsl 2004-11-30T15:29:52-05:00 Aziza Technology Associates--><!--Step 2 Conversion to BAD DTD 2004 using modblake.pl Fri Oct 15 10:43:11 2004 Aziza Technology Associates--><bad id="vda.c" type="illbk" work="Visions of the Daughters of Albion" copy="C" copyid="C" institution="glasgow" catalog="bentley" catid="C"><header><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Visions of the Daughters of Albion"><main>Visions of the Daughters of Albion</main><copy> Copy C</copy>
: electronic edition
</title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;  
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi,</name> University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler</name><resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah C. Jones, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Ashley Reed, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name></respstmt><sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, the
Library of Congress, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
with a software grant from Inso Corporation and hardware and software
grants from Sun Microsystems</sponsor><funder>National Endowment for the Humanities, 2000-02</funder><funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1997-98</funder><funder>Getty Grant Program, 1995-98</funder></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>XML file derived from 1 SGML (ISO 8879) encoded file approx. 135KB; 22 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files
ranging in size from 10KB to 635KB</extent><publicationstmt>Charlottesville: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH
         <date>November 1996</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The editors of the Blake Archive are pleased to announce that Copies F, H, and O of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> and copies a, C, and J of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> are now publicly accessible. The images are linked to enlargements and to transcriptions edited to correspond to the particular copy; plates are displayed in the order they appear in the copy and are identified by that order, as well as by their Bentley, Erdman, and Keynes plate numbers.<lb/><lb/>
            The source of the digital images are new 4x5 color transparencies, which were color corrected against the originals. They were scaled to the size of the originals and scanned in 24-bit color at 300dpi. The resulting digital images, which were color corrected against the transparencies, are displayed as jpeg images, at 100dpi and at 300dpi. The former image will be displayed larger or smaller than the original depending on your monitor's resolution. In the near future, though, using a program being developed by the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities , you will be able to receive these images resized on the fly according to your monitor's resolution.<lb/><lb/>
            We will continue to make copies of illuminated books accessible once we have scanned and color corrected the images and edited the texts. In the next few months, we will display <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> Copy D, <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> Copy G, <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> Copy B, <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> Copies B and E, and <hi rend="i">America</hi> Copy E. We will also post a general bibliography on Blake and select bibliographies for each of these books, as well as Erdman's edition of Blake's poetry and prose. Users will thus be able to browse the Archive, downloading images and texts (for private use only). When the search engine is operational, they will also be able to search the Archive for words, visual motifs, or bibliographical information, because we are also encoding all texts, plates, and images in Standard General Markup Language (see Plan of the Archive).<lb/><lb/>
            We presently have over 1200 transparencies of a projected 3000 for the Archive. With the entire Rosenwald Collection of illuminated books and the Essick Collection of prints, as well as works from the Glasgow University Library and the New York Public Library, we have at least one copy of every illuminated book, major series of prints (<hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>, Dante illustrations, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, etc.), and commercial engraving. We will be adding paintings and manuscripts as we add other important collections to the Archive. Scanning, editing, and encoding all of these images will keep the site under construction for the next few years.<lb/><lb/>
            Users can visit this page for future updates about our progress and about future developments at the Institute that affect the Archive, such as INOTE (written in the programming language Java), a tool that makes it possible for users to search, enlarge, compare, and annotate images.
         </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><userestrict>Copyright © <date>1997</date> by Morris Eaves, Robert N. Essick,
and Joseph Viscomi, all rights reserved.  Items in the Archive may be
shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium, requires
express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
publisher.
Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been
granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.<lb/><lb/>
This image copyright © 1997 Glasgow University Library.</userestrict><encodingdesc/><profiledesc/><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Conversion to Blake Archive Description DTD 2.1; Styles 2.0</change><date>Summer 2000</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><resp>Programmer/Analysts: </resp><name>Robert Bingler, </name><name>David Cosca, </name><name>Kirk V. Hastings</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
<name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
<name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
<resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>This work has been revised to include corrections and improvements to the textual transcriptions and editors' notes (for consistency, accuracy, and visual presentation) that were not reflected in the original XML conversion.</change><date>2007</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
               <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
               <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
               <resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah C. Jones, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Sarah Tolf</name><resp>Consultant: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></header><objdesc><source><objdescid><objtitle><title><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi></title></objtitle><origination>William Blake <role>author, </role><role>inventor, </role><role>delineator, </role><role>etcher, </role><role>printer, </role><role>colorist</role></origination><origination>Catherine Blake <role>printer</role></origination><imprint><publisher>William Blake</publisher><pubplace>London<note>The place of publication is not given in
the book, but Blake lived in London during the writing, etching,
and printing of this copy.</note></pubplace><date>1793</date></imprint><compdate value="1793.A">1793</compdate></objdescid><objinfo><printdate value="1793.D">1793</printdate><numberobj>11</numberobj><objorder>1-11</objorder><objsize>ranging between 17.2 x 12.9 cm. and 14.2 x 11.2 cm.</objsize><numberleaves>6<note>Plates 2-11 are printed recto/verso. Plate
1 is printed on a single sheet and faces plate 2 (the title
page).</note></numberleaves><leafsize>36.0 x 25.7 cm.</leafsize><medium>relief etching with white-line etching on plate 2</medium><printingstyle>relief</printingstyle><inkcolor>raw sienna</inkcolor><support>wove paper</support><watermark>J Whatman<note>The watermark appears only on plates 
8/9 (printed recto/verso).</note></watermark><etchednumbers><note>Numbered 2-3, 5-7 upper right on plates 5-6,
8-10.  The number (5) on plate 8 is very poorly printed; the number (7) is obscured by coloring on plate 10.</note></etchednumbers><pennednumbers>none</pennednumbers><framelines>none</framelines><binding>three-quarter maroon morocco over brown marbled
boards</binding><stabholes>three holes, 9.0 cm. from the top and 7.5 and 7.3 cm.
apart</stabholes></objinfo><provenance n="1"><name>Glasgow University Library, Glasgow, Scotland</name><date>lent by Her Majesty's Treasury in 1971 and later given to 
the Glasgow University Library</date><dealer>gift</dealer><price>gift</price><note>Acquired (perhaps bound with <hi rend="i">America</hi> Copy C) by Henry Reveley; W.
Wyndham; sold by Wyndham at Christie's, 12 May 1852, lot 345
(£4.4s. to the dealer Henry Bohn); perhaps the copy acquired by
Robert Arthington and sold at Sotheby's, 17 May 1866, lot 22 (£6
to Pickering); Charles J. Toovey; Henry Cunliffe; by bequest to his
great-nephew Lord Cunliffe; by gift in 1971 or shortly thereafter to the
Glasgow University Library.</note></provenance><repository><institution>Glasgow University Library</institution><addressline>Hillhead Street</addressline><addressline>Glasgow G12 8QE</addressline><addressline>United Kingdom</addressline><addressline>Telephone: 0141-330-5632</addressline><addressline>Fax: 0141-330-4952</addressline><addressline>URL: http://special.lib.gla.ac.uk/</addressline><department>Special Collections Department</department><collection>Glasgow University Library</collection><repositoryid label="Call number">RX131</repositoryid></repository></source><desc id="vda.c.illbk.01" dbi="vda.C.P1" compwith="bb85.B5"><objtitle><title type="transcribed">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</title>,
<objid><objnumber code="A1">Object 1 </objnumber><objcode code="B1">(Bentley 1, </objcode><objcode code="Ei">Erdman i, </objcode><objcode code="Ki">Keynes i)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.1 x 11.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="889" width="619"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>Three nude figures are seen within the mouth of a
cave that opens onto the sea.  Heavy clouds fill the sky, but
fail to cover the disc of the sun.  The open area where the sun
appears suggests an eye socket, perhaps in a skull outlined by
the cave and seen in left profile.  Indeterminate vegetation
dangles from the roof of the cave.  The figures sit or kneel on
large stones or, in the case of the single female, perhaps on
sand.  On the left is a heavily-muscled and bearded male seen in
left profile.  He sits or squats at the cave's mouth.  He looks
to the left with wide-open eyes; his face is deeply marked by
fear or worse; his hair stands on end.  His mouth is open and he
may be howling.  His knees are drawn up in a contracted position;
his right arm is drawing backwards as though bound behind him.
Large shackles are attached to both his ankles.  At least three
links of a massive chain descend below his left hip.  He may be
bound back to back with the female directly to the right.  This
pair is probably Oothoon, the central female figure in the poem,
and her tormentor Bromion.  She kneels, with her body bent down
and to the right.  The right-most link of the chain below Bromion
may be attached to Oothoon; her long hair cascades over her neck and down behind her head.  Above her and to the right, an extremely    
contracted figure sits among rocks.  This is probably Theotormon,
Oothoon's ineffectual lover.  His legs appear to be crossed, with
the left foot prominently poised below his heavy knees.  He faces
down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly
hair.  His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm 
bent at the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps
clutching his curly hair.  His right arm descends along the right
side of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left elbow. 
The design may illustrate the following lines on plate 5: "Bound
back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell / At     
entrance Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard" (lines 7-8).      
Given this textual parallel, the two figures on the left may be
personifications of terror (note the expression on Bromion's   
face) and meekness.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cave</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The three figures are situated within the mouth of a
cave formed of stones and possibly a sandy floor.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>shore</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see the sea behind and on each side of the figure
on the left.  Perhaps some of its waters come near to his      
feet.  The dark waters in the foreground include small waves.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky, seen above the figures and below the roof
of the cave, is filled with heavy clouds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>eye</characteristic><characteristic>eye socket</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The round disc of the sun appears through a break in
the clouds.  The shape of this opening suggests an eye socket.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>indeterminate</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Clumps of vegetation of an indeterminate type dangle
from the roof of the cave.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="structure" location="E"><characteristic>roof</characteristic><characteristic>floor</characteristic><characteristic>skull</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting for the design-the mouth of a cave-can
be considered a structure with both a roof and a floor.  Given  
the shape of the sun, the opening in the clouds around it, and  
the outline of the cave's mouth, the setting may also suggest a  
skull seen in left profile.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>terror</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>fear</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>howling</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>hair standing on end</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the left is a nude, heavily-muscled, and bearded
male seen in left profile.  He sits or squats on the sandy or   
stoney surface of a cave's mouth.  He looks to the left with     
wide-open eyes; his face is deeply marked by fear or worse; his  
flame-like hair stands on end.  His mouth is open and he may be  
howling.  His knees are drawn up in a contracted position; his   
right arm is drawing backwards as though bound behind him.  A  
large shackle is affixed to his left ankle; there may also be a 
shackle on his right ankle.  Three links of a massive chain      
descend below his left hip.  This is probably Bromion, the       
tormentor of the central female figure in the text, Oothoon.  He
may also be a personification of terror-see the following lines
on plate 5: "Bound back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp;       
meekness dwell / At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the       
threshold hard" (lines 7-8). </illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>meekness</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>eyes closed</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>bowing</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female, seen in right profile, kneels on the 
stones or sand of the cave's mouth.  She may be bound back to   
back to the male to the left.  This pair is probably Oothoon, the
central female figure in the poem, and her tormentor Bromion.    
Her body is bent down and to the right.  The right-most link of  
the chain below Bromion may be attached to Oothoon.  Her face,   
perhaps with eyes closed, is pointed down; her long hair cascades
over her neck and down behind her head.  She may also personify
meekness-see the following lines on plate 5: "Bound back to back
in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell / At entrance          
Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard" (lines 7-8).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Both ankles of the figure on the left bear shackles, with heavy links of a chain below.  The link on the right may be attached to the female figure to the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="BD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around head</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>fist</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male squats in an extremely contracted       
posture among rocks.  This is probably Theotormon, Oothoon's     
ineffectual lover.  His legs appear to be crossed, with the left 
foot prominently poised below his heavy knees.  He faces forward and down so that we see only the top of his head, covered with curly hair.  
His arms are wrapped around his head, with the left arm bent at  
the elbow and his left hand, formed into a fist, perhaps       
clutching his hair.  His right arm descends along the right side
of his hidden face and disappears beneath his left             
elbow.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc>
          <!--[Full-page design]--></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.02" dbi="vda.C.P2"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A2">Object 2 </objnumber><objcode code="B2">(Bentley 2, </objcode><objcode code="Eii">Erdman ii, </objcode><objcode code="Kii">Keynes ii)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.3 x 12.9 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="848" width="671"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The title page is a seascape, with two storm-tossed
waves in the lower margin, heavy clouds, rain, and at least
eleven human figures.  The angle of the waves suggests a strong
wind blowing from left to right.  A nude female runs toward us
with her right foot touching a trough between waves, lower
center.  She is probably the central female figure in the poem,
Oothoon, who "over the waves ... went" (plate 4, line 16).  Her left leg is
extended behind her, her arms are raised at 135 degrees, and the
fingers of both hands are separated and extended.  She appears to
look back and up; her long hair streams back and to the right as
though blown by a wind.  She may be looking at the figure         
hovering in the air above her, a bearded male who looks directly  
at the viewer and may be pursuing Oothoon.  This threatening male
may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or Urizen, the
evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in the text.  We
see only his head and face, shoulders, and arms and hands wrapped
around his shoulders in a contracted posture.  His large wings
extend horizontally.  His face is heavily lined, particularly the
forehead.  Flames spring from below his wings and rise above
them.  To the left is a ring of three female figures pictured as
though nude but with the twisted, spiraling hems of gowns
trailing behind them.  They form a circle, as though            
participating in an ecstatic dance.  The figure at the bottom of
the circle holds hands with her two companions.  Her arms are  
extended horizontally and her legs are spread apart as though she
were striding energetically to the right.  Her head probably
faces right or away from the viewer.  The dancer furthest to the left
also has her arms extended horizontally (relative to her body);
her head is tilted back as though she were looking up.  Like her
companion below, a strand of long hair extends from her head.    
The final dancer, top right in the circle, has her arms raised at
135 degrees and has her legs spread.  Her back and neck are       
arched backwards and she appears to be looking up.  Above the     
ring of dancers, and just left of the first diagonal of the      
letter "A" of "Albion" in line 4, is a slender, 
nude figure seen from the side with at least one arm extended    
downward.  She may be holding a small scepter in her extended    
hand.  This figure, probably female, seems to be descending       
head-first.  To the left of this figure, near the left margin of
the
plate, is a nude figure, probably female, seen from the side and
sitting on a cloud.  Her knees are drawn up towards her head,   
which is tilted down and to the left.  Her left arm, which we see
only from the shoulder to the elbow, extends behind her as though
it is propping her up or possibly bound behind her.  To the right
of these two figures, and near the center of the plate, is a   
figure, probably female and gowned, sitting on a cloud just above
the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 4.
She faces to the left and we see only her left side.  Her upper
body and head are bent over at such a sharp angle that they touch
her upper left leg.  In this contracted posture, her long hair  
cascades over her left knee.  Higher along the left margin of the 
design and left of the word "of" in line 2 are   
two figures on a cloud.  Both appear to be nude; at least the one 
on the left is probably female.  We see this figure on the left   
from behind.  Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm   
extending downwards (almost touching the head of the figure    
below) and her long hair cascading downwards.  Her right arm is  
bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or        
balance.  Her companion to the right lies on the cloud, with her  
or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted and contracted    
posture.  We apparently see only the top of her or his head; the
figure may be looking down.  The left arm is bent at the elbow  
with the left hand beneath the head.  To the right, and right of 
the word "of" in line 2, is a nude male with legs crossed.  He sits on a cloud.  His hair is
long; he faces down and to the right.  He twists and leans to the right,  
with arms raised at 45 degrees (but horizontally relative to his 
body) and extended downward and to the right.  The fingers of
both hands are spread and extended as though he were casting down
the indications of rain lower in the design.  Slightly    
below and to the right of the winged figure, the rain appears to
be cascading over cliffs that suggest the shapes of aged figures 
with shoulders hunched and heads lowered.  A rainbow arches      
dramatically from lower left, through the ring of dancers, and    
ends below the figure with crossed legs upper right. The words of 
the title are integrated into the design and seem to float on    
clouds.  The motto and imprint appear to float on the sea below
the two waves.</illusobjdesc><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The lower quarter of the plate is dominated by two   
large waves of a storm-tossed sea.  The angle of the waves      
suggests a strong wind blowing from left to right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky-the background for most of the plate-is  
filled with the outlines of clouds.  Their number and billowing  
shapes suggest a storm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="BD"><characteristic>rain</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wind</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Diagonal streaks of wash set against a darker        
background of washes apparently indicate rain.  These lines are   
most clearly seen below and to the right of "of" in line 3 and between the left wing of the  
hovering figure and the waves below.  The slight angle of these  
lines, left to right, suggests a wind blowing left to            
right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>rainbow</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A rainbow arches from the lower left margin towards 
the upper right margin, running through the ring of dancers and  
the third and fourth lines of the title                           
inscription.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Tongues of fire rise from beneath the wings of the   
hovering figure and extend above the upper edges of his wings,    
particularly on the right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>shoulders hunched</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>anthropomorphic</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The cliffs over which the rain cascades are shaped 
like old men with long hair standing with their shoulders hunched
and their heads lowered.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>running</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>palms facing viewer</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female runs toward the viewer, her right foot 
touching a trough between two waves.  Her left leg is extended    
backwards.  Her arms are raised at an angle of 135 degrees; her  
upper body and neck are twisted back and to the right.  She is 
probably looking up and back at the winged figured hovering over 
her.  The fingers of her upraised hands, with palms facing the   
viewer, are spread apart.  Her long hair streams out to the       
right, as though blown by a wind.  She is probably Oothoon, the   
central figure in the text, who "over the waves ... went"       
(plate 4, line 16).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>Urizen</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>pursuing</characteristic><characteristic>old</characteristic><characteristic>arms wrapped around body</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>beard</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A bearded male hovers above the running female.      
This male may be Bromion, Oothoon's tormentor in the poem; or   
Urizen, the evil sky-god (among other attributes) also named in 
the text.  We see only his head and face, shoulders, arms and    
hands wrapped around his shoulders in a contracted posture, and  
large wings extended horizontally.  He looks out at the viewer.  
His face is heavily lined, particularly the forehead.  Flames  
spring from below his wings and rise above them.  He may be      
pursuing the female figure below him.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, the lowest of three females in a   
circle, strides energetically to the right.  She appears to be   
nude, except that the hem of a gown curls to the left below her
right leg.  She holds hands with the two other women in this     
circle of dancers.  Her arms are extended horizontally; she faces
away from the viewer and to the right.  A strand of her long hair curls to the right.  We see her back from behind.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, furthest to the left in a circle of
three female dancers, rises near the left margin of the plate.   
She appears to be nude, except that the hem of a gown spirals    
below her left hand.  Her right arm is raised vertically but     
arches to the right; her left arm descends to hold hands with the
dancer below.  Her back is arched, with her head facing up.  A   
strand of her long hair curls below her head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 135 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>hand holding</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female figure, at the top of a circle of three    
female dancers, appears to be nude except that the hem of a long 
gown spirals between her spread legs and above and below her     
torso.  Her back is arched and her arms are raised at an angle of
135 degrees relative to her upper body.  With her left hand she   
holds the right hand of the dancer below her.  Her right hand     
appears to hold a piece of her gown.  Her head appears to be     
thrown back, but neither her face nor her hair is clearly      
indicated.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>conracted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Near the left margin of the plate is a nude figure,  
probably female, seen from the side and sitting on a cloud.  Her  
knees are drawn up towards her head, which is tilted down and to 
the left.  Her left arm, which we see only from the shoulder to
the elbow, extends behind her as though it is propping her up or 
possibly bound behind her.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AC"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>scepter</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Above the ring of dancers, and just left of the     
first diagonal of the letter "A" of "Albion" in line 4, is a slender, nude figure seen from the side with at
least one arm extended downward.  She may be holding a small      
object, possibly a scepter, in her extended hand.  This figure,   
probably female, seems to be falling head-first.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably female and gowned, sits on a   
cloud just above the letters "b" and "i" of "Albion" in line 4.  She faces to the left and we see only her left     
side.  Her upper body and head are bent over at such a sharp     
angle that they touch her upper left leg.  In this contracted    
posture, her long hair cascades over her left knee.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>arm reaching downward</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>We see a nude female figure near the left margin   
from behind.  Her upper body is bent over, with her left arm   
extending downwards (almost touching the head of the figure      
below) and her long hair cascading downwards.  Her right arm is  
bent sharply at the elbow as though braced for support or      
balance.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>hand under head</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure of indeterminate gender lies on a    
cloud, with her or his prominent knees on the left in a twisted 
and contracted posture.  We apparently see only the top of her or
his head; the figure may be looking down.  The left arm is bent  
at the elbow with the left hand beneath the head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting crossed-legged</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised at 45 degrees</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>fingers spread</characteristic><characteristic>casting</characteristic><illusobjdesc>To the right of the word "of" in line 2 is a nude male with legs crossed.
He sits on a cloud.  His hair is long; he faces down and to the  
right.  He twists and leans to the right, with arms raised at 45 degrees     
(but horizontally relative to his body) and extended downward and 
to the right.  The fingers of both hands are spread and extended
as though he were casting down the slight indications of rain   
below.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="text" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>The words of the title are integrated into the      
design and seem to float on clouds.</illusobjdesc><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</l></lg></transcription></component><component type="text" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>The words of the motto and imprint are integrated   
into the design and seem to float on the sea below the two     
waves.</illusobjdesc><transcription><lg type="prose" justify="left"><l justify="left">The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.</l><l justify="left"> Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l></lg></transcription></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.c.illbk.02.01" justify="center">VISIONS</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.c.illbk.02.02" justify="center">of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.c.illbk.02.03" justify="center">the Daughters of</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.c.illbk.02.04" justify="center">Albion</l></lg><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="prose" justify="center"><l n="vda.c.illbk.02.05" justify="center">The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.02.06" justify="center">Printed by Will:<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Blake : 1793.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.03" dbi="vda.C.P3" compwith="bb136.B20"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A3">Object 3 </objnumber><objcode code="B3">(Bentley 3, </objcode><objcode code="Eiii">Erdman iii, </objcode><objcode code="Kiii">Keynes iii)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>14.2 x 11.2 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="738" width="582"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to
the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands
over her breasts.  Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun,
yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.  She appears
to be kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female.  This
second nude figure is seen from behind; her arms are extended
horizontally.  Her right foot is poised just above one of the two
flowers, probably marigolds, growing on a plant lower right.  Her
left leg is bent at the knee in a dance-like posture.  She seems
to hover in the air.  The kneeling figure is probably Oothoon,
the smaller figure probably the "nymph" who personifies the
marigold.  As the text on plate 4 explains, "Oothoon wandered in
woe, / Along the vales of Leutha seeking flowers to comfort her;
/ And thus she spoke to the bright Marygold of Leutha's vale /
Art though a flower! art thou a nymph! I see thee now a flower; /
Now a nymph! (lines 4-8).  Given this textual point of contact, the 
landscape is Leutha's Vale, also named in the text on this plate.
The hovering nymph may also be identified with Leutha (see 
"Leutha's flower," plate 3, line 6).  The small mound on which the figure
kneels is colored as though covered with grass.  Etched shafts of
radiance and complementary washes fill the sky; they would seem
to emanate from a sun just below the horizon on the right and    
perhaps in part from the marigold furthest to the right.  Higher
in the sky are slight suggestions of stratus clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>kneeling</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>bun</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>hands on breasts</characteristic><characteristic>arms crossed</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A young nude woman kneels on the ground and leans to
the right with her arms crossed in front of her and her hands    
over her breasts.  Her hair appears to be drawn back in a bun,   
yet a few strands of long hair curl down her back.  She appears 
to be kissing a much smaller figure, probably also female.  Given
the text on this and the next plate, she is almost certainly
Oothoon.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>dancing</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>kissing</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>nymph</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><characteristic>marigold</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, is seen from the    
back.  She hovers in the air, with her right foot poised just   
above a flower from which she may be rising.  Her arms are       
extended horizontally and her left knee bent forward.  This 
dance-like posture includes a gracefully twisted torso.  She    
appears to be kissing the much larger female on the left.  If so,
then her head may be bent back so that she is looking up.  Given the textual   
parallels for the design, this small figure is probably the      
"nymph" who personifies the marigold flower below her (plate 4, line 7).  
She may also be identified with Leutha (see "Leutha's flower," plate 3, line 6).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>plant</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><characteristic>flower</characteristic><characteristic>marigold</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>petal</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>spiky</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A low-growing plant, perhaps leafless, appears lower
right in the landscape.  Two arching stems terminate in large
flowers-probably the marigolds noted in the text on plate 4 
(line 6).  Their petals are spiky or flame-like.  These may be    
"Leutha's flower[s]" (plate 3, line 6).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>grass</characteristic><characteristic>Leutha</characteristic><characteristic>valley</characteristic><characteristic>mound</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The mound on which the figure kneels is colored as    
though covered with grass.  This is probably part of "Leutha's
vale" (plate 3, line 5).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Four etched lines of radiance and complementary    
washes fill the sky.  Most of the light seems to emanate from a
rising or setting sun just below the horizon on the right, but a
one ray may emerge from the flower also lower                   
right.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few horizontal lines in the sky just above the 
figures suggest stratus clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.01" justify="left" indent="4">The Argument</l></texthead><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.02" justify="left" indent="1">I loved Theotormon</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.03" justify="left">And I was not ashamed</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.04" justify="left" indent="1">I trembled in my virgin fears</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.05" justify="left">And I hid in Leutha's vale!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.06" justify="left" indent="1">I plucked Leutha's flower,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.07" justify="left">And I rose up from the vale;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.08" justify="left" indent="2">But the terrible thunders tore</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.03.09" justify="left" indent="2">My virgin mantle in twain.</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.04" dbi="vda.C.P4"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A4">Object 4 </objnumber><objcode code="B4">(Bentley 4, </objcode><objcode code="E1">Erdman 1, </objcode><objcode code="K1">Keynes 1)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.0 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="884" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Six figures sport in the sky surrounding the letters
of the heading ("Visions," line 1).  Top left, a nude figure, probably
female, sits on top of the first diagonal of the letter "V."  She
faces left, with her left knee bent and her right leg extended
below her.  She holds in her left hand and to her mouth a curved
horn; she is very probably playing this musical instrument.  To
the right, just above the first "i," is a billowing cloud with a
long trailing edge.  On it sits a figure who is probably female.
She shows slight indications of a gown or drapery, but may be
unclothed in this copy.  She sits on the cloud sidesaddle, as
though it were a horse.  Her legs are crossed and her head rests
on her left hand-a posture traditionally associated with
melancholy.  A small, winged figure stands in her lap.  We
apparently see this small, slender figure from behind, with both
arms and wings extended horizontally.  This figure was etched on 
the plate, and thus the impression in this copy (C) represents a
unique first-state impression of the plate.  Further to the right
are two energetic male nudes.  Both hover in the air with their
legs extended and their bodies twisted.  The male above the
letters "o" and "n" draws his bow, held in his right hand with
the bowstring pulled back by his left hand.  The arrow, pointed
down and to the left, has not yet been released.  His companion  
to the right holds his bow below him in his right hand.  Neither
a bowstring nor an arrow are pictured; perhaps he has just       
released the latter.  His left arm is bent and appears to reach
behind his head; perhaps he is reaching for another arrow (not  
pictured).  Below the final letter of the heading is a hovering
figure, very probably female.  The long hem of her gown trails  
off to the top right in several snake-like curves.  She faces to
the left, with at least one arm extended horizontally.  She may
be holding something in her left hand; a few vertical lines  
indicate that some liquid is falling from her hand or what she  
holds.  The washes in the sky, particularly top left, suggest
clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>horn</characteristic><characteristic>trumpet</characteristic><characteristic>playing</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, sits on top of the 
first diagonal of the letter "V" in the heading ("Visions," line 1).  She
faces left, with her left knee bent and her right leg extended
below her.  She holds in her left hand and to her mouth a curved
horn or trumpet; she is very probably playing this musical        
instrument.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>head on hand</characteristic><characteristic>melancholy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably female, sits on a cloud above the
letter "i" in the heading ("Visions," line 1).  She may be nude, but a
line just right of her lower left leg and perhaps the shape of  
her right elbow suggest a gown or drapery.  Her crossed legs      
dangle on one side of the cloud as though she were riding it    
sidesaddle.  Her head rests in her left hand in a posture        
traditionally representative of melancholy.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>standing</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>angel</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A small winged figure stands in the lap of the  
female seated on the cloud.  We apparently see this figure from 
behind.  She or he has both arms and wings extended horizontally.
Perhaps this is an angel.  This figure was etched on the plate,
and thus the impression in this copy is a unique first-state    
impression before this figure was removed from the                
copperplate.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>shooting</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>arrow</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male hovers above the letter "n" in the    
heading ("Visions," line 1).  One leg (the right?) is extended down and 
to the left; his body is twisted as he draws the string of his bow
next to his face with his left arm.  He holds the bow with his  
extended right arm.  He appears to be about to shoot the arrow  
clearly visible below and to the left of his right             
hand.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>shooting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>bow</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm drawn back</characteristic><characteristic>reaching</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male hovers above the final "s" in the       
heading ("Visions," line 1).  Like his companion to the left, he seems to
be shooting arrows, although none is pictured.  One leg (the
right?) is extended down and to the left.  His body is twisted,
with his left arm bent at the elbow and perhaps reaching behind him
for another arrow.  He holds his bow in his extended right hand. 
He appears to be facing down and to the left.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>hem</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>vial</characteristic><characteristic>liquid</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Below the final letter of the heading ("Visions," line 1) is
a hovering figure, very probably female.  The long hem of her    
gown trails off to the top right in several snake-like curves.   
She faces to the left, with at least one arm extended          
horizontally.  She may be holding something in her left hand,
perhaps a vial; a few vertical lines indicate that some liquid is
falling from her hand or what she holds.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure above the first "i" in line 1 sits 
on a long, billowing cloud.  Its upper right extension looks like
a tail.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Washes in the sky, particularly on the left, suggest
clouds.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="plate" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>Two nude figures sprawl in a rocky landscape.  The  
left-most figure appears to be female.  She lies on her back    
with her body twisted.  Her head is turned downwards and her arms
extended horizontally.  On the right is a muscular male, also  
lying on his back, with knees bent, and his right arm extended  
horizontally.  One knee is raised, the other turned to the left. 
His barely-visible head leans backwards.  Both figures may be   
exhausted or dead.  These figures may be Oothoon and Bromion    
after the latter has raped Oothoon.  On the left are some         
ill-defined forms that may be stones or a pile of discarded
clothing.  The figures rest on low hills, perhaps covered with    
grass.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>exhausted</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude figure, probably female, lies supine with her long hair spread out on the ground.  Her    
body is twisted, with her head turned back and downwards.  Her  
arms are extended horizontally.  Her right leg is extended and
bent at the knee.  This posture suggests a dead body or perhaps
Oothoon exhausted after being raped by Bromion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>muscular</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><characteristic>corpse</characteristic><characteristic>exhausted</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A muscular nude male lies supine.  His right arm is
extended horizontally and his barely-visible head twisted
backward.  His legs are bent at the knees; the left leg is lifted
vertically and his right leg turned down and to the left.  This
posture suggests that the figure is dead-or perhaps Bromion
exhausted after he has raped Oothoon.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>hill</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>grass</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The landscape is dominated by low hills or large stones, perhaps     
covered with grass.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>clothing</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The ill-defined objects left of the figure's        
extended left arm may be stones or a pile of discarded           
clothing.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="A"><illusobjdesc>Two vines extend upward from the beginning of line 3.  The lower vine arches to the
right.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="A"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Two vines extend upward from the beginning of line 3.  The lower vine arches to the
right.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="AC"><illusobjdesc>Vines, perhaps with leaves, extend into the left
margin from lines 7 and 11.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AC"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Vines, perhaps with leaves, extend into the left
margin from lines 7 and 11.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.01" justify="left" indent="25">Visions</l></texthead><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.02" justify="left" indent="1">Enslav'd, the Daughters of Albion weep; a trembling lamentation</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.03" justify="left" indent="1">Upon their mountains; in their valleys, sighs toward America,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.04" justify="left">For the soft soul of America, Oothoon wanderd in woe,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.05" justify="left">Along the vales of Leutha seeking flowers to comfort her:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.06" justify="left">And thus she spoke to the bright Marygold of Leutha's vale</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.07" justify="left" indent="8">Art thou a flower! art thou a nymph! I see thee now a flower;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.08" justify="left" indent="8">Now a nymph! I dare not pluck thee from thy dewy bed!</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.09" justify="left" indent="61">(mild</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.10" justify="left" indent="10">The Golden nymph replied; pluck thou my flower Oothoon the</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.11" justify="left" indent="10">Another flower shall spring. because the soul of sweet delight</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.12" justify="left" indent="10">Can never pass away, she ceas'd &amp; closd her golden shrine.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.13" justify="left">Then Oothoon pluck'd the flower saying, I pluck thee from thy bed </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.14" justify="left">Sweet flower. and put thee here to glow between my breasts</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.15" justify="left">And thus I turn my face to where my whole soul seeks.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.16" justify="left">Over the waves she went in wing'd exulting swift delight;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.17" justify="left">And over Theotormons reign, took her impetuous course.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.18" justify="left">Bromion rent her with his thunders. on his stormy bed</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.19" justify="left">Lay the faint maid, and soon her woes appalld his thunders hoarse</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.20" justify="left">Bromion spoke. behold this harlot here on Bromions bed.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.21" justify="left">And let the jealous dolphins sport around the lovely maid;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.22" justify="left">Thy soft American plains are mine, and mine thy north &amp; south:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.23" justify="left">Stampt with my signet are the swarthy children of the sun:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.24" justify="left">They are obedient, they resist not, they obey the scourge:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.04.25" justify="left">Their daughters worship terrors and obey the violent:</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.05" dbi="vda.C.P5"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A5">Object 5 </objnumber><objcode code="B5">(Bentley 5, </objcode><objcode code="E2">Erdman 2, </objcode><objcode code="K2">Keynes 2)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.1 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="889" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A male nude lies prone on the ground.  He faces
down, with his right arm extended to the left and bent at the
elbow.  His right hand is on the ground, as though to support
himself.  He may be trying to rise.  His left arm, also bent at the
elbow, extends below his head.  One leg is extended to
the right, the other bent at the knee.  Given his dark coloring, he may be an African slave
(see "slaves beneath the sun," line 10).  Right of the figure is a
leafless tree, bent over to the right.  A pickax rests against
the trunk of the tree.  A vine with a few ivy-like leaves extends
horizontally to the left from the trunk of the tree near the
pickax and toward the figure.  Another vine with leaves extends
vertically over the trunk of the tree right of the
pickax.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>dark-skinned</characteristic><characteristic>African</characteristic><characteristic>slave</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>arm braced</characteristic><characteristic>hand on ground</characteristic><characteristic>rising</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A male nude lies in a twisted but basically prone posture on the ground.  He faces
down, with his right arm extended to the left and bent at the
elbow.  His right hand is on the ground, as though to support
him.  He may be trying to rise.  His left arm, also bent at the
elbow, extends below his head.  One leg is extended to
the right, the other bent at the knee.  Given his dark coloring, he may be an African slave (see "slaves beneath the sun," line 10).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>tree</characteristic><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leafless</characteristic><characteristic>dead</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A tree leans sharply to the right.  Its branches,
far right, are leafless; it may be dead.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>ivy</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine grows horizontally from the trunk of the tree
and extends to the left.  A few ivy-like leaves appear near its
left end.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="vegetation" location="B"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A vine with a few leaves extends vertically across
the trunk of the tree right of the pickax.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>pickax</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A pickax leans against the trunk of the        
tree.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Washes in the sky suggest thin clouds behind the
figure and the tree.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="A"><illusobjdesc>A nude female falls head-first in the left margin of
the text.  Her legs are spread, with the left leg extended
vertically and the right leg bent to the right.  Her arms appear
to be extended downward; perhaps she has long hair which is also
dangling down.  Above and to the left of her left leg is the
outline of a cloud.  Another cloud outline appears below her,
just to the left of lines 16-18 in the text.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>falling</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>arms down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female falls head-first in the left margin of
the text.  Her legs are spread, with the left leg extended
vertically and the right leg bent to the right.  Her arms appear
to be extended downward; perhaps she has long hair which is also
dangling down.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The outline of a cloud appears above and to the left
of the falling figure's left leg.  Another cloud outline appears
below her, just to the left of lines 16-18 in the
text.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.01" justify="left" indent="56"><physnumber type="etched">2</physnumber></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.02" justify="left">Now thou maist marry Bromions harlot, and protect the child</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.03" justify="left">Of Bromions rage, that Oothoon shall put forth in nine moons</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.04" justify="left" indent="50">time</l></lg><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.05" justify="left">Then storms rent Theotormons limbs; he rolld his waves around.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.06" justify="left">And folded his black jealous waters round the adulterate pair</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.07" justify="left">Bound back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.08" justify="left">At entrance Theotormon sits wearing the threshold hard</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.09" justify="left">With secret tears; beneath him sound like waves on a desart shore </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.10" justify="left">The voice of slaves beneath the sun, and children bought with money,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.11" justify="left">That shiver in religious caves beneath the burning fires</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.12" justify="left">Of lust, that belch incessant from the summits of the earth</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.13" justify="left">Oothoon weeps not; she cannot weep! her tears are locked up;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.14" justify="left">But she can howl incessant writhing her soft snowy limbs.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.15" justify="left">And calling Theotormons Eagles to prey upon her flesh.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.16" justify="left">I call with holy voice! kings of the sounding air,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.17" justify="left">Rend away this defiled bosom that I may reflect,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.18" justify="left">The image of Theotormon on my pure transparent breast.</l></lg><vspace extent="3"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.19" justify="left">The Eagles at her call descend &amp; rend their bleeding prey;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.20" justify="left">Theotormon severely smiles. her soul reflects the smile;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.21" justify="left">As the clear spring mudded with feet of beasts grows pure &amp; smiles</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.22" justify="left">The Daughters of Albion hear her woes. &amp; eccho back her sighs.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.23" justify="left">Why does my Theotormon sit weeping upon the threshold:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.24" justify="left">And Oothoon hovers by his side, perswading him in vain:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.25" justify="left">I cry arise O Theotormon for the village dog</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.26" justify="left">Barks at the breaking day. the nightingale has done lamenting,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.27" justify="left">The lark does rustle in the ripe corn, and the Eagle returns</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.28" justify="left">From nightly prey, and lifts his golden beak to the pure east;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.29" justify="left">Shaking the dust from his immortal pinions to awake</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.30" justify="left">The sun that sleeps too long.  Arise my Theotormon I am pure.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.31" justify="left">Because the night is gone that clos'd me in its deadly black.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.32" justify="left">They told me that the night &amp; day were all that I could see;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.33" justify="left">They told me that I had five senses to inclose me up.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.34" justify="left">And they inclos'd my infinite brain into a narrow circle,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.35" justify="left">And sunk my heart into the Abyss, a red round globe hot burning </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.36" justify="left">Till all from life I was obliterated and erased.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.37" justify="left">Instead of morn arises a bright shadow, like an eye</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.38" justify="left">In the eastern cloud; instead of night a sickly charnel house;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.39" justify="left">That Theotormon hears me not! to him the night and morn</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.05.40" justify="left">Are both alike: a night of sighs, a morning of fresh tears;</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.06" dbi="vda.C.P6"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A6">Object 6 </objnumber><objcode code="B6">(Bentley 6, </objcode><objcode code="E3">Erdman 3, </objcode><objcode code="K3">Keynes 3)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.8 x 11.6 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="874" width="603"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>A nude female lies supine on a cloud.  Her left arm
is extended horizontally to the right (but raised vertically relative to her body).  Her long
hair can be seen above her left forearm.  Her head is thrown back
and her belly exposed.  Her legs are spread apart and bent back
sharply at the knees so we see only her upper legs.  This posture
suggests erotic (or at least highly emotional) abandon.  Above
her hovers a large bird, probably an eagle.  The bird seems to
descend upon the female, with its beak touching her torso between
her stomach and breasts.  Above the female's head and above and
below the bird's wings is another cloud-or an extension of the
cloud on which the female lies.  The female is probably Oothoon
since, on plate 5, she is described as "calling" upon
"Theotormons Eagles to prey upon her flesh" (line 15).</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>supine</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>erotic</characteristic><characteristic>head bent back</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>legs bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female lies supine on a cloud.  Her left arm
is extended horizontally to the right (but raised vertically relative to her body).  Her long
hair can be seen above her left forearm.  Her head is thrown back
and her belly exposed.  Her legs are spread apart and bent back
sharply at the knees so we see only her upper legs.  This posture
suggests erotic (or at least highly emotional) abandon.  She is
probably Oothoon who, on plate 5, is described as "calling" upon
"Theotormons Eagles to prey upon her flesh" (line 15).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="animal" location="CD"><characteristic>bird</characteristic><characteristic>eagle</characteristic><characteristic>wing</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>preying</characteristic><characteristic>beak</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A large bird, probably one of "Theotormons Eagles" 
that Oothoon calls on to "prey upon her flesh" (plate 5, line 15), hovers over
the supine female.  Its wings extend horizontally; its head faces
downward toward the woman.  The bird's beak touches her        
torso; its prominent tail is slightly forked.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The nude female lies supine on a cloud.  Either an
extension of this cloud, or a second cloud, can be seen above her
head and above and below the bird's wings.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.01" justify="left" indent="56"><physnumber type="etched">3</physnumber></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.02" justify="left">And none but Bromion can hear my lamentations.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.03" justify="left">With what sense is it that the chicken shuns the ravenous hawk?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.04" justify="left">With what sense does the tame pigeon measure out the expanse?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.05" justify="left">With what sense does the bee form cells? have not the mouse &amp; frog</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.06" justify="left">Eyes and ears and sense of touch? yet are their habitations.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.07" justify="left">And their pursuits, as different as their forms and as their joys:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.08" justify="left">Ask the wild ass why he refuses burdens: and the meek camel</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.09" justify="left">Why he loves man; is it because of eye ear mouth or skin</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.10" justify="left">Or breathing nostrils? No, for these the wolf and tyger have.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.11" justify="left">Ask the blind worm the secrets of the grave, and why her spires</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.12" justify="left">Love to curl round the bones of death! and ask the rav'nous snake </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.13" justify="left">Where she gets poison: &amp; the wing'd eagle why he loves the sun</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.14" justify="left">And then tell me the thoughts of man, that have been hid of old.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.15" justify="left">Silent I hover all the night, and all day could be silent,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.16" justify="left">If Theotormon once would turn his loved eyes upon me;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.17" justify="left">How can I be defild when I reflect thy image pure?<space extent="9"/>(woe</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.18" justify="left">Sweetest the fruit that the worm feeds on. &amp; the soul prey'd on by</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.19" justify="left">The new wash'd lamb ting'd with the village smoke &amp; the bright swan</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.20" justify="left">By the red earth of our immortal river; I bathe my wings,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.21" justify="left">And I am white and pure to hover round Theotormons breast.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.22" justify="left">Then Theotormon broke his silence, and he answered.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.23" justify="left">Tell me what is the night or day to one o'erflowd with woe?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.24" justify="left">Tell me what is a thought? &amp; of what substance is it made?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.25" justify="left">Tell me what is a joy? &amp; in what gardens do joys grow?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.06.26" justify="left">And in what rivers swim the sorrows? and upon what mountains</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.07" dbi="vda.C.P7" compwith="bb85.B4"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A7">Object 7 </objnumber><objcode code="B7">(Bentley 7, </objcode><objcode code="E4">Erdman 4, </objcode><objcode code="K4">Keynes 4)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.0 x 11.5 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="884" width="598"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Two figures appear on the seashore.  One figure,
probably male, is seated on the sand or stones near the water.
He wears a long gown that covers his knees and lower legs.  We
see him from the front; his knees are drawn up to his upper chest
in a very contracted posture.  Given the position of his right
foot, his legs are probably crossed at the ankles.  His hands
rest upon his knees, and in turn his head is bent forward and
rests upon his hands.  We see only the top of his head, covered
with curly hair.  This is probably Theotormon, "weeping" (plate 5, 
line 23) near "the margind ocean" (plate 11, line 13).  To the left is a giant wave,
shaped like a tongue of flame.  Within this wave is a nude
female, shackled and chained on her left ankle.  Her right leg is
apparently extended behind her left.  She arches to the right, 
with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands clasped together
just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
supplication.  She faces down and apparently looks at the         
self-enclosed male below her.  Her long hair drifts behind her neck
and back.  She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover.
Right and left of the wave in which she appears is a rocky cliff.
Wavy lines along the lower margin of the design below both
figures suggest small waves of the sea.  Far right is the sea,
showing a few indications of waves, and a cloudy sky suggesting a
storm.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>crying</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting cross-legged</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>right foot</characteristic><characteristic>legs crossed</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>hands on knees</characteristic><characteristic>head on hands</characteristic><characteristic>head on knees</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure, probably male, is seated on the sand or
stones near the water.  He wears a long gown that covers his
knees and lower legs.  We see him from the front; his knees are
drawn up to his upper chest in a very contracted posture.  Given
the position of his right foot, his legs are probably crossed at
the ankles.  His hands rest upon his knees, and in turn his head
is bent forward and rests upon his hands.  We see only the top of
his head, covered with curly hair.  This is probably Theotormon,
"weeping" (plate 5, line 23) near "the margind ocean" (plate 11, line 13).</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>shackled</characteristic><characteristic>chained</characteristic><characteristic>hands together</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>praying</characteristic><characteristic>supplicating</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><characteristic>arching</characteristic><characteristic>twisted</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Within a tongue- or flame-like wave is a nude
female, shackled and chained on her left ankle.  Her right leg is
apparently extended behind her left.  She arches to the right,
with her arms bent at the elbows and her hands clasped together
just below her neck in a gesture that suggests prayer or
supplication.  She faces down and apparently looks at the
self-enclosed male below her.  Her long hair drifts behind her neck
and back.  She is very probably Oothoon, pleading to her lover
Theotormon.  Although her mouth is not clearly open, she may be
speaking.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="A"><characteristic>shackle</characteristic><characteristic>chain</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The left foot of the female figure is shackled and chained.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>seashore</characteristic><characteristic>cliff</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The landscape shows a cliff on the left near the 
seashore.  Both stones and sand may be represented below the     
seated figure.  The lower margin of the design has wavy lines 
indicating small waves of the sea.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="B"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The dark waters of the sea on the right show indications of waves.  Above and to the right is a dark and cloudy sky suggesting a   
storm.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>waves</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>tongue</characteristic><characteristic>flame-like</characteristic><characteristic>fire</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The female is pictured within a giant wave of dark water which, in its shape, resembles a tongue-of a creature or of            
fire.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="D"><illusobjdesc>The shape following line 6 might represent a branch bearing a leaf.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="D"><characteristic>branch</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The shape following line 6 might represent a branch bearing a leaf.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.01" justify="left">Wave shadows of discontent? and in what houses dwell the wretched </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.02" justify="left">Drunken with woe forgotten. and shut up from cold despair,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.03" justify="left">Tell me where dwell the thoughts forgotten till thou call them forth </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.04" justify="left">Tell me where dwell the joys of old? &amp; where the ancient loves?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.05" justify="left">And when will they renew again &amp; the night of oblivion past?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.06" justify="left">That I might traverse times &amp; spaces far remote and bring</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.07" justify="left">Comforts into a present sorrow and a night of pain</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.08" justify="left">Where goest thou O thought! to what remote land is thy flight?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.09" justify="left">If thou returnest to the present moment of affliction</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.10" justify="left">Wilt thou bring comforts on thy wings, and dews and honey and balm,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.11" justify="left">Or poison from the desart wilds, from the eyes of the envier.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.12" justify="left">Then Bromion said: and shook the cavern with his lamentation</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.13" justify="left">Thou knowest that the ancient trees seen by thine eyes have fruit;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.14" justify="left">But knowest thou that trees and fruits flourish upon the earth</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.15" justify="left">To gratify senses unknown? trees beasts and birds unknown:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.16" justify="left">Unknown, not unpercievd, spread in the infinite microscope,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.17" justify="left">In places yet unvisited by the voyager. and in worlds</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.18" justify="left">Over another kind of seas, and in atmospheres unknown.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.19" justify="left">Ah! are there other wars, beside the wars of sword and fire!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.20" justify="left">And are there other sorrows, beside the sorrows of poverty?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.21" justify="left">And are there other joys, beside the joys of riches and ease?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.22" justify="left">And is there not one law for both the lion and the ox?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.23" justify="left">And is there not eternal fire, and eternal chains?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.24" justify="left">To bind the phantoms of existence from eternal life?</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.07.25" justify="left">Then Oothoon waited silent all the day, and all the night,</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.08" dbi="vda.C.P8"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A8">Object 8 </objnumber><objcode code="B8">(Bentley 8, </objcode><objcode code="E5">Erdman 5, </objcode><objcode code="K5">Keynes 5)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>17.2 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="894" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="CD"><illusobjdesc>A figure lies huddled on the ground.  Given the long
hair and drapery, the figure is probably female.  Her gown (or a cloak or blanket) covers her legs and hips, but her back may be bare.  She is basically prone, but the position of her legs is unclear because of the
heavy drapery.  We see only the back of her head; her left arm
curls around in front of her head and rests on the pillow or
stone into which her face seems buried.  A snake-like tail
extends from the lower left corner of this pillow or stone; this
may be part of the drapery covering the figure.  She may be Oothoon in
despair.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="CD"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>cloak</characteristic><characteristic>blanket</characteristic><characteristic>partly nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>drapery</characteristic><characteristic>lying</characteristic><characteristic>prone</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing away</characteristic><characteristic>seen from behind</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm bent</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A figure lies huddled on the ground.  Given the long
hair and drapery, the figure is probably female.  Her gown (or cloak or blanket) covers her legs and hips, but her back may be bare.  She is basically prone, but the position of her legs is unclear because of the
heavy drapery.  We see only the back of her head; her left arm
curls around her head and rests on the pillow or stone into which
her face seems buried.  She may be Oothoon in
despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>pillow</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The figure has her face pressed against a pillow or
stone.  A snake-like tail extends from the lower left corner of
this pillow or stone; this may be part of the figure's        
drapery.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration><illustration type="interlinear" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>A long vine, perhaps a grape vine, wends its way
horizontally between lines 3 and 4.  A 
tendril on the left forms a spiral of three loops; the vine ends
on the right with many loops suggestive of (but not quite
forming) a spiral.  Five (grape?) leaves are
pictured.</illusobjdesc><component type="vegetation" location="AB"><characteristic>vine</characteristic><characteristic>grape</characteristic><characteristic>leaf</characteristic><characteristic>loop</characteristic><characteristic>spiral</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A long vine, perhaps a grape vine, wends its way
horizontally between lines 3 and 4.  A 
tendril on the left forms a spiral of three loops; the vine ends
on the right with many loops suggestive of (but not quite
forming) a spiral.  Five (grape?) leaves are
pictured.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.01" justify="left" indent="58"><physnumber type="etched">5</physnumber><note>The etched number "5" is very poorly printed in this copy.</note></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.02" justify="left">But when the morn arose, her lamentation renewd,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.03" justify="left">The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.</l></lg><vspace extent="2"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.04" justify="left">O Urizen! Creator of men! mistaken Demon of heaven;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.05" justify="left">Thy joys are tears! thy labour vain, to form men to thine image.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.06" justify="left">How can one joy absorb another? are not different joys</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.07" justify="left">Holy, eternal, infinite! and each joy is a Love.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.08" justify="left">Does not the great mouth laugh at a gift? &amp; the narrow eyelids mock </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.09" justify="left">At the labour that is above payment, and wilt thou take the ape</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.10" justify="left">For thy councellor? or the dog. for a schoolmaster to thy children?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.11" justify="left">Does he who contemns poverty, and he who turns with abhorrence</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.12" justify="left">From usury: feel the same passion or are they moved alike?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.13" justify="left">How can the giver of gifts experience the delights of the merchant?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.14" justify="left">How the industrious citizen the pains of the husbandman.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.15" justify="left">How different far the fat fed hireling with hollow drum;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.16" justify="left">Who buys whole corn fields into wastes, and sings upon the heath.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.17" justify="left">How different their eye and ear! how different the world to them!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.18" justify="left">With what sense does the parson claim the labour of the farmer?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.19" justify="left">What are his nets &amp; gins &amp; traps. &amp; how does he surround him</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.20" justify="left">With cold floods of abstraction, and with forests of solitude,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.21" justify="left">To build him castles and high spires, where kings &amp; priests may dwell.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.22" justify="left">Till she who burns with youth, and knows no fixed lot; is bound </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.23" justify="left">In spells of law to one she loaths: and must she drag the chain </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.24" justify="left">Of life, in weary lust! must chilling murderous thoughts, obscure </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.25" justify="left">The clear heaven of her eternal spring! to bear the wintry rage</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.26" justify="left">Of a harsh terror driv'n to madness, bound to hold a rod</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.27" justify="left">Over her shrinking shoulders all the day; &amp; all the night</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.28" justify="left">To turn the wheel of false desire: and longings that wake her womb</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.29" justify="left">To the abhorred birth of cherubs in the human form</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.30" justify="left">That live a pestilence &amp; die a meteor &amp; are no more.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.31" justify="left">Till the child dwell with one he hates, and do the deed he loaths</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.32" justify="left">And the impure scourge force his seed into its unripe birth</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.33" justify="left">E'er yet his eyelids can behold the arrows of the day.</l></lg><vspace extent="3"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.34" justify="left">Does the whale worship at thy footsteps as the hungry dog?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.35" justify="left">Or does he scent the mountain prey, because his nostrils wide</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.36" justify="left">Draw in the ocean? does his eye discern the flying cloud</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.37" justify="left">As the ravens eye? or does he measure the expanse like the vulture?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.38" justify="left">Does the still spider view the cliffs where eagles hide their young?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.39" justify="left">Or does the fly rejoice. because the harvest is brought in?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.40" justify="left">Does not the eagle scorn the earth &amp; despise the treasures beneath?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.41" justify="left">But the mole knoweth what is there, &amp; the worm shall tell it thee.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.08.42" justify="left">Does not the worm erect a pillar in the mouldering church yard?</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.09" dbi="vda.C.P9"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A9">Object 9 </objnumber><objcode code="B9">(Bentley 9, </objcode><objcode code="E6">Erdman 6, </objcode><objcode code="K6">Keynes 6)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>15.9 x 11.7 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="827" width="608"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a cloud and holds a whip with
three tails in his left hand.  His left upper arm is raised
vertically, with his forearm bent to the left over his head.  His
right arm is raised and arches over his head; he clutches his 
forehead with his right hand.  His left leg is extended, his
right bent at the knee.  Both his facial features and his
head-clutching gesture suggest despair.  To the right is a female
nude.  She strides, legs spread apart, forward and to the right.
Her arms are bent, with her hands clutching her face and head.
She is facing down and we see only the top of her head.  Her long
hair trails over her right shoulder.  She too may be supported by
the cloud on which the male sits, although perhaps we are meant
to think of her as hovering in the air.  Most of the disc of the
sun can be seen lower right; beams of light emanate from it.
Some of the washes defining this radiance extends up the right
margin of the text.  The female is very probably Oothoon; the
male may be Bromion, in his character as a slave owner, about to
strike the woman.  Alternatively, he may be Theotormon as a       
self-flagellant.  No such scene is described in the
text.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="C"><characteristic>male</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>Bromion</characteristic><characteristic>Theotormon</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised vertically</characteristic><characteristic>short hair</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>whipping</characteristic><characteristic>slave owner</characteristic><characteristic>self-flagellant</characteristic><characteristic>leg extended</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><characteristic>hand clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude male sits on a dark cloud and holds a whip
with three tails in his left hand.  His left upper arm is raised
vertically, with his forearm bent to the left over his head.  His
right arm is raised and arches over his head; he clutches his
forehead with his right hand.  His left leg is extended, his
right bent at the knee.  His body faces forward but his head is turned to the right.  His hair
is short and perhaps a little curly.  Both his facial features
and his head-clutching gesture suggest despair.  He may be
Bromion, in his character as a slave owner, about to strike the
woman on the right.  Alternatively, he may be Theotormon as a
self-flagellant.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>striding</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>legs spread</characteristic><characteristic>arms bent</characteristic><characteristic>hands clutching head</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A nude female strides, legs spread apart, forward
and to the right.  Her arms are bent, with her hands clutching
her face and head.  She is facing down and we see only the top of
her head.  Her long hair trails over her right shoulder.
She may be supported by the cloud below her left foot, although
perhaps we are meant to think of her as hovering in the air.  She
is very probably Oothoon in despair.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="C"><characteristic>whip</characteristic><characteristic>tail</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><characteristic>knot</characteristic><characteristic>spike</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male holds a whip with three snake-like tails.
Each tail appears to terminate in a knot or cluster of           
spikes.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The male sits on a cloud.  At least the left foot of
the female may also rest on this cloud.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="D"><characteristic>sun</characteristic><characteristic>sunrise</characteristic><characteristic>sunset</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Most of the disc of the sun can be seen in the lower 
right corner of the plate, just above a cloud.  Perhaps this is a
sunrise or sunset.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>beams of light</characteristic><characteristic>radiance</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Beams of light emanate from the sun in the lower
right corner of the plate.  The washes defining this radiance
extend behind the figures and up the right margin of the plate to
line 5.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.01" justify="left" indent="58"><physnumber type="etched">6</physnumber></l></texthead><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.02" justify="left">And a palace of eternity in the jaws of the hungry grave</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.03" justify="left">Over his porch these words are written. Take thy bliss O Man!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.04" justify="left">And sweet shall be thy taste &amp; sweet thy infant joys renew!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.05" justify="left">Infancy, fearless, lustful, happy! nestling for delight</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.06" justify="left">In laps of pleasure; Innocence! honest, open, seeking</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.07" justify="left">The vigorous joys of morning light; open to virgin bliss.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.08" justify="left">Who taught thee modesty, subtil modesty! child of night &amp; sleep </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.09" justify="left">When thou awakest. wilt thou dissemble all thy secret joys</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.10" justify="left">Or wert thou not awake when all this mystery was disclos'd!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.11" justify="left">Then com'st thou forth a modest virgin knowing to dissemble</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.12" justify="left">With nets found under thy night pillow, to catch virgin joy,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.13" justify="left">And brand it with the name of whore; &amp; sell it in the night,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.14" justify="left">In silence, ev'n without a whisper, and in seeming sleep;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.15" justify="left">Religious dreams and holy vespers, light thy smoky fires:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.16" justify="left">Once were thy fires lighted by the eyes of honest morn</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.17" justify="left">And does my Theotormon seek this hypocrite modesty!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.18" justify="left">This knowing, artful, secret, fearful, cautious, trembling hypocrite. </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.19" justify="left">Then is Oothoon a whore indeed! and all the virgin joys</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.20" justify="left">Of life are harlots; and Theotormon is a sick mans dream</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.21" justify="left">And Oothoon is the crafty slave of selfish holiness.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.22" justify="left">But Oothoon is not so, a virgin fill'd with virgin fancies</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.23" justify="left">Open to joy and to delight where ever beauty appears</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.09.24" justify="left">If in the morning sun I find it: there my eyes are fix'd</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.10" dbi="vda.C.P10" compwith="bb136.B17"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A10">Object 10 </objnumber><objcode code="B10">(Bentley 10, </objcode><objcode code="E7">Erdman 7, </objcode><objcode code="K7">Keynes 7)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.9 x 12.0 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="879" width="624"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="AB"><illusobjdesc>Four (possibly five) female figures huddle together
in contracted postures.  The four clearly pictured wear gowns.
The figure on the right squats with knees drawn up toward her
chest; her head leans forward onto her knees and we see only the
top of her head.  Her hair is long.  The figure in the center
foreground faces to the right, with her knees drawn up and her
upper body leaning forward.  Her right knee and lower leg cover
her face; we see only her head and long hair.  Above this central
figure and slightly behind are the shoulders and face of a woman
with long hair (spread out on both sides of her head) and a
desperate expression on her face.  Her hands are raised to her
shoulders with palms turned upward.  Her eyes look up.  The       
left-most figure  faces left.  Her upper body is bent over her legs
in a severely contracted posture.  Her head is on the far left,
bent low over her extended left arm.  Above this figure is an 
indeterminate cluster of wavy lines that may be the hair of a
fifth female figure.  These females are probably the Daughters of
Albion.  The sky above the figures is filled with dark
clouds.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="B"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female in a very contracted posture squats
on the ground.  Her large knees are drawn up to her chest; her
head is bent forward and rests on her knees.  We see only the top
of her head and long blonde hair.  She is probably one of the   
Daughters of Albion in this huddled group of four or five    
females.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>facing right</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>leg drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>leg bent at knee</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A gowned female sits in a contracted posture as the
front-most figure in the huddled group.  She faces to the right,
with her right knee drawn up and her upper body bent forward.
Her face is covered by her right knee and lower leg; we see only
her head and long, dark hair.  She is probably one of the
Daughters of Albion in this group of four or five
figures.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="AB"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>eyes raised</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>despair</characteristic><characteristic>hands raised, palms up</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Behind two other figures, we see the shoulders,
hands, and face of a gowned female.  Her long hair extends
horizontally on either side of her head.  Her face and eyes are
turned upward; her facial expression suggests despair.  Her hands
are raised to her shoulders, palms turned upward.  She is
probably one of the Daughters of Albion, sitting with others in
this huddled group.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>bending forward</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>arm dangling</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>On the far left of the huddled group of figures is a
gowned female with her upper body bent over her legs in an      
extremely contracted posture.  She faces to the left, with her  
head bent down and resting on her left arm.  Her left arm, and particularly her left hand, dangle to the left.  Her hair is probably
long.  She is probably one of the Daughters of                   
Albion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="A"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>curly hair</characteristic><characteristic>head down</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A few wavy lines, just above the left-most figure in
this huddled group of figures, may be the lowered head, curly(?)
hair, and shoulders of a fifth female.  She is probably one of
the Daughters of Albion, like the others in this                
group.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="AB"><characteristic>sky</characteristic><characteristic>night</characteristic><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>dark</characteristic><characteristic>storm</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting for the huddled figures consists of
a (night?) sky filled with dark clouds suggesting a
storm.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><vspace extent="1"/><texthead justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.01" justify="left" indent="60"><physnumber type="etched">7</physnumber><note>The etched number "7" is partially obscured by coloring.</note></l></texthead><vspace extent="6"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.02" justify="left">In happy copulation; if in evening mild. wearied with work;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.03" justify="left">Sit on a bank and draw the pleasures of this free born joy.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.04" justify="left" indent="2">The moment of desire! the moment of desire! The virgin</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.05" justify="left">That pines for man; shall awaken her womb to enormous joys</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.06" justify="left">In the secret shadows of her chamber; the youth shut up from</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.07" justify="left">The lustful joy, shall forget to generate. &amp; create an amorous image</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.08" justify="left">In the shadows of his curtains and in the folds of his silent pillow.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.09" justify="left">Are not these the places of religion? the rewards of continence!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.10" justify="left">The self enjoyings of self denial? Why dost thou seek religion?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.11" justify="left">Is it because acts are not lovely, that thou seekest solitude,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.12" justify="left">Where the horrible darkness is impressed with reflections of desire.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.13" justify="left">Father of Jealousy, be thou accursed from the earth!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.14" justify="left">Why hast thou taught my Theotormon this accursed thing?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.15" justify="left">Till beauty fades from off my shoulders darken'd and cast out,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.16" justify="left">A solitary shadow wailing on the margin of non-entity.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.17" justify="left">I cry, Love! Love! Love! happy happy Love! free as the mountain wind!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.18" justify="left">Can that be Love, that drinks another as a sponge drinks water?</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.19" justify="left">That clouds with jealousy his nights, with weepings all the day; </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.20" justify="left">To spin a web of age around him, grey and hoary! dark!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.21" justify="left">Till his eyes sicken at the fruit that hangs before his sight.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.22" justify="left">Such is self-love that envies all! a creeping skeleton</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.23" justify="left">With lamplike eyes watching around the frozen marriage bed.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.24" justify="left">But silken nets and traps of adamant will Oothoon spread,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.25" justify="left">And catch for thee girls of mild silver, or of furious gold:</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.26" justify="left">I'll lie beside thee on a bank &amp; view their wanton play</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.27" justify="left">In lovely copulation bliss on bliss with Theotormon;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.28" justify="left">Red as the rosy morning, lustful as the first born beam,</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.29" justify="left">Oothoon shall view his dear delight, nor e'er with jealous cloud </l><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.30" justify="left">Come in the heaven of generous love; nor selfish blightings bring.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.10.31" justify="left">Does the sun walk in glorious raiment, on the secret floor</l></lg></phystext></desc><desc id="vda.c.illbk.11" dbi="vda.C.P11"><objtitle>,
<objid><objnumber code="A11">Object 11 </objnumber><objcode code="B11">(Bentley 11, </objcode><objcode code="E8">Erdman 8, </objcode><objcode code="K8">Keynes 8)</objcode></objid></objtitle><physdesc desclevel="brief"><objsize>16.9 x 11.8 cm.</objsize><windowsize height="879" width="614"/></physdesc><illusdesc><illustration type="plate" location="E"><illusobjdesc>The design would appear to illustrate line 14: "The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho
back her [Oothoon's] sighs."  Three gowned female
figures-the Daughters of Albion-huddle together on the seashore,
lower right.  The right-most figure in the group has her legs drawn
up in a sitting or squatting position similar to her companions.
She looks up and to the left at the figure hovering above.  Her
companion to the left also looks up and to the left.  Both legs
are drawn up; her right arm is extended horizontally to the
right, with her right hand resting on her companion's left 
shoulder.  The left-most figure in the group has both legs drawn
up and her head lowered; we see only the top of her head.  All 
three females have long hair.  Above the group and to the left is
Oothoon, hovering in the air or on a cloud.  We see only her
unclothed chest, head facing forward, long hair streaming out on
both sides of her head, and long arms extended horizontally.  Her
hands seem to rest on or hold the cloud.  Flames emanate from
just below her chest and extend over both arms.  The sea, lower
left, includes some waves.</illusobjdesc><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>feet</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>One of the Daughters of Albion huddles in a seated
or squatting position, the right-most figure in a group of three
gowned women.  Her legs are drawn up to her chest.  She faces to
the left and looks up at the hovering figure above.  Her long
hair cascades over her left shoulder.  Both feet can be seen just
below the hem of her gown.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>left foot</characteristic><characteristic>arm raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><characteristic>facing left</characteristic><characteristic>facing up</characteristic><characteristic>looking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>One of the Daughters of Albion sits in the center of
the group of three huddled women who sit or squat on the
seashore. Like her companions, she is gowned.
Both legs are drawn up toward her chest.  Her left foot appears
just below the hem of her gown.  Her right arm extends
horizontally to the right and her right hand rests on the left
shoulder of her companion on the right.  She faces left and looks
up to the hovering figure above.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="D"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>gown</characteristic><characteristic>Daughters of Albion</characteristic><characteristic>huddled</characteristic><characteristic>sitting</characteristic><characteristic>squatting</characteristic><characteristic>contracted</characteristic><characteristic>knees</characteristic><characteristic>facing down</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>legs drawn up</characteristic><illusobjdesc>One of the Daughters of Albion huddles with three
others to the right.  Like her companions, she is gowned.  We see only her legs, drawn up to her chest, and the
top of her lowered head.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="figure" location="E"><characteristic>female</characteristic><characteristic>young</characteristic><characteristic>nude</characteristic><characteristic>hovering</characteristic><characteristic>Oothoon</characteristic><characteristic>arms raised horizontally</characteristic><characteristic>facing forward</characteristic><characteristic>mouth open</characteristic><characteristic>long hair</characteristic><characteristic>hands resting</characteristic><characteristic>holding</characteristic><characteristic>speaking</characteristic><illusobjdesc>A female hovers in the sky or on a cloud with arms
extended horizontally.  We see only her unclothed chest, arms and
hands, face, and long hair streaming out on each side of her
head.  She faces forward with a serious, perhaps worried,
expression.  She may be speaking to the women below, with her
mouth slightly open.  Her hands appear to rest on or hold the
cloud below her.  Flames emanate from beneath her chest and curl
over her arms.  This is almost certainly Oothoon addressing the
Daughters of Albion.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>fire</characteristic><characteristic>snake-like</characteristic><illusobjdesc>Fire emanates from below the hovering figure's chest
and curls upward over her arms.  The tongues of flame are         
snake-like.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="CD"><characteristic>seashore</characteristic><characteristic>sea</characteristic><characteristic>water</characteristic><characteristic>wave</characteristic><characteristic>sand</characteristic><characteristic>stone</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The setting is the seashore, with the sea on the
left and a sandy or stony shore on the right.  There are clear
indications of waves in the sea and along the                  
shore.</illusobjdesc></component><component type="object" location="E"><characteristic>cloud</characteristic><characteristic>sky</characteristic><illusobjdesc>The sky is dominated by a cloud extending from left 
to right across the middle of the plate.</illusobjdesc></component></illustration></illusdesc><phystext><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.01" justify="left" indent="49">(drop</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.02" justify="left">Where the cold miser spreads his gold? or does the bright cloud</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.03" justify="left">On his stone threshold? does his eye behold the beam that brings</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.04" justify="left">Expansion to the eye of pity? or will he bind himself</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.05" justify="left">Beside the ox to thy hard furrow? does not that mild beam blot</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.06" justify="left">The bat, the owl, the glowing tyger, and the king of night.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.07" justify="left">The sea fowl takes the wintry blast. for a cov'ring to her limbs;</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.08" justify="left">And the wild snake, the pestilence to adorn him with gems &amp; gold.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.09" justify="left">And trees. &amp; birds. &amp; beasts, &amp; men, behold their eternal joy.</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.10" justify="left">Arise you little glancing wings, and sing your infant joy!</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.11" justify="left">Arise and drink your bliss. for every thing that lives is holy!</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.12" justify="left">Thus every morning wails Oothoon. but Theotormon sits</l><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.13" justify="left">Upon the margind ocean conversing with shadows dire,</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.14" justify="left">The Daughters of Albion hear her woes. &amp; eccho back her sighs.</l></lg><vspace extent="1"/><lg type="verse" justify="left"><l n="vda.c.illbk.11.15" justify="left" indent="25">The End</l></lg></phystext></desc></objdesc></bad>