<vgroup name="MONOCHROME WASH DRAWINGS (COMPOSED C. 1774-1786)" id="1780smonowash">
    <include bad="but2.1"/>
    <include bad="butwba15.1"/>
    <include bad="but3.1"/>
    <include bad="but4.1"/>
    <include bad="but11.1"/>
    <include bad="but186r.1"/>
    <include bad="but82r.1"/>
    <include bad="but101.1"/>
    <include bad="but102r.1"/>
    <include bad="but104.1"/>
    <include bad="but108.1"/>
    <include bad="but111.1"/>
    <include bad="but112.1"/>
    <include bad="but115r.1"/>
    <include bad="but119.1"/>
    <include bad="but121.1"/>
    <include bad="but122r.1"/>
    <include bad="but123r.1"/>
    <include bad="but124.1"/>
    <include bad="but135.1"/>
    <include bad="but139a.1"/>
    <include bad="but141.1"/>
    <include bad="but142.1"/>
    <include bad="but145.1"/>
    <include bad="but147.1"/>
    <include bad="but148r.1"/>
    <include bad="butwba5.1"/>
    <include bad="but120v.1"/>
    <include bad="but85r.1"/>
    <include bad="but86r.1"/>
    <include bad="but92.1"/>
    <include bad="but93.1"/>
    <include bad="but153.1"/>
    <include bad="but159r.1"/>
    <include bad="but159v.1"/>
    <include bad="but162r.1"/>
    <include bad="but167.1"/>
    <include bad="but168r.1"/>
    <include bad="but168v.1"/>
    <include bad="but169r.1"/>
    <include bad="but169v.1"/>
    <include bad="but170r.1"/>
    <include bad="but170v.1"/>
    <include bad="but171.1"/>
    <include bad="butwba1.1"/>
    <include bad="butwba4.1"/>
    <include bad="butwba2.1"/>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <title reg="MONOCHROME WASH DRAWINGS (COMPOSED C. 1774-1786)"><main>MONOCHROME WASH DRAWINGS (COMPOSED C. 1774-1786)</main> : electronic edition </title>
            <principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel
                Hill</principal>
            <respstmt/>
            <sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of
                Congress</sponsor>
            <funder/>
        </titlestmt>
        <editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2006</editionstmt>
        <extent>47 XML files ranging in size from 10KB to 30KB; 94 JPEG (ISO/IEC 10918) files
            ranging in size from 80KB to 3600KB</extent>
        <publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>November
            2024</date></publicationstmt>
        <seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt>
<updatestmt> 
The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of a digital edition of forty-seven monochrome wash drawings created by Blake between c. 1774 and c. 1786.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
The use of monochrome washes to tint a pencil or pen and ink drawing offered eighteenth-century artists several advantages. They could register gradations in tone, from the white of the untouched paper to jet black, without the more time-consuming use of actual colors. No further work was required if the wash drawing was intended as a preliminary for an uncolored engraving. A monochrome wash could also be used to underlie subsequent applications of water colors, thereby darkening selected areas to create the illusion of depth or cast motifs in shadow.  
<lb/>
<lb/>
As the works presented here show, Blake made full use of monochrome washes from his earliest years as an artist. When assigned by his engraving master, James Basire, to record tombs in Westminster Abbey c. 1774-75, Blake applied black and gray washes to tint many of his drawings (Objects 1-5). These carefully executed works could then be used as preliminaries for subsequent engravings by Basire’s workshop.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s monochrome washes during his first decade as an independent artist and engraver include several interrelated groups. The seven drawings of figures from Michelangelo’s Sistine ceiling (Objects 37-43) demonstrate how copying engravings of works by Renaissance masters helped Blake learn postures and gestures he would later use in his own compositions. Other drawings provide visual evidence of how Blake developed a design from early sketches to highly finished water colors or engravings. The recto/verso drawings, <hi rend="i">Two Sketches for “Joseph Making Himself Known to His Brethren”</hi> (Objects 34 and 35), are preliminaries for the finished water color in the Fitzwilliam Museum, one of three illustrations of the biblical story of Joseph that are among Blake’s finest pictorial works of the 1780s. The three Joseph water colors are in the Archive along with a water color preliminary for <hi rend="i">Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound</hi>. The evolution of one of Blake’s earliest original book illustrations, a frontispiece for Thomas Commins’ <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi> of 1786, can be traced through three variant wash drawings (Objects 45-47) and a pencil sketch also in the Archive. The four wash versions of <hi rend="i">The Good Farmer</hi> reproduced here (Objects 16-19), in addition to two pen and ink drawings of the subject previously added to the Archive, show the complex ways Blake played variations on a theme as he worked toward a final version. No such finished work is known, and thus these drawings are our only record of Blake’s engagement with this subject. Similarly, for <hi rend="i">War Unchained by an Angel, Fire, Pestilence, and Famine Following</hi>, an untraced work Blake exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1784, we have only a preliminary study (Object 6).
<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake’s illustrations to his poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> of c. 1789 are among his most accomplished monochrome wash drawings. These have been published in the Archive as an independent group coordinated with the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript.  
<lb/>
<lb/>   
As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.   
            </updatestmt> 
        <notesstmt/>
    </filedesc>
    <revisiondesc>
       <changestmt>
                <change>Final proofing and publication</change>
                <date>November 2024</date>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Editors: </resp>
    <name>Robert Essick, </name>
    University of California, Riverside; and
    <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>
    University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Michael Fox</name>
    <resp>Assistant Editor: </resp>
    <name>Joseph Fletcher</name>
    <resp>Project Manager: </resp>
    <name>Grant Glass</name>
    <resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester: </resp>
    <name>Marcie Woehl</name>
    <resp>Consultants on Special Projects: </resp>
    <name>Josh Romphf</name>
    <resp>Bibliographer: </resp>
    <name>Chuck Ripley</name>
    <resp>Project Consultant: </resp>
    <name>Meaghan Green</name>
    <resp>Project Assistants: </resp>
    <name>Emily English, </name>
    <name>Tim Gress, </name>
    <name>Mary Learner, </name>
    <name>Anna Mertz, </name>
    <name>Celeste Seifert, </name>
    <name>Elizabeth Shand, </name>
    <name>Kate Soules, </name>
    <name>Samantha Steiner, </name>
    <name>Gabby Tapia, </name>
    <name>Dominique Townsend, </name>
    <name>Alice Wynd</name>
                </respstmt>
            </changestmt>
    </revisiondesc>
</vgroup>
