<vgroup name="Water Color Drawings Illustrating the Bible" id="biblicalwc"><include bad="but146.1" header="Old Testament Subjects"/><include bad="but435.1"/><include bad="but436.1"/><include bad="but438.1"/><include bad="but439.1"/><include bad="but440.1"/><include bad="but441.1"/><include bad="but442.1"/><include bad="but445.1"/><include bad="but446.1"/><include bad="but447.1"/><include bad="but448.1"/><include bad="but449.1"/><include bad="but450.1"/><include bad="but452.1"/><include bad="but453.1"/><include bad="but455.1"/><include bad="but457.1"/><include bad="but458.1"/><include bad="but461.1"/><include bad="but462.1"/><include bad="but463.1"/><include bad="but466.1"/><include bad="but467.1"/><include bad="but468.1"/><include bad="but469.1"/><include bad="but470.1" header="New Testament Subjects"/><include bad="but472.1"/><include bad="but473.1"/><include bad="but475.1"/><include bad="but476.1"/><include bad="but478.1"/><include bad="but480.1"/><include bad="but482.1"/><include bad="but484.1"/><include bad="but485.1"/><include bad="but486.1"/><include bad="but488.1"/><include bad="but489.1"/><include bad="but494.1"/><include bad="but495.1"/><include bad="but496.1"/><include bad="but497.1"/><include bad="but498.1"/><include bad="but499.1"/><include bad="but500.1"/><include bad="but501.1"/><include bad="but502.1"/><include bad="but503.1"/><include bad="but504.1"/><include bad="but505.1"/><include bad="but506.1"/><include bad="but507.1"/><include bad="but511.1"/><include bad="but512.1"/><include bad="but515.1"/><include bad="but517.1"/><include bad="but518.1"/><include bad="but519.1"/><include bad="but520.1"/><include bad="but521.1"/><include bad="but522.1"/><include bad="but523.1"/><include bad="but524.1"/><include bad="but525.1"/><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Water Color Drawings Illustrating the Bible"><main>Water Color Drawings Illustrating the Bible</main>
                : electronic edition
            </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>78 XML files approx. 30KB each; 329 JPEG (ISO/IEC
            10918)
            files ranging in size from 30KB to 4900KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>March 2010, March 2011 and November 2012</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt><lb/><b>November 2012</b><lb/><lb/>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of five of Blake's tempera paintings on biblical subjects, eleven of his water color illustrations to the Bible, and one of his large color printed drawings, <hi rend="i">Hecate, or The Night of Enitharmon's Joy.</hi>  These works have been added to groups previously published.  In addition, we have republished all the biblical temperas and water colors to add illustration descriptions and make their designs and inscriptions fully searchable.
            <lb/><lb/>
                    The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake's work as both artist and poet.  His tempera paintings and water colors of biblical subjects, mostly created for his patron Thomas Butts beginning in 1799, are among Blake's most important responses to that text.  The tempera paintings now published are based on passages in the New Testament concerning the life of Jesus and his family.  We are particularly pleased to include <hi rend="i">Christ Raising Jairus's Daughter</hi>, a well preserved but little known work recently acquired by the Mead Art Museum of Amherst College. The new group of water colors ranges from Numbers (<hi rend="i">Moses Striking the Rock</hi>) to two of Blake's most powerful explorations of the apocalyptic sublime, <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed with the Sun</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Number of the Beast is 666</hi>, both based on Revelation.  <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon</hi> from the Brooklyn Museum has received a good deal of contemporary attention because of its central role in Thomas Harris's bestselling 1981 novel, <hi rend="i">Red Dragon</hi>, and the films of 1986 and 2002 based on it.  The Archive now includes twenty-four tempera paintings and sixty-four water colors based on the Bible.  All of Blake's extant water color illustrations to Revelation are available.
            <lb/><lb/>
                        The publication of <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> from the National Gallery of Scotland completes our presentation of Blake's large color printed drawings, considered by some to be his greatest achievements as a pictorial artist.  The Archive now contains all thirty traced impressions of the twelve subjects portrayed in the large color prints.
            <lb/><lb/>
                            This publication includes works from several collections not previously represented in the Archive.  Accordingly, we are also publishing Blake collection lists for the Brooklyn Museum, Mead Art Museum (Amherst College), National Gallery of Scotland, Rhode Island School of Design Museum of Art, and Rosenbach Museum and Library.  These lists include all original works by Blake in their respective collections, not just those published in the Archive. 
            <lb/><lb/><b>March 2011</b><lb/><lb/>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of thirty-three of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. All take their subjects from the New Testament and have been added to the twenty Old Testament subjects published in March 2010 as “Illustrations to the Bible, c. 1780-1824,” under Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings. This new group is presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            Blake executed most of these New Testament water colors c. 1800-05 for his patron Thomas Butts. The exceptions are <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon</hi> of 1809 and <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi> in the Yale Center for British Art, datable to c. 1825. The subjects range from the childhood of Jesus to his ascension, the later history of his parents and one of his major followers, St. Paul, and a group of eight designs based on the Book of Revelation. While the illustrations of the life of Christ are fairly conventional in their subjects, in part because of the long tradition of picturing almost every event in the Gospels, individual motifs recall designs in Blake’s illuminated books and thus offer a window on Blake’s visual interpretation of the Bible. The illustrations of Revelation complement Blake’s intense engagement with apocalyptic events and images in his own poetry.
            <lb/><lb/>
            The selection of fifty-three biblical water colors now available in the Archive will be supplemented in the future with early works, such as Abraham and Isaac, datable to c. 1780, and will continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, such as <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi>.

            <lb/><lb/><b>March 2010</b><lb/><lb/>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of 20 of Blake’s water color illustrations to the Bible. These designs illustrate the Old Testament and are arranged according to the passages illustrated.  They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/>
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text are water color drawings.  The present group of 20 is selected from a sequence of about 80 biblical water colors of similar size Blake painted for Thomas Butts between c. 1800 and 1805.  These designs emphasize interactions between the human and the divine.  In works such as <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Wheels</hi> and <hi rend="i">David Delivered Out of Many Waters</hi>, the interaction is revelatory or redemptive.  In other designs, including <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Death of the First-Born</hi>, the relationship between God and humankind devolves into punishment and destruction.
            <lb/><lb/>
            This group of 20 water colors is the first installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake’s water color drawings illustrating the Bible.  In coming months we will publish a group of New Testament illustrations also from the series executed for Butts.  Later we will add early works, such as <hi rend="i">Abraham and Isaac</hi>, datable to c. 1780, and continue through Blake’s final biblical water colors, including <hi rend="i">Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes</hi> of c. 1824.
          
        </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Publication of 11 Old Testament and New Testament water colors in full mode; republication of 53 Old Testament and New Testament water colors in full mode</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kirilloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Publication of 33 New Testament water colors in preview mode</change><date>March 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Publication of 20 Old Testament water colors in preview mode</change><date>March 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></vgroup>