<vgroup name="Paintings Illustrating the Bible" id="biblicaltemperas"><include bad="but379.1"/><include bad="but381.1"/><include bad="but382.1"/><include bad="but387.1"/><include bad="but390.1"/><include bad="but392.1"/><include bad="but394.1"/><include bad="but396.1"/><include bad="but400.1"/><include bad="but401.1"/><include bad="but403.1"/><include bad="but404.1"/><include bad="but406.1"/><include bad="but409.1"/><include bad="but410.1"/><include bad="but411.1"/><include bad="but415.1"/><include bad="but416.1"/><include bad="but417.1"/><include bad="but419.1"/><include bad="but420.1"/><include bad="but424.1"/><include bad="but425.1"/><include bad="but426.1"/><include bad="but429.1"/><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Paintings Illustrating the Bible"><main>Paintings Illustrating the Bible </main>
                : electronic edition
            </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2004</editionstmt><extent>24 XML files ranging between 15KB and 30KB each; 48 JPEG (ISO/IEC
            10918)
            files ranging in size from 100KB to 6500KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>December 2010 and November 2012</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt><lb/><b>November 2012</b><lb/><lb/>                
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of five of Blake's tempera paintings on biblical subjects, eleven of his water color illustrations to the Bible, and one of his large color printed drawings, <hi rend="i">Hecate, or The Night of Enitharmon's Joy.</hi>  These works have been added to groups previously published.  In addition, we have republished all the biblical temperas and water colors to add illustration descriptions and make their designs and inscriptions fully searchable.
            <lb/><lb/> 
            The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake's work as both artist and poet.  His tempera paintings and water colors of biblical subjects, mostly created for his patron Thomas Butts beginning in 1799, are among Blake's most important responses to that text.  The tempera paintings now published are based on passages in the New Testament concerning the life of Jesus and his family.  We are particularly pleased to include <hi rend="i">Christ Raising Jairus's Daughter</hi>, a well preserved but little known work recently acquired by the Mead Art Museum of Amherst College. The new group of water colors ranges from Numbers (<hi rend="i">Moses Striking the Rock</hi>) to two of Blake's most powerful explorations of the apocalyptic sublime, <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed with the Sun</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Number of the Beast is 666</hi>, both based on Revelation.  <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon</hi> from the Brooklyn Museum has received a good deal of contemporary attention because of its central role in Thomas Harris's bestselling 1981 novel, <hi rend="i">Red Dragon</hi>, and the films of 1986 and 2002 based on it.  The Archive now includes twenty-four tempera paintings and sixty-four water colors based on the Bible.  All of Blake's extant water color illustrations to Revelation are available.
            <lb/><lb/> 
            The publication of <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> from the National Gallery of Scotland completes our presentation of Blake's large color printed drawings, considered by some to be his greatest achievements as a pictorial artist.  The Archive now contains all thirty traced impressions of the twelve subjects portrayed in the large color prints.
            <lb/><lb/> 
            This publication includes works from several collections not previously represented in the Archive.  Accordingly, we are also publishing Blake collection lists for the Brooklyn Museum, Mead Art Museum (Amherst College), National Gallery of Scotland, Rhode Island School of Design Museum of Art, and Rosenbach Museum and Library.  These lists include all original works by Blake in their respective collections, not just those published in the Archive. 
            <lb/><lb/><b>December 2010</b><lb/><lb/> 
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of nineteen of Blake’s tempera paintings illustrating the Bible.  They are presented in a new category, "Illustrations to the Bible (c. 1799-1803)"—see Paintings, under Drawings and Paintings, in the table of contents for Works in the Archive.  The designs are arranged according to the passages illustrated and are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (which provides detailed descriptions of Blake’s images).
            <lb/><lb/> 
                The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake's work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text is a group of paintings he created for his patron Thomas Butts, beginning in 1799.  Most were executed in that year and the next, but at least three were probably completed while Blake was in Felpham, 1802 and 1803.  Fifty-three of these "cabinet paintings" (as small works of this type were called in Blake's time) have been recorded.  Only thirty are now traceable, seven based on the Old Testament and the remainder on the New.
            <lb/><lb/> 
                    This group of nineteen paintings is the second installment in our publication of a large selection of Blake's drawings and paintings illustrating the Bible.  The first installment, a group of twenty water colors with subjects based on the Old Testament, was published in March of this year.
            <lb/><lb/> 
                        The medium of these paintings, now generally called "tempera," is water-based with a glue and/or gum binder.  Blake was probably trying to create jewel-like paintings; in his <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809, he compared them to "enamels" and "precious stones."  He never used the word "tempera" but called his medium "fresco"—a term that recalls Renaissance wall paintings—and claimed that he had invented the new genre of "portable Fresco," an alternative to paintings in oil.  Most were executed on canvas, but three are on copper and one (<hi rend="i">The Agony in the Garden</hi>) is on tinned iron.  
            <lb/><lb/> 
                            Unfortunately, Blake's medium was inherently unstable.  The pigment layers expanded and contracted at different rates.  Almost all his temperas of 1799-1803 show considerable surface cracking and other defects; many have been repaired at least once.  Some, such as <hi rend="i">The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes</hi>, have been over-painted in ways that misrepresent Blake's original work.                      
            <lb/><lb/> 
                                The biblical temperas of 1799-1803 can be divided into two groups according to size.  Most are approximately 27 x 38 cm., but five of the extant paintings measure about 32.5 x 49.5 cm.  The works in the larger size illustrate the life of Christ and may form their own series. 
            <lb/><lb/> 
                                    The Fitzwilliam Museum has requested some assistance with <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep on a Cross</hi>, recently presented to the museum by the heirs of George Goyder.  The provenance of this tempera painting includes its recovery from a "bombed house in 1940" by the dealer James Rimell of London in 1940 (Butlin 410).  The Fitzwilliam Museum would appreciate any information about the owner or owners of the painting prior to its acquisition by Rimell.  Please contact the Department of Paintings, Drawings and Prints (fitzmuseum-pdp@lists.cam.ac.uk; URL: http://www.fitzmuseum.cam.ac.uk/dept/pdp).
        </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Republication in full mode and publication of 5 additional objects</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kirilloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration markup</change><date>Summer 2011</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Publication of 19 objects in preview mode</change><date>December 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Lamperez,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></vgroup>