<vgroup name="The Large Color Printed Drawings of 1795 and c. 1805" id="cpd"><include bad="but325.1"/><include bad="but326.1"/><include bad="but327.1"/><include bad="but289.1"/><include bad="but294.1"/><include bad="but295.1"/><include bad="but296.1"/><include bad="but323.1"/><include bad="but324.1"/><include bad="but316.1"/><include bad="but317.1"/><include bad="but318.1"/><include bad="but320.1"/><include bad="but321.1"/><include bad="but322.1"/><include bad="but297.1"/><include bad="but298.1"/><include bad="but299.1"/><include bad="but300.1"/><include bad="but301.1"/><include bad="but302.1"/><include bad="but303.1"/><include bad="but306.1"/><include bad="but307.1"/><include bad="but313.1"/><include bad="but310.1"/><include bad="but311.1"/><include bad="but312.1"/><include bad="but291.1"/><include bad="but292.1"/><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="The Large Color Printed Drawings of 1795 and c. 1805"><main>The Large Color Printed Drawings of 1795 and c. 1805</main>
                : electronic edition
            </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>30 XML files approx. 25KB each; 60 JPEG (ISO/IEC
            10918)
            files ranging in size from 67KB to 5100KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; Carolina Digital Library and Archives<date>November 2004, February 2012, and November 2012</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt><lb/><b>November 2012</b><lb/><lb/>                
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of an electronic edition of five of Blake's tempera paintings on biblical subjects, eleven of his water color illustrations to the Bible, and one of his large color printed drawings, <hi rend="i">Hecate, or The Night of Enitharmon's Joy.</hi>  These works have been added to groups previously published.  In addition, we have republished all the biblical temperas and water colors to add illustration descriptions and make their designs and inscriptions fully searchable.
                <lb/><lb/> 
                    The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake's work as both artist and poet.  His tempera paintings and water colors of biblical subjects, mostly created for his patron Thomas Butts beginning in 1799, are among Blake's most important responses to that text.  The tempera paintings now published are based on passages in the New Testament concerning the life of Jesus and his family.  We are particularly pleased to include <hi rend="i">Christ Raising Jairus's Daughter</hi>, a well preserved but little known work recently acquired by the Mead Art Museum of Amherst College. The new group of water colors ranges from Numbers (<hi rend="i">Moses Striking the Rock</hi>) to two of Blake's most powerful explorations of the apocalyptic sublime, <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed with the Sun</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Number of the Beast is 666</hi>, both based on Revelation.  <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon</hi> from the Brooklyn Museum has received a good deal of contemporary attention because of its central role in Thomas Harris's bestselling 1981 novel, <hi rend="i">Red Dragon</hi>, and the films of 1986 and 2002 based on it.  The Archive now includes twenty-four tempera paintings and sixty-four water colors based on the Bible.  All of Blake's extant water color illustrations to Revelation are available.
                <lb/><lb/> 
                        The publication of <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> from the National Gallery of Scotland completes our presentation of Blake's large color printed drawings, considered by some to be his greatest achievements as a pictorial artist.  The Archive now contains all thirty traced impressions of the twelve subjects portrayed in the large color prints.
                <lb/><lb/> 
                            This publication includes works from several collections not previously represented in the Archive.  Accordingly, we are also publishing Blake collection lists for the Brooklyn Museum, Mead Art Museum (Amherst College), National Gallery of Scotland, Rhode Island School of Design Museum of Art, and Rosenbach Museum and Library.  These lists include all original works by Blake in their respective collections, not just those published in the Archive. 
                <lb/><lb/><b>February 2012</b><lb/><lb/>
           
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's <hi rend="i">Small Book of Designs</hi> copy A and <hi rend="i">Large Book of Designs</hi> copy A; the republication of Blake's large color printed drawings of 1795, with five additional impressions and all of them now searchable; and the addition to the Blake Collection Lists of the Philadelphia Museum of Art and the Minneapolis Institute of Arts—31 contributing institutions altogether. The Archive now also features newly revised textual transcriptions for Blake's descriptions of his illustrations to Milton's "L'Allegro" and "Il Penseroso," as well as updated Help documentation that reflects the launch of the Virtual Lightbox and recent improvements to the Archive's search engines.
                <lb/><lb/> 
                    The <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> were commissioned in 1796 by Ozias Humphry, a renowned miniaturist painter, and are now in the British Museum. The <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> consists of 23 plates from <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>. Blake masked the texts on these relief-etched plates and beautifully color printed the designs on 26 x 19 cm. leaves of Whatman paper. The <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> consists of eight color printed impressions pulled from etchings (<hi rend="i">Albion rose</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft, Adultery, Murder</hi>) and relief etchings, including plates from <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> and <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> and the separate relief plates of <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi> plate d and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Preaching</hi>, on the same type of paper, cut to 34.5 x 24.5 cm. With the Archive's Compare feature, users can examine the prints in the <hi rend="i">Small</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large Books of Designs</hi> with impressions from the illuminated books in the Archive. The <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> can be found in the Archive by moving through the following categories: Table of Contents &gt;Works in the Archive &gt;Separate Prints and Prints in Series &gt;Designed and Engraved by Blake. 
                <lb/><lb/> 
                        The <hi rend="i">Small Book</hi> was literally a book, its leaves bound through three stab holes, but the <hi rend="i">Large Book</hi> is a "book" only by analogy, for its leaves were neither stabbed nor, apparently, bound. Aesthetically, the <hi rend="i">Books</hi> grew out of Blake's twelve large color printed drawings of 1795. Although at least one of the designs, <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, shows evidence of having been color printed from a copperplate etched in relief, the other eleven appear to have been painted within pen and ink outlines on gessoed millboards (a thick cardboard) and printed onto large sheets of damp wove paper using a rolling press. From such a prepared matrix Blake was often able to print two impressions (a first and second pull) without repainting the matrix, and he finished all impressions in watercolors and pen and ink. He appears to have produced thirty impressions from the twelve designs in at least two printings, c. 1795 and c. 1804-05. No design has more than three extant impressions. As with the illuminated books, each impression is different due to variations in color printing and finishing. For a full technical description of Blake’s large color prints and their relation to the illuminated books and <hi rend="i">Small</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large Books of Designs</hi>, see Joseph Viscomi, "Blake's 'Annus Mirabilis': the Productions of 1795." <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> (Fall, 2007): 52-83.
                <lb/><lb/> 
                            The Archive has already published in its Preview Mode a selection of 23 impressions of the large color printed drawings (at least one impression of each) and the small version of <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> printed from a different matrix. With this republication, the Archive adds five impressions of five designs: <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (Lutheran Church in America), never before reproduced in color, <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> (Philadelphia Museum of Art), <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (Minneapolis Institute of Arts), <hi rend="i">Satan Exulting over Eve</hi> (Tate Collection), and <hi rend="i">Naomi Entreating Ruth and Orpah to Return to the Land of Moab</hi> (Fitzwilliam Museum). The Archive now contains all extant impressions of the twelve designs except the last impression of <hi rend="i">Hecate, or the Night of Enitharmon's Joy</hi>, in the National Gallery of Scotland, Edinburgh, which declined the Archive's request for a high-resolution image. With this republication, all the impressions of the color printed drawings are searchable and their illustration descriptions accessible, enabling users to engage in detailed, specific, and reliable searches of motifs, objects, subjects, and gestures. 
                            
            <lb/><lb/><b>November 2004</b><lb/><lb/>
                The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of Blake's 12 large color printed
                    drawings, designed and first printed in 1795.   They are presented in our Preview mode, one that provides all the features of the Archive except Image Search and Inote (our image annotation program).  They can be found in the Archive by moving through the following categories: Works in the Archive, Non-Illuminated Materials, Separate Prints and Prints in Series, and Color Printed Drawings. 
                    
                <lb/><lb/>Blake's 12 large color prints are often considered to be his greatest works as a pictorial artist.  Both their sublime imagery and Blake's printmaking technique evolved out of his illuminated books of 1790-95.  Although at least one of the designs, <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi>, shows evidence of having been printed from a copperplate etched in relief, the other 11 subjects were probably printed from the unetched surfaces of copperplates or millboards (a thick cardboard).  No more than 3 impressions from any one printing matrix are extant.  At least 2 of the designs, and probably a good many others, were reprinted c. 1805.  As with the illuminated books, each impression of the same basic image is different due to variations—some purposeful, some accidental—in both printing and hand-coloring.  The selection of 23 impressions presented here includes at least one impression of each design.  All 4 versions of <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, including the small version printed from a different matrix, are included.
                        
                <lb/><lb/>Modern scholars have interpreted the connections among the designs and their iconography, but no interpretation has become definitive.  It seems as though the 12 subjects are not a series with a fixed sequence, but rather a group of designs centered upon images of the fallen world.  Within that general group are a few companion prints, such as <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi> and <hi rend="i">Satan Exulting over Eve</hi>, associated in subject, design, or both.  The textual sources for the images range from the Bible to Shakespeare, Milton, and Blake's own poetic mythologies of the mid-1790s.
                            
        </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Publication of 1 additional object</change><date>November 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Gabrielle Kirilloff,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Publication of 5 additional objects and republication of original objects in full mode</change><date>February 2012</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson, </name><name>Laura Bell, </name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Katherine Carlson, </name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel, </name><name>Andrea Everett, </name><name>Joseph Fletcher, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Jennifer Park, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Hardeep Sidhu, </name><name>Sarah Tolf, </name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen, </name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Illustration description</change><date>Spring 2009</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Lauren Cameron, </name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Michelle Langston</name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Shaw, </name><name>Sarah Tolf </name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Republication using virtual group DTD 2009</change><date>2008</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold, </name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Kit Curtin, </name><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Sarah E. Jones, </name><name>Lauren Klapper-Lehman, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Rachel Lee, </name><name>Ali McGhee, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>Adair Rispoli, </name><name>Sarah Tolf </name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Conversion to XML and Blake Archive Description DTD 2004</change><date>2005</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Conversion: </resp><name>Aziza Technology Associates</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Justin Van Kleeck</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Christopher N. Jackson, </name><name>Kari Kraus, </name><name>Wesley N. Raabe, </name><name>Wayne C. Ripley, </name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Publication in Preview mode</change><date>October-November 2004</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Project Manager and Technical Editor: </resp><name>Andrea Laue</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Denise Vultee</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Wesley N. Raabe,</name><name>Wayne C. Ripley,</name><name>William Shaw</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></vgroup>