<vgroup name="Letters" id="letters"><include bad="lt18feb1800.1"/><include bad="lt1april1800.1"/><include bad="lt6may1800.1"/><include bad="lt2july1800.1"/><include bad="lt1sept1800.1"/><include bad="lt12sept1800.1"/><include bad="lt14sept1800.1"/><include bad="lt16sept1800.1"/><include bad="lt21sept1800.1"/><include bad="lt26nov1800.1"/><include bad="lt19oct1801.1"/><include bad="lt30jan1803.1"/><include bad="lt26oct1803.1"/><include bad="lt14jan1804.1"/><include bad="lt27jan1804.1"/><include bad="lt23feb1804.1"/><include bad="lt12march1804.1"/><include bad="lt16march1804.1"/><include bad="lt2april1804.1"/><include bad="lt7april1804.1"/><include bad="lt27april1804.1"/><include bad="lt4may1804.1"/><include bad="lt28may1804.1"/><include bad="lt22june1804.1"/><include bad="lt7aug1804.1"/><include bad="lt28sept1804.1"/><include bad="lt23oct1804.1"/><include bad="lt4dec1804.1"/><include bad="lt18dec1804.1"/><include bad="lt22jan1805.1"/><include bad="lt22march1805.1"/><include bad="lt4june1805.1"/><include bad="lt27nov1805.1"/><include bad="lt1825.1"/><include bad="lt7june1825.1"/><include bad="lt11oct1825.1"/><include bad="lt10nov1825.1"/><include bad="lt31jan1826.1"/><include bad="lt5feb1826.1"/><include bad="lt31march1826.1"/><include bad="lt19may1826.1"/><include bad="lt5july1826.1"/><include bad="lt14july1826.1"/><include bad="lt16july1826.1"/><include bad="lt29july1826.1"/><include bad="lt1aug1826.1"/><include bad="lt27jan1827.1"/><include bad="lt1827.1"/><include bad="ltfeb1827.1"/><include bad="lt15march1827.1"/><include bad="lt12april1827.1"/><include bad="lt25april1827.1"/><include bad="lt3july1827.1"/><include bad="lt15aug1827.1" header="Letters Not by Blake"/><filedesc><titlestmt><title reg="Letters"><main>Letters</main>
                : electronic edition
            </title><principal><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of
                Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</principal><respstmt/><sponsor>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and the Library of Congress</sponsor><funder/></titlestmt><editionstmt>Blake Archive Description DTD Version 2005</editionstmt><extent>54 XML files ranging in size from 10KB to 30KB; 108 JPEG (ISO/IEC
            10918)
            files ranging in size from 80KB to 2000KB</extent><publicationstmt>Chapel Hill: Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; UNC Libraries<date>March 2014</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt>The William Blake Archive</seriesstmt><updatestmt>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our second installment of Blake's letters, the correspondence of 1800-1805, which includes his three years with patron William Hayley in the coastal village of Felpham, West Sussex, and the frightening months leading up to his trial for sedition.
            <lb/>
            The letters in this group supplement the Archive’s publication in November 2013 of Blake's illustrations to works by Hayley, including his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>, the broadside ballad <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Life of George Romney</hi>, along with the republication of Blake’s etched and engraved illustrations to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads, Written by William Hayley</hi> (1802) and Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Letters from this period track the downward spiral from the most hopeful moments of Blake’s anticipations of working for the beloved “hermit of Eartham” to the bitterness and resentment he ultimately felt for that “pickthank.” The letters also show Blake in the process of conducting routine business: with Hayley but also with his important London patron Thomas Butts and with the publisher-promoter Robert Hartley Cromek, who was destined to become a focus of anger and frustration in the next stage of Blake’s life.  <lb/><lb/>
            About ninety of Blake’s letters survive, an unknown fraction of the total. Several—ten in the present group of thirty-three—are known only from partial and full transcriptions in the second, expanded, edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880). Blake traveled seldom and not very far. His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance. Occasionally the letters burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.&#160;    <lb/><lb/>
            The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the exigencies of everyday life than any other works from Blake’s hand. He seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.   <lb/><lb/>
            The Archive now contains 136 fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, including 90 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books—all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies.   <lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.           
            <lb/><lb/><hi rend="u">March 2013</hi><lb/><lb/>
            The William Blake Archive is pleased to announce the publication of electronic editions of our first installment of Blake’s letters, the correspondence of his last two years, 1825-27, mostly with his friend, benefactor, and fellow artist John Linnell, who sponsored such projects as Blake’s engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826) and <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Dante</hi>, on which he was still working when he died.
            <lb/><lb/>
            About ninety of Blake’s letters survive—an unknown fraction of the total. The surviving correspondence begins rather late in his career, in October 1791, the month before he turned 34, and ends, as far as we know, the month before his death at age 69 in August 1827—just three sentences to Linnell, to thank him for sending ten pounds and to indicate that his “journey to Hampstead on Sunday brought on a relapse . . . . however I am upon the mending hand to day &amp; hope soon to look as I did for I have been yellow accompanied by all the old Symptoms.”  <lb/><lb/>
            Blake traveled seldom and not very far, and he was little known beyond a small circle of British contemporaries, most of them in London.  His circle of correspondents was narrow and the geographical circuit small. But his modest body of correspondence comprises an absorbing, revealing miscellany of reports on work in progress alongside friendly and not so friendly exchanges on matters of practical and intellectual substance.  Occasionally they burst out into visions that amalgamate, in a characteristic Blakean vein, homely details, intensely energized prose, and inspired poetry.  <lb/><lb/>
            The letters are, in any case, indispensable in preserving facts and contexts for his life and work that would be otherwise unknown and in showing him shift pragmatically from role to role in a very natural—and human—way, exposing facets of character and personality not always so apparent in his art. The letters feel closer to the externalities of everyday life than any other work from Blake’s hand, and some start out to be one very ordinary thing and end up being another quite extraordinary thing.  If Blake is not an artist-thinker in correspondence with an international circle, he seldom puts pen to paper without interesting consequences for readers.<lb/><lb/>
            In his letter of 12 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake refers to a small card he plans to engrave for his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  An impression of the card is attached to the final page of the letter.  We are also publishing another impression of Cumberland’s card (see Separate Plates and Prints in Series, Designed and Engraved by Blake).<lb/><lb/>
            The Archive now contains fully searchable and scalable electronic editions of important manuscripts and series of engravings, color printed drawings, tempera paintings, water color drawings, and 85 copies of Blake's nineteen illuminated books--all in the context of full bibliographic information about each work, careful diplomatic transcriptions of all texts, detailed descriptions of all images, and extensive bibliographies. <lb/><lb/>
            Due to recent security concerns related to Java browser plugins, the Archive has disabled its Java-based ImageSizer and Virtual Lightbox applications. Users can still view 100 and 300 dpi JPEG images as well as complete transcriptions for all works in the Archive. Text searching is also still available for all works in the Archive, and image searching remains available for all works except those in preview mode. In the coming months the Archive will implement redesigned pages that restore the features of ImageSizer and the Virtual Lightbox without the need for Java.<lb/><lb/>
            As always, the William Blake Archive is a free site, imposing no access restrictions and charging no subscription fees. The site is made possible by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with the University of Rochester, the continuing support of the Library of Congress, and the cooperation of the international array of libraries and museums that have generously given us permission to reproduce works from their collections in the Archive.           
        </updatestmt><notesstmt/></filedesc><revisiondesc><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication of 33 letters written between 1800 and 1805</change><date>December 2013-March 2014</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>Michael Fox</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Joseph Fletcher</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Laura Bell</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Consultant on Special Projects:</resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Katherine Calvin,</name><name>Adam Engel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Gabrielle Kirilloff,</name><name>Morgan Lessley,</name><name>Eric Loy,</name><name>Kate Massie,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Anastasia Nikolis,</name><name>Kylie Regan,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Margaret Speer,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Danny Tsegai,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Megan Wilson</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Final proofing and publication of 21 letters written between 1825 and 1827</change><date>February-March 2013</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Project Coordinator, University of Rochester:</resp><name>Rachel Lee</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Technical Consultant:</resp><name>Joseph Ryan</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Duncan Graham,</name><name>Gabrielle Kirilloff,</name><name>Adam McCune,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Ted Scheinman</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Hardeep Sidhu,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Lisa Vandenbossche,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Alia Wegner,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt><changestmt><change>Virtual group created</change><date>November 2010</date><respstmt><resp>Editors: </resp><name>Morris Eaves, </name>University of Rochester;
                <name>Robert Essick, </name>University of California, Riverside; and
                <name>Joseph Viscomi, </name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
                <resp>Technical Editor: </resp><name>William Shaw</name><resp>Project Manager: </resp><name>Ashley Reed</name><resp>Bibliographer:</resp><name>Mark Crosby</name><resp>Project Assistants: </resp><name>Esther Arnold,</name><name>Kate Attkisson,</name><name>Laura Bell,</name><name>Lauren Cameron,</name><name>Katherine Carlson,</name><name>Robin Curry,</name><name>Cassandra Etter-Wenzel,</name><name>Andrea Everett,</name><name>Joseph Fletcher,</name><name>Elizabeth Goodfellow,</name><name>Rachel Lee,</name><name>Ali McGhee,</name><name>Jennifer Park,</name><name>Adair Rispoli,</name><name>Sarah Shaw,</name><name>Sarah Tolf,</name><name>Joseph Vogel,</name><name>Nikolaus Wasmoen,</name><name>Bihan Zhang</name></respstmt></changestmt></revisiondesc></vgroup>