<info id="allegropenseroso"><worktitle><div id="allegropenseroso.title"><h1>*Illustrations to Milton's "L'Allegro" and "Il
         Penseroso" and Descriptions of "L'Allegro" and "Il Penseroso"
         Designs*</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="allegropenseroso.top"><p>The poetry of John Milton was important to Blake as both poet
         and artist from his earliest years. As he told John Flaxman in a
         letter of 12 September 1800, "Milton lovd me in childhood &amp; shewd
         me his face" (Erdman page 707). Several early drawings, such as the
         <cite>Satan, Sin, and Death</cite> of c. 1780 (Butlin 101), were
         probably inspired by Milton. In 1790-92, Blake loosely sketched
         several illustrations to <cite>Paradise Lost</cite> in his Notebook
         (Butlin 201; see Related Works, below). He composed his first
         series of water colors illustrating one of Milton's poems in 1801
         when the Rev. Joseph Thomas commissioned eight designs for
         <cite>Comus</cite> (Butlin 527). Thomas later acquired (very
         probably on commission) a set of twelve water color illustrations
         to <cite>Paradise Lost</cite> in 1807 (Butlin 529) and six water
         colors illustrating "On the Morning of Christ's Nativity" in 1809
         (Butlin 538). Between 1808 and 1815, Blake produced similar (but
         not in every respect identical) sets of the <cite>Paradise
            Lost</cite> and "Nativity" designs for Thomas Butts (Butlin 529,
         542), to which he added the twelve illustrations to "L'Allegro" and
         "Il Penseroso" c. 1816-20 (Butlin 543) presented here. Although we
         can be confident that Butts was the first owner of these
         illustrations and very probably commissioned them, there are no
         extant records of such a commission. The dating of the water colors
         is based on the presence of an "1816" watermark in six of the
         designs and on stylistic features, particularly the high degree of
         finish with fine brush strokes, indicative of Blake's later
         style.</p><p>Each design is accompanied by a separate sheet of paper on which
         Blake wrote in pen and ink a brief title, now considered the verso
         of each sheet because glued to a backing sheet. The rectos of the
         inscribed sheets bear pen and ink quotations, in Blake's hand, of
         the lines illustrated, to which Blake added his own comments on the
         motifs pictured. These quotations and comments are of course
         important in understanding Blake's pictorial responses to
         "L'Allegro" and "Il Penseroso." The rectos of these inscribed
         sheets are presented here, each following the water color to which
         it refers. Because of the backing sheets, the verso inscriptions
         can only be read with the aid of a strong backing light, but they
         cannot be photographed. Thus, they are included here in the
         Editors' Notes, but they are not reproduced.</p><p>As is typical of his work as an illustrator of the works of
         other poets, Blake paid close attention to the text, but this
         disciplined approach did not preclude the inclusion of his own
         interpretations. In itself the selection of passages to illustrate
         indicates Blake's emphasis on imaginative states of consciousness,
         including dreams and visions.</p><p>Blake's literary response to the life and works of John Milton
         finds its fullest expression in the illuminated book <cite>Milton a
            Poem</cite> (c. 1804-10; see Related Works, below).</p></div></remarks>
            <related>
		     <relationship><link type="work" ptr="but543">*Illustrations to Milton's 'L'Allegro' and 'Il Penseroso'*</link><br/>
    Water color drawings, c. 1816-20. Butlin 543<br/>
    Morgan Library and Museum<br/>
    New York City
    </relationship>
            <relationship>*Mirth*<br/>
			Etching/engraving, first state, c. 1816-20. Essick XVIII.<br/>
			British Museum<br/>
			London<br/>
			Related to Object 1.</relationship>
	
			<relationship>*Mirth(?)*<br/>
			Pencil sketch, c. 1820-25. Butlin 795.<br/>
			Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>
			Cambridge, England<br/>
			Related to Object 1.</relationship>

			<relationship>*Mirth*<br/>
			Etching/engraving, second state, c. 1820-27. Essick XVIII.<br/>
			Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>
			Cambridge, England<br/>
			Related to Object 1.</relationship></related></info>
