<info id="aro"><worktitle><div id="ARO.title"><h1><i>All Religions are One</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="ARO.top"><p>Through aphoristic declarations and accompanying emblem-like

      designs, Blake argues for the essential unity of all religions as

      expressions of the "Poetic Genius" within all human beings. As the

      quoted phrase suggests, <cite>All Religions are One</cite> implies the unity of

      the artistic and religious imagination. Several of the numbered

      "Principle[s]," the term used as a heading to each text plate,

      assert a causal connection between inner spirit and outer body.

      Because of shared graphic styles, themes, and genre, <cite>All

       Religions are One</cite> is closely associated with <cite>There is

        No Natural Religion</cite> of the same year.</p><p>Blake etched the work on ten small plates c. 1788. There is only

      one known copy (A), now in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery. This copy,

      lacking the title page now in the Keynes Collection, Fitzwilliam

      Museum, was printed (with some touches of rudimentary color

      printing) as a large-paper copy in 1795. Some years later, probably

      in 1818 or later, Blake returned to these impressions and drew

      between four and six framing lines in black ink around each plate.

      The pen and ink work in the designs may have been executed at this

      same late date. There is one further example of the title page,

      produced in a different printing and with hand coloring, in the

      Victoria and Albert Museum.</p></div></remarks><related><relHeader>All Known Copies</relHeader><relationship><link type="copy" ptr="aro.a">Copy A, c. 1795</link><br/>

        Huntington Library and Art Gallery<br/>

        San Marino, California

       </relationship></related><related><relHeader>All Known Related Drawings</relHeader><relationship><i>Blake's Notebook</i>, Object 17<br/>
Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93. Bentley 122.<br/>
British Library<br/>
London<br/>
Related to Object 7.</relationship><relationship><i>Illustrations to Edward Young’s “Night Thoughts,”</i> Object 264<br/>
   Water color, c. 1795-97.  Butlin 330.<br/>
    British Museum<br/>
    London<br/>
    Related to Object 10.</relationship></related></info>