<info id="bb126"><worktitle><div id="bb126.title"><h1>*The Pickering Manuscript*</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb126.top"><p>An intriguing glimpse of the Pickering Manuscript poems surfaces on 16 August 1803,
                the month before Blake's return to London after three years in Felpham, Sussex. The
                increasingly miserable artist-in-residence for William Hayley writes his London
                friend and patron Thomas Butts a letter that attempts to give some "Picture of my
                Present state I pray God to keep you &amp; all men from it &amp; to deliver me in
                his own good time." Blake's verbal self-portrait culminates in three stanzas that
                open with an exclamatory couplet: "O why was I born with a different face / Why was
                I not born like the rest of my race" (Erdman pages 733-34).           
            </p><p>He varied that couplet only slightly in the separate poem "<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.08">Mary</link>," which may have been
                composed around the same time. At some point he copied "Mary" neatly into a 22-page
                manuscript with nine other poems, seven known from no other source. Not earlier than
                1802, probably after the abandonment of the quarto *Ballads* project in 1805 (see
                Blake's letter to William Hayley, 22 January 1805, Erdman pages 762-63), Blake
                reutilized paper that had been used in Hayley's *Designs to a Series of Ballads*, 1802
                (to which Blake had contributed engraved illustrations), trimmed off Hayley's
                printed texts (and with them the 1802 watermark), and on the spacious inside margins wrote out
                the ten poems that constitute the Pickering Manuscript—named after B. M. Pickering
                (1836-1878), one of its several nineteenth century owners.</p><p>The poems may have been composed from about 1800 through perhaps 1804 (see Bentley,
                *Blake Books* pages 341-42). In the final manuscript version, the clarity and
                formality of the hand, the neatness and uniformity of the arrangement, the scarcity
                of changes, and even the number of poems tantalizingly suggest a specific occasion
                for the collection. But there are no designs, no title page, and no concrete
                evidence to indicate whether Blake intended some form of publication or, perhaps, as
                David Erdman suggests, made the collection for a friend or patron (Erdman page
                859n). If so, that friend or patron never received it. It remained with Blake's wife
                Catherine after his death in 1827. The poems were not published until 1866—the year
                Pickering bought the manuscript—in *Songs of Innocence and Experience, with Other
                    Poems*, edited by R. H. Shepherd.</p><p>In attempts to capture the character of the collection in a title, it has also been
                called the Ballads Manuscript (Bentley) and the Auguries Manuscript (Johnson and
                Grant). Its sometimes ballad-like poems range in length from sixteen lines in four
                stanzas reminiscent of the *Songs of Innocence and of Experience* ("<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.01">The Smile</link>") to one
                undivided sequence of 132 aphoristic lines ("<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.13">Auguries of Innocence</link>"), with the other
                poems at various lengths in between. All have, in one way or another, strong
                precedents in earlier work—characteristic subject matter, ideology, and attitude;
                ballad- and hymn-like structures built upon characteristic rhythms, rhymes, and
                repetitions; a striking penchant (and talent) for aphorism and invented proverb; and
                strong ironies in strange mixtures of story and saying, among other familiar traits.
                No one who has read the *Songs* and the Proverbs of Hell in *The Marriage of Heaven and
                    Hell* will fail to recognize the poetic neighborhood of the Pickering Manuscript as
                Blake's.</p><p>But he must have sensed that these were ten instances of particularly
                masterful—refined, powerful, compelling, inspired—poetry underwritten by an
                increasingly codified mythology. Thus one of the most elegant and memorable
                narratives of the Pickering group, "The Mental Traveller," is the kind of poem that
                has helped give Blake the reputation of an artist who "must Create a System, or be
                enslav'd by another Mans" (as his hero Los says in *Jerusalem* Plate 10, Erdman page
                153). Like some other poems in the group, "The Mental Traveller" comes across as a
                module that Blake could easily have slipped into his more extended mythopoeic
                ventures. It encapsulates with extraordinary concision a smooth, dark core of
                Blake's storytelling: "She lives upon his shrieks &amp; cries / And She grows young
                as he grows old" (<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.03">Object 3</link>). Like most of the poems in this grouping, "The Mental Traveller" is
                sharp but enigmatic, as if it can simultaneously know precisely what it is about but
                remain baffling to readers who want to crack its code.</p><p>Then again, the manuscript also beckons to readers (and poets, artists, and
                musicians, because these are among Blake's most influential lines) who want light
                with their darkness—who prefer their unsparing social insights balanced against hope
                and healing. This attractive, popular Blake is best represented here in the long
                aphoristic sequence "Auguries of Innocence," where "under every grief &amp; pine / Runs
                a joy with silken twine," "Man was made for Joy &amp; Woe," and it is possible "To see a
                World in a Grain of Sand / And a Heaven in a Wild Flower / Hold Infinity in the palm
                of your hand / And Eternity in an hour" (<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.16">Object 16</link>). Miraculous acts of imagination can be
                achieved even in a world where "The Harlots cry from Street to Street / Shall weave
                Old Englands winding Sheet" (<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.18">Object 18</link>) and "The Babe that weeps the Rod beneath / Writes
                Revenge in realms of death" (<link type="object" ptr="bb126.1.ms.16">Object 16</link>).</p></div></remarks>
    <related><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/songsie.e?descId=songsie.e.illbk.54">"To Tirzah, "*Songs of Innocence and
    of Experience*</link><br/>
        A line from "William Bond." Erdman 490.<br/>  
        Relief etchings, composed 1789 and 1794, printed 1821-1826. Bentley 139, Plate 52.<br/>
        Related to Object 21.
    </relationship><relationship>*Blake's Notebook*, c. 1793-c. 1818
            <br/>Lines related to "The Grey Monk." Erdman 489. 
            <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 122.
            <br/>British Library
            <br/>London
            <br/>Related to Object 12.
        </relationship><relationship>*Blake's Notebook*, c. 1793-c. 1818
            <br/>Lines related to "The Golden Net." Erdman 483. 
            <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 122.
            <br/>British Library
            <br/>London
            <br/>Related to Objects 1 and 2.
        </relationship><relationship>"The Everlasting Gospel," part d, *Blake's Notebook*, c. 1793-c. 1818
            <br/>A line from "William Bond." Erdman 496. 
            <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 122.
            <br/>British Library
            <br/>London
            <br/>Related to Object 21.
        </relationship><relationship> Letter to Thomas Butts, 16 August 1803 
            <br/>Lines related to "Mary." Erdman 487. 
            <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 86.
            <br/>Westminster Library and Archives 
            <br/>Special Collections, 
            <br/>Preston Blake Collection 
            <br/>London 
            <br/>Related to Object 8.
        </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/jerusalem.e?descId=jerusalem.e.illbk.52">"To the Deists," *Jerusalem The Emanation of The Giant Albion*</link>, Copy E, c. 1821
            <br/>Lines related to "The Grey Monk." Erdman 489. 
            <br/>Relief and white-line etching, Bentley 75, Plate 52. 
            <br/>Multiple owners
            <br/>Related to Object 12.
        </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/gates-sexes.d?descId=gates-sexes.d.illbk.19">"The Keys," *For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise*</link>, c. 1825
            <br/>Lines related to "Auguries of Innocence." Erdman 490.
            <br/>Intaglio etching/engraving, Bentley 45, Plate 19.
            <br/>Multiple owners
            <br/>Related to Object 15.
        </relationship></related></info>