<info id="bb208">
    <worktitle>
        <div id="bb208.title">
            <h1>*Blake's Autograph in the Album of William Upcott*</h1>
        </div>
    </worktitle>
    <remarks>
        <div id="bb208.top">
            <p>Upcott (1779-1845) was the illegitimate son of Blake's friend and patron the
                miniaturist Ozias Humphry (1742-1810), who bequeathed to Upcott a number of Blake's
                works. Upcott was a bookseller, librarian, bibliographer, editor, and inveterate
                collector, but he was perhaps best known for what he called his "autographic mania"
                (qtd. in Freeman, "Upcott, William (1779-1845)," <i>ODNB</i>
                [http://www.oxforddnb.com, accessed 18 Jan 2014]), which he exercised in his
                "autograph cottage" in Islington-where he was living when Blake left his autograph
                in Upcott's album either during a visit just a few months before Blake died, or,
                more probably, off the premises as the album circulated among the authors and
                artists whose signatures Upcott sought to acquire. The album may have been at Samuel
                Leigh's bookshop in the Strand, where Blake (and others) may have signed it: "On 16
                Jan. 1826 he inscribed William Upcott's autograph album 'by the desire of Mr Leigh' "
                (Bentley, <i>Records</i>, 369n).</p>
            <p>Upcott seems to have been a colorful character who earned the title Emperor of
                Autographs—he owned at least 40,000 according to his obituary. And he owned
                illuminated works that his father bought directly from Blake: <i>Songs of Innocence
                    and of Experience</i> Copy H (containing only <i>Experience</i>), <i>America a
                    Prophecy</i> Copy H, <i>Europe a Prophecy</i> Copy D, <i>A Small Book of
                    Designs</i> Copy A, and <i>A Large Book of Designs</i>. Upcott's copy of
                    <i>Europe</i> and both books of <i>Designs</i> are in the Archive.</p>
            <p>Blake, perhaps "very much delighted with being in good Company" (Object 1, lines
                1-2), inscribed a striking, elaborate signature with a characteristically Blakean
                note "Writ helter skelter like a hog upon a rope" (Object 1, lines 10-11)
                incorporating an equally characteristic sketch of a floating male, nude, with arms
                outstretched. Blake's signature appears just under that of the painter Benjamin
                Haydon.</p>
        </div>
    </remarks>
    <related>
        <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/songsie.l?descId=songsie.l.illbk.42">"To
                Tirzah," *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*</link>
            <br/>A line from "William Bond." Erdman 490. <br/>Relief etchings, composed 1789 and
            1794, printed 1821-1826. Bentley 139, plate 52. </relationship>
        <relationship>*Blake's Notebook*, c. 1793-c. 1818 <br/>Page 12, lines related to "The Grey
            Monk." Erdman 489. <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 122. <br/>Morgan Library and Museum <br/>New
            York City </relationship>
        <relationship>*Blake's Notebook*, c. 1793-c. 1818 <br/>Page 14, lines related to "The Golden
            Net." Erdman 483. <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 122. <br/>Morgan Library and Museum <br/>New
            York City </relationship>
        <relationship> "The Everlasting Gospel," part d, *Blake's Notebook*, c. 1793-c. 1818
            <br/>Page 120, a line from "William Bond." Erdman 496. <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 122.
            <br/>Morgan Library and Museum <br/>New York City </relationship>
        <relationship> Letter to Thomas Butts, 16 August 1803 <br/>Lines related to "Mary." Erdman
            487. <br/>Manuscript. Bentley 86. <br/>Westminster Library and Archives <br/>Special
            Collections, <br/>Preston Blake Collection <br/>London </relationship>
        <relationship><link type="object" ptr="jcopy/jerusalem.e?descId=jerusalem.e.illbk.52">"To the
                Deists," *Jerusalem The Emanation of The Giant Albion*, copy E, c. 1821</link>
            <br/>Lines related to "The Grey Monk." Erdman 489. <br/>Relief and white-line etching
            with hand coloring, Bentley 75, plate 52. <br/>Yale Center for British Art <br/>New
            Haven, CT </relationship>
        <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/gates-sexes.d?descId=gates-sexes.d.illbk.19">"The
                Keys," *For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise*, copy D, c. 1825</link>
            <br/>Lines related to "Auguries of Innocence." Erdman 490. <br/>Intaglio
            etching/engraving, Bentley 45, plate 19. <br/>Morgan Library and Museum <br/>New York
            City </relationship>
    </related>
</info>
