<info id="bb466"><worktitle><div id="bb466.title"><h2>William Hayley, <i>Designs to a Series of Ballads</i></h2></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb466.top"><p>While Blake was resident in Felpham on the Sussex coast, his new patron William Hayley began to write a series of ballads to be illustrated by the artist-engraver.  These were published in 1802 as quarto numbers, each with three engravings by Blake.  As the general title page indicates, the poems all deal with “Anecdotes Relating to Animals.”  In his “Preface,” Hayley states that his plan was to issue one ballad a month, “and to complete the whole series in fifteen Numbers.”  The letterpress text was printed by the Chichester printer Joseph Seagrave; the plates were printed by Blake and his wife Catherine on their own rolling press.  Although two book dealers, P. Humphry and R. H. Evans, were selected to sell the ballads, most copies seem to have been sold by Hayley to his friends.  Sales were less than brisk and the project ceased after only four ballads were issued.  Blake designed and executed twelve plates, including a frontispiece for the general title page and a tailpiece to the “Preface,” both issued with the first ballad.  Two further plates were engraved by Blake after designs on antique gems (plates 5 and 11).</p><p>The London bookseller Richard Phillips published an octavo edition of fifteen ballads by Hayley in 1805.  For this volume, Blake engraved new plates of his designs for three of the ballads first published in 1802 and both designed and engraved new illustrations for two of the additional ballads.</p></div></remarks><related><relationship><i>Blake's Notebook</i><br/> 

          Page 73, three pencil sketches related to "The Eagle," 1802.  Butlin 201.73.<br/>

          British Library<br/>

          London

       </relationship><relationship><i>Sketch for the Frontispiece to “The Eagle”</i><br/> 

          Pencil sketch, 1802.  Butlin 360.<br/>

          British Museum<br/>

          London</relationship><relationship><i>Sketch for the Frontispiece to “The Eagle”</i><br/>

          Pencil sketch, 1802.  Butlin 361 recto.<br/>

          Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress<br/>

          Washington, DC</relationship><relationship><i>Sketch for the Headpiece to “The Eagle”</i><br/> 

          Pencil sketch, 1802.  Butlin 362 recto.<br/>

          British Museum<br/>

          London</relationship><relationship><i>Two Sketches for the Frontispiece to “The Elephant” (recto), Sketch for the Frontispiece to “The Lion” (verso)</i><br/>

          Pencil and pen and ink drawings, 1802.  Butlin 364.<br/>

          Royal Academy<br/>

          London</relationship><relationship><i>The Resurrection</i> or <i>The Last Trumpet</i>, with verso sketches related to "The Dog" and "The Eagle"<br/> 

          Pencil sketches, 1802.  Butlin 79 (recto only).<br/>

          John Windle Books<br/>

          San Francisco, California</relationship><relationship><i>The Resurrection</i> or <i>The Last Trumpet</i> (recto), with verso sketches related to "The Dog," "The Eagle," and "The Lion"<br/> 

          Pencil sketches, 1802.  Butlin 617 (recto only, untraced).<br/>

          W/S Fine Art Ltd.<br/>

          London</relationship><relationship><i>A Lion Attacking a Man and a Woman</i><br/> 

          Pencil (?), 1802 or 1805, possibly related to “The Lion, Ballad the Third.”  Butlin 365.<br/>

          Untraced</relationship><relationship><i>“The Eagle” Frontispiece, Finished Drawing</i><br/>

          Monochrome wash drawing, 1805 (?).  Butlin 363.<br/>

          Morgan Library and Museum<br/>

          New York City</relationship><relationship><link type="work" ptr="bb465">
            William Hayley, <i>Ballads, Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals</i>, 1805.</link><br/>

          With five etchings/engravings designed and engraved by Blake.  Bentley 465.</relationship><relationship><i>The Horse</i><br/>

          Tempera painting, 1805 (?).  Butlin 366.<br/>

          Yale Center for British Art<br/>

          Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut</relationship></related></info>