<info id="bb467"><worktitle><div id="bb467.title"><h1>William Hayley, <i>An Essay on Sculpture</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb467.top"><p>
                Published in 1800 and dedicated to John Flaxman, Hayley’s verse epistle celebrating sculpture as one of the sister arts contains three plates, two of which are signed by Blake.  Epistolary evidence indicates that Blake was responsible for the unsigned plate. 
            </p><p>By the end of 1799, Hayley was hurrying to prepare the poem for publication before the death of his terminally ill son, Thomas Alphonso Hayley. In a letter to Flaxman of 21 December, Hayley states “I wish to have only the two following Decorations, if you approve them—a Frontispiece &amp; a vignette at the close—the first from poor Toms outline of Demosthenes at the base of Neptunes Statue . . . &amp; a neat small Head, as a closing vignette, from your medallion of the dear disciple [Thomas Hayley]” (Bentley, <i>Records</i> page 85). In January 1800, Blake had been commissioned to execute these engravings (objects 2 and 3), probably through the recommendation of Flaxman. In addition, Blake engraved the bust of Pericles after a drawing by Tom Hayley that became the frontispieces in the published work.  With his letter of 1 April 1800, Blake sent Hayley a proof of the medallion of Tom Hayley (Erdman page 705). On 17 April, Hayley responded with some criticisms of the proof and, after his son’s death on 2 May, invited Blake to Felpham to complete the engraving (Bentley, <i>Records</i> pages 87-88, 90). </p><p>Blake spent at least three weeks working beside Hayley in Felpham during July 1800. He completed both a half-length drawing of Thomas Alphonso and the engraving of the medallion portrait (object 3). Later that year, after Blake had relocated to Sussex, he painted a series of 18 portrait heads to decorate Hayley’s library, including portraits of Thomas Alphonso and Demosthenes. </p></div></remarks><related><relationship>
            Roman copy of a Greek original, <i>Bust of Pericles</i><br/>
            
            Marble, 2<sup>nd</sup> century BC. 
            <br/>
            
            British Museum<br/>
            
            London 
        </relationship><relationship>
            Thomas Alphonso Hayley, <i>Bust of Pericles</i><br/>
            
            Drawing, c. 1799-1800. 
            <br/>
  
            Untraced 
        </relationship><relationship>
            Thomas Alphonso Hayley and possibly John Flaxman, <i>The Death of Demosthenes</i><br/>
            
            Pen and ink drawing, c. 1800. 
            <br/>
            
            Keynes Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum 
            <br/>
            
            Cambridge, England 
        </relationship><relationship>
            Thomas Alphonso Hayley and possibly John Flaxman, <i>The Death of Demosthenes</i><br/>
            
            Pencil sketch, c. 1800. 
            <br/>
            
            Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art 
            <br/>
            
            Washington, D.C. 
        </relationship><relationship>
            John Flaxman and/or Thomas Alphonso Hayley, <i>The Death of Demosthenes</i><br/>
            
            Pen and ink drawing, c. 1800. 
            <br/>
            
            Collection of Robert N. Essick 
            <br/>
            
            Altadena, California 
        </relationship><relationship><i>Thomas Alphonso Hayley, Profile Drawing</i><br/>
            
            Drawing, 1800. Butlin 344.
            <br/>
        
            Untraced 
        </relationship><relationship><i>Thomas Alphonso Hayley, Half-Length Drawing</i><br/>
            
            Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1800. Butlin 345.
            <br/>
            
            Yale Center for British Art
            <br/>
            
            New Haven, Connecticut 
        </relationship><relationship>
            John Flaxman, <i>Medallion Portrait of Thomas Alphonso Hayley</i><br/>
            
            Sculpture, c. 1800. 
            <br/>
            
            Untraced 
        </relationship><relationship>
            Henry Howard, <i>Drawing of Flaxman's Medallion Portrait of Thomas Alphonso Hayley</i><br/>
            
            Drawing, 1800. 
            <br/>
            
            Untraced 
        </relationship><relationship><i>Demosthenes</i>, one of Blake's "Heads of Poets"
            <br/>
            
            Tempera painting, c. 1800-03. Butlin 343.2.
            <br/>
            
            Manchester City Art Galleries
            <br/>
            
            Manchester, England 
        </relationship><relationship><i>Thomas Alphonso Hayley</i>, one of Blake's "Heads of Poets"
            <br/>
            
            Tempera painting, c. 1800-03. Butlin 343.18.
            <br/>
            
            Manchester City Art Galleries
            <br/>
            
            Manchester, England 
        </relationship></related></info>