<info id="bb471"><worktitle><div id="bb471.title"><h1>William Hayley, <i>The Triumphs of Temper</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb471.top"><p>
                First published in 1781, William Hayley’s long mock-epic poem was one of the most popular works of the final decades of the eighteenth century. Heavily indebted to Alexander Pope’s <i>The Rape of the Lock</i>, Hayley’s didactic poem seeks to teach adolescent girls to become accomplished wives by exercising their temper.  The sixth edition of the poem, published in 1788, was the first to be illustrated; it contains seven plates after designs by Thomas Stothard. In 1803, Hayley commissioned Blake to engrave a series of new illustrations based on designs by  John Flaxman’s half-sister, Maria Flaxman, for a twelfth edition of the poem. She produced seven designs, of which Blake engraved six.
            </p><p>Blake worked on these plates for the first six months of 1803. In his letter to Thomas Butts of 10 January 1803, Blake reports that he was “now engaged in Engraving 6 small plates for a New Edition of M<sup>r</sup> Hayleys Triumphs of Temper. from drawings by Maria Flaxman sister to my friend the Sculptor” (Erdman page 723). At the end of the month, on 30 January, Blake informs his brother James of the commission and state that he would be paid “10 G[uineas]” for each plate (Erdman page 726). By the end of June, the engravings were evidently complete, for Hayley sent a copy of the twelfth edition to Lady Harriet Hesketh, William Cowper’s cousin. In a letter of 1 July, she tells Hayley of her disappointment with the prints. In a letter to John Flaxman of 7 August 1803, Hayley, presumably referring to Hesketh’s comments, states: “I am sorry to say that the Ladies (&amp; it is a Ladys Book) find fault with the Engravings— our poor industrious Blake has received sixty Guineas for them from my Bookseller &amp; I believe both the artist &amp; the paymaster are dissatisfied on the occasion” (Bentley, <i>Records</i> page 157). In the same letter, Hayley also reports that he and Blake made the decision to omit from the engravings the figure of Minerva represented in one of Maria Flaxman’s original designs. In response, John Flaxman remarked in a letter to Hayley of 24 August 1803 that one of his half-sister’s drawings depicting “Serena viewing herself in the Glass when dressed for the Masquerade whilst her Maid adjusts her train” was overlooked for engraving (Bentley, <i>Records</i> page 166).</p><p>Two of Maria Flaxman’s original designs were on display at the Royal Academy annual exhibition in 1800. All seven drawings were sold at auction at Christie’s on 26 February 1883. These are currently untraced.   </p><p>
                Blake’s engravings were repeated in a very small print run of the thirteenth edition of <i>The Triumphs of Temper</i>, published in 1807. The copperplates had worn significantly and were replaced by the original engravings after designs by Stothard in another 1807 issue of the poem. </p></div></remarks><related><relationship>
            Maria Flaxman, seven drawings illustrating Hayley's <i>The Triumphs of Temper</i><br/>
            
            Monochrome wash (?) drawings, 1800. 
            <br/>

            Untraced  
        </relationship></related></info>