<info id="bb470"><worktitle><div id="bb470.title"><h1>William Hayley, <i>Little Tom the Sailor</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb470.top"><p>
                Upon arriving in Felpham on the Sussex coast in 1800, one of the first commissions Blake received from his new patron, William Hayley, was the broadside ballad <i>Little Tom the Sailor</i>. According to his <i>Memoirs</i>, Hayley composed the poem on 22 September 1800 “to relieve the necessities of a meritorious poor Woman on the Kentish coast” (Bentley, <i>Records</i>, pages 99-100). In a letter to Thomas Butts of 23 September, Blake states, “I have begun to Work &amp; find … that Felpham is propitious to the Arts” (Erdman page 711). Blake was almost certainly referring to <i>Little Tom the Sailor</i>, which comprises head and tailpiece designs on separate plates, etched and engraved in white line, and the texts of Hayley’s ballad and a colophon etched in relief on two copperplates. 
        </p><p>
                Hayley probably gave Blake the ballad to etch on the day of its composition or shortly thereafter. The ballad was published, according to the colophon, on 5 October 1800. It therefore took Blake approximately thirteen days to relief etch the texts as well as design and execute the two illustrations. A preliminary sketch of the headpiece is in the Victoria and Albert Museum. To print the ballad, Blake placed his four plates one above the other in his rolling press and printed them on one leaf of paper.
            </p><p>By the end of the November 1800, the initial print run appears to have almost sold out. In a letter to Hayley of 26 November, Blake, referring to the ballad, claims, “we can muster a few in colours and some in black which I hope will be no less favour’d tho’ they are rough like rough sailors” (Erdman page 714). There are three extant hand colored examples of <i>Little Tom the Sailor</i>, two printed in brown ink and one in green.</p></div></remarks><related>
<relationship><i>Sketch for the Headpiece of “Little Tom the Sailor.”</i><br/>
            Pencil sketch, 1800. Butlin 359 recto.<br/>
            Victorian and Albert Museum<br/>
            London<br/>
            Related to object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 26 November 1800.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Untraced; printed in Gilchrist, <i>Life of Blake</i>, 1880.<br/>
    Related to object 1.
</relationship></related></info>