<info id="bb499"><worktitle><div id="bb499.title"><h1>
                John Gabriel Stedman, *Narrative, of a Five Years' Expedition, against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam*</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb499.top"><p>

         J. G. Stedman's *Narrative* contains a frontispiece to volume 1, an engraved vignette on the title page of each of the two volumes, and eighty numbered full-page plates (including three maps).  Thirteen of the numbered plates and the title-page vignette are signed by Blake; a further three unsigned plates (7, 12, and 14) have been attributed to Blake by modern scholars.  As both title pages indicate, the full-page plates are based on drawings by Stedman.  None of the drawings on which Blake based his engravings has been traced, but it is likely that Blake made various minor alterations in Stedman's amateur designs.

      </p><p>

         Blake began work on the Stedman plates in 1791.  Stedman visited Blake in June 1794 and subsequently the engraver helped the author with various business matters, very probably including negotiations with the book's publisher, Joseph Johnson.  Blake's attitudes towards slavery and colonialism were indebted to Stedman's autobiographical narrative, as is particularly evident in the texts and designs of his illuminated books *Visions of the Daughters of Albion* and *America*, both dated 1793.  Stedman's relationship with a female slave, Joanna, may have influenced Blake's complex representations of gender and sexuality.

      </p><p>

         Most, possibly all, of the large-paper copies issued in 1796 have hand-colored plates that include touches of gold and silver.  This tinting was very probably executed by anonymous commercial colorists hired by Johnson.  A second edition was issued in 1806 and reprinted in 1813.  Some copies of these two later issues also have hand-colored plates, but in a style different from the 1796 coloring.

      </p></div></remarks><related><relationship>*Los and Orc*<br/>

          Water color, c. 1792-93.  Butlin 255.<br/>

          Tate Collection at Tate Britain<br/>

          London<br/>
          
          Related to Object 15.
       </relationship>
  <relationship>Title page vignette, proof<br/>

          Etching and engraving, c. 1792-95.<br/>
          
          Related to Object 1.
       </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/america.e?descId=america.e.illbk.03">*America a Prophecy*, Plate 3</link><br/>

          Relief and white-line etching, 1793.  Bentley 6.<br/>
          
          Related to Object 15.
</relationship></related></info>
