<info id="bb74"><worktitle><div id="bb74.title"><h1>*An Island in the Moon*</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bb74.top"><p>Perhaps drawing on a literary tradition of moon-voyage or flight narratives, Blake sets the
    earliest extended manifestation of his penchant for satire "In the Moon" on a "certain Island"
    with "some affinity to England" (<link type="object" ptr="bb74.1.ms.01">Object 1</link>, page 1,
    Erdman page 449), which provides the domestic settings—study, parlor, garden—for a boisterous
    sendup of middle class London social and intellectual life distilled into eleven brief chapters
    of "Great confusion &amp; disorder" (<link type="object" ptr="bb74.1.ms.10">Object 10</link>).
    The use of dialogue interspersed with song lyrics links *An Island in the Moon* to both
    contemporary theatrical forms and broader eighteenth-century traditions of satirical narrative.
    Blake’s experiences in the London social circle of the Rev. A. S. Mathew and his wife Harriet in
    the 1780s may be the main inspiration for these mocking reflections, which feature impertinent,
    passionate, confrontational characters, some if not all derived from Blake’s contemporaries. The
    philosopher-trio Suction the Epicurean, Quid the Cynic (perhaps Robert and William Blake), and
    Sipsop the Pythagorean join such companions as Inflammable Gass the Wind Finder, Obtuse Angle,
    and Mrs. Nannicantipot in a swirl of idle gossip, recitation, rude joking, drunken singing, and
    passionate wrangling about topics of current interest: "Fissic Follogy, Pistinology[,] . . .
    Hogamy HAtomy, &amp; hall that" (<link type="object" ptr="bb74.1.ms.05">Object 5</link>). The
    resulting disarray, bordering on farce —"O ay come Ill sing you a song said the Cynic. the
    trumpeter shit in his hat said the Epicurean" (<link type="object" ptr="bb74.1.ms.03">object
     3</link>) — is a self-undermining scramble that deflates nearly every pretense to lyricism or
    serious thought. Blake, writing in his mid to late 20s, demonstrates a born satirist’s instincts
    for the ridiculous. Though satire is never entirely absent from the illuminated books, only in
     *The Marriage of Heaven and Hell* (1790) is it the dominant mode. *An Island in the
     Moon* underscores the importance of the extensive stretches of humor and satire that show up
    frequently among his other writings. So, although Blake left it orphaned, untitled, and
    unfinished in a heavily revised manuscript, *Island* is in some sense a primary literary
    experiment for him, setting the undertone of much to follow.</p><p>*Island* is an incomplete manuscript written in pen and ink in Blake’s hand. It notably
    contains the earliest extant drafts of "Nurse’s Song," "HOLY THURSDAY," and "The Little Boy
    Lost," which make their first published appearance in his *Songs of Innocence* (1789). The
    history of Blake’s associations with the Mathew circle, along with topical allusions to balloon
    hats—a short-lived fashion associated with early demonstrations of ballooning—and the performing
    monkey General Jacko, suggest a period of composition c. 1784-85. Before the manuscript was
    given to the Fitzwilliam Museum in 1905, two or more leaves may have been removed, stranding the
    passage (". . . them Illuminating the Manuscript . . .") that begins abruptly on <link type="object" ptr="bb74.1.ms.17">Object 17</link>. The contents of a final page of lettering
    and rough sketches (<link type="object" ptr="bb74.1.ms.18">Object 18</link>) seem unrelated to
    the text of *Island*. The sketches and lettering on the verso of Object 18 may reflect
    Robert Blake's attempts to draw subjects that had been set as exercises for him by older brother
    William, and, in some instances, corrected by one of them (see the Object Note under Editors'
    Notes for Object 18). For more details about the entire manuscript, see Work Information,
    available from each object view page. </p></div></remarks>
    
    <related><relationship><link type="compare" ptr="s-inn.b" objnum="B13">"The Little Boy Lost,"</link> plate
   13 in *Songs of Innocence* and *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*<br/> Relief
   etching and some white-line etching, 1789. Bentley 139, Plate 13.<br/>Related to Object 15.</relationship><relationship><link type="compare" ptr="s-inn.b" objnum="B19">"HOLY THURSDAY,"</link> Plate 19 in
    *Songs of Innocence* and *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*<br/> Relief etching
   and some white-line etching, 1789. Bentley 139, Plate 19.<br/>Related to Object 14.</relationship><relationship><link type="compare" ptr="s-inn.b" objnum="B24">"Nurse's Song,"</link> Plate 24 in
    *Songs of Innocence* and *Songs of Innocence and of Experience*<br/> Relief etching
   and some white-line etching, 1789. Bentley 139, Plate 24.<br/>Related to Objects 14 and 15.</relationship></related></info>