<info id="bbwba14"><worktitle><div id="bbwba14.title"><h1>*Portrait of George Romney*</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="bbwba14.top"><p>
                In the final months of his three-year sojourn in Felpham, Blake began working on two sketches based on a painting of a shipwreck and a self-portrait by the artist George Romney. These were prepared as preliminary drawings for engravings to illustrate Hayley’s biography of Romney. In a letter to John Flaxman of 7 August 1803, Hayley reveals that Blake had “made two excellent drawings of Romney,” one of which was after an unfinished self-portrait of Romney in Hayley’s possession, before stating that he intends for both drawings to be “engraved for a single quarto volume of [Romney’s] Life” (Bentley, *Records*, page 157). In the same letter, Hayley reveals that after some haggling with Blake over fees, they had agreed on a price of 40 guineas for a portrait engraving of Romney’s self-portrait. 
            </p><p>Shortly after he returned to London, Blake wrote to Hayley on 7 October 1803, stating “I lose no moment to complete Romney to satisfaction” (Erdman page 736). Over the next few weeks Blake made significant progress on the plate, informing Hayley on 26 October, “I go on finishing Romney with spirit” (Erdman page 738). In a letter to Hayley of 13 December, Blake implies that the plate was sufficiently finished for proofs to be taken: “M<sup>r</sup> Romney[s] Portrait goes on with spirit. I do not send a proof because I cannot get one the Printers [*being*] &lt;having been this afternoon&gt; unable or unwilling &amp; my Press not yet being put up” (Erdman page 739). By the beginning of May 1804, Blake had either assembled his own press or convinced the copperplate printer to pull a proof impression, which Blake showed to one of Romney’s oldest friends, Adam Walker (Blake’s letter to Hayley, 4 May 1804, Erdman page 748). On 22 June Blake offered Hayley another update, citing his former partner, James Parker, to emphasize the plate’s quality: “Head of Romney is in very great forwardness. Parker commends it highly. Flaxman has not yet seen it. but shall soon, &amp; then you shall have a Proof of it for your remarks also” (Erdman page 753). On 16 July 1804 Blake finally sent Hayley a proof, “still [in] an unfinishd state” (Erdman page 753).</p><p>Blake continued to work on the portrait engraving during the second half of 1804. In his letter of 7 August, Blake describes working on “Romneys Head” with “Spirit &amp; neatness.” In a letter to Hayley of 28 September, Blake promises a second proof of the engraving: “You shall soon see a Proof of Him in a very advancd state. I have not yet proved it but shall soon when I will send you one” (Erdman page 755). On 23 October Blake claims that he will soon send proofs of “the Head of R” and repeats this claim in his letter of 4 December (Erdman pages 756-57). Blake finally sent Hayley the second proof on 18 December and ten days later sent Hayley a letter commenting that “I am very far from shewing the Portrait of Romney as a finishd Proof. be assured that with our Good Flaxmans good help &amp; with your remarks on it in addition I hope to make it a Supernaculum” (Erdman pages 758-60). In a postscript, Blake reiterates his claim that the portrait engraving required more work: “I made a very high finishd Drawing &lt;of Romney&gt; as a Companion to my &lt;drawings of the&gt; head of Cowper (you remember) with which Flaxman is very much satisfied &amp; says that when my Print is like that I need wish it no better, &amp; I am determind to make it so at least” (Erdman page 760). Despite these assurances, Hayley did not include the engraving in his biography of Romney, not published until 1809. Only Blake’s engraving of the shipwreck design appears in the book.</p><p>Blake’s sketch for the Romney portrait engraving was auctioned at Sotheby’s on 29 April 1862, lot 178, but has not been recorded since that sale. In his 1942 edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s *Life of William Blake*, Ruthven Todd claims that a copy of the engraving was in the Rosenwald Collection. There is, however, no record of it in that collection, now divided between the National Gallery of Art, Washington, and the Library of Congress.  The only known impression, only recently discovered, is the example published here.  </p></div></remarks><related><relationship>
            George Romney, *Self-Portrait*<br/>
            
            Oil painting, 1784. 
          <br/>
            
            National Portrait Gallery<br/>
            
            London<br/>
            
            Related to Object 1.
        </relationship><relationship>*Two Miniatures of George Romney*<br/>
            
            Water color (?), 1801. Butlin 348.
            <br/>
            
            Untraced since 1801<br/>
            
            Related to Object 1.
        </relationship><relationship>
        “George Romney”<br/>
   Etching/engraving by William Ridley after Romney, 1803.<br/>
   Multiple owners<br/>
   Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>*Sketch of George Romney*<br/>
            
            Pencil sketch (?), 1803. Butlin 349.
            <br/>
            
            Untraced since 1862<br/>
            
            Related to Object 1.
        </relationship><relationship>
        To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 26 October 1803.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Untraced; printed in Gilchrist, *Life of Blake*, 1880.<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
      Letter, 27 January 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
      Houghton Library, Harvard University<br/>
      Cambridge, Massachusetts<br/>
      Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 23 February 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    British Library<br/>
    London<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 16 March 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Morgan Library and Museum<br/>
    New York City<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 4 May 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Untraced; printed in Gilchrist, *Life of Blake*, 1880.<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 22 June 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Morgan Library and Museum<br/>
    New York City<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 7 August 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Collection of Robert N. Essick<br/>
    Altadena, California<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 28 September 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Library of Congress<br/>
    Washington, D.C.<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 23 October 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Untraced; printed in Gilchrist, *Life of Blake*, 1880.<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
        To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 4 December 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Library of Congress<br/>
    Washington, D.C.<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
        To William Hayley<br/>
    Letter, 18 December 1804.  Bentley 86.<br/>
    Untraced; printed in Gilchrist, *Life of Blake*, 1880.<br/>
    Related to Object 1.
</relationship><relationship>
        Frontispiece in William Hayley, *Life of George Romney*<br/>
   Etching/engraving by Caroline Watson after Romney, 1809.<br/>
   Multiple owners<br/>
   Related to Object 1.
</relationship></related></info>