<info id="biblicaltemperas"><worktitle><div id="biblicaltemperas.title"><h1>Paintings Illustrating the Bible</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="biblicaltemperas.top"><p>The Bible had an enormous influence on Blake’s work as both artist and poet.  Among his many and complex responses to that text is a group of paintings he created for his patron Thomas Butts, beginning in 1799.  Most were executed in that year and the next, but at least three were probably completed while Blake was in Felpham, 1802 and 1803.  Fifty-three of these “cabinet paintings” (as small works of this type were called in Blake’s time) have been recorded.  Only thirty are now traceable, seven based on the Old Testament and the remainder on the New.</p><p>The medium of these paintings, now generally called “tempera,” is water-based with a glue and/or gum binder.  Blake applied his pigments in multiple layers, including intervening applications of transparent glue or gum.  Outlines were often reinforced with black ink and the finished compositions glazed with glue.  Blake was probably trying to create jewel-like paintings; in his *Descriptive Catalogue* of 1809, he compared them to “enamels” and “precious stones” (Erdman page 531).  He never used the word “tempera” but called his medium “fresco”—a term that recalls Renaissance wall paintings—and claimed that he had invented the new genre of “portable Fresco” (*Exhibition of Paintings in Fresco*, Erdman pages 527), an alternative to paintings in oil.  Most were executed on canvas, but three are on copper and one (*The Agony in the Garden*) is on tinned iron.</p><p>Unfortunately, Blake’s medium was inherently unstable.  The pigment layers expanded and contracted at different rates.  Almost all his temperas of 1799-1803 show considerable surface cracking and other defects; many have been repaired at least once.  Some, such as *The Miracle of the Loaves and Fishes*, have been over-painted in ways that misrepresent Blake’s original work.</p><p>Blake’s biblical temperas of 1799-1803 can be divided into two groups according to size.  Most are approximately 27 x 38 cm., but five of the extant paintings measure about 32.5 x 49.5 cm.  The works in the larger size illustrate the life of Christ and may form their own series.  The four paintings of the Evangelists (two extant) may constitute another sub-category. </p><p>Most of the biblical passages illustrated by these paintings are associated with long-standing iconographic conventions.  Blake appears to have been aware of these traditions, probably learned through reproductive engravings.  Blake’s *Lot and His Daughters* is strikingly similar to Rubens’ painting of the scene.  Although Matthew 2.14 does not indicate that Joseph, Mary, and Jesus were accompanied by guardian angels and putti in their journey to Egypt, Blake’s *The Flight into Egypt* includes such figures in accord with many representations of the event from the fifteenth through the eighteenth centuries.</p><p>The paintings are arranged here according to the biblical texts illustrated.  Some of the subjects, including *The Christ Child Asleep on a Cross*, *The Body of Christ Borne to the Tomb*, and *Christ the Mediator*, are not based on specific passages but can be associated with events related in the Bible.</p></div></remarks><related><relationship>*Abraham and Isaac*<br/>

          Water color, c. 1780.  Butlin 108.<br/>

          Philadelphia Museum of Art<br/>

Philadelphia, Pennsylvania<br/>

Related to Object 3.
       </relationship><relationship>*Abraham and Isaac*<br/>

          Water color, c. 1780.  Butlin 109.<br/>

          Museum of Fine Arts<br/>

Boston, Massachusetts<br/>

Related to Object 3.
        </relationship><relationship>
        *Sketch (?) for “The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist.”*<br/>
        Pencil sketch, c. 1799 (?).  Butlin 407.<br/>
        Untraced since 1918<br/>
        Related to Object 13.   
        </relationship><relationship>
    	To George Cumberland<br/>
    	Letter, 26 August 1799<br/>
  	    British Library<br/>
  	    London
</relationship><relationship>*Tracing of “The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist, Who Approaches the Sleeping Infant Jesus.”*<br/>
            Pencil sketch, c. 1799 (?).  Butlin 408.<br/>
            Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>
            Cambridge, England<br/>
            Related to Object 13.
        </relationship><relationship>*The Christ Child Asleep upon a Wooden Cross Laid upon the Ground*<br/>

          Tempera painting, c. 1799-1800 (?).  Butlin 412.<br/>

Untraced since 1863<br/>
Related to Objects 15 and 16.
        </relationship><relationship>*The Raising of Jairus’s Daughter*<br/>
            Tempera painting (?), c. 1799-1800.  Butlin 418.<br/>
            Untraced since 1853<br/>
            Related to Object 19.
        </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/biblicalwc?descId=but475.1.wc.01">*The Baptism of Christ*</link><br/>
            Water color, c. 1803.  Butlin 475.<br/>
            Ashmolean Museum<br/>
            Oxford, England<br/>
            Related to Object 17.
        </relationship><relationship>*Eve Tempted by the Serpent*<br/>

          Pencil sketch, c. 1805-10.  Butlin 589 recto.<br/>

          Victoria and Albert Museum<br/>

London<br/>

Related to Object 1.

       </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/but529.1?descId=but529.1.wc.09">*The Temptation and Fall of Eve*</link><br/>

          Water color, 1807.  Butlin 529.9.<br/>

          Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery<br/>

San Marino, California<br/>

Related to Object 1.

       </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/but529.1?descId=but536.1.wc.09">*The Temptation and Fall of Eve*</link><br/> 

          Water color, 1808.  Butlin 536.9.<br/>

          Museum of Fine Arts<br/>

Boston, Massachusetts<br/>

Related to Object 1.

       </relationship><relationship>*Sketch for “Job and His Daughters”*<br/> 

          Pencil sketch, c. 1821.  Butlin 555.<br/>

Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art<br/>
          
          Washington, DC<br/>
          
          Related to Object 7.

       </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/but551.1?descId=but551.1.wc.20">*Job and His Daughters*</link><br/> 

          Water color, 1821.  Butlin 551.20.<br/>

          Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University<br/>

Cambridge, Massachusetts<br/>

Related to Object 7.

       </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/but550.1?descId=but550.1.wc.20">*Job and His Daughters*</link><br/> 

          Water color, c. 1821-27.  Butlin 550.20.<br/>

          Morgan Library and Museum<br/>

New York<br/>

Related to Object 7.

       </relationship><relationship>*Job and His Daughters*<br/> 

          Water color, c. 1821-27.  Butlin 556.<br/>

Private collection<br/>
        
        United States<br/>
        
        Related to Object 7.

       </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/but557.1?descId=but557.1.penc.25">*Rough Sketch for Plate 20, Job and His Daughters*</link><br/> 

          Pencil sketch, 1823.  Butlin 557.42.<br/>

          Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>

Cambridge, England<br/>

Related to Object 7.

</relationship><relationship>
       *Study for Plate 20: Job and His Daughters*<br/>
    Pencil sketch, 1823.  Butlin 557.49.<br/>
    Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>
    Cambridge, England<br/>
    Related to Object 7.
</relationship><relationship>
The twenty-two copperplates for the Book of Job, Object 21<br/>
    Copperplate, 1823-26.  Bentley 421.<br/>
    British Museum<br/>
    London<br/>
    Related to Object 7.
</relationship><relationship>
*Illustrations of the Book of Job*, Rosenwald proofs, Object 42<br/>
   Engraving, 1823-26.  Bentley 421.<br/>
   National Gallery of Art<br/>
   Washington, D.C.<br/>
   Related to Object 7.
</relationship><relationship>
*Illustrations of the Book of Job*, Rosenwald proofs, Object 43<br/>
   Engraving, 1823-26.  Bentley 421.<br/>
   National Gallery of Art<br/>
   Washington, D.C.<br/>
   Related to Object 7.
</relationship><relationship>
       <link type="object" ptr="copy/bb421.1?descId=bb421.1.spb.22">*Illustrations of the Book of Job, Object 22*</link><br/> 
Engraving, 1826.  Bentley 421.<br/>
Mutliple owners<br/>
Related to Object 7.
       </relationship><relationship>*The Agony in the Garden*<br/> 

          Medium and date unknown.  Butlin 843.<br/>

          Untraced since 1854<br/>
          
          Related to Object 23.
       </relationship><relationship>*The Agony in the Garden, Probably only Partly by Blake*<br/> 

          Monochrome wash drawing, date uncertain.  Butlin 375.<br/>

Private collection<br/>
          
          Great Britain<br/>
          
          Related to Object 23.
       </relationship></related></info>
