<info id="but557"><worktitle><div id="but557.title"><h1><i>Sketchbook Containing Drawings for the Engraved Illustrations to the Book of Job</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="but557.top"><p>Blake's pictorial engagements with The Book of Job extended over many decades.  His first efforts were a small group of wash drawings of the mid-1780s showing Job in his misery with his wife and three friends (Butlin 162-164).  Another version of this subject appears among Blake's emblem series he sketched in his Notebook (Butlin 201.20), but the composition appearing in the wash drawings culminated in the large intaglio etching/engraving, "Job" (Essick V) which Blake listed in his advertisement <i>To the Public</i> of 10 October 1793.  This print may have stimulated Blake's chief patron, Thomas Butts, to commission a tempera painting, <i>Job and His Daughters</i> (Butlin 394) c. 1799-1800 and, about six years later, a series of nineteen water colors illustrating the story of Job (Butlin 550, the so-called "Butts set").  In 1821, Blake and his new patron John Linnell borrowed the water colors from Butts.  Linnell traced the series and Blake colored them (Butlin 551, the so-called "Linnell set").  Blake also added two more compositions to this later group and added versions of these same compositions to the earlier group, so that both sets now have twenty-one designs.  The Linnell set led directly to his commissioning engravings.  These began as a series of reduced sketches executed in 1823 (Butlin 557); the engravings themselves, with a title page added, were not finished and published until 1826.</p><p>The sketchbook containing the reduced drawings, preparatory for the engravings, is presented here.  We have reproduced the full leaves, edge to edge, to give a sense of the work as a whole and to include the numbers top right, possibly inscribed by Linnell or a member of his family.  Also included are the covers that bear inscriptions, one by John Linnell (object 3), and others possibly attributable to Blake, Linnell, or members of Linnell's family (objects 1 and 32).</p><p>Blake follows the general outline of the story of Job in the Bible, but also incorporates into his designs many motifs representing his personal interpretation.  At the beginning, Job and his family attend only to the letter, rather than the spirit, of God's laws.  Job thereby falls under a false conception of God and into the hands of Satan.  Job's sufferings are recorded in the first half of the series, culminating in his horrific vision of a devil-god in the eleventh design.  Job's spiritual education and material restoration are pictured in the second half of the series.  In the penultimate design, Job tells his story to his daughters; the entire family is restored to life in the final design.  Some critics and biographers have interpreted the Job series as personal statements about Blake's own tribulations and the spiritual peace he found late in life.  However appealing this approach may be, it is made questionable by the earlier dating of the Butts series, the basis for all the later works.</p></div></remarks><related><relationship>             
            <link type="object" ptr="but146.1.wc.01">                 
                <i>Enoch Walked with God</i>             
            </link>             
            <br/>                  
            Water color, c. 1780-1785. Butlin 146.<br/>                  
            Cincinnati Art Museum<br/>                  
            Cincinnati, Ohio                
        </relationship><relationship><i>The Complaint of Job</i> (recto); <i>Standing Figure</i> (verso)<br/>
          Monochrome wash drawing (recto); pencil sketch (verso), c. 1785.  Butlin 163.<br/>
          Private Collection<br/>
          San Francisco, California</relationship><relationship><i>The Complaint of Job: "What is Man that Thou Shouldest Try Him Every Moment?"</i><br/>
          Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1785.  Butlin 164.<br/>
          Fine Art Museums of San Francisco<br/>
          San Francisco, California</relationship><relationship><i>Job, His Wife and His Friends: The Complaint of Job</i> (recto); <i>Job's Wife and Other Sketches</i> (verso)<br/>
          Monochrome wash drawing (recto); pencil sketch (verso), c. 1785.  Butlin 162.<br/>
          Tate Collection at Tate Britain<br/>
          London</relationship><relationship><i>Blake's Notebook</i>, page 20<br/>
          Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93.  Butlin 201.20.<br/>
          British Library<br/>
          London</relationship><relationship><i>Job</i><br/>
          Etching/engraving, 1st state c. 1793, 2nd state c. 1820-26.  Essick V.<br/>
          1st state: Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, England; Private Collection, London<br/>
          2nd state: Keynes Family Trust; Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, England; British Museum, London</relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="but394.1.pt.01"><i>Job and His Daughters</i></link><br/>
          Tempera painting, c. 1799-1800.  Butlin 394.<br/>
          National Gallery of Art<br/>
          Washington, DC</relationship><relationship><i>Job Confessing His Presumption to God Who Answers from the
          Whirlwind</i><br/>
          Water color, c. 1803-05. Butlin 461.<br/>
          National Gallery of Scotland<br/>
          Edinburgh, Scotland</relationship><relationship><link type="work" ptr="but550"><i>Illustrations to the Book of Job</i>: The Butts Set</link><br/>
          Water colors, c. 1805-06 and c. 1821-27.  Butlin 550.<br/>
          Morgan Library and Museum<br/>
          New York City</relationship><relationship><link type="work" ptr="but551"><i>Illustrations to the Book of Job</i>: The Linnell Set</link><br/>
          Water colors, 1821.  Butlin 551.<br/>
          Designs 1, 3-20: Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts<br/>
          Design 2: American private collection, Paris<br/>
          Design 21: National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC</relationship><relationship><i>Job's Sacrifice</i><br/>
          Water color, c. 1821.  Butlin 552.<br/>
          City Art Gallery<br/>
          Leeds, England</relationship><relationship><i>Sketch for "Job and His Daughters"</i><br/>
          Pencil sketch, c. 1821.  Butlin 555.<br/>
          Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art<br/>
          Washington, DC</relationship><relationship><i>Every Man also Gave Him a Piece of Money, Alternative Composition</i><br/>
          Water color, c. 1821-23.  Butlin 553.<br/>
          Tate Collection at Tate Britain<br/>
          London</relationship><relationship><i>Every Man also Gave Him a Piece of Money, Sketch for Alternative Composition</i><br/>
          Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1821-23.  Butlin 554.<br/>
          British Museum<br/>
          London</relationship><relationship><i>Job and His Daughters</i><br/>
          Water color, c. 1821-27.  Butlin 556.<br/>
          Private Collection</relationship><relationship>The twenty-two copperplates for the Book of Job<br/>
          Copperplates, 1823-26. Bentley 421.<br/> 
          British Museum, Dept. of Prints and Drawings<br/>
          London
       </relationship><relationship><i>Illustrations of the Book of Job: Six Proof Engravings with Marginal Drawings</i><br/>
          Engravings with pencil sketches, c. 1823-26.  Butlin 559.<br/>
          Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art<br/>
          Washington, DC</relationship><relationship><link type="work" ptr="BB421"><i>Illustrations of the Book of Job Invented and Engraved by William Blake</i></link><br/>
          Engravings, 1826.  Bentley 421.</relationship></related></info>