<info id="but829">
    <worktitle>
        <div id="but829.title">
            <h1> *Pilgrim's Progress* </h1>
        </div>
    </worktitle>
    <remarks>
        <div id="but829.top">
            <p>It’s not surprising that Blake would illustrate <i>The Pilgrim’s Progress</i>, second only to
                the Bible as the most read book in Britain and America in Blake’s time, but
                it’s difficult to determine his motivation for taking on the project and the
                designs raise several questions that are hard to answer.Part one of Bunyan’s allegorical tale was
                described on the title page as “the similitude of a dream” when first published
                in 1678. Blake began work on his
                illustrations no earlier than 1824 and left them unfinished upon his death in
                August 1827.</p>
            <p>In the last four years of his life, Blake was busy with
                several major projects, including the final stages of engraving his twenty-two
                illustrations to the Book of Job, the 102 water color and seven engraved
                illustrations to Dante’s <i>Divine Comedy</i>,
                an illustrated manuscript of Genesis, and the printing and detailed coloring of
                five copies of <i>Songs of Innocence and of
                    Experience</i> with a total of 270 plates. In light of these undertakings and Blake’s increasing bouts of illness,
                it is difficult to believe that he would further burden himself with the task
                of illustrating <i>The Pilgrim’s Progress</i>
                on speculation—that is, without a commission but in the hope of finding a
                purchaser. John Linnell, who
                commissioned the Job and Dante projects, would seem to be a logical candidate,
                but there is no record of his involvement. Object 20, <i>Christian with the
                    Shield of Faith, Taking Leave of His Companions,</i> was acquired, possibly as
                early as 1827, by Elizabeth (Mrs. Charles) Aders, a
                friend of Linnell’s who met Blake no later than August 1825 and in December
                acquired from him <i>Songs of Innocence and
                    of Experience</i> Copy AA. She may have
                commissioned the entire <i>Pilgrim’s Progress</i>
                group but kept only one of the few designs with fine, albeit incomplete,
                coloring by Blake. Aders apparently rejected the remaining designs or returned them to Blake’s widow,
                Catherine, because of their unfinished condition.The first written reference to the existence
                of the Bunyan designs, lacking only the one retained by Aders,
                is in the catalogue of Sotheby’s auction of 29 April 1862, lot 187, “a series
                of twenty-eight designs for The Pilgrim’s Progress.”The large number of works by Blake in this
                sale, offered anonymously “from the cabinet of an amateur” and possibly other
                vendors, were once in Frederick Tatham’s possession, although with an
                intervening collector and/or dealer. Tatham
                acquired Blake’s works remaining in his estate by inheritance or gift in 1831
                from Catherine Blake. Thus it seems probable that either the Bunyan water colors were executed without a
                patron or they are the product of a commission from Aders never completed.</p>
            
            
            
            <p>William Michael Rossetti, in his catalogue of Blake’s works
                published in the 1863 edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <i>Life of William Blake</i>, claimed that the Bunyan designs were “much injured by the handiwork of Mrs. Blake, the colour being untidy-looking and
                heavy for the most part, and crude where strength is intended.Two of the designs, at any rate, may be
                considered untouched by Mrs. Blake” (volume 2, page 235).Subsequent scholars have taken a less harsh
                view of the coloring, but most have accepted the idea that Catherine Blake,
                probably after her husband’s death, tinted many of the designs or at least
                substantially augmented coloring already executed by him.Attributions of the coloring of each design
                are briefly noted in Butlin 829.1-29. In
                the list below of each object we quote or summarize Butlin’s comments and add
                our own opinions about the attribution of the coloring to either William or
                Catherine Blake. These observations on
                coloring are also presented in the Editors’ Notes to each object.</p>
            
            <p>Object 1: Butlin states that the coloring was “more or less
                finished by [William] Blake himself.” Catherine Blake may have added a few touches to the coloring.</p>
            
            <p>Object 2: Butlin states that the coloring is “by
                Blake.” Catherine may have reinforced
                some of the dark areas.</p>
            
            <p>Object 3: Butlin attributes the coloring to Blake but adds
                that “the colouring of the sky near Evangelist’s extended right hand seems to
                have been reinforced.” The reinforcing
                may have been by Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 4: Butlin states that the design is “finished, but
                not by Blake.” We attribute most,
                possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 5: Butlin states that “Pliable seems originally to
                have been nude but is now clothed in blue and pink.The clouds look very dead and have probably
                been worked over, as have the outlines of the figures.”We attribute most, possibly all, of the
                coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 6: Butlin states that the design was “finished by
                another hand,” presumably Catherine’s. We attribute the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 7: Butlin states that “the figures and landscape have
                been finished by another hand,” presumably Catherine’s.The sky may have been colored by William but we attribute the coloring of the figures and
                landscape to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 8: Butlin states that the coloring is “mainly by
                Blake but with some touching-up, for instance the ink outlines on the figure of
                Christian and the colouring of the flames.” We attribute most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 9: Butlin states that the design was “finished by
                another hand,” presumably Catherine’s. We attribute most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 10: Butlin states that “the figure of Christian, the
                wall to his left and the sky appear to have been worked over, though the rainbow
                effect on the right of the gate is probably Blake’s.”The rainbow may be by William, but we
                attribute most, possibly all, of the other coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 11: Butlin implies that William colored the design,
                “with only a few outlines touched in in [sic] ink by a later hand.”We attribute the coloring to William and the
                ink outlining to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 12: Butlin states that the design was “left very
                unfinished by Blake but the cage heavily gone over in black and the figures
                touched-up” by another hand. We
                attribute most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 13: Butlin states that “both figures and setting have
                been heavily gone over [by another hand] to produce a finished watercolour, though the granular treatment of the flesh may
                be Blake’s.” We attribute most, possibly
                all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 14: Butlin states that the design, presumably
                including the coloring, is “entirely by Blake apart from some possible
                reinforcement in the dark blues.” We
                attribute most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 15: Butlin states that there is “some touching-up [by
                another hand] on Christian’s outlines; also the mauve edge of the leading
                Shining One’s wing.” We attribute most
                of the coloring to Catherine, but the blue sky may have been colored by
                William.</p>
            
            <p>Object 16: Butlin states that the design, presumably
                including the coloring, is “largely by Blake though ink outlines probably
                added” by another hand. We attribute
                most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 17: Butlin states that the design was “finished by
                Blake with the exception of the rainbow which seems to have been reinforced by
                another hand.” We attribute the coloring
                to both William and Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 18: Butlin states that the design was “finished by
                Blake with only slight reinforcement in pen” by another hand.We attribute most, possibly all, of the
                coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 19: Butlin states that the design was “lightly
                sketched and coloured by Blake. Prudence
                and the portcullis have been reinforced [by another hand?] and a streaky sky
                introduced into the solid architecture above the gateway.The penwork on Christian himself is probably
                original.” We attribute most, possibly
                all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 20: Butlin states that the design “escaped the
                going-over [by another hand] suffered by most of the rest of the series.”We attribute the unfinished coloring to
                William.</p>
            
            <p>Object 21: Butlin states that the design has been “heavily
                gone over in all parts,” presumably by another hand.We attribute most, possibly all, of the
                coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 22: Butlin states that the design was “left
                unfinished by Blake, with some subsequent reinforcement in pen of Christian’s
                head, the outlines of the main figures and the architectural forms
                behind.” We concur and attribute this
                “subsequent” work to Catherine. We also attribute
                to her the black coloring of the trees along the left and right margins.</p>
            
            <p>Object 23: Butlin states that the design was “left largely
                unfinished by Blake in pencil and delicate washes, though the colouring of the
                right-hand mountebank may also be his; the quartering and heavy outlines of the
                other one were almost certainly added later.” We attribute most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 24: Butlin states that the design is “unfinished,
                with outlines reinforced in pen or point of brush and some strengthening of
                colour in the flames” by another hand. We attribute most, possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 25: Butlin states that “all the outlines have been
                gone over and the greys, which fill most of the background, have probably been reinforced”
                by another hand. We attribute most,
                possibly all, of the coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 26: Butlin states that “the outlines of the figures
                have been reinforced in ink [by another hand], and the colour of the sky and
                the tone of the architectural landscape are probably not original.”We attribute most, possibly all, of the
                coloring to Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 27: Butlin states that “the heads and outlines have
                been reinforced in pen and ink [by another hand].The colour of the sky has probably been added;
                it clashes with the tones of the four shepherds.”We attribute the coloring to both William and
                Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 28: Butlin states that the design was “left
                unfinished by Blake and miraculously free from later accretions.”The coloring of the foliage may have been
                added by Catherine.</p>
            
            <p>Object 29: Butlin states that “the heads of Christian and
                Hopeful and their two attendant angels have been reinforced in pen and ink,
                and, although the rainbow-like bands of colour running through the figures are
                Blake’s, some of the heavier touches of colour on the angels’ wings may have
                been added” by another hand. We
                attribute the coloring of the background, lower left, and the landscape at the
                bottom to Catherine.</p>
            
            
            
            <p>In addition to Blake’s own inscription within the design of
                Object 10, the margins and versos of Blake’s water colors bear several
                inscriptions in pencil, both numbers (apparently an attempt to sequence the
                designs) and captions or titles above and below the designs.Transcriptions are given in Butlin 829.1-29, in
                G. E. Bentley, Jr., “The Inscriptions on Blake’s Designs to <i>Pilgrim’s Progress</i>,” <i>Blake Newsletter</i> 6.2 (fall 1972): 68-70,
                and in Sotheby’s auction catalogue of 14 November 1996, lot 253.With the exception of the title above the
                design of Object 23, these inscriptions are not shown in the Archive’s
                reproductions. We quote Butlin’s
                transcriptions in the Editors’ Notes to each object.Butlin suggests “that some at least of the
                numbers may have been the work of Blake himself” and tentatively attributes the
                long inscription top right on Object 2 to Blake, but does not attribute what he
                calls the “usual hand” that wrote all others. Bentley attributes all the inscriptions to Frederick Tatham, but in our
                view his authorship is questionable.</p>
            
            
            
            <p>Blake produced one further illustration to <i>The Pilgrim’s Progress</i>, a white-line
                etching titled <i>The Man Sweeping the
                    Interpreter’s Parlour</i>, based on a famous passage contrasting the harsh laws
                of the Old Testament to the salvific forgiveness of the New.The print probably dates from c. 1822 and
                thus at about the same time that the circle of young artists, including Samuel
                Palmer and George Richmond, who gathered around Blake in his final years began
                to refer to his dwelling as “the house of the Interpreter,” clearly an allusion
                to Bunyan’s text and possibly to the print as well.In “A Vision of the Last Judgment” that he
                wrote in his Notebook c. 1810, Blake comments as follows on <i>The Pilgrim’s Progress</i>: “Note here that
                Fable or Allegory is Seldom without some Vision Pilgrims Progress is full of
                it…” (Erdman page 554). Perhaps Blake intended
                his illustrations to expand the viewer’s mental state and thereby perceive the
                imaginative “Vision” within Bunyan’s allegory, the “dream” within the
                “similitude.”</p>
        </div>
    </remarks>
    <related>
        <relHeader>All Known Related Items</relHeader>
        <relationship>*Sketch, Probably for “Bunyan’s Dream”*
            Pencil sketch, c. 1824-27.  Butlin 830.
            <br/> Collection of Robert N. Essick<br/>Altadena, California<br/> Related to Object 7. </relationship>
        <relationship>*Sketch for “Christian
            Directed by Mr. Worldly-Wiseman”*<br/>
            
            Pencil sketch, c. 1824-27. Butlin 831.<br/>
            
            Untraced<br/>
            
            Related to Object 7.<br/></relationship>
        <relationship>*Sketch for “Vanity
            Fair”*<br/>
            
            Pencil sketch, c. 1824-27. Butlin 832.<br/>
            
            Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>
            
            Cambridge, England<br/>
            
            Related to Object 23.<br/></relationship>
        
        <relationship>
            *A Seated Man Spurning
            a Standing Woman, Perhaps for “The Pilgrim’s Progress”<br/>*<br/>
            
            Pencil sketch, touches of wash, c. 1824-27.Butlin 833.<br/>
            
            British Museum<br/>
            
            London<br/>
            
            Design not included in the water colors.<br/>
        </relationship>
        *Sketch Possibly for
        “The Pilgrimage of Christiana”*<br/>
        
        Pencil sketch, c. 1824-27. Butlin 834.<br/>
        
        Untraced<br/>
        
        Design not included in the water colors.<br/>
        <relationship>
            
        </relationship>
    </related>
</info>
