<info id="cpd">
  <worktitle>
    <div id="cpd.title">
      <h1>*The Large Color Printed Drawings of 1795 and c. 1805*</h1>
    </div>
  </worktitle>
  <remarks>
    <div id="cpd.top">
      <p>Blake's twelve large color prints, first designed and executed in 1795, are often
        considered to be his greatest works as a pictorial artist. Both their sublime imagery and
        the printmaking technique Blake used to create them evolved out of his illuminated books of
        1790-95. Although at least one of the prints, *God Judging Adam*, shows evidence of having
        been printed from a copperplate etched in relief, the other eleven appear to have been
        painted within pen and ink outlines on gessoed millboards (a thick cardboard) and printed
        onto large sheets of damp wove paper using a rolling press. From such a prepared matrix
        Blake was often able to print two impressions (a first and second pull) without repainting
        the matrix, and he finished all impressions in water colors and pen and ink. No more than
        three impressions of any one of the twelve designs are extant. After printing, each
        impression was worked up with pen and ink outlining and water colors. For a full technical
        description of Blake’s large color prints and their relation to the illuminated books and
        *Book of Designs*, see Joseph Viscomi, <a
          href="http://viscomi.sites.oasis.unc.edu/viscomi/Annus_Mirabilis/index.html">Blake's 'Annus
          Mirabilis': the Productions of 1795,"</a>*Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly* (fall, 2007):
        52-83.</p>
      <p>An impression of *Elohim Creating Adam* (Butlin 290) and an impression of *Nebuchadnezzar*
        (Butlin 304) may be untraced. There are twenty-nine extant impressions of twelve designs,
        all produced in at least two printings, c. 1795 and c. 1804-05. It is possible that, c.
        1805, Blake added more hand outlining and tinting to some impressions printed in 1795. No
        design has more than three extant impressions. As with the illuminated books, each
        impression is different due to variations in color printing and finishing. </p>
      <p> Modern scholars have interpreted the connections among the designs and their iconography,
        but no interpretation has become definitive. It seems as though the twelve subjects are not
        a series with a fixed sequence, but rather a group of designs centered upon images of the
        fallen world. Within that group are a few companion prints, such as *Elohim Creating Adam*
        and *Satan Exulting over Eve*, associated in subject, design, or both. The textual sources
        for the images range from the Bible to Shakespeare, Milton, and Blake's own poetic
        mythologies of the mid-1790s.</p>
      <p>The large color prints are widely dispersed. The Archive contains all extant impressions of
        the twelve designs except the last impression of *Hecate, or the Night of Enitharmon’s Joy*,
        in the National Gallery of Scotland, Edinburgh, which declined the Archive’s request for a
        high-resolution image. Eleven prints are drawn from the Tate Collection, by far the largest
        single collection; the others are from the British Museum; the Collection of Robert N.
        Essick; the Fitzwilliam Museum; the J. Paul Getty Museum; the Philadelphia Museum of Art;
        the Minneapolis Institute of Arts; the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery; the
        Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York; the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; the National Gallery
        of Art, Washington; a private collection; the Victoria and Albert Museum; and the Yale
        Center for British Art.</p>
    </div>
  </remarks>
  <related>
    <relationship>*The House of Death*<br/> Monochrome wash drawing, c. 1790. Butlin 259.<br/> Tate
      Collection<br/> London<br/> Related to objects 13, 14, and 15.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/mhh.a?descId=mhh.a.illbk.04">*The Marriage of Heaven
        and Hell*, Plate 4</link> Relief etching, 1790. Butlin 98<br/> Multiple owners<br/> Related
      to objects 8 and 9.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/mhh.a?descId=mhh.a.illbk.04">*The Marriage of Heaven
        and Hell*, Plate 4</link> Relief etching, 1790. Butlin 98<br/> Multiple owners<br/> Related
      to objects 20, 21, and 22.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/bb122.1?descId=bb122.1.ms.46">*Blake’s Notebook*,
        Object 46</link><br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93. Bentley 122.<br/> British Library<br/>
      London<br/> Related to objects 20, 21, and 22.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/bb122.1?descId=bb122.1.ms.50">*Blake’s Notebook*,
        Object 50</link><br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93. Bentley 122.<br/> British Library<br/>
      London<br/> Related to objects 20, 21, and 22.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/bb122.1?descId=bb122.1.ms.56">*Blake’s Notebook*,
        Object 56</link><br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93. Bentley 122.<br/> British Library<br/>
      London<br/> Related to object 4.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/bb122.1?descId=bb122.1.ms.108">*Blake’s Notebook*,
        Object 108</link><br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93. Bentley 122.<br/> British Library<br/>
      London<br/> Related to objects 25, 26, 27, and 28.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/bb122.1?descId=bb122.1.ms.114">*Blake’s Notebook*,
        Object 114</link><br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1790-93. Bentley 122.<br/> British Library<br/>
      London<br/> Related to objects 29 and 30.</relationship>
    <relationship>*God Judging Adam*<br/> Water color, c. 1790-93. Butlin 258.<br/> Estate of George
      Goyder, on long term loan to the Fitzwilliam Museum<br/> Cambridge, England<br/> Related to
      objects 5, 6, and 7.</relationship>
    <relationship>*The Good and Evil Angels*<br/> Water color, c. 1793-94. Butlin 257.<br/> Cecil
      Higgins Museum<br/> Bedford, England<br/> Related to objects 8 and 9.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Elohim Creating Adam*<br/> Planographic color print, designed 1795, possibly
      printed c. 1805. Butlin 290.<br/> Untraced<br/> Related to object 4.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Eve and Satan (?)*<br/> Pencil sketch, c 1795 (?) Butlin 293.<br/> Untraced<br/>
      Related to objects 29 and 30.</relationship>
    <relationship>*God Judging Adam*<br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1795, on the verso of *Europe*, Copy a,
      Plate 18. Not in Butlin.<br/> British Museum<br/> London<br/> Related to objects 5, 6, and
      7.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Hecate, or The Night of Enitharmon's Joy*<br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1795. Butlin
      319.<br/> Collection of Robert N. Essick<br/> Altadena, California<br/> Related to objects 10,
      11, and 12.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Nebuchadnezzar*<br/> Planographic color print, 1795 (?). Butlin 304.<br/>
      Untraced<br/> Related to objects 20, 21, and 22.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Newton*<br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1795. Butlin 308.<br/> Keynes Family Trust, on
      deposit at the Fitzwilliam Museum<br/> Cambridge, England<br/> Related to objects 23 and
      24.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Pity*<br/> Pencil sketch, c. 1795. Butlin 314 recto.<br/> British Museum<br/>
      London<br/> Related to objects 25, 26, 27, and 28.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Pity*<br/> Pencil sketches, recto and verso, c. 1795. Butlin 315 (recto
      only).<br/> British Museum<br/> London<br/> Related to objects 25, 26, 27, and
      28.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Christ Overcoming the Incredulity of St. Thomas*<br/> Tempera painting (?), c.
      1800 (?) Butlin 328.<br/> Untraced<br/> Related to objects 1, 2, and 3.</relationship>
    <relationship>*Ruth the Dutiful Daughter-in-Law*<br/> Water color, 1803. Butlin 456.<br/>
      Southampton Art Gallery<br/> Southampton, England<br/> Related to objects 18 and
      19.</relationship>
    <relationship><link type="object" ptr="copy/bb134.6?descId=bb134.6.ms.01">To Thomas Butts</link><br/> Receipt, 5 July 1805. Bentley 134.<br/> City of Westminster
      Archives Centre<br/> London<br/> Related to objects 5, 8, 13, and 16.</relationship>
    <relationship>To Dawson Turner<br/> Letter, 9 June 1818. Bentley 86.<br/> Rosenbach Museum and
      Library<br/> Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</relationship>
    <relationship>*Christ Showing the Print of the Nails to the Apostles*<br/> Pen and ink drawing.
      Butlin 329.<br/> Untraced<br/> Related to objects 1, 2, and 3.</relationship>
  </related>
</info>
