<info id="esxxi"><worktitle><div id="esxxi.title"><h1><i>George Cumberland's Card</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="esxxii.top"><p>This small card is Blake’s last work as an engraver.  The design and its execution in copper were commissioned by his friend of many years, George Cumberland.  The card may have been originally intended as a calling card rather than a bookplate.  The early history of the plate is well documented.  Blake first refers to it in his letter to Cumberland of 12 April 1827: “The Little Card I will do as soon as Possible but when you Consider that I have been reduced to a Skeleton from which I am slowly recovering you will I hope have Patience with me” (Erdman page 784).  Blake’s fatal illness did indeed impede work on the engraving, left unfinished at his death on 12 August 1827.  Cumberland’s son, George Jr., took delivery of the copperplate from Blake’s wife Catherine on 17 January 1828 and paid her £3.3s. for it.  Shortly after receiving the plate, George Jr. wrote to his father that “M.<sup>rs</sup> Blake sends her Compts with many thanks[;] she tells me that the Card would have been more finished if WB had lived[,] that it was the last thing he attempted to engrav” (Bentley, <i>Records</i>, page 482).</p><p>
                Cumberland had sent a copperplate of his calling card to Blake so that he could add a design to it.  This plate very probably already had Cumberland’s name engraved on it by a writing engraver.  Even if Blake began with a new piece of copper, a writing engraver may have added the name.  Blake appears to have executed his design with the graver and drypoint needle without preliminary etching.  Most extant impressions are on paper rather than card, in either black or brown ink, and may have been printed after Cumberland’s death in 1848.  There are no recorded impressions of the plate lacking Cumberland’s name; the copperplate itself is untraced.
                </p><p>
                Blake inscribed the plate, lower right, with his name and age, “A Æ 70.”  He may have sensed that 1827 could well be the last year of his life, but took pride in being capable of pursuing his art and craft to the end.  Blake was in fact 69 when he died; perhaps he inscribed “70” on the Cumberland card in anticipation of working on it until he turned that age.  At least when considered in retrospect, this most unusual inscription contributes to the elegiac and prophetic iconography of the design.
            </p></div></remarks><related>
<relationship>
To George Cumberland<br/>
Letter, 12 April 1827.  Bentley 86.<br/>
Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>
Cambridge, England<br/>
Related to object 1.
</relationship></related></info>