<info id="gravewd"><worktitle><div id="gravewd.title"><h1><i>Drawings for Robert Blair's "The Grave"</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="gravewd.top"><p>In October 1805, Blake was commissioned by the engraver and would-be publisher Robert H. Cromek to prepare forty drawings illustrating Robert Blair's <i>The Grave</i>, a popular "Graveyard" school poem first published in 1743. Cromek planned to select twenty of these designs for a de luxe edition of the poem. In Cromek's first prospectus of November 1805, Blake is named as both the designer and engraver of fifteen designs. Blake etched one image, "Deaths Door," in white-line, but Cromek rejected it. The dark power of the white-line print appeals to modern tastes, but was far from fashionable in the early nineteenth century.  In a second prospectus, also of November 1805, Cromek announced that Louis Schiavonetti would engrave twelve designs for the new edition. Blake had lost the potentially lucrative commission to engrave his own designs; his relationship with Cromek descended into anger and argument.  In spite of their disagreement, Cromek included a portrait of Blake as a frontispiece to the volume, published in 1808. Cromek promoted the book aggressively and the illustrations to <i>The Grave</i> became Blake's best known work through much of the nineteenth century.
            </p><p>Blake’s preliminary designs for the <i>Grave</i> illustrations include a few monochrome wash drawings.  We present here two of these works.  Object 1, <i>An Angel Awakening the Dead with a Trumpet</i>, may be an alternative version of the title page for Blake’s illustrations to <i>The Grave</i> or possibly a design for the “characteristic Frontispiece” Cromek listed in his first prospectus.  Object 2, <i>The Gambols of Ghosts According with Their Affections Previous to the Final Judgment</i>, was developed into a finished water color Blake submitted to Cromek, but it was not chosen for publication in the 1808 volume.  Selections of Blake’s pencil sketches and preliminary water colors for <i>The Grave</i> are also available in the Archive under their respective genre headings.
            </p><p>For further information on Blake’s illustrations to <i>The Grave</i>, see Drawings and Paintings, Water Color Drawings, <link type="work" ptr="butwba10">Illustrations to Robert Blair's <i>The Grave</i></link>; and Commercial Book Illustrations, Designed by Blake and Engraved by Other Engravers, <link type="work" ptr="bb435">Robert Blair, <i>The Grave</i></link>.
            </p></div></remarks><related><relationship><i>Illustration to Young's</i> Night Thoughts, Night II, page 5
            <br/>
            Water color, c. 1795-97.  Butlin 330.38.<br/>
            British Museum<br/>
            London</relationship><relationship><i>Vala, or The Four Zoas,</i> title page<br/>
            Pencil, pen and ink, c. 1797.  Butlin 337.1.<br/>
            British Library<br/>
            London</relationship><relationship><link type="compare" ptr="bb515.1" objnum="B12">Edward Young, <i>Night Thoughts</i>, object 12
            </link><br/>
            Etching/engraving, 1797.  Bentley 515, plate 12.<br/></relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="butwba10.1.wc.03"><i>The Gambols of Ghosts According with Their Affections Previous to the Final Judgment</i></link><br/> 
            Water color, 1805. Rediscovered in 2001.<br/>
            Private Collection
        </relationship><relationship><i>An Allegory of Human Life</i><br/>
            Pen and ink drawing, c. 1805 (?).  Butlin 637<br/>
            Untraced</relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="but611.1.wc.01"><i>An Angel with a Trumpet</i></link><br/> 
            Water color, c. 1805 (?). Butlin 611.<br/>
            Yale Center for British Art<br/>
            New Haven, Connecticut
        </relationship><relationship><i>Study for the Title Page (?): The Skeleton Re-Animated</i><br/> 
            Pencil sketch, c. 1805 (?). Butlin 609.<br/>
            Untraced
        </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="butwba10.1.wc.01"><i>Title Page: The Skeleton Re-Animated</i></link><br/> 
            Water color, 1805-06, with inscription dated 1806. Rediscovered in 2001.<br/>
            Private Collection
        </relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="but614r.1.penc.01"><i>Sketch for Alternative Title Page</i> (recto)</link>; <link type="object" ptr="but614v.1.penc.01"><i>Sketch
                        
                        Perhaps for the Same</i> (verso)</link><br/>
            Pencil sketches, c. 1806.  Butlin 614.<br/>
            Morgan Library and Museum<br/>
            New York City</relationship><relationship><link type="object" ptr="bb435.1.comdes.02">Robert Blair, <i>The Grave</i></link> (London: R. H. Cromek, 1808)<br/>
            With twelve plates after Blake's designs, etched and engraved by Louis Schiavonetti. Bentley 435A.<br/>
            Object 2
        </relationship></related></info>