<info id="milton"><worktitle><div id="MILTON.title"><h1>*Milton a Poem*</h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="MILTON.top"><p>One of Blake's two final epics, <cite>Milton</cite> follows the

      titular hero in a journey of self-discovery and renewal. In the

      poem's first "Book," John Milton returns from heaven to the mortal

      world and unites with the imagination through the person of William

      Blake. Together, they set out to reconfigure the relationship

      between a living poet and a great predecessor. In the second and

      final book, Milton unites with his feminine aspect, Ololon, in

      progress towards the apocalyptic overcoming of divisions between

      the sexes, between the living and the dead, and between human

      consciousness and its alienated projections into the external

      world. This plot is integrated with expansive references and

      allusions that range from the Bible to Blake's own life,

      particularly the difficult relationship with his patron William

      Hayley. Portions of <cite>The Four Zoas</cite>, Blake's long

      manuscript poem, are repeated (often with little revision) in

      <cite>Milton</cite>.</p><p>Blake etched forty-five plates for <cite>Milton</cite> in

      relief, with some full-page designs in white-line etching, between

      c. 1804 (the date on the title page) and c. 1811. Six additional

      plates (a-f) were probably etched in subsequent years up to 1818.

      No copy contains all fifty-one plates. The prose "Preface" (plate

      2) appears only in Copies A and B. Plates a-e appear only in copies

      C and D, plate f only in Copy D. The first printing, late in 1810

      or early in 1811, produced Copies A-C. Blake retained Copy C and

      added new plates and rearranged others at least twice; the volume

      was not finished until c. 1821. Copy D was printed in 1818. As a

      partly masked white-line inscription on the title page suggests,

      Blake may have originally planned to write twelve "Books" for

      <cite>Milton</cite>.</p></div></remarks><related><relHeader>All Known Copies</relHeader><relationship><link type="copy" ptr="milton.a">Copy A, c. 1811</link><br/>

        British Museum, Dept. of Prints and Drawings<br/>

        London

       </relationship><relationship><link type="copy" ptr="milton.b">Copy B, c. 1811</link><br/>

      Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery<br/>

      San Marino, California</relationship><relationship><link type="copy" ptr="milton.c">Copy C, c. 1811</link><br/>

      New York Public Library<br/>

      New York City</relationship><relationship><link type="copy" ptr="milton.d">Copy D, 1818</link><br/>

      Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress<br/>

      Washington, DC</relationship></related><related><relHeader>All Known Related Drawings</relHeader><relationship>
      <link type="object" ptr="copy/pid?descId=but85v.1.penink.01">*Four Composition Sketches*</link><br/>

    Pen and ink drawings, c. 1785-90.  Butlin 85 verso.<br/>

    British Museum<br/>

    London<br/>
    
    Related to Plate 38.
</relationship><relationship>*A Woman with Snaky Locks, Perhaps for "The Gates of Paradise"*<br/>

    Pencil sketch, c. 1793.  Butlin 202 recto.<br/>

    Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress<br/>

    Washington D.C.<br/>
    
    Related to Plate 45.
</relationship><relationship>*Sketch for "Milton" Plate 41/45: Milton and Ololon*<br/>

    Pencil sketch, c. 1804-06.  Butlin 560 recto.<br/>

    Victoria and Albert Museum<br/>

    London<br/>
    
    Related to Plate 41.
</relationship><relationship>
<link type="object" ptr="copy/jerusalem.e?descId=jerusalem.e.illbk.70">*Jerusalem*, Plate 70</link><br/>
Relief etching, 1804-c.1820.  Bentley 75.<br/>
Multiple owners<br/>
Related to Plate 4.
</relationship></related></info>
