<info id="s-exp"><worktitle><div id="s-exp.title"><h1><i>Songs of Experience</i></h1></div></worktitle><remarks><div id="s-exp.top"><p>Four copies of <cite>Songs of Experience</cite>, printed by Blake independent of <cite>Songs of Innocence</cite>, are now extant, although their letter designations are part of the sequence of the combined <cite>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</cite>.  Copies G and H, consisting of 17 plates (28-33, 37, 38, 40-43, 46, 47, 49-51), were produced in the first (1794) printing of <cite>Experience</cite>, along with what is now the “Experience” section of combined <cite>Songs</cite> Copy F and plates (designated copy T1) now integrated into combined <cite>Songs</cite> Copy T.  These four copies were probably printed before Blake had etched four plates (39, 44, 45, 48) for <cite>Songs of Experience</cite> and were produced by him as complete Copies at the time of printing.  Copies K and N (printed 1795) were once part of copies of the combined <cite>Songs</cite> (as their numbering in pen and ink indicates) but are now separate.  Copy K was once bound with the “Innocence” section of <cite>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</cite> Copy O; Copy N may have been bound with untraced Copy W of <cite>Songs of Innocence</cite>.  Two posthumous copies, k and l, contain only plates from <cite>Songs of Experience</cite>.

     </p><p> See also <cite>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</cite></p></div></remarks><related><relHeader>All Known Copies</relHeader><relationship>

        Copy G, 1794 <br/>

        Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>

        Cambridge, England</relationship><relationship>Copy H, 1794<br/>

      Maurice Sendak</relationship><relationship>Copy K, 1795<br/>

      Morgan Library and Museum<br/>

      New York City</relationship><relationship>Copy N, 1795<br/>

      Huntington Library and Art Gallery<br/>

      San Marino, California</relationship><relationship>Copy k, c. 1832<br/>

      Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>

      Cambridge, England</relationship><relationship>Copy l, c. 1832<br/>

      Fitzwilliam Museum<br/>

      Cambridge, England</relationship></related><related><relHeader>All Known Related Drawings</relHeader><relationship><i>Blake's Notebook</i>, pages 15, 21, 43, 54, 57, 65, 74, 89<br/>

   Pencil sketches, c. 1790-94.  Butlin 201.15, 21, 43, 54, 57, 65, 74, 89.<br/>

   British Library<br/>

   London</relationship></related></info>