<teiheader type="aacr2"><filedesc><titlestmt><title>The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake: an Electronic Edition</title><author>William Blake</author><editor>David V. Erdman</editor><respstmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Amy Sexton and Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities</name><resp>Creation of digital images:</resp><name>Amy Sexton</name><resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp><name>Amy Sexton and Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities</name><resp>Revisions to accomodate DynaWeb display:</resp><name>Greg Murray, Matthew Kirschenbaum, Andrea Laue</name><resp>DynaWeb programming:</resp><name>David Cosca and Susan Munson</name></respstmt></titlestmt><extent>2826 kilobytes</extent><publicationstmt><publisher>Eaves, Essick, Viscomi; IATH</publisher><pubplace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubplace><availability><p>Available from: The William Blake Archive</p><p>URL: http://www.blakearchive.org</p></availability><date>©2001</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt><p>The William Blake Archive</p></seriesstmt><notesstmt><note>Illustrations have been included from the print version.</note><note type="foreword"><p>This file, the electronic Erdman (eE), makes a fitting
new form for a work which began over thirty years ago in the preparation of
a text for the printed <title level="m">Concordance to the poetry and prose
of William Blake</title> and which now will serve as the basis for an even
more useful electronic version.</p><p>For assistance with this digital edition,
I am grateful to the University of Georgia Research Foundation and to University
of Georgia Department of English, especially its research assistants William
Cole, Margaret Crumpton, Patrick Darden, and Beth-Ann Neighbors. Alexander
S. Gourlay gave extensive help and valuable advice on several occasions. Also
offering assistance were Elisa E. Beshero, Gregg A. Hecimovich, Thomas A.
Vogler, and Paul Yoder. Thanks also to Mark Trevor Smith and Joseph Viscomi
as the first to spot needed corrections, and Alexander Gourlay, again, for
many, many more.</p><p>This "beta" release of eE offers an ascii version of
the 1988 Erdman text, with a line length of 65 characters. The commentary
and most references to it are not included. Textual notes are indicated by
a lower-case "t" in the right margin (the notes will be linked to the text
in a later release). The Erdman page numbers are at the bottom of each page
of text, surrounded by hyphen and space (- xxx -). A very few typographical
errors in the printed text have been silently corrected, and soft hyphenations
have been eliminated.</p><p>Presently in preparation are an SGML version
of this file, under the auspices of the Blake Archive, and an online concordance.</p><p>Corrections, suggestions, and comments are most welcome.</p><p>Nelson
Hilton</p><p>3 September 1996</p><p>Digital Blake Text Project</p><p>blaketxt@english.uga.edu</p></note></notesstmt><sourcedesc><biblfull><titlestmt><title>The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</title><author>William Blake</author><respstmt><resp>Editor</resp><name>David V. Erdman</name></respstmt></titlestmt><editionstmt><p>Newly Revised Edition, 1988</p></editionstmt><extent/><publicationstmt><publisher>Doubleday</publisher><pubplace>New York</pubplace><date>1988</date></publicationstmt><seriesstmt><p/></seriesstmt><notesstmt><note/></notesstmt></biblfull></sourcedesc></filedesc><encodingdesc><projectdesc><p>Prepared for The William Blake Archive</p></projectdesc><editorialdecl><p>The dtd for this markup is a composite of TEI dtds.  It was formed by Daniel
Pitti in the spring of 1997 using Arbortext.</p><p>The TEI dtds used are: tei.2, TEI.mixed, TEI.prose, TEI.verse, TEI.drama,
 TEI.transcr, TEI.figures, and TEI.linking.</p><p>All sgml files forming this document were verified using SGMLS.</p><p>All quotation marks have been replaced by entities.</p><p>All enjambed text in the printed volume has been formatted in continuous
lines.</p><p>Ornamental horizontal rules in the print version are indicated by the empty
TEI tag "lb" for line break, with a "rend" attribute having a value of "hardrule."</p><p>The images exist as archived 300 dpi TIFF images, and as 300 and 100 dpi
 JPEG versions for general use.</p><p>Images have been made of text with unique and/or difficult to reproduce
 formatting.  This enables the preservation of the appearance of certain 
problematic formatting.</p><p>The "rend" attribute has been applied liberally throughout the markup 
to reflect the orientation of certain text features as they appear in the
 print version. The most common values assigned to this attribute are  "left,"
"center," and "right."  A value of "1" for this attribute signifies  that
a given line, stanza, or paragraph has been indented.</p><p>Three potentially concurrent structures exist within the print version:
the  logical structure of each component work (e.g., a poem, a letter, etc.);
 the physical structure of the print volume's pagination; and the  physical
structure of Blake's original pages and plates.  The markup of  each structure
will be described in turn.</p><p>The book's logical structures are indicated by the use of numbered  divisional
tags.  Each logical grouping, or chapter, is marked as "div1",  and the subdivisions
within each chapter (individual works) are marked as  divisions numbered 1
through 3 as needed.  Front and back matter are marked  using unnumbered divisions.</p><p>The manuscript's pagination is indicated by the empty TEI tag "pb", or
 "page break," to which the "n" or number attribute has been applied.  Although
 the page numbers appear on the bottom of each page in the print version,
for  ease of use online, the page numbers have been repositioned at the top
of  each page.  Page content remains the same.</p><p>Blake's original plate or page structures are indicated by the empty TEI
 "milestone" tag.  The attributes "unit," "n," and "rend" have been added
to  this tag.  The first attribute describes the discreet structure of  the
original Blake artifact, be it a page or a plate. The second  indicates the
archival number assigned to each unit: often, the value of  this attribute
includes both Erdman's archival number and any number etched  or penned on
the artifact by Blake.  The third attribute, "rend," indicates  the palcement
of the unit and number information on a given page in the print  version.
 In this context, the value of this attribute is usually either  "left" or
"inline."</p><p>Any editorial or authorial notes contained within the body of the text
 are indicated by the TEI "note" tag pair, which has a "resp" attribute  indicating
the person responsible for adding the note.  This attribute has  a value of
"ed" if the remark was added by Erdman or "auth" if the remark  is Blake's.
 The latter value is used primarily within chapter 12, The  Marginalia.</p></editorialdecl><refsdecl><p>ID attributes are provided for each technical note.  Each ID is formed
by  pairing the suffix "TN" with the unique identifying number assigned to
each  note.  These unique numbers indicate the page number in the primary
text on  which the note marker appears, and its orientation among the notes
on that  page. For example, the fifth note on page 365 would have an ID of
"TN365.5".</p><p>Within the primary text, each technical note marker indicated by a  superscript
letter "t" in the print version has been replace with the  TEI tag "xptr,"
which has a "target" attribute containing the ID value  defined above.</p><p>Within the end matter, each technical note is enclosed in TEI "note"  tags
that have an "id" attribute whose value is described above.</p></refsdecl></encodingdesc><profiledesc><creation><date>1965</date></creation></profiledesc></teiheader>