<front><div1 type="etitlepage" id="a1"><p><hi rend="i">  Note: The editors of the William Blake Archive believe that its digital version of Erdman's texts of Blake, which we first published in 2001, is a convenience to users.  We recognize, however, that it is far from flawless.  We hope to publish a corrected and improved version when our resources allow.  Meanwhile, use the current implementation with caution, and check all quotations against the printed edition.  Comments are welcome.<lb/><lb/></hi></p><p><xptr doc="erdman.cover"/></p><biblstruct><monogr><title>THE COMPLETE<lb/>POETRY AND PROSE OF<lb/><hi rend="i">
William Blake</hi></title><edition>ELECTRONIC EDITION</edition><respstmt><resp>EDITED BY</resp><name>David V. Erdman</name></respstmt><respstmt><resp>COMMENTARY BY</resp><name>Harold Bloom</name></respstmt><imprint><publisher>Morris Eaves <lb/>Robert Essick <lb/>Joseph Viscomi <lb/>Institute
for Advanced Technology in the Humanities</publisher><pubplace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubplace><date>©2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblstruct></div1><div1 type="preliminaries" id="a2"><head>[Preliminaries]</head><div2 type="cover" id="a2.1"><head>[Cover]</head><biblstruct><monogr><title>The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake
</title><edition>Newly Revised Edition </edition><respstmt><resp>Edited by </resp><name>David V. Erdman </name></respstmt><respstmt><resp>Commentary by </resp><name>Harold Bloom</name></respstmt><imprint/></monogr></biblstruct><p><figure entity="erdman.cover"><figdesc>image of cover</figdesc></figure></p></div2><div2 type="halftitle" id="a2.2"><head>[Half Title]</head><p><hi rend="i">The Complete<lb/>Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi></p></div2><div2 type="blankpage" id="a2.3"><note>blank page</note></div2><div2 type="titlepage" id="a2.4"><head>[Title Page]</head><biblstruct><monogr><title>THE COMPLETE<lb/>POETRY AND PROSE OF<lb/>William
Blake</title><edition>NEWLY REVISED EDITION </edition><respstmt><resp>EDITED BY </resp><name>David V. Erdman </name></respstmt><respstmt><resp>COMMENTARY BY </resp><name>Harold Bloom </name></respstmt><imprint><publisher>ANCHOR BOOKS<lb/>DOUBLEDAY </publisher><pubplace>NEW YORK LONDON TORONTO SYDNEY AUCKLAND</pubplace></imprint></monogr></biblstruct></div2><div2 type="titlepageverso" id="a2.5"><pb n="IV"/><head>[Verso of Title Page]</head><p>AN ANCHOR BOOK<lb/>PUBLISHED  BY  DOUBLEDAY<lb/>a division of Bantam Doubleday
Dell Publishing Group, Inc.<lb/>1540 Broadway, New York, New York 10036</p><p>ANCHOR BOOKS, DOUBLEDAY, and the portrayal of an<lb/>anchor are trademarks
of Doubleday, a division of Bantam<lb/>Doubleday Dell Publishing Group, Inc.</p><p>Newly Revised Edition, 1988</p><p>Library of Congress Cataloging in Publication Data<lb/>Blake, William 1757-1827.<lb/>The
complete poetry and prose of William Blake.<lb/>First published in 1965 under
title: Poetry and prose of William      Blake.<lb/>I. Erdman, David V.    
 II. Bloom Harold.  III.  Title.<lb/>PR4141.E7 1981          821'7<lb/></p><p>ISBN: 0-385-15213-2<lb/>LIBRARY OF CONGRESS CATALOG CARD NUMBER 79-7196<lb/>COPYRIGHT©
1965, 1982 BY DAVID V. ERDMAN<lb/>ALL RIGHTS RESERVED<lb/>PRINTED IN THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA</p><p>9  8 </p></div2></div1><div1 type="acknowledgments" id="a3"><pb n="V"/><head rend="center">Acknowledgments</head><lb rend="hardrule"/><div2 type="section" id="a3.1"><head rend="center">1965</head><p>This new text of Blake's writings is in large part an outgrowth of six
years of labor over perfecting a text for the Cornell University <title>Concordance
to the poetry and prose of William Blake</title> (published in 1967).  The
editor is particularly indebted to his collaborators in this project, G. E.
Bentley, Jr, Palmer Brown, Robert F. Gleckner, George M. Harper, Karl Kiralis,
Martin K. Nurmi, Richard J. Wolfe, and Paul M. Zall, to the general editor
of the concordance series, Stephen M. Parrish, and to the presiding spirit
over all Blake textual study, Geoffrey Keynes.</p><p>     For generous help and encouragement both of us are grateful to Ruth
Aldrich, F. W. Bateson, John Beer, Morchard Bishop, Anthony Blunt, Edward
E. Bostetter, Fredson Bowers, Martin Butlin, S. Foster Damon, Robert Carl
Elliott, William Elton, Martha Winburn England, Wendy Erdman, Alvin Feinman,
the late Peter F. Fisher, John Fleming, Anne Freedgood, Northrop Frye, George
Goyder, John E. Grant, Jean Hagstrum, Geoffrey Hartman, Robert Hewetson, Desiree
Hirst, John Hollander, Arthur Hudd, Anne T. Kostelanetz, Margot Kriel, Lewis
and Heidi Lichterman, Paul Miner, Kerrison Preston, Martin Price, David H.
Stam, W. H. Stevenson, Irene Tayler, Craig Thompson, Michael J. Tolley, Willis
Van Devanter, and Lucyle Werkmeister; also to Marcia Allentuck, Margaret Manners,
Ellie Thompson, Marvin Sadick, and William Coakley.</p><p>     For their cooperation and courtesy in allowing original manuscripts
or illuminated works to be consulted and photographed we are greatly obliged
to the owners and curators indicated in the notes on sources, in particular
Frederick B. Adams, Jr., Lady Cunliffe and the late Lord Rolf Cunliffe, David
Foxon, John D. Gordan, Esther Harvey, the late William A. Jackson, Geoffrey
Keynes, William H. McCarthy, Paul Mellon, Kerrison Preston, Mrs. Landon K.
Thorne, Charles J. Rosenbloom, Lessing J. Rosenwald, Lord Rothschild, T. C.
Skeat, Lewis M. Stark, Willis Van Devanter, and Marjorie Wynne.</p></div2><div2 type="section" id="a3.2"><head rend="center">1982</head><p>     For particular assistance and general encouragement in the preparation
of this enlarged edition we are grateful to many of the persons named above,
in particular Marcia Allentuck, G. E. Bentley, Jr, Martin Butlin, William
Coakley, John E. Grant, Sir Geoffrey Keynes, Irene Tayler, and Michael J.
Tolley--and in addition: David Bindman, Clive E. Driver, Irene Chayes, Robert
N. Essick, Everett C. Frost, Robert F. Gleckner, William F. Halloran, Mary
Lynn Johnson, Maurice Johnson, John Kilgore, Robert Kolker, Mark Lefebvre,
Zulema R. Levine, Andrew Lincoln, Marilan Lund, John McLean, Francis Wood
Metcalf, Donald K. Moore, Alicia Ostriker, Michael J. Phillips, Dennis Read,
Robert J. Shroyer, William Strachan, and Joanne Witke.</p><p>     We are grateful to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, for enabling
us to use in this edition, in illustration of "A Vision of the Last Judgment",
the Rosenwald version<pb n="VI"/> of The Last Judgment (B-11,082), the painting
that has details closest to those of the manuscript text.</p><p>     And finally, after these words are set in type, they must convey a
special gratitude to the volunteer proofreaders Robert Essick, John and Mary
Lynn Grant, and E. B. Murray.</p><p>     We are all grateful to Tim McGinnis, our Doubleday editor, and to
the patient and precise compositors Diane Schlater, Nancy Nolte, and Sherry
Eddy.</p></div2><div2 id="a3.3"><head>[Modern Language Association]</head><p>     The Modern Language Association Committee on Scholarly Editions has
voted to award this revised edition its emblem of approval.  According to
the CSE chairman, Don L. Cook of Indiana University, this is the first time
that a volume that can be expected to receive immediate acceptance both as
a standard scholarly edition and a classroom text has received the CSE emblem.
 “We are particularly pleased to have been able to cooperate in this
wedding of scholarly and practical publishing”.</p><p>     The advice and inspection by the committee have inspired the editor
to reconsider and improve the exactness of the several kinds of editorial
treatment required by the diversity of textual sources.  “By award of
this emblem the CSE signifies that this volume is based on a thorough study
of the variant forms, is prepared through consistent application of explicit
editorial principles, records all emendations to the copy-text introduced
by the editors, and has been scrupulously and repeatedly proofread to prevent
unintentional alterations”.</p></div2></div1><div1 type="tocs" id="a4"><head rend="center">[Editors' Note]</head><note>Pages VII through XXII omitted from electronic edition.</note></div1><div1 type="preface" id="a5"><pb n="XXIII"/><head rend="center">Preface</head><lb rend="hardrule"/><p>This edition of William Blake seeks to supply a sounder and more uncluttered
text for reading than has been heretofore available, with a full apparatus
of variant and deleted passages for study. Many of these deleted passages
are printed here for the first time and allow us a comprehensive view of Blake
as a reviser of his own poetry.  Readers and students of Blake, with this
text before them, confront an accurate and well-nigh complete collection--some
erasures continue to defy transcription--of the writings of one of the greatest
of English poets, and certainly one of the most original, and most relevant
to us now.</p><p>The writings Blake issued in etched Illuminated Printing are given first,
as the major canon of his Songs, Prophecies, and Tractates.  The unpublished
long poems follow, and then the lesser works, predominantly in verse, from
 <title level="m"><hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi></title> to  <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi></title>.  Lyrics that were omitted from
the illuminated canon are brought together as <title level="a">“Songs
and Ballads”</title>,  with a further group of <title level="a">“Satiric
Verses and Epigrams”</title>.   The late prose treatises are followed
by the marginalia, other miscellaneous prose, and all of the letters. Verses
occurring in the Reynolds marginalia and in the letters have not been disturbed.
</p><p>Within these groups a rough chronology is observed, but only when thematic
or generic relations fail to offer more meaningful groupings.  A definitive
chronological sequence of Blake's writings is impossible from present knowledge.
</p><p>Lines in the longer poems are here numbered by relatively small units,
usually page or plate, since no standard numbering that suits a diplomatic
text has been established.  The numbering of plates for <title level="m"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title>, which varies in Chapter II, is that of the
British Museum, Rinder, and Morgan copies.  The problem of there being two
sections in the manuscript of <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas
</hi></title> titled “Night the Seventh” has been resolved with
the least injustice to the claims of narrative and the manuscript evidence
by conflating them into one Night VII.</p><p>The Textual Notes at the end of the book are exhaustive for the poetry,
and the designation of first, second, and later readings will permit reconstruction
of first and subsequent drafts.  For the prose, however, deletions and insertions
of any substance have been retained in the body of the text,<pb n="XXIV"/>
distinguished by appropriate bracketing; less significant deletions and mendings
are given in the notes; mended letters in the prose are generally ignored.
</p><p>Sources of the text are indicated at the head of each group or subdivision
of the notes, and problems of dating are discussed.  For a more detailed account
of editorial aims and procedures, see the introductory section of the Textual
Notes.</p><note>Paragraph on Harold Bloom's critical commentary omitted.</note><div2 id="a5.1"><head rend="center">SYMBOLS</head><p>     Superior letters call attention to textual notes <hi rend="sup">t 
</hi>.   Italics within square brackets <del>[<hi rend="i">thus</hi>]</del>
indicate words or letters deleted or erased or written over.  Matter in Roman
type within square brackets <supplied>[thus]</supplied> is supplied by the
editor.  Angle brackets <add>&lt;thus&gt;</add> enclose words or letters written
to replace deletions, or as additions, not including words written immediately
following and in the same ink or pencil as deleted matter.  For the poetry,
however, all these details are relegated to the Textual Notes except for the
few emendations necessary to avoid lacunae.</p></div2></div1><div1 type="nature" id="a6"><pb n="XXV"/><head rend="center">THE NATURE OF THIS<lb/> COMPLETE EDITION</head><p>Each (after the first) of the five printings of the 1965 edition of <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose</hi></title> contained several
minor and some major corrections.  This revised and complete edition has involved
a thorough correction of every section of the text and an extensive revision
of the Textual Notes.  Seventy letters added to section XV, making it now
Complete, constitute the bulk of the new matter, though several small items
have been added to sections XIII (Inscriptions) and XIV (Miscellaneous Prose).
 Most of the corrections of text have been small, corrections of spelling
and capitalization and of editorial bracketing or spacing.  Blake's eloquent
use of different colors in his hand-lettering of the Proverbs of Hell in copy
H has been interpreted by differences in spacing the groups of proverbs. But
a device impossible to reproduce and explain simultaneously is Blake's etching
of delete signs fitted to the tops of certain letters in a line in <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi></title>, inviting the reader
to read the line and immediately revise it. See the textual note.</p><p>     In the printings since 1965 there have been many corrections of readings
of words; there are more here, such as <quote>“mossy”</quote>
corrected to <quote>“massy”</quote>, <quote>“garden”
</quote> to <quote>“gardens”</quote>, <quote>“neatly”
</quote> to <quote>“nobly”</quote>, <quote>“I heard”
</quote> to <quote>“Heavd”</quote>.  Several mistakes in the deciphering
of deleted passages have been corrected, the most striking being the correction,
in the <title level="m"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title> preface, of <quote>
“entrusted their love to their Writing”</quote> to  <quote>“acknowledge
their love to their Deities”</quote> and, toward the end of the Lavater
marginalia, of <quote>“they converse with the spirit of God”</quote>
to  <quote>“these are either Good or Evil”</quote>.  The most
important revisions are the rearranging of the early tractates, in accord
with Geoffrey Keynes's new evidence, including the moving of the <title level="a">
“Conclusion”</title> from one tract to another; the improved transcripts
of <title level="a">“My Spectre”</title> and  <title level="a">
“Sir Joshua Praises Michael Angelo”</title> and extensive revision
of the apparatus of ms revisions of lines related to <title level="a">“Infant
Sorrow”</title>; a rearrangement of Blake's Thornton marginalia, because
of Robert N. Essick's discovery of the correct sequence of the loose pages
of the Thornton book; and, of greatest importance, the drastic revision of
the text of pages 5, 6, and 7 of <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas
</hi></title> and the conflation of what were previously treated as separate
Nights VIIa and VIIb into a single Night the Seventh. Of considerable importance
is the recognition that the <title level="a">“Joseph of Arimathea”
</title> couplets<pb n="XXVI"/> in the Notebook belong to <title level="a">
“The Everlasting Gospel”</title>.  And evidence supplied by E.
B. Murray and Mary Lynn Johnson has corrected the dating and identification
of the letters here numbered 20 and 24.</p><p>     It was the collaboration with Donald K. Moore on the 1973 and 1977
editions of the facsimile <title level="m"><hi rend="i">Notebook</hi></title>,
based on infrared photographs, that led to many improvements in the apparatus
of all the Notebook poems and prose, with Moore giving special attention to
the text of <title level="a">“Infant Sorrow.”</title> For the
revisions of Night I of <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi></title>
I have to thank Andrew Lincoln, who discovered that certain blocks of poetry
assumed to have been deleted had actually been marked by Blake for restoration--also
that the treatment of page 143 as a revision of page 7 was an editorial mistake.
 More recently three scholars, Andrew Lincoln and Mark Lefebvre and John Kilgore,
working independently and then drawing me into a fresh study of the thorny
textual problem of the harmonizing of the two Seventh Nights of <title level="m"><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi></title>, have made impressive clarifications of
the problem.  Blake simply left no instructions--to himself or to posterity--for
their arrangement (we do not even know what order they were in when he gave
the ms to John Linnell).  Editors are left with the problem of choosing a
sequence which will work best, in the context of the whole poem.  Neither
traditional arrangement, the relegating of VIIb to a postscript (as in the
previous Doubleday edition) or the printing of VIIa and VIIb in tandem (as
in the Longman edition), is an adequate response to the manuscript or to the
reader's appreciation of an inclusive yet coherent narrative or thematic sequence
or structure.  The Textual Notes may be consulted for an explanation of the
new arrangement and for the other sequences suggested.  As for the work of
recovering the numerous and extensive palimpsest passages in that ms, the
technology that may make that possible is emerging and hence the somewhat
distant promise of a still more complete text.  Meanwhile, of course, this
new printing will have its own fresh errors, which readers are urged to call
to our attention.</p><p>     The design on our cover, constructed upon plate 64 of the Mellon copy
of <title level="m"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title>, was inspired by our
editorial respect for the Committee on Scholarly Editions (CSE).  The proofreader
at the bottom with knuckles on text represents the five of us who, as required
by the Committee <quote>“to prevent recontamination of the text,”
</quote> will have been <quote>“scrupulously and repeatedly”</quote>
proofreading during the course of this book's production.  Why that left hand
held to shield the text from the light shining from the inspired (but nodding)
author, with quill on scroll beautifully unfolding to constitute a New Heaven?
Our attention must be upon what the author wrote, not upon our vision of his
vision, even though we keep watching.  That greater liberty is the reader's
privilege.</p></div1><div1 type="ltitle" id="a7"><p><hi rend="i">The Complete<lb/>Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi></p></div1><div1 type="blankpage" id="a8"><note>[blank page]</note></div1></front>