<exhibit id="illum" title="Illuminated Printing by Joseph Viscomi" article="illum.exhibit.html">

		<image dbi="1.1.100" id="1">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Tools of engraving</p></title>

      <caption>

          The two kinds of reproductive prints in the 18<sup>th</sup>
            century were relief and intaglio. In the former, the design
          is put into relief by cutting what is not part of the design below the surface,
          and in the latter, designs are incised into metal plates. Woodcut, an example
          of the former, was the first printing technique, in use by the late 14th
          century. Engraving, invented in the 15th century, was the first of the intaglio
          techniques. It requires gravers or burins (figs. 1, 2, C) with
          wedge-shaped tips for gouging lines into the surface of metal plates, scrapers
          (figs. 4, 5) to remove the metal forced up by the burin (the
          burr), and burnishers (figs. 6, 7) to polish lines smooth. A
          whetstone (fig. D) is used to sharpen the burins.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.2.100" id="2">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Tools and materials of engraving</p></title>

      <caption>

          Engravers also used a leather pad (fig. 9) upon which
          the plate is engraved and turned, a hammer and anvil (figs. 12, 13) to plane
          and repair plates, a tightly rolled piece of felt and oil (figs. 16, 19) for
          polishing the plates surface, a compass (fig. 17) for measurements, and
          calipers (fig. 18) to mark the point on the plates verso that needed to
          be hammered up when lines on the surface had been scraped down to erase a
          mistake.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.3.100" id="3">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Holding the burin</p></title>

      <caption>

          Burins are held in the palm of the hand (fig. 4) and
          pushed into the plate and away from the body (fig. 5). To make a curved line,
          the plate is turned on its leather pad while the burin ploughs straight. Unlike
          drawing, writing, painting, and etching, engraving is nonautographic and a
          skill requiring years of training. This is why most painters interested in
          making prints learned etching, a technique in which one uses a needle like a
          pen and thus drawing skills already acquired, rather than engraving.

            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.4.100" id="4">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Kinds of engraved lines and their combinations</p></title>

      <caption>

          Lines cut deeper into the plate will be wider, hold
          more ink, and print darker than those cut slightly (figs. 12, 13). By varying
          the depths and widths of lines, the engraver creates lines that taper and swell
          (fig. 10), and by combining and hatching them in various ways (figs. 6, 7),
          creates the illusion of tone and mass.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.5.100" id="5">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Engraving in practice</p></title>

      <caption>

          Engraving fine lines in the background of a recreation
          of Blakes Marriage plate 10, executed on a zinc plate.

      </caption>

		</image>
		<image dbi="1.6.100" id="6">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Engraving and Etching</p></title>

      <caption>

          The first engravers practiced pure
          engraving: an outline of the design was transferred from paper onto a thin wax
          ground covering the plates surface and the lines were cut directly into
          the metal with burins. By the 18<sup>th</sup>
            century, this practice had been replaced by
          mixed method engraving, a combination of etching and engraving,
          in which the design was first scratched through the ground with a needle and
          bitten into the plate with acid and then finished with burins (see series of
          illustrations demonstrating etching).

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.7.100" id="7">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">“Mixed method” engraving of the 18th century</p></title>

      <caption>

          Mixed-method engraving had become the economic and
          aesthetic norms, because it greatly shortened the amount of time required to
          produce a print and because the resulting line systems were believed (though
          not by Blake) to be more supple, versatile, and grand than either engraving or
          etching alone and hence superior to the works of the ancient
          engravers. As an apprentice to James Basire, a master engraver, Blake learned
          the arts of etching and engraving and excelled in the commercial styles then
          popular, and though he felt spiritually aligned with the ancient engravers, he
          did not emulate their practice until late in the last decade of his
          life.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.8.100" id="8">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Dot-and-lozenge line system</p></title>

      <caption>

          The complex hatching system seen here was known as
          dot and lozenge and came to define 18<sup>th</sup>
            -century engraving, for small book illustrations as well as
          the larger, separately sold, reproductions of paintings, and lives today in
          bank-note engraving. Whereas renaissance engravers had drawing as their
          paradigm, which guided how they made and combined lines and used the white of
          the paper, the modern engravers had engraving, now centuries old,
          as their paradigm, which had evolved into a highly artificial, albeit virtuoso,
          performance in metal in which every part of the design, even the highlights,
          were enmeshed in a unifying line system. Detail of
            <i>Orlando Uprooting a Pine</i>, engraved by Blake after Stothard. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.9.100" id="9">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Engravers as copyists</p></title>

      <caption>

          Despite their remarkable graphic language and skill,
          engravers were considered more copyist and craftsman than artist because they
          were not the inventors of the designs. The muse inspires the artist, pointing
          to his head as the true origin of the design, which moves from concept to work
          on paper or canvas and through the reproductive process, through etching (boy
          agitating the acid) to engraving, a move symbolizing the distance between
          original and copy. The dismissal of craft or execution as less significant than
          invention deeply bothered Blake; philosophically, in a platonic aesthetic, this
          hierarchy and separation extended to the artist as well, since the material
          artifact could not realize perfectly the idea as originally conceived in the
          mind. While Blake stated that he copied imagination as others copied nature, he
          countered this received hierarchy and separation by arguing that invention can
          only be known as it is executed and that execution generates invention.

            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1751-52. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.10.100" id="10">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Printing intaglio plates on the rolling press</p></title>

      <caption>

          Engravings, like all intaglio plates, are printed on
          rolling presses. A printer operates a rolling press, another inks a plate on a
          brassier, and another wipes a plates surfaces of ink in preparation for
          the press. The intaglio plate is placed face up on the long plank
          (bed) of the press, dampened paper is placed on top of it, and
          three or four felt blankets cover them as the bed passes through heavy top and
          bottom rollers. The top roller exerts great pressure to force the paper into
          the incised lines of the plate.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767.
          Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.11.100" id="11">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake,
          <i>Illustrations of the Book of Job</i>, Plate 12</p></title>

      <caption>

          In his 22
            <i>Illustrations of the Book of Job</i>
            engravings, published in 1826, Blake reproduced his own designs
          and, hence, as artist and engraver produced what was understood as
          original rather than reproductive prints. He
          returned to the earliest style of engraving, to the pure engraving practiced by
          his heroes, Albrecht Durer and Marcantonio Raimondi. The lines, engraved
          directly into the plate without preliminary etching, are densely laid in a
          parallel rather than cross-hatched style, as evinced by the detail of plate
          12. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.12.100" id="12">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Albrecht Durer,
          <i>Meloncholia</i>, 1514</p></title>

      <caption>

          The detail of Durers
            <i>Meloncholia I</i>, a pure engraving from 1514, reveals lines,
          flicks, untouched highlights, and sharp contrasts similar to those used in the
          Job engravings. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,  National Gallery of Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.13.100" id="13">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake,
          <i>Illustrations of Dante</i>, Plate 4</p></title>

      <caption>

          During 1827, the last year of his life, Blake engraved
          seven of his 101 watercolor designs of Dantes
            <i>Divine
          Comedy</i>
            . These are all unfinished, but it seems that he was again emulating
          renaissance models, as evinced by this detail of plate 4, in which form is
          defined in a more open, less dense manner than the Job, showing more of the
          white of the paper. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="1.14.100" id="14">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:skyblue">Engraving</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Andrea Mantegna,
          <i>Madonna and Child</i>, c. 1485-91</p></title>

      <caption>

          The detail of Andrea Mantegnas Madonna and
          Child, a pure engraving, c. 1485-91, reveals a manner of laying in lines and
          modeling form similar to that used by Blake in the Dante engravings. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,  National Gallery of Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.1.100" id="15">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake,
          <i>The Approach of Doom</i></p></title>

      <caption>

          By the last quarter of the 18<sup>th</sup>
            century, with new printing technologies capable of reproducing tone and the
          appearances of pencil, chalk, pen, and brush, prints in imitation of drawings
          and watercolors became very popular. Blakes first experiment in relief
          etching appears to have been
            <i>The Approach of Doom</i>,
          1788, after his brothers drawing. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.2.100" id="16">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Robert Blake,
          <i>The Approach of Doom</i></p></title>

      <caption>


            <i>The Approach of Doom</i>, pen and
          wash drawing by Robert Blake, c. 1786. British Museum.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.3.100" id="17">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Chiaroscuro woodcut</p></title>

      <caption>

          The first tonal printmaking process, dating from the
          mid-16
            <sup>th</sup>
            century, was invented to imitate drawings on
          colored paper in several monochromatic washes. It consisted of multiple
          woodcuts, with a key block for outline and one or two for tones, printed on top
          of one another. This technique, called chiaroscuro woodcut, was revived in the
          18th century by John Baptist Jackson, whose
            <i>Descent from the
          Cross</i>, after Rembrandt, was executed in 1738 as part of a series of prints
          in imitation of old master paintings. Yale Center for British Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.4.100" id="18">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Tools of Mezzotint</p></title>

      <caption>

          The first intaglio tonal method was mezzotint,
          developed in the late 17th century to reproduce the tonal gradations of oil
          paint. Mezzotinters work from black to white, rather than on a white ground
          with black line. The plate is roughened with a rocker, a tool
          with serrated edges (fig. 1) that incised the entire plate with thousands of
          overlapping lines to create, when printed, a solid black ground. Working with
          scrapers and burnishers, the mezzotinter reduces the ground and thus the amount
          of ink printed to create grays and whites (fig. 9).
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.5.100" id="19">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Mezzotint print</p></title>

      <caption>

          A detail of Richard Earloms mezzotint of
          flowers, after Jan Van Huysum, 1778, reveals a wide range of blacks, grays, and
          whites used to define forms without lines. Yale Center for British Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.6.100" id="20">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Tools of Stipple and Chalk engraving</p></title>

      <caption>

          Using multi-pointed needles (figs. 1-3), punches (figs.
          4-7), and roulettes (figs. 8, 9), engravers could create stipple
          and chalk engravings that imitated the appearance of chalk,
          pencil, and conté crayon (figs. 11-13). Abraham Bosse,
            <i>De la
          Manière de graver a leauforte et au burin</i>
            . 1758. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.7.100" id="21">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Stipple engraving</p></title>

      <caption>

          A detail of a stipple engraving printed in reddish
          brown ink in imitation of conté crayon, by Francesco Bartolozzi, a master of
          the technique. Stipples and mezzotints were often printed in colors and
          finished in watercolors. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.8.100" id="22">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Pure etching</p></title>

      <caption>

          The etched line is freer, more spontaneous and pen like
          than the engraved line, as is demonstrated by Paul Sandbys

            <i>Sketch of Tree with House in the Background</i>, c. 1760.
          Etching as a fine art, though, had a much smaller share of the English print
          market than engraving. Yale Center for British Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.9.100" id="23">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Etching with roulette imitating marks of a brush</p></title>

      <caption>

          A facsimile of Van Dykes pen and ink drawing of

            <i>Jacob Sending Benjamin with his Brethren into Egypt</i>,
          executed by William Ryland in 1762 for Charles Rogers 2 volume

            <i>A Collection of Prints in Imitations of Drawings</i>, 1778.
          Ryland used etching needles and roulettes to carefully reconstruct the
          appearance of pen and brush marks made spontaneously, imitating the look rather
          than the process of drawing. Yale Center for British Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.10.100" id="24">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Etching with mezzotint imitating pen and wash</p></title>

      <caption>

          A facsimile by Charles Knapton, c. 1760, of a wash
          drawing by Giovani Pannini, combining mezzotint rockers for tone and etching
          needles for outlines. Yale Center for British Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.11.100" id="25">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Aquatints, monochrome and colored</p></title>

      <caption>

          By 1775, the new technique of aquatint was used to
          reproduce wash drawings (detail, top) and watercolor drawings (detail, bottom),
          the latter often printed in two inks and hand colored.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="2.12.100" id="26">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:yellowgreen">New Printing Technologies</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Pen and ink sketch and facsimile reproduction</p></title>

      <caption>

          By the 1780s, prints in imitation of drawings were
          very popular, reflecting the taste for the autographic or spontaneous gesture
          of an artists first thoughts. The popularity of the sketch is evinced by
          the hundreds of rough drawings Cipriani (detail, top) provided Bartolozzi for
          reproduction (detail, bottom).

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.1.100" id="27">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Cutting plates from sheet of copper</p></title>

      <caption>

          Scoring the sheet of copper deeply with a needle,
          clamping it at the edge of a table under a second plate or steel ruler, and
          snapping it into smaller plates; alternatively, the plates could be cut out
          with a hammer and chisel on an anvil.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.2.100" id="28">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Planing the copper plate with charcoal</p></title>

      <caption>

          Copper sheets were hand-hammered and thus had fine, densely textured surfaces that could interfere with burins and needles. The plates were planed smooth first with charcoal.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.3.100" id="29">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Planing the copper plate with pumice</p></title>

      <caption>

          Planing the hand-hammered copper plate with pumice, or “snakestone” and water.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.4.100" id="30">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Polishing the copper plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          Polishing the copper plate with tightly rolled felt, powdered pumice, and oil, to remove scratches from the planing process.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.5.100" id="31">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Testing the plate’s surface for oil</p></title>

      <caption>

          Oily film on the copper plate, evinced by water not
          spreading across the plate, will prevent the waxy layer of acid-resistant
          varnish, called an etching ground, from adhering to the metal and
          cause it to lift off during the acid bath.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.6.100" id="32">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Degreasing the plate with whiting and water</p></title>

      <caption>

          The plate is cleaned or degreased of the
          oil with a paste of whiting and water.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="3.7.100" id="33">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber One: Preparing the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Testing the plate’s surface for oil</p></title>

      <caption>

          Oily film on the plates surface is removed, as
          evinced by the water spreading evenly over the plate. The plate is now ready to
          receive its etching ground.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.1.100" id="34">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Tools of etching</p></title>

      <caption>

          Tools of etching, showing taper for smoking the plate
          (fig. 4), dabber for spreading the etching ground (fig. 3), ball of etching
          ground (fig. 1 bis), copper plate with ground melted on its surface and spread
          into a film (figs. 1, 2), brassier (fig. 5), needles (figs. 6-9), brushes (fig.
          10), and stop-out varnish (fig. 11).
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>,
          1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.2.100" id="35">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Melting the etching ground</p></title>

      <caption>

          Melting etching ground onto a copper plate over
          electric heater.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.3.100" id="36">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Spreading the etching ground</p></title>

      <caption>

          Spreading etching ground into a thin film with a linen
          dabber.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.4.100" id="37">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blackening the ground</p></title>

      <caption>

          Blackening the ground with soot from a flaming taper so
          that lines scratched into it will show up with maximum contrast.

            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1751-52. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.5.100" id="38">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Technique for transferring drawing to plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          Transferring a design onto an etching ground using the
          calking or carbon paper method.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.6.100" id="39">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Transferring a drawing</p></title>

      <caption>

          Design is traced with a stylus onto the ground through
          a sheet of thin paper with red chalk on the verso.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.7.100" id="40">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The transferred drawing</p></title>

      <caption>

          Designs calked onto the plate are the
          same direction as the original and thus reversed in the impressions.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.8.100" id="41">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Counterproofing a design onto plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          Transferring a pencil design onto the ground using the
          counterproof method, in which a dampened outline drawing is placed faced down
          on the plate and passed through the press. The outline is reversed onto the
          plate, which means that it will be the same direction as the original drawing.
          This technique was often used for text.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.9.100" id="42">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Scratching the design through the ground</p></title>

      <caption>

          With the design transferred onto the copper plate, the
          etcher knows what to copy and, with the etching needle, scratches through the
          lines and darkened ground to expose the metal to acid, which, in the next
          stage, will etch the design into the metal.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.10.100" id="43">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Stop-out varnish</p></title>

      <caption>

          Standard tools in etching include stop-out varnish
          (fig. 11), which is a liquid ground made of resin dissolved in turpentine,
          stored in bottles, and applied with brushes from sea shells (figs. 12, 13).

            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.17.100" id="44">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Loading the quill with a brush</p></title>

      <caption>

          The stop-out varnish mixed with lampblack for color is
          loaded into the quill by a brush, a technique used by illuminators. Blake used
          stop-out varnish as an acid-resistant ink, writing and drawing
          with both quills and brushes as he would if he were working on paper. The
          printed results look like drawings not out of imitation but because Blake was
          actually drawing and writing with similar tools.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.11.100" id="45">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Writing with stop-out varnish as an ink</p></title>

      <caption>

          Writing with a quill in stop-out varnish directly on
          the plate in reverse so that it will print correctly.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.12.100" id="46">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Creating fine white and black lines</p></title>

      <caption>

          To create fine white and black lines, Blake could cut
          into the varnish with a needle as though it were an etching ground, as is
          evinced by the white lines in the vegetation in The Divine Image
          from
            <i>Songs of Innocence</i>, copy U (1789). Houghton Library, Harvard University.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.13.100" id="47">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake writing backwards</p></title>

      <caption>

          Blake picturing himself writing backwards with a quill
          in
            <i>Jerusalem</i>
            copy E, plate 41, detail. Yale Center for British Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.15.100" id="48">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Design executed in stop-out varnish</p></title>

      <caption>

          Design of text and illustration drawn directly on the
          plate
            <i>without</i>
            the aid of transfers. The lettering
          style, letter size, spacing between word and line, number of lines, the
          texts shape, the vignettes placement are all determined when the
          text is rewritten on the plate, which means that the parts that form the

            <i>page design</i>
            are visually composed when executed.
          Because the page design as such does not pre-exist its execution, relief
          etching produces rather than reproduces its designs.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.16.100" id="49">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Sketches for
          <i>Thel</i>
          plates 6 and 7</p></title>

      <caption>

          Pencil sketches for
            <i>Thel</i>
            plates 6 and 7, roughly blocking out space for text and vignette. British Museum.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="4.17.100" id="50">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:violet">Chamber Two: Executing the Design</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">
          <i>Thel</i>, copy H, plates 6 and 7</p></title>

      <caption>


            <i>Thel</i> Copy H, plates 6 and 7;
          the prints differ considerably from the sketches. The vignette beginning
          section III (plate 6) was used to conclude the section on plate 7, and the
          vignette used to conclude the section (plate 7) was completely redrawn and
          placed at the beginning of plate 6. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.1.100" id="51">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Diking the plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          Walling in the plate with wax to create a dike to hold
          acid.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.2.100" id="52">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Feathering the acid</p></title>

      <caption>

          Copper plate diked with wax walls to hold acid and an
          engravers assistant, or printmakers devil,
          agitating the acid with a feather.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1751-52. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.3.100" id="53">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Feathering gas bubbles from the lines</p></title>

      <caption>

          The acid attacks the exposed metal and bites the lines
          into the plate; the gas bubbles are removed from the etched lines with a
          feather to protect the ground from pitting or lifting.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.4.100" id="54">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Drying the plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          Removing the acid and drying the plate in preparation
          for stopping out portions of the design.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.5.100" id="55">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Stopping out areas of the design</p></title>

      <caption>

          Painting over areas of the design in stop-out varnish
          to protect them from the acid in subsequent bites; these lines will be the
          least deep and will print lightest.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.6.100" id="56">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Diagram explaining effects of stopping out</p></title>

      <caption>

          Lines bitten longest are deepest and print
          darkestand vice versa; by varying the time different areas of the design
          is in acid, the etcher varies tone and creates the illusion of aerial
          perspective and roundness.
            <i>Sculptura Historico-Technica</i>,
          1760.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.7.100" id="57">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Re-etching the plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          With the lightest lines stopped out, the plate is
          etched again, a stage that can be repeated many times, with new lines stopped
          out each time the plate is etched.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.8.100" id="58">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Removing the etching ground</p></title>

      <caption>

          The etching ground is removed with turpentine.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.9.100" id="59">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Design incised into the metal and edges beveled</p></title>

      <caption>

          The design has been bitten into the metal by the acid;
          the sides of intaglio plates must be beveled with a file so they do not tear
          the paper when the plate is printed with the great pressure required to force
          paper into the incised line.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.10.100" id="60">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Pouring acid on the plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          Pouring nitric acid onto a recreation of

            <i>Marriage</i>
            plate 10 diked with wax walls; the acid etches
          the bare metal so that it will become lower than the design, the areas drawn in
          the acid-resist, thereby putting the design into relief. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.11.100" id="61">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Feathering the acid</p></title>

      <caption>

          Agitating the acid with a feather to remove gas
          bubbles, which helps to protect the design from lifting, pitting, or being
          uncut.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.12.100" id="62">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Feathering gas bubbles, detail</p></title>

      <caption>

          Gas bubbles forming along lines of the design.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.13.100" id="63">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Feathering gas bubbles, detail</p></title>

      <caption>

          Removing the gas bubbles with a feather.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.14.100" id="64">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Stopping out delicate areas to protect them</p></title>

      <caption>

          After an initial bite to put the design into low relief, the acid is poured out and the plate is dried. The more delicate parts of the design are painted over with stop-out varnish to protect them from the acid in a second, longer bite. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.15.100" id="65">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Re-etching the plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          The plate is rebitten for a second, longer time that will put the design into printable relief; stopping out is for protecting lines and not, as it is in etching, to create tone. All the lines in a relief etching are on the same surface, which creates a two-tone print, like a woodcut.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.16.100" id="66">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Removing the wax walls</p></title>

      <caption>

          After the plate is etched into printable relief, the wax walls are removed.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.17.100" id="67">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Removing the acid-resist</p></title>

      <caption>

          The acid resist is removed with turpentine and the plate is ready to be printed; the sides do not need to be beveled because the relief plate will be printed with relatively light pressure, unlike intaglio plates.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="5.18.100" id="68">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:red">Chamber Three: Etching with Acid</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Fragment of an illuminated plate</p></title>

      <caption>

          A fragment of the only extant illuminated plate, a rejected plate from
            <i>America</i>
            (1793). It reveals a two-step biting process in the plateaus around the lettering, evidence that the letters were stopped out after a short initial bite.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.1.100" id="69">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Pigments for ink</p></title>

      <caption>

          Intaglio ink is made with powered pigments mixed with various grades of burnt linseed oil.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.2.100" id="70">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Grinding pigment in oil</p></title>

      <caption>

          The pigment is ground on a marble slab with a heavy grinder.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.3.100" id="71">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Mixing pigment in oil with palette knife </p></title>

      <caption>

          Mixing the ink with a broad palette knife.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.4.100" id="72">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Intaglio ink</p></title>

      <caption>

          The resulting intaglio ink is tacky and buttery.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.5.100" id="73">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Rubbing ink into incised lines</p></title>

      <caption>

          Using a tightly rolled piece of felt, the etcher rubs ink into the incised lines of the plate; this is usually done over a brassier, which warms the ink and makes it easier to spread.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.6.100" id="74">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Wiping the surface of ink with muslin rag </p></title>

      <caption>

          The plate’s surface is wiped of excess ink with a muslin rag.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.7.100" id="75">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Wiping the surface clean with palm of the hand</p></title>

      <caption>

          The plate’s surface and edges are given their finishing touches by being wiped clean of all ink and plate tone with the palm of the hand and a little whiting.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.8.100" id="76">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Inking with a dabber</p></title>

      <caption>

          The relief-etched plate was inked with tacky intaglio ink, the kind Blake was used to making, rather than relief ink, as is evinced by the reticulated textures on impressions. The linen dabber, with a bottom flat and stiff with dried ink, spreads the ink and is supported by the dense line system and the plate borders created by the wax walls, which help the dabber avoid touching the shallows.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.9.100" id="77">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The inked design</p></title>

      <caption>

          The design etched in relief is inked in black and the shallows of the plate are left untouched.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.10.100" id="78">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Wiping ink to erase lines</p></title>

      <caption>

          The thin borders along the sides of the plate and the cave forms at the bottom of the plate are wiped of ink, which erases these design elements since without ink they will not print.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.11.100" id="79">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Adding colors to the plate’s shallows</p></title>

      <caption>

          Colors can be added to inked plates and printed with ink simultaneously to produce a “color print.” The colors can be oil based inks or, in the case of Blake’s illuminated plates, water-based, pigments mixed with glue or gum Arabic. The water-based colors, should they dry on the plate, are reconstituted when printed onto damp paper.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.12.100" id="80">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Painting the plate’s illustration</p></title>

      <caption>

          The plate is painted in various colors with small brushes or dabbers in the standard color printing technique known as “à la poupée,” which was commonly used to print stipples, chalk engravings, and mezzotints.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.13.100" id="81">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The color-printed impression</p></title>

      <caption>


            <i>Marriage</i> Copy F plate 10, color printed c. 1794; visually, its colors are opaque and roughly textured, more like a la prima oil sketches than watercolors. The Pierpont Morgan Library.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="6.14.100" id="82">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:pink">Chamber Four: Inking the Plate</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake,
          <i>The House of Death</i></p></title>

      <caption>


            <i>The House of Death</i>, color-print drawing, 1795, from a series of twelve. These color prints, approximately 40 x 60 cm., brilliantly combine printmaking and painting. Most of the plates were printed twice, with the second impression a little lighter than the first because it was taken from the plate without it being recolored. Most of the plates were reprinted c. 1805. Fitzwilliam Museum.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.1.100" id="83">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Preparing paper for printing</p></title>

      <caption>

          For intaglio printing, paper is cut to size and dampened.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.2.100" id="84">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The rolling press</p></title>

      <caption>

          The intaglio plate is placed face up on the long plank (“bed”) of the rolling press, paper is placed on top of it, and three or four felt blankets cover them as they pass under the heavy top roller.
            <i>Encyclopédie</i>, 1767. Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.3.100" id="85">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The intaglio impression</p></title>

      <caption>

          After the intaglio print is pulled through the press, the paper is lifted off the plate and hung or laid flat to dry. Impressions from intaglio plates have pronounced platemarks, the embossment of the plate, because of the pressure necessary to force paper into the plate’s incised lines.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.4.100" id="86">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The rolling press and division of labor</p></title>

      <caption>

          Blake used his rolling press to print relief-etchings, adjusting it so it printed with less pressure. Whereas commercial printers of intaglio plates could use three people in the printing processone handling the press and paper, one for inking the plate, another for wiping ink from the surface of the plateBlake needed only two, since he did not have to wipe the surface of his plates clean of ink. He and his wife probably worked as a team, with Mrs. Blake handling the paper and press and Blake inking the plates and placing them on the bed of the press. Abraham Bosse,
            <i>Traicté des manières e graveur en taille douce</i>
            . 1645. Essick Collection.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.5.100" id="87">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">The relief-etched impression</p></title>

      <caption>

          The printed sheet is registered to the sheet under the plate or marks on that bottom sheet. Because the design is in relief and not below the surface, Blake printed his relief etchings with less pressure, which eliminated overt platemarks and enabled him to print on both sides of the sheet and thereby create books with facing pages, a style of printing he used till 1794, when he began printing on one side of the sheet only.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.6.100" id="88">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Printing in colors</p></title>

      <caption>

          In 1794 and 1795, Blake routinely printed his illuminated plates in colors, by painting the plate after inking it and printing ink and colors simultaneously. The color-printed impression was then finished in watercolors and pen and ink.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.7.100" id="89">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Making watercolors</p></title>

      <caption>

          Blake usually printed in colored inks and then finished his impressions in watercolors. He made his colors by mixing pigments into its vehicle, gum Arabic or glue.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.8.100" id="90">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Grinding pigments</p></title>

      <caption>

          Pigments are ground very finely into the vehicle on a slab with a flat pestle.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.9.100" id="91">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Diluting watercolor</p></title>

      <caption>

          The watercolor paint can be diluted with water to produce stains or translucency, or used undiluted or with whiting to produce a paint film and more opaque tones.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.10.100" id="92">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake’s early style of coloring prints</p></title>

      <caption>

          Jacqueline  Marshall hand coloring the master copy of “The Ecchoing Green” for the Manchester  Etching Workshop’s facsimile of
            <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i>
            copy B. The coloring is in Blake’s early style of illumination.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="7.11.100" id="93">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:purple">Chamber Five: Printing and Coloring Impressions</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;">Blake’s late style of coloring prints</p></title>

      <caption>

          “The Ecchoing Green,”
            <i>Songs of Innocence and of Experience</i> Copy Z, 1826, printed in orange-red ink and finished in watercolors, pen and ink, and gold, and given frame lines like a miniature painting. This was Blake’s late coloring style, used for nearly all works printed after 1800. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="8.1.100" id="94">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:blue">Chamber Six: Prints into Books</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;"><i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy E, 1789, in original wrappers</p></title>

      <caption>


            <i>Songs of Innocence</i> Copy E, 1789, as it left Blake’s printshop: the impressions were stabbed through three holes between sheets of wove paper (“wrappers”). In the 18<sup>th</sup>
            century, books were sold in uncut sheets, with binding the responsibility of the buyer. Blake knew that purchasers would have the books rebound to fit the style of the other books in their libraries. Berg Collection, New York Public Library.

      </caption>

    </image>
		<image dbi="8.2.100" id="95">

        <title><p style="font-size:x-small;line-height: 10px;margin-top: 4%;color:blue">Chamber Six: Prints into Books</p><br/><p style="font-size: 19px;"><i>The Book of Thel</i> Copy R, c. 1790, in original stitching</p></title>

      <caption>


            <i>The Book of Thel</i>, copy R, c. 1790; impressions stabbed through three holes and bound with string. Yale Center for British Art.
            <span>this is embedded html</span>
      </caption>
    </image>
</exhibit>
