<exhibit id="illuminatingvala" title="Illuminating VALA"
 article="illuminatingvala.exhibit.html">
	<image dbi="bb209.1.1.ms.100" id="1">
		<title></title>
		<caption>
			THE FOUR ZOAS<br/>
				
			The torments of Love &amp; Jealousy in <br/>
				
				The Death and Judgement <br/>
				
				of Albion the Ancient Man<br/>
			by William Blake 1797<br/>
		</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.2.ms.100" id="2">
<title></title>
<caption>
			
				Rest before Labour<br/>
			
			</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.3.ms.100" id="3">
<title></title>
<caption>
			
				
					
						[Greek text]<br/>
						4 lines of Greek text; Ephesians 6: 12<br/>
							
					
				
			
			
				
					
						[For we wrestle not against flesh and blood, but<br/>
					
					
						against principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the<br/>
					
					
						darkness of this world, against spiritual wickedness in high<br/>
					
					
						places. (King James version)]<br/>
					
				
			
			
				VALA <br/>
					
					Night the First<br/>
				
					The Song of the Aged Mother which shook the heavens with wrath<br/>
						
					Hearing the march of long resounding strong heroic Verse<br/>
					Marshalld in order for the day of Intellectual Battle<br/>
				
				
					Four Mighty Ones are in every Man; a Perfect Unity John XVII c. 21 &amp; 22 &amp; 23 v<br/>
					Cannot Exist. but from the Universal Brotherhood of Eden<br/>
 John I c. 14. v<br/>
					
					The Universal Man. To Whom be Glory Evermore Amen <br/>
						
							[kai eskanosen en [h]amen]<br/>
							Greek text<br/>
					
				
				
					
						[
							What<br/>
							]are the Natures of those Living Creatures the Heavenly Father only<br/>
					
						[
							Knoweth<br/>
							]no Individual <br/>
						
							[
							Knoweth nor<br/>
							]Can know in all Eternity<br/>
						
				
				
					Los was the fourth immortal starry one, &amp; in the Earth<br/>
					Of a bright Universe Empery attended day &amp; night <br/>
					Days &amp; nights of revolving joy, Urthona was his name<br/>
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.4.ms.100" id="4">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					In Eden; in the Auricular Nerves of Human life<br/>
						
					Which is the Earth of Eden, he his Emanations propagated<br/>
					Fairies of Albion afterwards Gods of the Heathen, Daughter of Beulah Sing<br/>
					His fall into Division &amp; his Resurrection to Unity<br/>
					His fall into the Generation of Decay &amp; Death &amp; his Regeneration by the Resurrection from the dead<br/>
						
				
				
					Begin with Tharmas Parent power. darkning in the West<br/>
				
				
					Lost! Lost! Lost! are my Emanations Enion O Enion<br/>
						
					We are become a Victim to the Living We hide in secret<br/>
						
					I have hidden Jerusalem in Silent Contrition O Pity Me<br/>
						
					I will build thee a Labyrinth also O pity me O Enion <br/>
						
					Why hast thou taken sweet Jerusalem from my inmost Soul <br/>
						
					Let her Lay secret in the Soft recess of darkness &amp; silence<br/>

					It is not Love I bear to <br/>
						[Jerusalem]<br/>
						It is Pity <br/>
						
					She hath taken refuge in my bosom &amp; I cannot cast her out.
				
				
					The Men have recieved their death wounds &amp; their Emanations are fled <br/>
					To me for refuge &amp; I cannot turn them out for Pitys sake<br/>
				
				
					Enion said—Thy fear has made me tremble thy terrors have surrounded me<br/>
						
					All Love is lost Terror succeeds &amp; Hatred instead of Love<br/>
					And stern demands of Right &amp; Duty instead of Liberty.
					Once thou wast to Me the loveliest son of heaven—But now <br/>
 <br/>
				
				
					Why art thou Terrible and yet I love thee in thy terror till<br/>
					I am almost Extinct &amp; soon shall be a Shadow in Oblivion<br/>
					Unless some way can be found that I may look upon thee &amp; live<br/>

					Hide me some Shadowy semblance. secret whispring in my Ear<br/>
					In secret of soft wings. in mazes of delusive beauty <br/>
					I have lookd into the secret soul of him I lovd<br/>
					And in the Dark recesses found Sin &amp; cannot return<br/>
				
				
					Trembling &amp; pale sat Tharmas weeping in his clouds<br/>
					
					Why wilt thou Examine every little fibre of my soul<br/>
					Spreading them out before the Sun like Stalks of flax to dry <br/>
					The infant joy is beautiful but its anatomy<br/>
					Horrible Ghast &amp; Deadly nought shalt thou find in it<br/>
					But Death Despair &amp; Everlasting brooding Melancholy<br/>
				
				
					Thou wilt go mad with horror if thou dost Examine thus<br/>
					Every moment of my secret hours Yea I know <br/>
					That I have sinnd &amp; that my Emanations are become harlots<br/>
					I am already distracted at their deeds &amp; if I look<br/>
					Upon them more Despair will bring self murder on my soul<br/>
					O Enion thou art thyself a root growing in hell<br/>
					Tho thus heavenly beautiful to draw me to destruction<br/>
				
				
					Sometimes I think thou art a flower expanding<br/>
					Sometimes I think thou art fruit breaking from its bud<br/>
					In dreadful dolor &amp; pain &amp; I am like an atom<br/>
					A Nothing left in darkness yet I am an identity<br/>
					I wish &amp; feel &amp; weep &amp; groan Ah terrible terrible<br/>
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.5.ms.100" id="5">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					In Eden,Females sleep the winter in soft silken veils <br/>
						
					Woven by their own hands to hide them in the darksom grave<br/>
					But Males immortal live renewd by female deaths. in soft<br/>
					Delight they die &amp; they revive in spring with music &amp; songs<br/>

					Enion said Farewell I die I hide. from thy searching eyes<br/>
				
				
					So saying—From her bosom weaving soft in Sinewy threads<br/>
					A tabernacle for Jerusalem she sat among the Rocks<br/>
						
					Singing her lamentation. Tharmas groand among his Clouds<br/>
					Weeping, then bending from his Clouds he stoopd his innocent head<br/>
						
					And stretching out his holy hand in the vast Deep sublime<br/>
					Turnd round the circle of Destiny with tears &amp; bitter sighs<br/>

					And said. Return O Wanderer when the Day of Clouds is oer<br/>
				
				
					So saying he sunk down into the sea a pale white corse<br/>
					In torment he sunk down &amp; flowd among her filmy Woof<br/>
						
					His Spectre issuing from his feet in flames of fire<br/>
					In gnawing pain drawn out by her lovd fingers every nerve <br/>
						
					She counted. every vein &amp; lacteal threading them among<br/>
					Her woof of terror. Terrified &amp; drinking tears of woe<br/>
					Shuddring she wove—nine days &amp; nights Sleepless her food was tears<br/>
					Wondring she saw her woof begin to animate. &amp; not<br/>
					As Garments woven subservient to her hands but having a will<br/>
					Of its own perverse &amp; wayward Enion lovd &amp; wept<br/>
				
				
					Nine days she labourd at her work. &amp; nine dark sleepless nights<br/>

					But on the tenth trembling morn the Circle of Destiny Complete<br/>
						
					Round rolld the Sea Englobing in a watry Globe self balancd<br/>
					
					A Frowning Continent appeard Where Enion in the Desart<br/>
					Terrified in her own Creation viewing her woven shadow<br/>
					Sat in a dread intoxication of Repentance &amp; Contrition<br/>
						
				
				
					There is from Great Eternity a mild &amp; pleasant rest<br/>
					Namd Beulah a Soft Moony Universe feminine lovely <br/>
					Pure mild &amp; Gentle given in Mercy to those who sleep<br/>
					Eternally. Created by the Lamb of God around<br/>
					On all sides within &amp; without the Universal Man<br/>
					The Daughters of Beulah follow sleepers in all their Dreams<br/>
						
					Creating Spaces lest they fall into Eternal Death<br/>
				
				
					The Circle of Destiny complete they gave to it a Space<br/>
					And namd the Space Ulro &amp; brooded over it in care &amp; love<br/>

					They said The Spectre is in every man insane &amp; most<br/>
					Deformd Thro the three heavens descending in fury &amp; fire<br/>

					We meet it with our Songs &amp; loving blandishments &amp; give<br/>

					To it a form of vegetation But this Spectre of Tharmas<br/>
					Is Eternal Death What shall we do O God pity &amp; help <br/>
						
					So spoke they &amp; closd the Gate of the Tongue in trembling fear <br/>
						
				
				
					What have I done! said Enion accursed wretch! What deed.
						
					Is this a deed of Love I know what I have done. I know<br/>
					Too late now to repent. Love is changd to deadly Hate <br/>
						
					A <br/>
						
							[
							ll<br/>
							]life is blotted out &amp; I alone remain possessd with Fears <br/>
						
					I see the Shadow of the dead within my Soul wandering <br/>
						
					In darkness &amp; solitude forming Seas of Doubt &amp; rocks of Repentance<br/>
						
					Already are my Eyes reverted. all that I behold<br/>
					Within my Soul has lost its splendor &amp; a brooding Fear<br/>
					Shadows me oer &amp; drives me outward to a world of woe<br/>
					So waild she trembling before her own Created Phantasm<br/>
						
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.6.ms.100" id="6">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					She drew the Spectre forth from Tharmas in her shining loom <br/>
						
					Of Vegetation weeping in wayward infancy &amp; sullen youth<br/>
					Listning to her soft lamentations soon his tongue began<br/>
					To Lisp out words &amp; soon in masculine strength augmenting he<br/>

					Reard up a form of gold &amp; stood upon the glittering rock <br/>
					A shadowy human form winged &amp; in his depths<br/>
					The dazzlings as of gems shone clear, rapturous in fury <br/>
						
					Glorying in his own eyes Exalted in terrific Pride<br/>
						
					The Spectre thus spoke. Who art thou Diminutive husk &amp; shell<br/>
						
					If thou hast sinnd &amp; art polluted know that I am pure <br/>
						
					And unpolluted &amp; will bring to rigid strict account<br/>
					All thy past deeds <br/>
						
							[
							So<br/>
							]hear what I tell thee! mark it well! remember!
						
					This world is Thine in which thou dwellest that within thy soul<br/>
						
					That dark &amp; dismal infinite where Thought roams up &amp; down<br/>

					
					Is Mine &amp; there thou goest when with one Sting of my tongue <br/>
						
					Envenomd thou rolist inwards to the place whence I emergd <br/>
						
				
				
					She trembling answerd Wherefore was I born &amp; what am I<br/>
						
					I thought to weave a Covering for my Sins from wrath of Tharmas <br/>
						
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.7.ms.100" id="7">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					I thought Tharmas a Sinner &amp; I murderd his Emanations<br/>
						
					His secret loves &amp; Graces Ah me wretched What have I done <br/>
						
					For now I find that all those Emanations were my Childrens Souls <br/>
						
					And I have murderd them with Cruelty above atonement<br/>
						
					Those that remain have fled from my cruelty into the desarts <br/>
					And thou the delusive tempter to these deeds sittest before me<br/>
						
					In this thy world not mine tho dark I feel my world within<br/>
						
				
				
					Mingling his horrible brightness with her tender limbs then high she soard<br/>
						
					Above the ocean; a bright wonder that Nature shudder'd at <br/>
						
					Half Woman &amp; half Spectre, all his lovely changing colours mix<br/>
						
					With her fair crystal clearness; in her lips &amp; cheeks his poisons rose<br/>
						
					In blushes like the morning, and his scaly armour softening <br/>
						
					A monster lovely in the heavens or wandering on the earth,
						
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.8.ms.100" id="8">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					Till with fierce pain she brought forth on the rocks her sorrow &amp; woe<br/>
					Behold two little Infants wept upon the desolate wind.
						
				
				
					The first state weeping they began &amp; helpless as a wave<br/>
					Beaten along its sightless way growing enormous in its motion to<br/>

					Its utmost goal, till strength from Enion like richest summer shining <br/>
						
					Raisd the bright boy &amp; girl with glories from their heads out beaming <br/>
						
					Drawing forth drooping mothers pity drooping mothers sorrow <br/>
						
				
				
					They sulk upon her breast her hair became like snow on mountains<br/>
						
					Weaker &amp; weaker, weeping woful, wearier and wearier<br/>
					Faded &amp; her bright Eyes decayd melted with pity &amp; love <br/>

				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.9.ms.100" id="9">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					And then they wanderd far away she sought for them in vain<br/>
						
					In weeping blindness stumbling she followd them oer rocks &amp; mountains<br/>

					Rehumanizing from the Spectre in pangs of maternal love<br/>
					Ingrate they wanderd scorning her drawing her Spectrous Life<br/>
					Repelling her away &amp; away by a dread repulsive power <br/>
					Into Non Entity revolving round in dark despair.
					And drawing in the Spectrous life in pride and haughty joy<br/>
						
					Thus Enion gave them all her spectrous life<br/>
						
				
				
					Then Eno a daughter of Beulah took a Moment of Time <br/>
						
					And drew it out to Seven thousand years with much care &amp; affliction<br/>
						
					And many tears &amp; in Every year made windows into Eden <br/>
						
					
					She also took an atom of space &amp; opend its center<br/>
					Into Infinitude &amp; ornamented it with wondrous art<br/>
					Astonishd sat her Sisters of Beulah to see her soft affections<br/>
					To Enion &amp; her children &amp; they ponderd these things wondring <br/>

					And they Alternate kept watch over the Youthful terrors<br/>
					They saw not yet the Hand Divine for it was not yet reveald<br/>
					But they went on in Silent Hope &amp; Feminine repose<br/>
				
				
					But Los &amp; Enitharmon delighted in the Moony spaces of Eno <br/>
						
					Nine Times they livd among the forests, feeding on sweet fruits<br/>

					And nine bright Spaces wanderd weaving mazes of delight<br/>
					Snaring the wild Goats for their milk they eat the flesh of Lambs<br/>

					A male &amp; female naked &amp; ruddy as the pride of summer<br/>
					Alternate Love &amp; Hate his breast; hers Scorn &amp; Jealousy<br/>

					In embryon passions. they kiss'd not nor embrac'd for shame &amp; fear<br/>
						
					His head beamd light &amp; in his vigorous voice was prophecy<br/>
					He could controll the times &amp; seasons, &amp; the days &amp; years<br/>
					She could controll the spaces, regions, desart, flood &amp; forest<br/>

					But had no power to weave a Veil of covering for her Sins<br/>
					She drave the Females all away from Los<br/>
					And Los drave all the Males from her away<br/>
					They wanderd long, till they sat down upon the margind sea.
					Conversing with the visions of Beulah in dark slumberous bliss<br/>
						
				
				
					But the two youthful wonders wanderd in the world of Tharmas<br/>
						
					Thy name is Enitharmon; said the fierce prophetic boy<br/>
						
					While thy mild voice fills all these Caverns with sweet harmony<br/>

					O how our Parents sit &amp; mourn in their silent secret bowers<br/>
						
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.10.ms.100" id="10">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					But Enitharmon answerd with a dropping tear &amp; frowning<br/>
						
					Dark as a dewy morning when the crimson light appears <br/>
						
					To make us happy let them weary their immortal powers <br/>
						
					While we draw in their sweet delights while we return them scorn<br/>
						
					On scorn to feed our discontent; for if we grateful prove<br/>
					They will withhold sweet love, whose food is thorns &amp; bitter roots.
					We hear the warlike clarions we view the turning spheres<br/>
						
					Yet Thou in indolence reposest holding me in bonds<br/>
					Hear! I will sing a Song of Death! it is a Song of Vala!
						
					The Fallen Man takes his repose: Urizen sleeps in the porch<br/>
						
					Luvah and Vala woke &amp; flew up from the Human Heart<br/>
						
					Into the Brain; from thence upon the pillow Vala slumber'd.
					And Luvah siez'd the Horses of Light, &amp; rose into the Chariot of Day<br/>
					Sweet laughter siezd me in my sleep! silent &amp; close I laughd<br/>
						
					For in the visions of Vala I walkd with the mighty Fallen One <br/>
						
					I heard his voice among the branches, &amp; among sweet flowers.
						
					
					Why is the light of Enitharmon darken'd in dewy morn<br/>
						
					Why is the silence of Enitharmon a terror &amp; her smile a whirlwind<br/>
						
					Uttering this darkness in my halls, in the pillars of my Holy-ones<br/>

					Why dost thou weep as Vala? &amp; wet thy veil with dewy tears,
						
					In slumbers of my night-repose, infusing a false morning?
					Driving the Female Emanations all away from Los <br/>
						
					I have refusd to look upon the Universal Vision<br/>
					And wilt thou slay with death him who devotes himself to thee<br/>
						
					Once born for the sport &amp; amusement of Man now born to drink up all his Powers<br/>
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.11.ms.100" id="11">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					I heard the sounding sea; I heard the voice weaker and weaker;
					The voice came &amp; went like a dream, I awoke in my sweet bliss.

					Then Los smote her upon the Earth twas long eer she revivd<br/>
					He answer'd, darkning more with indignation hid in smiles<br/>
						
				
				
					I die not Enitharmon tho thou singst thy Song of Death<br/>
						
					Nor shalt thou me torment For I behold the Fallen Man<br/>
						
					Seeking to comfort Vala, she will not be comforted<br/>
						
					She rises from his throne and seeks the shadows of her garden<br/>
					Weeping for Luvah lost, in the bloody beams of your false morning<br/>

					Sickning lies the Fallen Man his head sick his heart faint<br/>
						
					Mighty atchievement of your power! Beware the punishment<br/>
					I see, invisible descend into the Gardens of Vala<br/>
					Luvah walking on the winds, I see the invisible knife<br/>
					I see the shower of blood: I see the swords &amp; spears of futurity<br/>

					Tho in the Brain of Man we live, &amp; in his circling Nerves. <br/>

					Tho' this bright world of all our joy is in the Human Brain.
					Where Urizen &amp; all his Hosts hang their immortal lamps<br/>
					Thou neer shalt leave this cold expanse where watry Tharmas mourns<br/>

				
				
					So spoke Los. Scorn &amp; Indignation rose upon Enitharmon<br/>
					Then Enitharmon reddning fierce stretchd her immortal hands <br/>
						
				
				
					Descend O Urizen descend with horse &amp; chariots<br/>
					Threaten not me O visionary thine the punishment<br/>
					The Human Nature shall no more remain nor Human acts<br/>
					Form the rebellious Spirits of Heaven. but War &amp; Princedom &amp; Victory &amp; Blood<br/>
						
				
				</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.12.ms.100" id="12">
<title></title>
<caption>
				
					Night darkend as she spoke! a shuddring ran from East to West<br/>
						
					A Groan was heard on high. The warlike clarions ceast. the Spirits <br/>

					Of Luvah &amp; Vala shudderd in their Orb: an orb of blood! <br/>
						
				
				
					Eternity groand &amp; was troubled at the Image of Eternal Death<br/>

					The Wandering Man bow'd his faint head and Urizen descended<br/>
					And the one must have murderd the other if he had not descended <br/>
						
					
					Indignant muttering low thunders; Urizen descended<br/>
					Gloomy sounding, Now I am God from Eternity to Eternity<br/>
				
				
					Sullen sat Los plotting Revenge. Silent he eye'd the Prince <br/>
						
					Of Light. Silent the prince of Light viewd Los. at length a brooded<br/>
						
					Smile broke from Urizen for Enitharmon brightend more &amp; more<br/>

					Sullen he lowerd on Enitharmon but he smild on Los<br/>
				
				
					Saying Thou art the Lord of Luvah into thine hands I give<br/>
					The prince of Love the murderer his soul is in thine hands<br/>
					Pity not Vala for she pitied not the Eternal Man <br/>
					Nor pity thou the cries of Luvah. Lo these starry hosts<br/>
					They are thy servants if thou wilt obey my awful Law<br/>
				
				
					Los answerd furious art thou one of those who when most complacent<br/>

					Mean mischief most. If you are such Lo! I am also such<br/>
					One must be master. try thy Arts I also will try mine<br/>
					For I percieve Thou hast Abundance which I claim as mine<br/>
				
				
					Urizen startled stood but not Long soon he cried<br/>
					Obey my voice young Demon I am God from Eternity to Eternity<br/>
					
						Thus Urizen spoke collected in himself in awful pride<br/>
					
					
						Art thou a visionary of Jesus the soft delusion of Eternity <br/>
						Lo I am God the terrible destroyer &amp; not the Saviour<br/>
						Why should the Divine Vision compell the sons of Eden<br/>
						to forego each his own delight to war against his Spectre <br/>
							
						The Spectre is the Man the rest is only delusion &amp; fancy<br/>
					
					
						So spoke the Prince of Light &amp; sat beside the Seat of Los<br/>
						Upon the sandy shore rested his chariot of fire<br/>
					
					
						Ten thousand thousand were his hosts of spirits on the wind:
						Ten thousand thousand glittering Chariots shining in the sky:
						They pour upon the golden shore beside the silent ocean.
						Rejoicing in the Victory &amp; the heavens were filld with blood<br/>
							
					
					
						The Earth spread forth her table wide. the Night a silver cup<br/>
						Fill'd with the wine of anguish waited at the golden feast<br/>
						But the bright Sun was not as yet; he filling all the expanse<br/>
						Slept as a bird in the blue shell that soon shall burst away<br/>
					
					
						Los saw the wound of his blow he saw he pitied he wept<br/>
							
						Los now repented that he had smitten Enitharmon he felt love<br/>
						Arise in all his Veins he threw his arms around her loins<br/>
						To heal the wound of his smiting<br/>
					
					
						They eat the fleshly bread, they drank the nervous wine<br/>
							
					
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.13.ms.100" id="13">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						They listend to the Elemental Harps &amp; Sphery Song<br/>
						They view'd the dancing Hours, quick sporting thro' the sky <br/>
						With winged radiance scattering joys thro the ever changing light<br/>

					
					
						But Luvah &amp; Vala standing in the bloody sky <br/>
							
						On high remaind alone forsaken in fierce jealousy<br/>
						They stood above the heavens forsaken desolate suspended in blood<br/>

						Descend they could not. nor from Each other avert their eyes<br/>
						Eternity appeard above them as One Man infolded<br/>
						In Luvah<br/>
							[s]<br/>
							robes of blood &amp; bearing all his afflictions<br/>
							
						As the sun shines down on the misty earth Such was the Vision<br/>
					
					
						But purple night and crimson morning &amp; golden day descending<br/>
							
						Thro' the clear changing atmosphere display'd green fields among<br/>

						The varying clouds, like paradises stretch'd in the expanse<br/>
						With towns &amp; villages and temples, tents sheep-folds and pastures<br/>

						Where dwell the children of the elemental worlds in harmony, <br/>
						Not long in harmony they dwell, their life is drawn away<br/>
							
						And wintry woes succeed; successive driven into the Void<br/>
						Where Enion craves: successive drawn into the golden feast<br/>
					
					
						And Los &amp; Enitharmon sat in discontent &amp; scorn<br/>
							
						The Nuptial Song arose from all the thousand thousand spirits<br/>
							
						Over the joyful Earth &amp; Sea, and ascended into the Heavens<br/>
						For Elemental Gods their thunderous Organs blew; creating<br/>
						Delicious Viands. Demons of Waves their watry Eccho's woke!
						Bright Souls of vegetative life, budding and blossoming <br/>
							
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.14.ms.100" id="14">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						Stretch their immortal hands to smite the gold &amp; silver Wires<br/>

						And with immortal Voice soft warbling fill all Earth &amp; Heaven.

						With doubling Voices &amp; loud Horns wound round sounding<br/>
						Cavernous dwellers fill'd the enormous Revelry, Responsing!
						And Spirits of Flaming fire on high, govern'd the mighty Song. <br/>
					
					
						And This the Song! sung at The Feast of Los &amp; Enitharmon<br/>
					
					
						Ephraim calld out to Zion: Awake O Brother Mountain <br/>
							
						Let us refuse the Plow &amp; Spade, the heavy Roller &amp; spiked<br/>

						Harrow. burn all these Corn fields. throw down all these fences<br/>
						Fattend on Human blood &amp; drunk with wine of life is better far <br/>

					
					
						Than all these labours of the harvest &amp; the vintage. See the river<br/>
						Red with the blood of Men. swells lustful round my rocky knees<br/>
						My clouds are not the clouds of verdant fields &amp; groves of fruit<br/>

						But Clouds of Human Souls. my nostrils drink the lives of Men<br/>
							
					
					
						The Villages Lament. they faint outstretchd upon the plain <br/>
						Wailing runs round the Valleys from the Mill &amp; from the Barn<br/>
							
						
						But most the polishd Palaces dark silent bow with dread<br/>
							
						Hiding their books &amp; pictures. underneath the dens of Earth<br/>

					
					
						The Cities send to one another saying My sons are Mad<br/>
						With wine of cruelty. Let us plat a Scourge O Sister City<br/>
							
						Children are nourishd for the Slaughter; once the Child was fed<br/>

						With Milk; but wherefore now are Children fed with blood<br/>
							
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.15.ms.100" id="15">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						The Horse is of more value than the Man. The Tyger fierce<br/>
						Laughs at the Human form. the Lion mocks &amp; thirsts for blood<br/>

						They cry O Spider spread thy web! Enlarge thy bones &amp; fill'd<br/>

						With marrow. sinews &amp; flesh Exalt thyself attain a voice<br/>
					
					
						Call to thy dark armd hosts, for all the sons of Men muster together <br/>

						To desolate their cities! Man shall be no more! Awake O Hosts<br/>
						The bow string sang upon the hills! Luvah &amp; Vala ride<br/>
						Triumphant in the bloody sky. &amp; the Human form is no more <br/>
							
					
					
						The listning Stars heard, &amp; the first beam of the morning started back<br/>
						He cried out to his Father, depart! depart! but sudden Siez'd <br/>
							
						And clad in steel. &amp; his Horse proudly neighd; he smelt the battle<br/>
							
						Afar off, Rushing back, reddning with rage the Mighty Father<br/>
							
					
					
						Siezd his bright Sheephook studded with gems &amp; gold, he Swung it round<br/>
						His head shrill sounding in the sky, down rushd the Sun with noise<br/>

						Of war, The Mountains fled away they sought a place beneath<br/>
						Vala remaind in desarts of dark solitude. nor Sun nor Moon<br/>
					
					
						By night nor day to comfort her, she labourd in thick smoke <br/>
							
						Tharmas endurd not, he fled howling. then a barren waste sunk&gt;
						Conglobing in the dark confusion, Mean time Los was born<br/>
						And Thou O Enitharmon! Hark I hear the hammers of Los <br/>
							
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.16.ms.100" id="16">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						They melt the bones of Vala, &amp; the bones of Luvah into wedges<br/>

						The innumerable sons &amp; daughters of Luvah closd in furnaces<br/>
						Melt into furrows. winter blows his bellows: ice &amp; Snow<br/>
						Tend the dire anvils. Mountains mourn &amp; Rivers faint &amp; fail<br/>

					
					
						There is no City nor Corn-field nor Orchard! all is Rock &amp; Sand<br/>

						There is no Sun nor Moon nor Star. but rugged wintry rocks<br/>
						Justling together in the void suspended by inward fires<br/>
						Impatience now no longer can endure. Distracted Luvah<br/>
					
					
						Bursting forth from the loins of Enitharmon, Thou fierce Terror<br/>
						Go howl in vain, Smite Smite his fetters Smite O wintry hammers<br/>

						Smite Spectre of Urthona, mock the fiend who drew us down<br/>
						From heavens of joy into this Deep. Now rage but rage in vain<br/>
						
						Thus Sang the Demons of the Deep. the Clarions of War blew loud<br/>

						The Feast redounds &amp; Crownd with roses &amp; the circling vine<br/>

						The Enormous Bride &amp; Bridegroom sat, beside them Urizen<br/>
						With faded radiance sighd, forgetful of the flowing wine<br/>
						And of Ahania his Pure Bride but She was distant far<br/>
					
					
						But Los &amp; Enitharmon sat in discontent &amp; scorn<br/>
						Craving the more the more enjoying, drawing out sweet bliss<br/>
						From all the turning wheels of heaven &amp; the chariots of the Slain<br/>
					
					
						At distance Far in Night repelld. in direful hunger craving<br/>
						Summers &amp; Winters round revolving in the frightful deep.
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.17.ms.100" id="17">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						Enion blind &amp; age-bent wept upon the desolate wind<br/>
							
					
					
						Why does the Raven cry aloud and no eye pities her?
						Why fall the Sparrow &amp; the Robin in the foodless winter?
						Faint! shivering they sit on leafless bush, or frozen stone<br/>
							
					
					
						Wearied with seeking food across the snowy waste; the little <br/>
						Heart, cold; and the little tongue consum'd, that once in thoughtless joy<br/>
						Gave songs of gratitude to waving corn fields round their nest. <br/>
							
					
					
						Why howl the Lion &amp; the Wolf? why do they roam abroad?
							
						Deluded by summers heat they sport in enormous love <br/>
							
						And cast their young out to the hungry wilds &amp; sandy desarts <br/>

					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.18.ms.100" id="18">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						Why is the Sheep given to the knife? the Lamb plays in the Sun<br/>
						He starts! he hears the foot of Man! he says, Take thou my wool<br/>
						But spare my life, but he knows not that winter cometh fast.
							
					
					
						The Spider sits in his labourd Web, eager watching for the Fly<br/>
						Presently comes a famishd Bird &amp; takes away the Spider <br/>
						His Web is left all desolate, that his little anxious heart<br/>
						So careful wove; &amp; spread it out with sighs and weariness.
					
					
						This was the Lamentation of Enion round the golden Feast<br/>
						Eternity groand and was troubled at the image of Eternal Death<br/>
						Without the body of Man an Exudation from his sickning limbs <br/>
					
					
						Now Man was come to the Palm tree &amp; to the Oak of Weeping<br/>
							
						Which stand upon the Edge of Beulah &amp; he sunk down<br/>
						From the Supporting arms of the Eternal Saviour; who disposd<br/>
						The pale limbs of his Eternal Individuality<br/>
						Upon The Rock of Ages. Watching over him with Love &amp; Care <br/>
							
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.18.ms.100" id="19">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						Why is the Sheep given to the knife? the Lamb plays in the Sun<br/>
						He starts! he hears the foot of Man! he says, Take thou my wool<br/>
						But spare my life, but he knows not that winter cometh fast.
							
					
					
						The Spider sits in his labourd Web, eager watching for the Fly<br/>
						Presently comes a famishd Bird &amp; takes away the Spider <br/>
						His Web is left all desolate, that his little anxious heart<br/>
						So careful wove; &amp; spread it out with sighs and weariness.
					
					
						This was the Lamentation of Enion round the golden Feast<br/>
						Eternity groand and was troubled at the image of Eternal Death<br/>
						Without the body of Man an Exudation from his sickning limbs <br/>
					
					
						Now Man was come to the Palm tree &amp; to the Oak of Weeping<br/>
							
						Which stand upon the Edge of Beulah &amp; he sunk down<br/>
						From the Supporting arms of the Eternal Saviour; who disposd<br/>
						The pale limbs of his Eternal Individuality<br/>
						Upon The Rock of Ages. Watching over him with Love &amp; Care <br/>
							
					
					</caption>
</image>
<image dbi="bb209.1.18.ms.100" id="20">
<title></title>
<caption>
					
						Why is the Sheep given to the knife? the Lamb plays in the Sun<br/>
						He starts! he hears the foot of Man! he says, Take thou my wool<br/>
						But spare my life, but he knows not that winter cometh fast.
							
					
					
						The Spider sits in his labourd Web, eager watching for the Fly<br/>
						Presently comes a famishd Bird &amp; takes away the Spider <br/>
						His Web is left all desolate, that his little anxious heart<br/>
						So careful wove; &amp; spread it out with sighs and weariness.
					
					
						This was the Lamentation of Enion round the golden Feast<br/>
						Eternity groand and was troubled at the image of Eternal Death<br/>
						Without the body of Man an Exudation from his sickning limbs <br/>
					
					
						Now Man was come to the Palm tree &amp; to the Oak of Weeping<br/>
							
						Which stand upon the Edge of Beulah &amp; he sunk down<br/>
						From the Supporting arms of the Eternal Saviour; who disposd<br/>
						The pale limbs of his Eternal Individuality<br/>
						Upon The Rock of Ages. Watching over him with Love &amp; Care <br/>
							
					
					</caption>
</image>

</exhibit>
					